<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1000" title="Hercule Poirot" authors="4" lines="87">
  <entry author_id="280326" end="11" start="0">In The Mysterious Affair at Styles, Poirot operates as a fairly conventional, clue-based detective, depending on logic, which is represented in his vocabulary by two common phrases: his use of "the little grey cells" and "order and method".
Irritating to Hastings (and, sometimes, to the reader) is the fact that Poirot will sometimes conceal from him important details of his plans, as in The Big Four where Hastings is kept in the dark throughout the climax.
This aspect of Poirot is less evident in the later novels, partly because there is rarely a narrator so there is no one for Poirot to mislead.

As early as Murder on the Links, where he still largely depends on clues, Poirot mocks a rival detective who focuses on the traditional trail of clues that had been established in detective fiction by the example of Sherlock Holmes: footprints, fingerprints and cigar ash.
From this point on he establishes himself as a psychological detective who proceeds not by a painstaking examination of the crime scene, but by enquiring either into the nature of the victim or the murderer.
Central to his behaviour in the later novels is the underlying assumption that particular crimes are only committed by particular types of person.

Poirot's methods focus on getting people to talk.
Early in the novels, he frequently casts himself in the role of "Papa Poirot", a benign confessor, especially to young women.
Later he lies freely in order gain the confidences of other characters, either inventing his own reason for being interested in the case or a family excuse for pursuing a line of questioning.
Poirot is also willing to appear more foreign or vain than he really is in an effort to make people underestimate him.
He admits as much: In the later novels Christie often uses the word mountebank when Poirot is being assessed by other characters, showing that he has successfully passed himself off as a charlatan or fraud.</entry>
  <entry author_id="962716" end="41" start="11">All these techniques help Poirot attain his principal target: "For in the long run, either through a lie, or through truth, people were bound to give themselves away..." This page details the other fictional characters created by Agatha Christie in her stories about the Belgian detective, Hercule Poirot.
Hastings first meets Poirot during his years as a private detective in Europe and almost immediately after they both arrive in England, becomes his life-long partner and appears in many of the novels and stories.
Poirot’s view of Hastings was of a man with plenty of imagination but not a great deal of brains.

The two were an airtight team until Hastings met and married Dulcie Duveen, a beautiful music hall performer half his age, which was not objectionable in the late Victorian, Edwardian world.
They later emigrated to Argentina leaving Poirot behind a "very unhappy old man."
The frequently recurring detective novelist Ariadne is Agatha Christie's humorous self-caricature.
We never learn about her husband but we know that she hates alcohol and public appearances and has a great fondness for apples until she is put off them by the events of the Hallowe’en party.
She has a maid called Milly who prevents the public adoration from becoming too much of a burden on her employer, but does nothing to prevent her aggravating employer from becoming too much of a burden on others.

She has authored over fifty six novels and she has a great dislike of people taking and modifying her story characters.
She is also the only one in Poirot's universe to have noted that "It’s not natural for five or six people to be on the spot when B is murdered and all have a motive for killing B."
She first met Poirot when they put their Cards on the Table and has been bothering him ever since.
Poirot's secretary, Miss Lemon, has few human weaknesses and the only two mistakes she is ever recorded making is a typing error during the events of Hickory Dickory Dock and the mis-mailing of an electric bill.
Poirot described her has being "Unbelievably ugly and incredibly efficient.
Anything that she mentioned as worth consideration usually was worth consideration."
She is an expert on nearly everything and plans to create the perfect filing system.
Interesting enough is the fact that she once worked for the government agent-turned-philanthropist, Parker Pyne.
Whether this was during one of Poirot’s numerous retirements or before she entered his employ is unknown.
Japp is an Inspector from Scotland Yard and appears in many of the stories, trying to solve the cases Poirot is working on.
Japp is an outward going, loud and sometimes inconsiderate man by nature and his relationship with the bourgeois Belgian is one of the stranger aspects of Poirot’s world.
He first met Poirot in Belgium, 1904, during the Abercrombie Forgery and later that year joined forces again to hunt down a criminal known as Baron Altara.
They have also meet in England where Poirot often helps Japp solve a case and lets him take the credit in return for special favours.
These favours usually entail being supplied with cases that would interest him.
In addition to these regular characters, it is noteworthy that all the gentlemen in the novels have butlers; Poirot's butler is the most incurable snob he could find.
George (we are never told his last name) is a classic English valet and first entered Poirot’s employ in 1923 and didn’t leave his side until the 1970’s, shortly before Poirot’s death.
A competent, matter-of-fact man, with an extensive knowledge of the English aristocracy and absolutely no imagination, George provides a steady contrast to Hastings.
Although Agatha Christie never wrote the much demanded "Poirot meets Miss Marple", some fans claim that they share the same universe anyway.
In The Pale Horse, Mrs. Oliver is acquainted with the Rev.
and Mrs. Dane Colthorp, who are also friends of Miss Marple (as seen in The Moving Finger)- thus establishing that Miss Marple and Hercule Poirot exist in the same world.
Also a few fans have taken this further, noting that in the Labours of Hercules, it was (jokingly) mentioned that Poirot's mother came up with his name while talking to Sherlock Holmes’s mother.
Since this is contradicted in The Clocks when Poirot discusses with Colin Lamb Sir Doyle's creation of Holmes and Watson (and says the stories are somewhat far-fetched), we learn that the refference in Labours of hercules was indeed just a joke.</entry>
  <entry author_id="4135" end="52" start="41">His name was derived from two other fictional detectives of the time: Marie Belloc Lowndes' Hercule Popeau and Frank Howel Evans' Monsieur Poiret, a retired Belgian police officer living in London.
Hercule Poirot's initials replicate that of the sauce which he happens to like, HP Brown Sauce as he comments in Elephants Can Remember: "Ah yes, that is correct my initials do appear to be the same as such a fine delicacy, a good English creation."
A more obvious influence on the early Poirot stories is that of Arthur Conan Doyle.
In An Autobiography Christie admits that "I was still writing in the Sherlock Holmes tradition –eccentric detective, stooge assistant, with a Lestrade-type Scotland Yard detective, Inspector Japp."
For his part Conan Doyle acknowledged basing his detective stories on the model of Edgar Allan Poe's C. Auguste Dupin, and his anonymous narrator, and based his character Sherlock Holmes on Joseph Bell, who in his use of "ratiocination" prefigures Poirot's reliance on his "little grey cells".

Poirot also bears a striking resemblance to A. E. W. Mason's fictional detective—Inspector Hanaud of the French Sûreté—who, first appearing in the 1910 novel At the Villa Rose predates the writing of the first Poirot novel by six years.
In chapter 4 of the second Inspector Hanaud novel, The House of the Arrow (1924), Hanaud declares sanctimoniously to the heroine, "You are wise, Mademoiselle…For, after all, I am Hanaud.
There is only one."

Christie's Poirot was Belgian, likely a Walloon.
Unlike the models mentioned above, Christie's Poirot character was clearly the result of her early development of the detective in her first book written in 1916 (although not published until 1920).
Not only was his Belgian nationality interesting because of Belgium's occupation by Germany (which provided a valid explanation of why such a skilled detective would be out of work and available to solve mysteries at an English country house), but also at the time of Christie's writing, it was considered patriotic to express sympathy with the Belgians, since the invasion of their country had constituted Britain's casus belli for entering World War I, and British wartime propaganda emphasized the "Rape of Belgium".</entry>
  <entry author_id="15657148" end="87" start="52">Hastings, a former British Army officer, first meets Poirot during Poirot's years as a police officer in Belgium and almost immediately after they both arrive in England.
He becomes Poirot's lifelong friend and appears in many of the novels and stories.
Poirot regards Hastings as a poor private detective, not particularly intelligent, yet helpful in his way of being fooled by the criminal or seeing things the way the average man would see them, and for his tendency to unknowingly "stumble" onto the truth.
Hastings marries and has four children – two sons and two daughters.

Hastings is a man who is capable of great bravery and courage, facing death unflinchingly when confronted by The Big Four and possessing unwavering loyalty towards Poirot.
However, when forced to choose between Poirot and his wife in that novel, he initially chooses to betray Poirot to the Big Four so that they would not torture and kill his wife.
Later, though, he tells Poirot to draw back and escape the trap.

The two are an airtight team until Hastings meets and marries Dulcie Duveen, a beautiful music hall performer half his age.
They later emigrate to Argentina, leaving Poirot behind as a "very unhappy old man."
Poirot and Hastings are reunited in Curtain: Poirot's Last Case, having been earlier reunited in The ABC Murders and Dumb Witness when Hastings arrives in England for business.
The detective novelist Ariadne Oliver is Agatha Christie's humorous self-caricature.
Like Agatha Christie, she isn't overly fond of the detective she is most famous for creating – in Ariadne's case the Finnish sleuth Sven Hjerson.
We never learn anything about her husband, but we do know that she hates alcohol and public appearances, and has a great fondness for apples until she is put off them by the events of Hallowe'en Party.
She also has a habit of constantly changing her hairstyle, and in every appearance by her much is made of the clothes and hats she wears.
She has a maid called Maria who prevents the public adoration from becoming too much of a burden on her employer, but does nothing to prevent her from becoming too much of a burden on others.

She has authored over fifty-six novels and she has a great dislike of people taking and modifying her story characters.
She is also the only one in Poirot's universe to have noted that "It’s not natural for five or six people to be on the spot when B is murdered and all have a motive for killing B."
She first met Poirot in the story Cards on the Table and has been bothering him ever since.
Poirot's secretary, Miss Felicity Lemon, has few human weaknesses.
The only two mistakes she is ever recorded making are a typing error during the events of Hickory Dickory Dock and the mis-mailing of an electricity bill, although in her defence she was worried about strange events surrounding her sister at the time.
Poirot described her as being "Unbelievably ugly and incredibly efficient.
Anything that she mentioned as worth consideration usually was worth consideration."
She is an expert on nearly everything and plans to create the perfect filing system.
She also once worked for the government agent-turned-philanthropist, Parker Pyne.
Whether this was during one of Poirot’s numerous retirements or before she entered his employment is unknown.
In The Agatha Christie Hour, she was portrayed by British actress Angela Easterling, while in Agatha Christie's Poirot, she was portrayed by singer and guitarist Pauline Moran.
Japp is an Inspector from Scotland Yard and appears in many of the stories, trying to solve the cases Poirot is working on.
Japp is an outgoing, loud and sometimes inconsiderate man by nature and his relationship with the bourgeois Belgian is one of the stranger aspects of Poirot’s world.
He first met Poirot in Belgium, 1904, during the Abercrombie Forgery and later that year joined forces again to hunt down a criminal known as Baron Altara.
They also meet in England where Poirot often helps Japp solve a case and lets him take credit for the collar in return for special favours.
These favours usually entail Poirot being supplied with cases that would interest him.
In Agatha Christie's Poirot, Japp was portrayed by Philip Jackson.
George (we are never told his last name) is a classic English valet who first entered Poirot’s employ in 1923 and didn’t leave his side until the 1970s, shortly before Poirot’s death.
A competent, matter-of-fact man with an extensive knowledge of the English aristocracy and absolutely no imagination, George provides a steady contrast to Hastings.
In Agatha Christie's Poirot, George is played by actor David Yelland.</entry>
</article>
