<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1006" title="Aaron" authors="3" lines="165">
  <entry author_id="1817546" end="25" start="0">Aaron, like Moses, was not permitted to enter Canaan.
The reason alleged is that the two brothers showed impatience at Meribah (Kadesh) in the last year of the desert pilgrimage, when they, or rather Moses, brought water out of a rock to quench the thirst of the people.
The action was construed as displaying a want of deference to the Lord, since they had been commanded to speak to the rock, whereas Moses struck it with the wonder-working rod.
Of the death of Aaron we have two accounts.
The principal one gives a detailed statement to the effect that, soon after the above incident, Aaron, with his son Eleazar and Moses, ascended Mount Hor.
There Moses stripped him (Aaron) of his priestly garments, and transferred them to Eleazar.
Aaron died, aged 123, on the summit of the mountain, and the people mourned for him thirty days.
The other account is found in Deuteronomy 10:6, where Moses is reported as saying that Aaron died at Mosera and was buried there.
Some scholars think that Mosera is not on Mount Hor, since the itinerary in Numbers 33:31-37 records seven stages between Moseroth (thought by some to be Mosera) and Mount Hor.

In fulfillment of the promise of peaceful life, symbolized by the pouring of oil upon his head, Aaron’s death, as described in the Haggadah, was of a wonderful tranquillity.
Accompanied by Moses, his brother, and by Eleazar, his son, Aaron went to the summit of Mount Hor, where the rock suddenly opened before him and a beautiful cave lit by a lamp presented itself to his view.
“Take off thy priestly raiment and place it upon thy son Eleazar!” said Moses; “and then follow me.” Aaron did as commanded; and they entered the cave, where was prepared a bed around which angels stood.
“Go lie down upon thy bed, my brother,” Moses continued; and Aaron obeyed without a murmur.
Then his soul departed as if by a kiss from God.
The cave closed behind Moses as he left; and he went down the hill with Eleazar, with garments rent, and crying: “Alas, Aaron, my brother!
thou, the pillar of supplication of Israel!” When the Israelites cried in bewilderment, “Where is Aaron?” angels were seen carrying Aaron’s bier through the air.
A voice was then heard saying: “The law of truth was in his mouth, and iniquity was not found on his lips: he walked with me in righteousness, and brought many back from sin”.
He died, according to Seder Olam Rabbah 9, Rosh Hashanna 2, 3a, and Josephus on the first of Ab.
Josephus says also that “he died while the multitude looked upon him.” The pillar of cloud which proceeded in front of Israel’s camp disappeared at Aaron’s death.
The seeming contradiction between Numbers 20:22 et seq.
and Deuteronomy 10:6 is solved by the rabbis in the following manner: Aaron’s death on Mount Hor was marked by the defeat of the people in a war with the king of Arad, in consequence of which the Israelites fled, marching seven stations backward to Mosera, where they performed the rites of mourning for Aaron; wherefore it is said: “There [[Moseroth|Mosera]] died Aaron.” The rabbis also dwell with special laudation on the brotherly sentiment which united Aaron and Moses.
When the latter was appointed ruler and Aaron high priest, neither betrayed any jealousy; instead they rejoiced in one another’s greatness.
When Moses at first declined to go to Pharaoh, saying: “O my Lord, send, I pray thee, by the hand of him whom thou wilt send”, he was unwilling to deprive Aaron, his brother, of the high position the latter had held for so many years; but the Lord reassured him, saying: “Behold, when he seeth thee, he will be glad in his heart.” Indeed, Aaron was to find his reward, says Simon ben Yohai; for that heart which had leaped with joy over his younger brother’s rise to glory greater than his was decorated with the Urim and Thummim, which were to “be upon Aaron’s heart when he goeth in before the Lord.”  Moses and Aaron met in gladness of heart, kissing each other as true brothers and of them it is written: “Behold how good and how pleasant is for brethren to dwell together in unity!” Of them it is said: “Mercy and truth are met together; righteousness and peace have kissed other”; for Moses stood for righteousness, according to Deuteronomy 33:21, and Aaron for peace, according to Malachi 2:6.
Again, mercy was personified in Aaron, according to Deuteronomy 33:8, and truth in Moses, according to Numbers 12:7.
When Moses poured the oil of anointment upon the head of Aaron, Aaron modestly shrank back and said: “Who knows whether I have not cast some blemish upon this sacred oil so as to forfeit this high office.” Then the Holy Spirit spake the words: “Behold the precious ointment upon the head, that ran down upon the beard of Aaron, that even went down to the skirts of his garment, is as pure as the dew of Hermon.”</entry>
  <entry author_id="3215199" end="45" start="25">Aaron, like Moses, was not permitted to enter Canaan with the successful invaders.
The reason alleged is that the two brothers showed impatience at Meribah (Kadesh) in the last year of the desert pilgrimage (Num.
xx.
12, 13), when they, or rather Moses, brought water out of a rock to quench the thirst of the people.
The action was construed as displaying a want of deference to the Lord, since they had been commanded to speak to the rock, whereas Moses struck it with the wonder-working rod (Num.
xx.
7-11).
Of the death of Aaron we have two accounts.
The principal one gives a detailed statement to the effect that, soon after the above incident, Aaron, with his son Eleazar and Moses, ascended Mount Hor.
There Moses stripped him (Aaron) of his priestly garments, and transferred them to Eleazar.
Aaron died on the summit of the mountain, and the people mourned for him thirty days (Num.
xx.
22-29; compare xxxiii.
38, 39).
The other account is found in Deut.
x.
6, where Moses is reported as saying that Aaron died at Mosera and was buried there.
Mosera is not on Mount Hor, since the itinerary in Num.
xxxiii.
31-37 records seven stages between Moseroth (Mosera) and Mount Hor.</entry>
  <entry author_id="3215199" end="117" start="45">In fulfilment of the promise of peaceful life, symbolized by the pouring of oil upon his head (Lev.
R. x., Midr.
Teh.
cxxxiii.
1), Aaron's death, as described in the Haggadah, was of a wonderful tranquillity.
Accompanied by Moses, his brother, and by Eleazar, his son, Aaron went to the summit of Mount Hor, where the rock suddenly opened before him and a beautiful cave lit by a lamp presented itself to his view.
"Take off thy priestly raiment and place it upon thy son Eleazar!"
said Moses; "and then follow me."
Aaron did as commanded; and they entered the cave, where was prepared a bed around which angels stood.
"Go lie down upon thy bed, my brother," Moses continued; and Aaron obeyed without a murmur.
Then his soul departed as if by a kiss from God.
The cave closed behind Moses as he left; and he went down the hill with Eleazar, with garments rent, and crying: "Alas, Aaron, my brother!
thou, the pillar of supplication of Israel!"
When the Israelites cried in bewilderment, "Where is Aaron?"
angels were seen carrying Aaron's bier through the air.
A voice was then heard saying: "The law of truth was in his mouth, and iniquity was not found on his lips: he walked with me in righteousness, and brought many back from sin" (Mal.
ii.
6, 7).
He died, according to Seder 'Olam R.
ix., R. H. 2, 3a, on the first of Ab.
Josephus says also that "he died while the multitude looked upon him."
The pillar of cloud which proceeded in front of Israel's camp disappeared at Aaron's death (see Seder 'Olam, ix.
and R. H. 2b-3a).
The seeming contradiction between Num.
xx.
22 et seq.
and Deut.
x.
6 is solved by the rabbis in the following manner: Aaron's death on Mount Hor was marked by the defeat of the people in a war with the king of Arad, in consequence of which the Israelites fled, marching seven stations backward to Mosera, where they performed the rites of mourning for Aaron; wherefore it is said: "There Mosera died Aaron."
See Mek., Beshallaḥ, Wayassa', i.; Tan., Huḳḳat, 18; Yer.
Soṭah, i.
17c, and Targ.
Yer.
Num.
and Deut.
on the abovementioned passages.

The rabbis also dwell with special laudation on the brotherly sentiment which united Aaron and Moses.
When the latter was appointed ruler and Aaron high priest, neither betrayed any jealousy; instead they rejoiced in one another's greatness.
When Moses at first declined to go to Pharaoh, saying: "O my Lord, send, I pray thee, by the hand of him whom thou wilt send" (Ex.
iv.
13), he was unwilling to deprive Aaron, his brother, of the high position the latter had held for so many years; but the Lord reassured him, saying: "Behold, when he seeth thee, he will be glad in his heart" (Ex.
iv.
14).
Indeed, Aaron was to find his reward, says Simon bar Yochai; for that heart which had leaped with joy over his younger brother's rise to glory greater than his was decorated with the Urim and Thummim, which were to "be upon Aaron's heart when he goeth in before the Lord" (Cant.
R. i.
10).
Moses and Aaron met in gladness of heart, kissing each other as true brothers (Ex.
iv.
27; compare Song of Songs, viii.
1), and of them it is written: "Behold how good and how pleasant is for brethren to dwell together in unity!"
(Ps.
cxxxiii.
1).
Of them it is said (Ps.
lxxxv.
10): "Mercy and truth are met together; righteousness and peace have kissed other"; for Moses stood for righteousness, according to Deut.
xxxiii.
21, and Aaron for peace, according to Mal.
ii.
6.
Again, mercy was personified in Aaron, according to Deut.
xxxiii.
8, and truth in Moses, according to Num.
xii.
7 (Tan., Shemot, ed.
Buber, 24-26).

When Moses poured the oil of anointment upon the head of Aaron, Aaron modestly shrank back and said: "Who knows whether I have not cast some blemish upon this sacred oil so as to forfeit this high office."
Then the Holy Spirit spake the words: "Behold the precious ointment upon the head, that ran down upon the beard of Aaron, that even went down to the skirts of his garment, is as pure as the dew of Hermon" (Ps.
cxxxiii.
2, 3, Heb.
; Sifra, Shemini, Milluim; Tan., Korah, ed.
Buber, 14).</entry>
  <entry author_id="3215199" end="131" start="117">All scholars, admit that in Aaron's High Priesthood the sacred writer intended to describe a model, the prototype, so to say, of the Jewish High Priest.
God, on Mount Sinai, instituting a worship, and also instituted an order of priests.
According to the patriarchal customs, the first born son in every family used to perform the functions connected with God's worship.
It might have been expected, consequently, that Rueben's family would be chosen by God for the ministry of the new altar.
However, according to the biblical narrative, it was Aaron, however, who was the object of God's choice.
To what jealousies this gave rise later, has been indicated above.
The office of the Aaronites was at first merely to take care of the lamp that should ever burn before the veil of the tabernacle (Exodus 27:21).
A more formal calling soon followed (Exodus 28:1).
Aaron and his sons, distinguished from the common people by their sacred functions, were likewise to receive holy vestments suitable to their office.

Aaron offered the different sacrifices and performed the many ceremonies of the consecration of the new priests, according to the divine instructions (Exodus 29), and repeated these rites for seven days, during which Aaron and his sons were entirely separated from the rest of the people.
When, on the eighth day, the High Priest had inaugurated his office of sacrificer by killing the animals, he blessed the people, very likely according to the prescriptions of Num., vi, 24-26, and, with Moses, entered into the tabernacle so as to take possession thereof.
As they "came forth and blessed the people.
And the glory of the Lord appeared to all the multitude: And behold a fire, coming forth from the Lord, devoured the holocaust, and the fat that was upon the altar: which when the multitude saw, they praised the Lord, falling on their faces" (Leviticus 9:23, 24).
So was the institution of the Aaronic priesthood inaugurated and solemnly ratified by the Lord.</entry>
  <entry author_id="12053355" end="165" start="131">Harun (Arabic: هارون; meaning Mountain of strength) (circa 1439 BC - 1317 BC?
), is an Islamic prophet and messenger mentioned in the Qur'an.
In the Bible he is known as Aaron (Aharōn in Hebrew).
It is believed that Aaron lived for 122 years.

It was he who preached and prophesied with Moses (Musa) during the reign of the terrible Pharaoh of the Exodus, known in Islam as Firaun.
Aaron is one of the prophets who Muhammad is said to have met on the night of the Mi'raj (Night Journey), his ascension through the heavens.

Aaron is also important for being a patriarch the ancestor of the priestly lineage of the family of Amram.
The figures mentioned in the Qur'an who came from Aaron's lineage were Mary and Jesus.
Furthermore, the other figures present in the household - such as the high priest Zachariah and his wife Elizabeth - are also mentioned as coming through the same bloodline.

Aaron was a gifted speaker.
He was largely responsible with teaching the Israelites the way of worship as it was laid out in the Torah (Tawrat) of that time.
According to the Qur'an, Moses prayed to God to grant him his brother Aaron as a helper to be with him in all his tasks ahead.
God, in the Qur'an, says that Moses said:

Aaron, being a prophetic messenger, was also given the law by God, to preach to the Children of Israel according to the Torah.
The Qur'an mentions the holy scripture as a light and guidance for those who would accept the Message.
God says in the Qur'an:

When Moses led his people on the Exodus to Mount Sinai, he told them that he would be gone for a few days to receive the Tablets of the Law.
He informed the Israelites that Aaron would be their leader in his absence.
However, the moment Moses left, an evil man, Samiri, fashioned an idol calf out of the people's gold and jewelery and he made the Israelites succumb to idolatry.

Aaron preached with powerful zeal to his people, but they refused to listen to him.
It is here that the Qur'anic narrative of the incident sharply contrasts with the Biblical story, which puts blames Aaron for making the golden calf.
Aaron was overpowered and was threatened with being killed by his people.
When Moses returned from Mount Sinai, he blamed Aaron for allowing the Israelites to worship this idol and seized his brother by his beard, but Aaron then gave his explanation, after which Moses prayed to God to forgive both of them.
As God says in the Qur'an:

Muhammad, in many of his sayings, speaks of Aaron.
In the event of the Mi'raj, his miraculous ascension through the Heavens, Muhammad is said to have encountered Aaron in the fifth heaven.
According to old scholars, including Ibn Hisham, Muhammad, in particular, mentioned the beauty of Aaron when he encountered him in Heaven.
Martin Lings, in his biographical Muhammad, speaks of Muhammad's wonderment at seeing fellow prophets in their heavenly glory:

Aaron was also mentioned by Muhammad in likeness to Ali.
Muhammad had left Ali to look after his family, but the hypocrites of the time begun to spread the rumor that the prophet found Ali a burden and was relieved to be rid of his presence.
Ali, grieved at hearing this wicked taunt, told Muhammad what the local people were saying.
In reply, the prophet said: "They lie, I bade thee remain for the sake of what I had left behind me.
So return and represent me in my family and in thine.
Art thou not content, O Ali, that thou should be unto me as Aaron was unto Moses, save that after me there is no prophet."</entry>
</article>
