<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1013" title="August 27" authors="1" lines="20">
  <entry author_id="1972950" end="20" start="0">Farid Ghadry, the president of the Reform Party of Syria, has offered a provocative explanation for this delay.
He asserts that the Supreme National Security Council of Iran chose the August 22 date “for a very precise reason.

The Night Journey, or Miraj, is central to Islam’s claim to Jerusalem as an Islamic holy city.
According to Islamic tradition, Muhammad was carried on a Buraq, a miraculous horse with a human head, from Mecca to Jerusalem, where he ascended into heaven and met the other prophets.
The only thing the Qur’an has to say about it is this: “Glory to (Allah) Who did take His servant for a Journey by night from the Sacred Mosque to the farthest Mosque, whose precincts We did bless, in order that We might show him some of Our Signs: for He is the One Who heareth and seeth (all things)” (17:1).

The traditions say that Muhammad and the Buraq, along with the angel Gabriel, went to the Temple Mount, and from there to heaven itself, where Muhammad encountered various prophets.
In the sixth heaven was Moses, occasioning a dig at the Jews.
“When I left him,” Muhammad says, “he wept.

Evidently, however, Muhammad’s stories of his journey were not altogether convincing: even some of the Muslims abandoned their faith and challenged Muhammad’s most faithful follower, Abu Bakr, to do the same.
Abu Bakr was contemptuous: “If he says so then it is true.
And what is so surprising in that?

Did Muhammad really go anywhere?
According to his favorite wife, Aisha, he did not: “The apostle’s body remained where it was but God removed his spirit by night.” Nevertheless, the Night Journey has become firmly embedded in the Islamic consciousness, such that Muslims today celebrate it as one of the central events of Muhammad’s life.
And now, according to Ghadry, Ahmadinejad is planning an illumination of the night sky over Jerusalem to rival the one that greeted the Prophet of Islam on his journey.
What the Iranian President, he says, is “promising the world by August 22 is the light in the sky over the Aqsa Mosque that took place the night before.

Will he attempt to make good on these threats this year on the anniversary of the Miraj, illuminating the night sky over Jerusalem?
Will Western powers heed Farid Ghadry’s words and move to stop Iran before it is too late?
---------------------------------------------------------------------------- Robert Spencer is a scholar of Islamic history, theology, and law and the director of Jihad Watch.
He is the author of five books, seven monographs, and hundreds of articles about jihad and Islamic terrorism, including Islam Unveiled: Disturbing Questions About the World’s Fastest Growing Faith and the New York Times Bestseller The Politically Incorrect Guide to Islam (and the Crusades).
His latest book, The Truth About Muhammad, is coming October 9 from Regnery Publishing.</entry>
</article>
