<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1023" title="Anarcho-capitalism" authors="5" lines="85">
  <entry author_id="14878" end="16" start="0">One illustration might be the present debate over same-sex marriage.
For anarcho-capitalists, both sides of the debate operate on fundamentally flawed premises.
Opponents of same-sex marriage on the Right argue that the State should give special status to the family arrangements of heterosexual couples who enter into an "official" marriage, and inflict special penalties on same-sex couples by refusing to give legal status to their private family arrangements.
Liberal advocates of same-sex marriage, on the other hand, argue that both heterosexual and same-sex couples should be allowed to enter into an "official" marriage and gain special benefits from the State.
Anarcho-capitalists differ from both positions: they deny the legitimacy of distinguishing between "official" and "unofficial" family arrangements, and argue that no-one should receive special legal benefits.
Thus, they argue that in a free society any group of two (or more, for that matter) consenting adults have the right to set down a private agreement about family arrangements, and that that private agreement is as good in legal terms as any other.

Of course, just as with corporations, a private agreement between two or more parties doesn't place a duty on anyone else.
Private individuals have every right to choose for themselves whether or not to smile upon the family arrangements that particular consenting adults make.
Thus, the owner of an insurance company that disagrees with same-sex marriages should not be forced to extend benefits to same-sex partners; on the other hand, the owner of an insurance company who endorses same-sex marriages has every right to extend benefits to same-sex partners that he wishes.
Gay liberation activists are free to boycott the first provider and support the second provider; Christian conservatives are free to boycott the second and support the first.

Anarcho-capitalists have very widely differing social views, ranging from the conservative and often religious paleolibertarians to moderate liberals to the far Left.
As such, they tend to disagree about which of these arrangements are best.
What they don't disagree about is which of these communities ought to be legal--they should all be allowed in a free society.
Most anarcho-capitalists expect that different communities will tend to coalesce around different social norms and attitudes; within these communities, more common forms of private arrangements will have more extensive jurisprudence than less common forms, and thus lower enforcement costs, which might make some arrangements more common than others.
The only important political issue, however, is that people are free from the threat of violence no matter which community they live in, and that they can freely move from one community to another.
As long as that is the case, there may be many arguments about fairness or virtue, but there are no arguments of legality.</entry>
  <entry author_id="20585" end="29" start="16">Another related argument, characteristic of opposing anarchist views, is to deny the claim that natural monopolies cannot be coercive.
This view holds that capitalist defense agencies and the owners who employ them would constitute de facto monopoly governments in themselves due both to the economic powers they hold and their exclusive right to legitimate defense of those properties they claim.
Proponents of this view say that a cooperative group which sets to enforce its claims in such a manner, without accounting for the active involvement of dissenting parties, would amount to the very same monopoly on violence that anarcho-capitalists claim to reject.
As such, some hold anarcho-capitalist businesses to be identical to a state in all but name - thus incompatible with anarchism.

Anarcho-capitalists were the first group to claim the title anarchist while expressly embracing private property and capital.
Given this, many anarchists have questioned the legitimacy of the title "anarcho-capitalist," claiming that anarchism is essentially antithetical to capital relations due to their perception that capitalism inhibits individual freedom.
Because these forms of anarchism originally arose, in part, to decry capital relations, anarchists of many different factions have a diverse set of arguments against property (which some distinguish from possession).
All of these arguments, some of which occupy the space of several books, would thus apply as arguments against anarcho-capitalism.
One brief example of such an argument is to consider private property an institution enforced privilege, and so regard individual or collective defense of it to be a form of coercive violence used to oppress non-owners.

Other anarchists, like the individualists, are also weary of collective arguments, but critique anarcho-capitalism on other grounds.
For example, some individualists argue from the labor theory of value to conclude that capital enforcement, and thus the institutions of rent and interest, are destructive of free market relations.
Others argue that wage labor is exploitative and thus incompatible with individual freedom.
Still others, like the egoists, deny the validity of property claims altogether, arguing that they are mere "spooks," nothing more than figments of the mind that serve no essential purpose.</entry>
  <entry author_id="51464" end="57" start="29">Anarcho-capitalism is a philosophy that combines individual property rights and the free market with a form of anarchism.
Supporters of it oppose any initiation of force or threat of such within the context of a system of private property; this opposition means that a state is unacceptable.
It is also referred to as anti-state capitalism by those who believe anarchism is incompatible with capitalism, or market anarchism who want a more readable term and sometimes by those who consider capitalism a loaded term.

Anarcho-capitalists tend to identify themselves as libertarians, opposing any and all government or state control on their personal lives or business.
They believe the individual is paramount, and their freedom is absolute as long as their actions harm no one else; to this end, they believe that a system of private property is the best way to protect these individual rights.
To most anarcho-capitalists, the only crimes are those that involve trespass, destruction or theft of life or property, and many include fraud in this as well.
However, one can make their own rules for their own property, which becomes a form of private law.

Anarcho-capitalism synthesizes certain ideas from the tradition of classical liberalism (see libertarianism) and arguably from individualist anarchism as well.
It opposes traditional anarchism on the issue of private property; while anarchists such as libertarian socialists and individualist anarchists reject all property beyond personal possessions, saying such property constitutes a form of authority, anarcho-capitalists embrace the establishment of private property, and the freedom of each individual to acquire or produce more property.
There is no concept of "owning too much" in anarcho-capitalism, which sets it apart from many other philosophies which tend to espouse taking only that which you need.
"Greed" is not a bad thing to anarcho-capitalists; rather, as Adam Smith wrote about the Invisible Hand, it is the engine that drives all economic action.
There is no taboo at all against inheritance.

Anarcho-capitalists are not a monolithic movement; many support using force to prevent others trespassing on their land, while some denounce even retaliatory force.
Some believe prisons would be necessary to incarcerate those who commit crimes, while others believe excommunication or restitution are sufficient.
Some see a minarchist system that provides court and law services without charging a tax (i.e. surviving totally on user fees) as being sufficiently free, since no one is coerced into joining, and so long as competition is allowed.

"Capitalism" has typically meant the system of private property and contracts protected by the state, so that the market and transactions may be properly managed by the government.
Anarcho-capitalists claim a "pure" version of capitalism can exist, one which consists of only a free market, with people trading on their own without any coercion or government management, regulation or protection.
However, since "capitalism" is seen by some to be a loaded word, many have taken up the alternate name, "market anarchist," which is also seen by some as an easier term to use.

Many anarcho-capitalists identify most with the Austrian School of economics, developed primarily by Ludwig von Mises, Carl Menger and Hans-Hermann Hoppe.
Other anarcho-capitalists however, such as David Friedman, do not agree with the Austrian School.
However, all anarcho-capitalists generally agree on most issues.
Like most mainstream economists, anarcho-capitalists accept the subjective theory of value, which says that all value is purely subjective.
Only the buyer, the seller, and the information supplied by the market can dictate what the price of a good or service is.
Any government interference, via regulation, tariff or tax, interferes with this relationship and information.

Anarcho-capitalists believe that any goods or services worth having, and which people want, can be supplied entirely by the private sector.
Thus, government services such as fire protection, police, unemployment protection, schools, welfare, drug testing, road construction, and sometimes such things as courts and copyrights, can be provided by the free market, if they can be done so sustainably.
If the output is less than the input - that is, if there is no profit, or if no one is willing to donate - the market has determined the service or good is not beneficial enough to be produced at that time.
Anarcho-capitalists don't agree with the concept of a market failure, and never support using government or coercive intervention to help any individual, business or charity.</entry>
  <entry author_id="208573" end="69" start="57">Similarly, some people believe that anarcho-capitalism is ill-equipped to manage common resources.
For example, owners or managers of factories may choose to pollute the air, rather than voluntarily joining pollution-management agreements.
Most libertarians, however, including some anarcho-capitalists, respond that the government is ill-equipped to manage the commons and advocate radical expansions of property rights.
See libertarian perspectives on natural resources for more information

Many anarcho-capitalists argue that it is government that creates most of the opportunities for companies to pollute common resources in the first place, by claiming to have sole control over common resources such as national forests, waterways and air quality, and by using ex ante regulation to shield companies from liability for pollution as long as they follow the letter of the rules.
Tragedies of the commons would be minimized as people were able to sue environmental offenders in a private arbitration forum for damage to the enjoyment of their own property.
(Of course, this raises a second-order free rider problem: how will people harmed by pollution be able to get environmental offenders to agree to a common private arbitrator with them?
Whether or not an anarcho-capitalist society would have mechanisms that could effectively bring about arbitration of disputes over damages is a matter of further controversy.)

Another common proposal is to treat the right to emit substances into the air as private property owned by someone, but only owned in measurable quantities.
Those who may be harmed by emissions would have actions against those who emitted more than their (tradeable) rights allowed, and the parties to such a dispute would then use the usual arbitration system.
Such a system, already in existence in some respects, would internalize the costs of pollution.
Nonetheless, some regard more thorough reliance upon such schemes as an untested thought experiment that would introduce problems of its own.</entry>
  <entry author_id="287446" end="85" start="69">The Austrian school of economics was founded with the publication of Carl Menger's 1871 book, Principles of Economics.
The Austrians approach economics as an a priori system like logic or mathematics, rather than as an empirical science like geology.
It attempts to discover axioms of human action, and make deductions therefrom.
Some of these praxeological axioms are:These are macro-level generalizations, or heuristics, which are true for the many, but not necessarily true for any particular person.

Even in the early days, Austrian economics was used as a theoretical weapon against socialism and statist socialist policy.
Eugen von Böhm-Bawerk, a colleague of Menger, wrote one of the first and most devastating critiques of socialism ever written - one that still holds up today - in his treatise, "The Exploitation Theory of Socialism-Communism."
Later, Friedrich Hayek wrote such classics as "The Road to Serfdom," warning that a command economy destroys the information function of prices, and that authority over the economy leads to totalitarianism.
Another very influential Austrian economist was Ludwig von Mises.

Murray Rothbard is the man who melded Austrian economics with classical liberalism and individualist anarchism, and is credited with coining the term "anarcho-capitalism."
He was probably the first to use "libertarian" in its current (US) pro-capitalist sense.
He was a trained economist, but also extremely erudite in history and political philosophy.
When young, he considered himself part of the Old Right, an anti-statist and anti-interventionist branch of the US Republican party.
When interventionist cold warriors of the National Review, such as William Buckley, captured the Republican party in the 1950s, Rothbard quit that group and formed an alliance with left-wing anti-war groups.
Later, Rothbard was a founder of the US Libertarian Party.
In the sixties, Rothbard was a part of Ayn Rand's objectivist group, but later had a falling out.
Rothbard's books, such as "Man Economy and State", "Power and Market", "The Ethics of Liberty", and "For a New Liberty", are considered classics of natural law libertarian thought.</entry>
</article>
