<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1030" title="Austrian School" authors="6" lines="248">
  <entry author_id="37249" end="10" start="0">It's most famous adherents are Friedrich Hayek, Ludwig von Mises and Carl Menger.
While often controversial, and standing to some extent outside of the mainstream of neoclassical theory - as well as being staunchly against much of Keynes' theory and its results - the Austrian School has been widely influential because of its emphasis on the creative phase of economic productivity and their questioning of the basis of the behavioral theory underlying neo-classical economics.
The Austrian School is generally associated with right leaning libertarian notions of social, political and economic organization.

Austrian economics can be broken into two general trends.
One, exemplified by Hayek, while distrusting of many neoclassical concepts, generally accepts their formulations, the other exemplified by the Ludwig von Mises Institute, seeks a different formalism for economics.
The primary areas of contention between neo-classical theory and the Austrian school are on the possibility of consumer indifference - neo-classical theory says it is possible, where as Mises rejected it as being "impossible to observe in practice" - Mises and his students argued that utility functions are ordinal, and not cardinal, that is, one can only rank preferences, and not measure their intensity.
Finally there are a host of questions about uncertainty raised by Mises and other Austrians which argue for a different means of risk assessment.

While the Austrian school itself is radically conservative, some would even say reactionary, many of their specific problems with the neo-classical formulation have analogs in other parts of economics.
Game theory is used to challenge probability, volatility argued for as a better measure of preference and risk assessment than price, and xaos theory argues for highly discrete rather than very smooth functions of utility and value.
Neo-classical economists have replies to each of the Austrian objections, which is why, while specific results of Austrian economics have been adopted by mainstream theory, as a whole, the paradigmatic assumption that economics should rest on induction from principles rather than deduction from observation has been largely rejected.</entry>
  <entry author_id="37249" end="25" start="10">Classical economics focused on the exchange theory of value.
In late late 19th century, however, there was a focus on the concept of the "marginal" cost and value.
(See Marginalism).
Carl Menger's 1871 book, Principles of Economics, is considered one of the crucial works that began the period known as neo-classical economics, which is now referred to as microeconomics.
While marginalism was generally influential, there was also a more specific school which grew up around Menger, which came to be known as the "Vienna School" or "Austrian School".

An area which is often overlooked is the influence that Austrian school ideas have had on Keynesian macro-economics.
The source of this influence is the period of time where the London School of Economics brought in Hayek and other "continental" economists.

The core of the Austrian framework can be summarized as taking a subjectivist approahc to marginal economics, and a focus on the idea that theory should absolutely over rule observation.
Austrians focus completely on the opportunity cost of goods, as opposed to balancing downside or disutility costs.
It is an Austrian assertion that everyone is off in an exchange, or they would not have carried it out.
A fuller explanation of this in more exact term is available at the New School's economic pages.

This focus on opportunity cost alone means that their interpretation of the time value of a good has a strict relationship: since goods will be as restricted by scarcity at a later point in time as they are now, the strict relationship between investment and time must also hold.
A factory making goods next year is worth as much less as the goods it is making next year are worth.
This means that the business cycle is driven by miscoordination between sectors of the same economy, caused by money not carrying incentive information correct about present choices, rather than within a single economy where money causes people to make bad decisions about how to spend their time.
This means, in the Austrian context, the correct way to prevent imbalances in the economy is to make people want to buy the correct goods, rather than controlling when people buy goods.</entry>
  <entry author_id="131606" end="75" start="25">The Austrian School is a school of economic thought, named somewhat oddly for the country of its first major architect, Carl Menger.
A school may be identified by certain basic standards of scholarly work.
These include the worldview, the epistemology, the methodology, and the rhetoric.
The Austrian School may be contrasted to other schools, especially the Classical School and the Neoclassical School.

The Austrian School’s worldview is that the economy exists as a social entity.
Its epistemology is that the goal of economic science is to discover the logic of action behind the observed events in the economy.
Its methodology is captured by the term Methodological Individualism, which says that economic events originate in individual human action so that the method of inquiry must trace all events back to their individual origins.
The rhetorical preference of the School is for verbal exposition.

The Austrian School shares the same basic worldview of the Classical School and the same rhetorical style of verbal exposition.
In both worldviews, the economy is catallactic (exchange-based) and the job of the science is to explain why and how exchange occurs.
That is why both believe that economics is a study of exchange (Richard Whately 1832).

But Austrian School differs fundamentally from the Classical School in matters of both epistemology and methodology.
Epistemologically, while the classical school thinks that economic events must be explained by discovering natural laws, the Austrian School insists on finding praxeological laws derived from the logic of individual human action.
In older jargon, the classical school adopts mechanism while the Austrian School adopts teleology as the proper explanatory framework.
The emphasis on teleology is stated as subjectivism, since the reason or purpose (telos) is a subjective phenomenon.
To avoid the unfortunate association with various abuses of ancient teleology, Ludwig von Mises prefers the term praxeology (logic of rational action) in place of teleology.

Worldview: The Neoclassical worldview is limited to that of an isolated individual who performs optimization behavior.
It therefore defines economics as study of allocation (Lionel Robbins 1932).
This is very different from economics as a study of exchange driven by entrepreneurial action, which is fundamentally different from optimizing behavior.
The key differences in the worldviews are brought out in epistemology, methodology, and rhetoric.

In the Austrian School view, an individual is an optimizer as well as an entrepreneur.
The focus is on entrepreneurial action, while optimizer behavior is not the central issue.
While optimizer behavior is modeled as applying human rationality, entrepreneurial action is understood in terms of what Kirzner calls ‘alertness’.
Indeed, it is possible to show that alertness gives rise to actions that would be deemed irrational from the viewpoint of an optimizer.
More importantly, entrepreneurial behavior gives rise to conclusions that are often at odds with the conclusions of optimization models.
For example, optimization models conclude that profit in equilibrium is zero, while an entrepreneurial model emphasizes that the entrepreneur acts as an arbitrageur who earns a pure profit in equilibrium.

Epistemology: The Austrian School regards it as the job of economic science to explain the market process according to the explanatory framework of praxeology or logic of action.
It does not accept mere description without explanation.
It endorses deductive logic, and does not support inductive inferences of the type historicists want.
The neoclassical school does not explain the market process as such, but only the behavior of the individuals.

Methodology: The neoclassical schools does not believe in methodological individualism, unless it gives a misleading name to the classical (implicit) idea of representative individual, which is the idea of the classical natural law where all individuals lack individuality and are governed by the same natural propensities to produce, consume, truck, barter and exchange.
The failure of the neoclassical school to implement methodological individualism is found in the rise of macroeconomics as a separate discipline, where aggregates are compared to other aggregates, without any effort to derive them from the actions of many individuals who are necessarily different form one another by virtue of entrepreneurial actions.
The mechanistic idea of representative individual is inconsistent with entrepreneurial actions that necessarily make individuals unrepresentative of one other.

Rhetoric: Neoclassical School is fond of marginalism.
It employs mathematical exposition not just as a style of presentation but also as an engine of inquiry.
The Austrian School does not reject either marginalism or use of mathematics, but its does not favor the obsession with the mathematical nature of presentation.
It favors use of coherent verbal expositions.
Some people have thought of this distinction as being between '(neoclassical) data without theory' and '(Austrian) theory without data'.
It is a truly big mistake to suppose that the Austrian School does not support observation.
The Austrian School’s key ideas were developed by eminently practical man who worked as finance ministers or the like or were teaching at business schools.
They insist that mere presentation of data without explanation is useless.
They want the data to be explained.

The Historicists for example believed that one could learn about causation by presenting mountains of data, that history would reveal the truth in the observations unaided by any theory.
But from Menger onwards, the Austrian School insists that the scientific understanding must be in the form of theory, which goes beyond and beneath data to explain its causal character.
For example, a historical description of aggregative relations, say between the inflation rate and the unemployment rate (as in Phillips Curve), would not give any sense of what is causing what and exactly how, and hence would not be a source of scientific or theoretical knowledge.
The need is to find an explanation of the observed events, and the explanation must be provided in terms of the market process in which various individuals act differently.

The Austrian Schools’ founder Menger and most other major authors did use mathematics and data when they had reason to do so.
The misgiving is that the School disapproves of mathematics.
No, it does not.
It disapproves of what is in its view an improper use of mathematics that has no explanatory value.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7477830" end="120" start="75">The Austrian School or Austrian School of Economics, also known as the “Vienna School,” bases its foundation for economic reason upon Natural Systems -- with it's premises running contrary to Keynesian theory.
Austrians correctly identify that production drives an economy -- not consumption.
Because if consumption (or demand) drove an economy, then anyone could consume their way to prosperity -- a practical impossibility.
Also, if demand drove an economy, then the Continent of Africa would be quite wealthy, because there is plenty of demand there.
What is missing in Africa is the production.
Therefore, Africa remains an impoverished Continent, while China prospers because of its high-level of production.

Austrians believe in a laissez-faire approach in which consumers send signals throughout the marketplace to producers by means of their expenditures.
Participants in the marketplace can only buy as a result of their excess production.
So in the case of a baker, he must produce extra loaves of bread to sell, so he can buy something he needs that will improve his well-being --- maybe nails to build his house.
Each participant produces something that the market wants in order to meet his own specific needs.
If he cannot produce something of value to the marketplace, then he will not prosper.

Similarly, Austrians rightfully view that savings(consumption differed) are essential for economic prosperity as excess production is directed into improvements that expand the levels of production -- whereby, creating more wealth.
Deflation -- or the increased value of money -- is the natural by-product as the levels of production expand.
Everyone within the economy benefits as prices drop and the buying power of money increases.
This reality is contrary to current thought within the United States, and most of the world, as Central Banks destroy a nation's wealth through Inflation -- expansion of the money supply -- that in turn reduces the value of the money.
Deflation benefits savers, while Inflation benefits borrowers.
So, it is clear that the US Federal Government is the beneficiary of Inflation within the US as it destroys the wealth of its citizens through the ravages of Inflation.

Austrians believe that markets operate properly whenever the signals of the marketplace can function unfettered by government.
Contrary to Keynesian thought, Austrians see the interference of Government as being the primary destroyer of wealth and skewing of the Marketplace.
Government does not contribute to a nation's wealth, but depletes its wealth.
So, similar to the outlook of the Founding Fathers (of the United States), Austrians view "less government" as being better for a healthier and more productive economy.
Because government does not produce anything, it depletes a nation's wealth as it takes valuable resources away and squanders those resources on special interest groups and political favortism -- at the expense of the producers.

Austrians understand that prices are set at the margin by the participants within the Market, as goods are produced and auctioned to the highest bidder.
Prices change in reaction to the principles of supply and demand.
Production increases the total goods available and reduces prices (over the long-run).
Inflation is the creation of either excess money or credit, with the net result usually being an increase in prices (but not always).
Many times, the symptoms of Inflation occur as assets increase in price (and apparent, but nominal value) -- often viewed positively due to the false premise that the nominal value increases -- or the "wealth effect".
But in truth, the price increases due to expansion of the money supply -- or Inflation.
And while the nominal price of an asset may appear to increase, it requires more currency of lower value to buy the asset.

Austrian thinking is predicated upon individuals acting in their own best interest and the composite reactions of many becoming the basis for economic activity.
Austrian's cite that wealth is created by production.
And wealth is increased by increasing the levels of production.
In other words, oil is not very usefull by itself.
But refining oil into gasoline (at the 2nd level of production) makes oil more valuable.
As the levels of production expand, then even more wealth is produced by the value imparted through the higher levels of production.
Oil is used to make plastics and plastics are used to make parts for automobiles.
In each instance, higher levels of production create more useful products and hence, more wealth.
At the other end of the spectrum, economies collapse with excessive consumption and the ravages of Inflation, caused by Fiat Currency and an expansion of the currency.

The Austrian School advocates adherence to methodological individualism that is logically derived from basic principles of human action -- that are based upon the way humans react to actual value and their desire to improve their conditions.
Savings becomes the bedrock of Austrian thinking, because savings (excess production) drive an economy.
Austrian's correctly state that "savings become the engine of an economy."
It is only through the use of excess savings that improvements can occur that increase the levels of production, and hence, the wealth of a nation.

Alongside the formal approach, often called praxeology, the school has traditionally advocated an interpretive approach to history.
Proponents of praxeological method hold that it allows for the discovery of economic laws valid for all human action.
The Austrian School has been historically influential due to its emphasis on the creative phase (i.e. the time element) of economic productivity and its questioning of the basis of the behavioral theory underlying neoclassical economics.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7823237" end="131" start="120">Inflation is one of the three means by which it can fund its activities, the other two being taxing and borrowing.
Therefore, the actual cause of inflation is government's need to create new money.
The money created then goes to fund various government programs, for instance welfare and warfare.

Given that in almost all modern economies the central government "borrows" money from the central bank to fund deficit spending, in reality there are only two ways a modern government can fund its activities: taxing the populace, or borrowing (either from the central bank, private savers or overseas investors).
The issuance of debt-free money from the central government ended in the United States with the cessation of silver certificates.
Austrian economists assert that inherently damaging and ineffective central bank policies are the predominant cause of most business cycles, as they tend to set "artificial" interest rates too low for too long, resulting in excessive credit creation, speculative "bubbles" and "artificially" low savings.

According to the Austrian business cycle theory, the business cycle unfolds in the following way.
Low interest rates tend to stimulate borrowing from the banking system.
This expansion of credit causes an expansion of the supply of money, through the money creation process in a fractional reserve banking system.
This in turn leads to an unsustainable "monetary boom" during which the "artificially stimulated" borrowing seeks out diminishing investment opportunities.
This boom results in widespread malinvestments, causing capital resources to be misallocated into areas which would not attract investment if the money supply remained stable.</entry>
  <entry author_id="9659349" end="155" start="131">Murray Rothbard has argued that the scientific method of the natural sciences is not applicable to the social sciences, and has rejected any attempt of using mathematics in the study of economics calling it "scientism".
Rothbard has argued that the use of the wrong methodology is what is truly unscientific.
Economic historian Bruce Caldwell has described Ludwig von Mises as the mid-20th century's "archetypal 'unscientific' economist."
Austrians argue that empirical data in and of itself cannot explain anything, which in turn implies that empirical data cannot falsify a theory.

Krugman has been critical of the Austrian business cycle theory, which he dubs the "hangover theory".
Austrians believe that booms and busts are caused by the misallocation of resources from consumption to investment; entrepreneurs invest funds in sectors inconsistent with consumers' buying preferences, causing booms and leading to excess capacity.
Busts occur when resources reallocated back into consumption sectors.
Krugman argues that this theory does not explain unemployment.
Since total spending is equal to total income, the reallocation of resources during recessions would increase employment in consumption sections.
In addition, the initial booms also cause resource reallocation, which implies an increase in unemployment under the Austrians' theory of the business cycle.
Krugman also points out that recessions impact productive workers as well, and notes that spending declines in almost all sectors of an economy during recessions.

Jeffery Hummel offers some solutions to Krugman's argument, but then argues that none are satisfactory.
First Hummel cites Hayek's solution in Prices and Production, where Hayek argues that the decrease in spending in investment sectors creates unemployment, because a decline in investment spending causes some laborers to return to the consumption sector where demand is increasing.
The remaining laborers are unable to complete the industrial projects causing them to be laid-off.
There are, however, too many of these jobs created from entrepreneurs' investments to be accepted into the consumption sectors of the economy, because consumption projects, Hayek argues, can be completed more quickly.
Hummel dismisses this argument on two fronts.
First he notes that this explanation makes many "bizarre" assumptions about the investment and consumption sectors of an economy, and then he argues that there must be some low wage at which these industrial works can be reabsorbed into the work force.
Hummel provides a second solution to Krugman's argument.
He claims that the labor asymmetry can be explained in terms of a change in real wages.
However, this solution is inconsistent with the Austrians' explanation of the business cycle as being caused by a maldistribution of labor.
Krugman also points out that Hummel's second solution amounts to an acceptance of Keynesian principals.

In addition, Hummel argues that the Austrian explanation of the business cycle fails on empirical grounds.
In particular, he points out that investment spending has decreased but has remained positive in all recessions where there are data, except for the Great Depression.
This casts doubt on the notion that recessions are caused by a reallocation of resources from industrial production to consumption, since the Austrian business cycle theory implies that net investment should be below zero during recessions.</entry>
  <entry author_id="9659349" end="199" start="155">Thomas Mayer has said the Austrian School has advocated a rejection of scientific methods which involve directly using empirical data in the development of (falsifiable) theories; application of empirical data is fundamental to the scientific method.
Murray Rothbard has argued that the scientific method of the natural sciences is not applicable to the social sciences, and has rejected any attempt of using mathematics in the study of economics calling it "scientism".
Rothbard has argued that the use of the wrong methodology is what is truly unscientific.
Economic historian Bruce Caldwell has described Ludwig von Mises as the mid-20th century's "archetypal 'unscientific' economist."
Austrians argue that empirical data in and of itself cannot explain anything, which in turn implies that empirical data cannot falsify a theory.
Paul A. Samuelson has said such rejections of empirical evidence in economics has led to the Austrian School being dismissed within mainstream economics.

Economist Bryan Caplan has noted that, "what prevents Austrian economists from getting more publications in mainstream journals is that their papers rarely use mathematics or econometrics."
Austrian theories are not formulated in formal mathematical form, instead they use mainly verbal arguments based on, what proponents claim, are self-evident axioms.
Mainstream economists believe that this makes Austrian theories too imprecisely defined to be clearly used to explain or predict real world events.
More generally, Paul Krugman has noted that the Austrians' failure to use models has left them unaware of holes in their own thinking.

Bryan Caplan has argued that Austrian economists have often misunderstood modern economics, causing them to overstate their differences with it.
For example, many Austrian economists object to the use of cardinal utility in microeconomic theory; however, microeconomic theorists go to great pains to show that their results hold for all strictly monotonic transformations of utility, and so are true for purely ordinal preferences.
The result is that conclusions about utility preferences hold no matter what values are assigned to them.
Another general criticism of the school is that although it claims to highlight shortcomings in traditional methodology, it fails to provide viable alternatives for making positive contributions to economic theory.

Economist Jeffrey Sachs observes that among developed countries, those with high rates of taxation and high social welfare spending perform better on most measures of economic performance compared to countries with low rates of taxation and low social outlays.
He concludes that Friedrich Hayek was wrong to argue that high levels of government spending harms an economy, and "a generous social-welfare state is not a road to serfdom but rather to fairness, economic equality and international competitiveness."
Austrian school economist Sudha Shenoy countered by claiming that countries with large public sectors have grown more slowly.

Krugman has been critical of the Austrian business cycle theory, which he dubs the "hangover theory".
Austrians believe that many booms and busts are caused by the misallocation of resources from consumption to investment; entrepreneurs invest funds in sectors inconsistent with consumers' buying preferences, causing booms and leading to excess capacity.
Busts occur when resources reallocated back into consumption sectors.
Krugman argues that this theory does not explain unemployment.
Since total spending is equal to total income, the reallocation of resources during recessions would increase employment in consumption sections.
In addition, the initial booms also cause resource reallocation, which implies an increase in unemployment under the Austrians' theory of the business cycle.
Krugman also points out that recessions impact productive workers as well, and notes that spending declines in almost all sectors of an economy during recessions.
In response to Krugman's argument, Austrian economist David Gordon has argued that prices on consumption goods may go up as a result of the investment bust, which could mean that the amount spent on consumption could increase even though the quantity of goods consumed has not.

Jeffery Hummel offers a solution to Krugman's argument, but then argues that none are satisfactory.
Hummel cites Hayek's solution in Prices and Production, where Hayek argues that the decrease in spending in investment sectors creates unemployment, because a decline in investment spending causes some laborers to return to the consumption sector where demand is increasing.
The remaining laborers are unable to complete the industrial projects causing them to be laid-off.
There are, however, too many of these jobs created from entrepreneurs' investments to be accepted into the consumption sectors of the economy, because consumption projects, Hayek argues, can be completed more quickly.
Hummel dismisses this argument on two fronts.
First he notes that this explanation makes many "bizarre" assumptions about the investment and consumption sectors of an economy, and then he argues that there must be some low wage at which these industrial works can be reabsorbed into the work force.

In addition, Hummel argues that the Austrian explanation of the business cycle fails on empirical grounds.
In particular, he points out that investment spending has decreased but has remained positive in all recessions where there are data, except for the Great Depression.
This casts doubt on the notion that recessions are caused by a reallocation of resources from industrial production to consumption, since the Austrian business cycle theory implies that net investment should be below zero during recessions.

Mainstream economists argue that the Austrians' theory of the business cycle requires bankers and investors to exhibit a kind of irrationality, because their theory requires bankers to be regularly fooled into making unprofitable investments by temporarily low interest rates.
In response, Austrian economists Carilli and Dempster have argued that a banker or firm loses market share if it does not borrow or loan at a magnitude consistent with current interest rates, regardless of whether rates are below their natural levels.
Thus businesses are forced to operate as though rates were set appropriately, because the consequence of a single entity deviating would be a loss of business.

According to economic historians, economies have experienced less severe boom-bust cycles after World War II, because governments have addressed the problem of economic recessions.
This has especially been true after central banks were granted independence in the 1980s, and started using monetary policy to stabilize the business cycle, an event known as The Great Moderation.
Critics have also argued that, as the Austrian business cycle theory points to the actions of fractional-reserve banks and central banks to explain the business cycles, it fails to explain the severity of business cycles before the establishment of the Federal Reserve in 1913.
For example, the Panic of 1873 initiated the Long Depression in the United States and much of Europe.
There were also severe market crashes in the United States of magnitude comparable to the 1929 crash in 1869, 1884, 1896, 1901, and 1907, though there was no central bank or national monetary policy in the US during these crises.
In fact, the movement to establish central banking in the United States was in part a response to the business cycle, particularly the Panic of 1907.
Austrian School historian Thomas Woods argues that the crashes were caused by various privately-owned banks with state charters that issued paper money, supposedly convertible to gold, in amounts greatly exceeding their gold reserves.</entry>
  <entry author_id="98127" end="248" start="199">Critics argue that Austrian economics generally lacks scientific rigor, rejects the scientific method, and rejects the use of empirical data.
Thomas Mayer has said the Austrian School has advocated a rejection of scientific methods which involve directly using empirical data in the development of (falsifiable) theories; application of empirical data is fundamental to the scientific method.
Murray Rothbard has argued that the scientific method of the natural sciences is not applicable to the social sciences, and has rejected any attempt of using mathematics in the study of economics calling it "scientism".
Rothbard has argued that the use of the wrong methodology is what is truly unscientific.
Economic historian Bruce Caldwell has described Ludwig von Mises as the mid-20th century's "archetypal 'unscientific' economist."
Austrians argue that empirical data in and of itself cannot explain anything, which in turn implies that empirical data cannot falsify a theory.
Paul A. Samuelson has said such rejections of empirical evidence in economics has led to the Austrian School being dismissed within mainstream economics.

Economist Bryan Caplan has noted that, "what prevents Austrian economists from getting more publications in mainstream journals is that their papers rarely use mathematics or econometrics."
Austrian theories are not formulated in formal mathematical form, instead they use mainly verbal arguments based on, what proponents claim, are self-evident axioms.
Mainstream economists believe that this makes Austrian theories too imprecisely defined to be clearly used to explain or predict real world events.
More generally, Paul Krugman has noted that the Austrians' failure to use models has left them unaware of holes in their own thinking.

Bryan Caplan has argued that Austrian economists have often misunderstood modern economics, causing them to overstate their differences with it.
For example, many Austrian economists object to the use of cardinal utility in microeconomic theory; however, microeconomic theorists go to great pains to show that their results hold for all strictly monotonic transformations of utility, and so are true for purely ordinal preferences.
The result is that conclusions about utility preferences hold no matter what values are assigned to them.
Another general criticism of the school is that although it claims to highlight shortcomings in traditional methodology, it fails to provide viable alternatives for making positive contributions to economic theory.

Economist Jeffrey Sachs observes that among developed countries, those with high rates of taxation and high social welfare spending perform better on most measures of economic performance compared to countries with low rates of taxation and low social outlays.
He concludes that Friedrich Hayek was wrong to argue that high levels of government spending harms an economy, and "a generous social-welfare state is not a road to serfdom but rather to fairness, economic equality and international competitiveness."
Austrian school economist Sudha Shenoy countered by claiming that countries with large public sectors have grown more slowly.

Krugman has been critical of the Austrian business cycle theory, which he dubs the "hangover theory".
Austrians believe that many booms and busts are caused by the misallocation of resources from consumption to investment; entrepreneurs invest funds in sectors inconsistent with consumers' buying preferences, causing booms and leading to excess capacity.
Busts occur when resources reallocated back into consumption sectors.
Krugman argues that this theory does not explain unemployment.
Since total spending is equal to total income, the reallocation of resources during recessions would increase employment in consumption sections.
In addition, the initial booms also cause resource reallocation, which implies an increase in unemployment under the Austrians' theory of the business cycle.
Krugman also points out that recessions impact productive workers as well, and notes that spending declines in almost all sectors of an economy during recessions.
In response, Austrian economist David Gordon has argued that prices on consumption goods may go up as a result of the investment bust, which could mean that the amount spent on consumption could increase even though the quantity of goods consumed has not.

Jeffery Hummel points out Hayek's solution in Prices and Production to Krugman's argument, but then argues that it is unsatisfactory.
Hayek argues that the decrease in spending in investment sectors creates unemployment, because a decline in investment spending causes some laborers to return to the consumption sector where demand is increasing.
The result is that there is an insufficient amount of laborers left to complete industrial projects, which causes them to be laid-off.
Hayek continues by arguing that there are too many industrial workers laid-off to be accepted into the consumption sectors of the economy, because consumption projects can be completed more quickly.
Hummel dismisses this argument on two fronts.
He notes that this explanation makes peculiar assumptions about demand curves for labor.

In addition, Hummel argues that the Austrian explanation of the business cycle fails on empirical grounds.
In particular, he points out that investment spending has decreased but has remained positive in all recessions where there are data, except for the Great Depression.
This casts doubt on the notion that recessions are caused by a reallocation of resources from industrial production to consumption, since the Austrian business cycle theory implies that net investment should be below zero during recessions.
In 1969, Nobel Laureate Milton Friedman, after examining the history of business cycles in the US, concluded that "The Hayek-Mises explanation of the business cycle is contradicted by the evidence.
It is, I believe, false."
He analyzed the issue using newer data in 1993, and again reached the same conclusions.
In 2001, Austrian economist James P. Keeler stated that the hypotheses of the theory are consistent with empirical evidence.

Mainstream economists argue that the Austrians' theory of the business cycle requires bankers and investors to exhibit a kind of irrationality, because their theory requires bankers to be regularly fooled into making unprofitable investments by temporarily low interest rates.
In response, Austrian economists Carilli and Dempster have argued that a banker or firm loses market share if it does not borrow or loan at a magnitude consistent with current interest rates, regardless of whether rates are below their natural levels.
Thus businesses are forced to operate as though rates were set appropriately, because the consequence of a single entity deviating would be a loss of business.

According to economic historians, economies have experienced less severe boom-bust cycles after World War II, because governments have addressed the problem of economic recessions.
This has especially been true after central banks were granted independence in the 1980s, and started using monetary policy to stabilize the business cycle, an event known as The Great Moderation.
Critics have also argued that, as the Austrian business cycle theory points to the actions of fractional-reserve banks and central banks to explain the business cycles, it fails to explain the severity of business cycles before the establishment of the Federal Reserve in 1913.
For example, the Panic of 1873 initiated the Long Depression in the United States and much of Europe.
There were also severe market crashes in the United States of magnitude comparable to the 1929 crash in 1869, 1884, 1896, 1901, and 1907, though there was no central bank or national monetary policy in the US during these crises.
In fact, the movement to establish central banking in the United States was in part a response to the business cycle, particularly the Panic of 1907.
Austrian School historian Thomas Woods argues that the crashes were caused by various privately-owned banks with state charters that issued paper money, supposedly convertible to gold, in amounts greatly exceeding their gold reserves.</entry>
</article>
