<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1034" title="Ancient Pueblo Peoples" authors="2" lines="75">
  <entry author_id="194861" end="22" start="0">The Ancient Pueblo were one of four major prehistoric archaeology|archaeological traditions of the American Southwest.
In relation to the other cultures, these people occupied the northeast quadrant of the area.
The Ancient Pueblo homeland centers on the Colorado Plateau, but extends from central New Mexico, on the east to Southern Nevada, on the west.
Areas of southern Nevada, Utah and Colorado form the northern boundary, while the southern edge is defined by the Colorado and Little Colorado rivers in Arizona and the Rio Puerco and Rio Grande in New Mexico.
However, evidence of Ancient Pueblo culture has been found extending east onto the American Great Plains, in areas near the Cimarron and Pecos rivers and in the Galisteo Basin.

Topography and resources within this large region varies greatly.
The plateau regions are generally high, with elevations ranging from 4500 to 8500 feet (1350-1600 meters).
Extensive horizontal mesas are capped by sedimentary formations and support woodlands of junipers, pinyon, ponderosa pines, and yellow pines, each favoring different elevations.
Wind and water erosion have created steep walled canyons, and sculpted windows and bridges out of the sandstone landscape.
In areas with harder stone, such as shale or limestone, rock overhangs formed.
These overhangs were favored sites for shelters and building sites.
The low range country in areas such as the San Juan, Gallup and Albuquerque basins is low and arid, supporting desert grasses and shrubs.
Streams in these regions allow the growth of willows and reeds, and were utilized by the Ancient Pueblo for agriculture.
Mountains in the region reach are as tall as 12,000 feet (3650 meters), and provided timber, game, minerals, and stone used for flaked tools.

In the Southwest, access to water was essential.
All areas of the Ancient Pueblo homeland suffered from periods of drought and wind and water erosion.
Summer rains could be undependable and often arrived in destructive thunderstorms.
While the amount of winter snowfall varied greatly, the Ancient Pueblo depended on the snow for most of their water.
Snow melt allowed the spring germination of seeds, both wild and agricultural.
Where sandstone layers overlay shale, snow melt can accumulate and create seeps and springs, which the Ancient Pueblo used as water sources.
Snow also fed the smaller, more predictable rivers, such as the Chinle, Animas, Jemez and Taos rivers.
The larger rivers were less important to the ancient culture, as smaller streams were more easily diverted or controlled for irrigation.</entry>
  <entry author_id="194861" end="40" start="22">Archaeological cultural units such as "Anasazi", Hohokam, Patayan or Mogollon are used by archaeologists to define material culture similarities and differences that may identify prehistoric socio-cultural units, equivalent to modern societies or peoples.
The names and divisions are classification devices based on theoretical perspectives, analytical methods and data available at the time of analysis and publication.
They are subject to change, not only on the basis of new information and discoveries, but also as attitudes and perspectives change within the scientific community.
It should not be assumed that an archaeological division or culture unit corresponds to a particular language group or to a socio-political entity such as a tribe.
The term "Anasazi" was established in archaeological terminology through the Pecos Classification system in 1927.
Archaeologist Linda Cordell discussed the word's etymology and use: Some modern Pueblo peoples object to the use of the term Anasazi, although there is still controversy among them on a native alternative.
The modern Hopi use the word "Hisatsinom" in preference to Anasazi.
However, Navajo Nation Historic Preservation Department (NNHPD) spokesperson Ronald Maldonado has indicated the Navajo do not favor use of the term "Ancestral Puebloan."
In fact, reports submitted for review by NNHPD are rejected if they include use of the term.
When making use of modern cultural divisions in the American Southwest, it is important to understand three limitations in the current conventions:  Defining cultural groups, such as the Ancient Pueblo peoples, tends to create an image of territories separated by clear-cut boundaries, like modern state lines.
These simply did not exist.
Prehistoric people traded, worshipped and collaborated most often with other nearby groups with episodic warfare.
Cultural differences should therefore be understood as “clinal”, "increasing gradually as the distance separating groups also increases."
(Plog, p.
72.)
Departures from the expected pattern may occur because of unidentified social or political situations or because of geographic barriers.
In the Southwest, mountain ranges, rivers and, most obviously, the Grand Canyon can be significant barriers for human communities, likely reducing the frequency of contact with other groups.
Current opinion holds that the closer cultural similarity between the Mogollon and Ancient Pueblos and their greater differences from the Hohokam and Patayan is due to both the geography and the variety of climate zones in the Southwest.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11704430" end="75" start="40">The Ancestral Puebloan People crafted a very unique and isoteric Architecture and Planned Community Spaces, that are both advanced in their stonework and beautiful to look upon today, as they were hundreds of years ago.
The ancient population centers such as Chaco Canyon (outside Crownpoint, NM) and Mesa Verde (outside Cortex, CO), to which the Ancestral Puebloan are renowed for, consisted of apartment-like complexes and structures made from stone, adobe mud, and other local material.
Each were influenced by themselves and design details from other cultures as far away as modern-day Mexico.
In their day, these ancient towns and cities were usually multi-storied and multi-purposed buildings surrounding open plazas and viewsheds and were occupied by hundreds to thousands of Ancestral Puebloan People.
These population complexes hosted cultural and civic events and infrastructure that supported a vast outlying region hundreds of miles away linked by transportation roadways.

Constructed well before 1492 A.D., these Ancestral Puebloan towns and villages in the Southwestern U.S. were located in various defensive positions, for example, on high steep mesas such as at Mesa Verde or predent-day Acoma "Sky City" Pueblo, in New Mexico.
Earlier than AD 900 and progressing past the 13th century, The population complexes were a major center of culture for the Ancient Pueblo Peoples.α In Chaco Canyon, Chacoan developers quarried sandstone blocks and hauled timber from great distances, assembling 15 major complexes which remained the largest buildings in North America until the 19th century.
Evidence of archaeoastronomy at Chaco has been proposed, with the Sun Dagger petroglyph at Fajada Butte a popular example.
Many Chacoan buildings may have been aligned to capture the solar and lunar cycles, requiring generations of astronomical observations and centuries of skillfully coordinated construction.
Climate change is thought to have led to the emigration of Chacoans and the eventual abandonment of the canyon, beginning with a 50-year drought in 1130.

Immense complexes known as "Great Houses" embodied worship at Chaco.
As architectural forms evolved and centuries passed, the houses kept several core traits.
Most apparent is their sheer bulk; complexes averaged more than 200 rooms each, and some enclosed up to 700 rooms.
Individual rooms were substantial in size, with higher ceilings than Anasazi works of preceding periods.
They were well-planned: vast sections or wings erected were finished in a single stage, rather than in increments.
Houses generally faced the south, and plaza areas were almost always girt with edifices of sealed-off rooms or high walls.
Houses often stood four or five stories tall, with single-story rooms facing the plaza; room blocks were terraced to allow the tallest sections to compose the pueblo's rear edifice.
Rooms were often organized into suites, with front rooms larger than rear, interior, and storage rooms or areas.

Ceremonial structures known as kivas were built in proportion to the number of rooms in a pueblo.
One small kiva was built for roughly every 29 rooms.
Nine complexes each hosted an oversized Great Kiva, each up to 63 ft in diameter.
T-shaped doorways and stone lintels marked all Chacoan kivas.
Though simple and compound walls were often used, Great Houses were primarily constructed of core-and-veneer walls: two parallel load-bearing walls comprising dressed, flat sandstone blocks bound in clay mortar were erected.
Gaps between walls were packed with rubble, forming the wall's core.
Walls were then covered in a veneer of small sandstone pieces, which were pressed into a layer of binding mud.
These surfacing stones were often placed in distinctive patterns.
The Chacoan structures altogether required the wood of 200,000 coniferous trees, mostly hauled—on foot—from mountain ranges up to 70 mi away.&lt;ref name="Raynolds_2005_1062

Mesa Verde is best known for a large number of well preserved cliff dwellings, houses built in shallow caves and under rock overhangs along the canyon walls.
The structures contained within these alcoves were mostly blocks of hard sandstone, held together and plastered with adobe mortar.
Specific constructions had many similarities, but were generally unique in form due to the individual topography of different alcoves along the canyon walls.
In marked contrast to earlier constructions and villages on top of the mesas, the cliff dwellings of Mesa Verde reflected a region-wide trend towards the aggregation of growing regional populations into close, highly defensible quarters during the 13th century.

Not all of the people in the region lived in cliff dwellings; many colonized the canyon rims and slopes in multi-family structures that grew to unprecedented size as populations swelled.
Decorative motifs for these sandstone/mortar constructions, both cliff dwellings and non-, included T-shaped windows and doors.
This has been taken by some archaeologists, such as Stephen Lekson (1999), as evidence of the continuing reach of the Chaco Canyon elite system, which had seemingly collapsed around a century before.
Other researchers see these motifs as part of a more generalized Puebloan style and/or spiritual significance, rather than evidence of a continuing specific elite socioeconomic system.</entry>
</article>
