<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1051" title="Alexis Carrel" authors="2" lines="49">
  <entry author_id="361801" end="16" start="0">Rudolf Walter sees Carrel as a primary (if unwitting) influence on the origin of Islamism.
Quoting from his article: (t)he superficial commonalities between Carrel and Qutb are plain: we meet the medical man's elite in a "scientific monastery" as Qutb's "avant garde," and the Carrel's "biological classes" are Qutb's "belief classes."
Whether "civilization" (Carrel) or "barbarism" (Qutb) -- neither are "worthy of us," because they contradict "our true nature" (Carrel) or Qutb's "good, healthy nature."
Both are quite in agreement in their goal to reconcile knowledge and belief.

"The decisive affinities lie deeper, though.
Qutb cites no author aside from the Koran as often and as extensively as Carrel.
(emphasis added) What fascinated Qutb about Carrel was, as Islamic Studies scholar Ibrahim M. Abu-Rabi wrote in his 1996 book "Intellectual Origins of Islamic Resurgence," first of all his view of humanity "which he relies on more than the Koran."
Second, Qutb follows Carrel's method.
The pious doctor complains that "man, this whole," this unique, complex being, is being subdivided and torn apart by social reality and science...
The exclusive concentration on the material nature of man had the effect of repressing his spiritual side.

Qutb follows Carrel in making "human nature" the condition and measure of all thought and action.
Because "human nature" is simultaneously posited as God-given, both immunize "human nature" against criticism, because God answers queries as little as "nature" does objections.
The core of Qutb's supposed Middle Eastern Islamism is formed by a naturalistic logical error that is deeply rooted in European philosophy... Carrel writes: "The goal of life is to follow the laws of life.
We decipher these laws from our bodies and our souls, not from philosophical systems and concepts."
Thus ethical norms ("laws of life") are derived directly from biological facts and psychological diagnoses.
Translated to Qutb's language, human freedom and thus a free, varied society are not possible, only obedience to the law of God.</entry>
  <entry author_id="4847962" end="49" start="16">In 1935, Carrel published a best-selling book titled L'Homme, cet inconnu (Man, The Unknown) which advocated, in part, that mankind could better itself by following the guidance of an elite group of intellectuals, and by implementing a regime of enforced eugenics.
Sociologist Roger Caillois quoted and paraphrased L'Homme, cet inconnu in The Edge of Surrealism: " '(p)resent-day proletarians owe their status to inherited intellectual and physical defects' (sancta simplicitas).
And he suggests that this state of affairs should be accentuated through appropriate measures, so as to correlate social and biological inequalities more precisely.
Society would then be directed by a hereditary aristocracy composed of descendants from the Crusaders, the heroes of the Revolution, the great criminals, the financial and industrial magnates" (p. 360).

Carrel advocated the use of gas chambers to rid humanity of "inferior stock", thus endorsing the scientific racism discourse.
His endorsement of this idea began in the mid-1930s, prior to the Nazi implementation of such practices in Germany.
In the 1936 German introduction of his book, at the publishers request, he added the following praise of the Nazi regime which did not appear in the editions in other languages:

Carrel also wrote:  In 1937, Carrel joined Jean Coutrot’s Centre d’Etudes des Problèmes Humains - Coutrot’s aim was to develop what he called an "economic humanism" through "collective thinking."
In 1941, through connections to the cabinet of Marshal Philippe Pétain (specifically, French industrial physicians André Gros and Jacques Ménétrier) he went on to advocate for the creation of the Fondation Française pour l’Etude des Problèmes Humains (French Foundation for the Study of Human Problems) which was created by decree of the Vichy regime in 1941, and where he served as 'regent'.
The foundation was at the origin of the October 11, 1946 law, enacted by the Provisional Government of the French Republic (GPRF), which institutionalized the field of occupational medicine.
It worked on demographics (Robert Gessain, Paul Vincent, Jean Bourgeois-Pichat), on economics, (François Perroux), on nutrition (Jean Sutter), on habitation (Jean Merlet) and on the first opinion polls (Jean Stoetzel).
"The foundation was chartered as a public institution under the joint supervision of the ministries of finance and public health.
It was given financial autonomy and a budget of forty million francs—roughly one franc per inhabitant—a true luxury considering the burdens imposed by the German Occupation on the nation’s resources.
By way of comparison, the whole Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS) was given a budget of fifty million francs."

According to Gwen Terrenoire, writing in Eugenics in France (1913-1941): a review of research findings, "The foundation was a pluridisciplinary centre that employed around 300 researchers (mainly statisticians, psychologists, physicians) from the summer of 1942 to the end of the autumn of 1944.
After the liberation of Paris, Carrel was suspended by the Minister of Health; he died in November 1944, but the Foundation itself was "purged", only to reappear in a short time as the Institut national d’études démographiques (INED) that is still active."
Although Carrel himself died on November 5, 1944, most members of his team did move to the INED, which was led by famous demographist Alfred Sauvy, who coined the expression "Third World".
Others joined Robert Debré's "Institut national d'hygiène" (National Hygiene Institute), which later became the INSERM.
Some left-wing scholars, such as Lucien Bonnafé (who belongs to the French Communist Party), Patrick Tort and Max Lafont have accused Carrel of responsibility for the execution of thousands of mentally ill or impaired patients under Vichy.
They argue that this policy was inspired by Carrel's advocacy of eugenics.
Carrel's association with Vichy, and the harshness of his advocacy for eugenics, has led to his descent from fame to obscurity.
In recent years, Jean-Marie le Pen, leader of the far-right Front National party ("National Front"), has become an advocate for Carrel, referring to him as "the first environmentalist, or, if you will, the first modern ecologist, precisely because he committed himself to defining the relationships of natural harmony.".
His writings on eugenics are studied "avidly in the training camps of the National Front".

In the 1990s, the attention the National Front's support brought to Carrel's fascist associations and controversial views created a series of controversies with respect to streets and institutions named in honor of Carrel.
Over 20 French cities and towns, including Paris, renamed streets previously named for Carrel.
The controversy came to a head in Lyon, the city next to his birthplace, where he studied medicine.
One of the four medicine faculties of the university Claude Bernard - Lyon I had been named in his honor in 1968.
Lyon libération questioned the wisdom of this.
In response to this, in May 1995, the Palais des Congrès of Lyon hosted a conference on Carrel and scientific racism at which several of the participants accused the inquiry commission of whitewashing the controversial scientist.
In early 1996, after five years of embarrassing publicity, the governing board of the University of Lyon decided to rename its school of medicine after René Laënnec, inventor of the stethoscope."

In the United States as well as in France, the 1990s were not kind to Carrel's reputation.
In an interview for PBS' The American Experience, historian Arthur Schlesinger, Jr. blamed Carrel for Charles Lindbergh's increasing racism in the 1930s.
Schlesinger stated in response to a question concerning the source of Lindbergh's beliefs on this subject: "I suppose he got a lot of it from Alexis Carrel, the French biologist who had a kind of racial mysticism of a sort."</entry>
</article>
