<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1088" title="Azerbaijani Armed Forces" authors="3" lines="297">
  <entry author_id="391474" end="21" start="0">Turkey is the closest allie of Azerbaijan, the two countries cooporate on multiple departements and issues.
Azerbaijan and Turkey oftenly exchange soldiers for cultural and military objectives.
Its been reported that Turkey has over a thousand soldiers and resources stationed in Azerbaijan Turkey has provided Azerbaijan with professional military training and resources.
Almost all Azerbaijani officers are trained by the Turkish Armed Forces.
The training is conducted in Azerbaijani territory.
In 2005 Turkey has stated that Azerbaijani troops are just as professional and well prepared as the Turkish troops and that Azerbaijan is now ready to hold excersize and train its troops on a professional level.
During the construction of the Baku-Tbilisi-Ceyhan pipeline it was feared that terrorists could target the pipeline.
Because of this Turkey organized a military anti-terrorism excersize with Azerbaijan and Georgia in 2005.
The excersize is planned to continue on to the end of 2006.
The anti-terrorism programm has a budget of about $17 million in Azerbaijan, of which 7 million is being invested in the Baku-Tbilisi-Ceyhan pipeline.
The Section 907 of the Freedom Support Act bans US government’s direct assistance to the Azerbaijani government, the Azerbaijani goverment has put alot of effort in continuing to improve the relations between the two countries.
In 2006 the president of Azerbaijan, Ilham Aliev visited the U.S. and came to the conculsion that the Section 907 may be repealed soon http://www.azernews.net/eng/gizli/view.php?d=14500.
But the United States remains one of the closest allies of Azerbaijan.
In 2003, the U.S. goverment announced its plans to hold military programs in the Caucasus region.
So far the U.S. has provided Azerbaijan with a military aid of $9 million.
The U.S. also provided Azerbaijani military with the latest radar technology and 3 navy boats in 2006.
The relations remain tie, Donald Rumsfeld had visited Azerbaijan 5 times in 2005.

Its been widly rumoured that the U.S. might use Nahkhcivan airport, in Azerbaijan as the main position to attack Iran.
So far the Azerbaijani politician, including the Azerbaijani president have denied this.
The rumour continues and Iran and Azerbaijan are having some discussion on this.
Azerbaijan is participating in NATO's Partnership for Peace Program and has received assistence from the U.S. and Turkey.</entry>
  <entry author_id="391474" end="32" start="21">There are USSR-made MiG-21, MiG-23, MiG-25, Su-24 and Su-25, as well as fourth generation of MiG-29 purchased from Ukraine in 2006, Soviet-made Il-76.
And military aircrafts, USSR-inherited far range Tu-16 bombardment aircrafts in the Azerbaijan Air Force fleet now.
Azerbaijan is holding talks with Pakistan to purchase JF-17 Thunder aircrafts.

In June 2008, Azerbaijan acquired six Orbiter and Aerostar unmanned aircrafts produced by Israel’s Aeronautics Company.
These aircrafts were demonstrated for the first time during the military parade in Baku in 2008.
According to the Israeli newspapers, Azerbaijan is holding the talks for purchasing Hermes and Heron-TP unmanned crafts now.

Azerbaijani military companies as IGLAM SPE and RPE IGLIM also is developing its own aircraft industry both for civilian and for military purposes in Azerbaijan.
The Azerbaijan Defense Industry is cooperating with Russian, Ukrainian, Turkish and Czech companies.
The helicopter fleet contains mostly the USSR- and Russia-made Mi-26, Mi-8 and Mi-6 helicopters.
Last year Azerbaijan signed a deal with Russia to purchase Mi-171 helicopters.
Alongside with the Azerbaijan Air Force, the Border Guard, Interior Guard and Ministry of Emergency Situations have their helicopter squadrons.</entry>
  <entry author_id="391474" end="43" start="32">Azerbaijani pilots are trained in the Azerbaijan Air Force School and then developing their skills in the military bases.
Azerbaijan has an experience exchange with Turkey, Ukraine, the United States and number of NATO countries.
Turkish Air Force School has a great role in the training of military pilots.
The Azerbaijani pilots are also trained in the Ukraine’s Pilot Training School.
The United States is the most active participant in the modernization of the Azerbaijani Air Force.
Azerbaijani airfields in Gala and Haji Zeynalabidin Tagiyev settlements were modernized with the US support in the framework of the Azerbaijan-NATO Individual Partnership Action Plan.
The special equipments were installed there to provide security of the flights.
The starting command points, engineering control systems and engineering air force service were provided with the new buildings.
Now modernization of the Kurdamir airfield is negotiated now.

Since September, 2008, Turkey has participated in the project of modernization of Central Command of Air Forces.
According the agreement reached, central command management center will be installed in accordance with NATO standards.</entry>
  <entry author_id="276745" end="155" start="43">Since the fall of the Soviet Union, Azerbaijan has been trying to further develop its armed forces into a professional, well trained, and mobile military.
Since 2005 Azerbaijan has increased its military budget to $2.46 billion in 2009.
Based on the 2008 statistics the country has over 600 Main Battle Tanks, 900 Armored Combat Vehicles and over 720 Artillery Systems.
Its air force has over 220 aircraft and more than 75 helicopters.

In July 1992, Azerbaijan ratified the Treaty on Conventional Armed Forces in Europe (CFE), which establishes comprehensive limits on key categories of conventional military equipment.
The country approved the CFE flank agreement in May 1997.
It also has acceded to the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty as a non-nuclear weapons state.
Azerbaijan also participates in NATO's Partnership for Peace.

Azerbaijan joined the Coalition of the Willing during Iraq War, and as of 2006, is protecting the northern parts of Iraq.
One hundred soldiers were sent on December 29, 2004 to reinforce the 150 soldiers already in the country.
They provide security for local Turkmen populations, religious sites and convoys.

The history of the modern Azerbaijan army dates back to Azerbaijan Democratic Republic in 1918, when the Armed Forces of Azerbaijan Republic were created in June 26, 1918.
First de facto Minister of Defense of ADR was Dr. Khosrov bey Sultanov.
When the Ministry was formally established Gen. Samedbey Mehmandarov became the minister, and then Lt-Gen. Ali-Agha Shikhlinski his deputy.
Chiefs of Staff of ADR Army were Lt-Gen. Mamedbey Sulkevich (March 1919 - 10 December 1919) and Maj-Gen. Abdulhamid bey Gaitabashi (10 December 1919 – April 1920).

The Red Army invaded Azerbaijan on April 28, 1920.
Although the bulk of the newly formed Azerbaijani army was engaged in putting down an Armenian revolt that had just broken out in Karabakh, the Azeris did not surrender their brief independence of 1918-20 quickly or easily.
As many as 20,000 died resisting what was effectively a Russian reconquest.

In summer 1992, the Defense Ministry of Azerbaijan, following a resolution by the Azerbaijani president on the privatization of units and formations in Azerbaijani territory, forwarded an ultimatum demanding control over vehicles and armaments of the 135th and 139th motorized rifle regiments of the 295th Motor Rifle Division.
Azerbaijan had been the deployment area of units of the 4th Army that consisted of four motorized rifle divisions (23rd, 60th, 296th and 75th) and prescribed army units that included missile and air defense brigades and artillery and rocket regiments.
It also hosted the 49th arsenal of the Main Agency of Missiles and Artillery of the Ministry of Defense of the Russian Federation, which contained over 7,000 train-car loads of ammunition to the excess of one billion units.
The transfer of the property of the 4th Army (except for part of the property of the 366th motorized rifle regiment of the 23rd division captured by Armenian armed formations in 1992 during the regiment's withdrawal from Stepanakert) and the 49th arsenal was completed in 1992.
Thus, by the end of 1992, Azerbaijan received arms and military hardware sufficient for approximately four motorized rifle divisions with prescribed army units.
It also inherited 50 combat aircraft from the disbanded 19th Air Defense Army and naval ships.

Upon the re-establishment of independence in 1991, Azerbaijan started forming the national military forces.
Lt-Gen. Valeh Barshadli became the first Minister of Defense (September-December 1991, from May to October 1992 he served as Chief of Staff).
Subsequent defense ministers from 1992 until 1995 were:  Chief military advisors to the President of Azerbaijan included: Turkish Air Force Brig.
Gen. Yasar Demirbulak (1992-1994), Maj. Gen. Nuraddin Sadykhov (1993-1999), Col. Gen. Tofig Aghahuseynov (1997-2002) and National Security Lt. Gen. Vahid Aliyev (since April 2002).

Azerbaijan has been undergoing serious modernization and capacity expanding programs, the military budget alone increased from around $300 million in 2005 to $2.46 billion in 2009.
The Azerbaijani active forces number about 126,000, with an additional National Guard of 575,000.
In addition, the Azeri ground forces have 15,000 paramilitary troops.
Azerbaijan has signed numerous contracts to strengthen its armed forces and to train its military with Turkey's assistance.

Azerbaijan has also implemented a new organizational style in order to modernize its army.
Over the last 15 years, Azerbaijan has been preparing its military for possible action against Armenian forces in Nagorno-Karabakh.
It is feared that Azerbaijan may attempt to retake Karabakh and the surrounding regions by military force because the last negotiations in France were a failure.
Azerbaijan has continually stated that it is interested in a diplomatic and peaceful solution.
According to the European Lateral Treaty on Conventional Arms, Azerbaijan may keep 100 fighter jets and 50 helicopters.
The country has 6 major military airports:There are USSR-made MiG-21, MiG-23, MiG-25, Su-24 and Su-25, as well as fourth generation of MiG-29 purchased from Ukraine in 2006 and Soviet-made Il-76 and military aircraft.
Azerbaijan is holding talks with Pakistan to purchase JF-17 Thunder aircraft.

In June 2008, Azerbaijan acquired six Orbiter, six Aerostar and another three IAI Searcher unmanned aircraft produced by Israel’s Aeronautics Company.
These aircraft were demonstrated for the first time during the military parade in Baku in 2008.
According to the Israeli newspapers, Azerbaijan is holding the talks for purchasing Hermes and Heron-TP unmanned crafts.

The Air Force stockpiles L-29 and L-39 practice fighter jets produced in Czech Republic and Ukraine.
The Azerbaijan Border Guard and Voluntary Society of Defense, Patriotism and Sport have Yakovlev light assault aircraft.
Azerbaijani pilots are trained in the Azerbaijan Air Force School and then developing their skills in the military bases.
Azerbaijan has an experience exchange with Turkey, Ukraine, the United States and number of NATO countries.
Turkish Air Force School has a great role in the training of military pilots.
The Azerbaijani pilots are also trained in the Ukraine’s Pilot Training School.

The helicopter fleet contains Soviet made Mi-24, Mi-8Mi-17 and Mi-6 helicopters.
Last year Azerbaijan signed a deal with Russia to purchase Mi-171 helicopters.
Alongside with the Azerbaijan Air Force, the Border Guard, Interior Guard and Ministry of Emergency Situations have their helicopter squadrons.

The Azerbaijan Navy has about 5,000 personnel in twenty two units including the Caspian Flotilla and a Border Coast Guard.
The navy has 7 patrol boats consisting out of; 2 - OSA-II-Class and 5 - Stenka-Class patrol boats.
There are 7 minesweepers consisting out of; 2 - Sonya-Class and 5 - Yevgenya-Class minesweepers.
There are 6 landing crafts, 2 landing cutters, 1 special purposes warship and 1 special purposes cutter.

Azerbaijan is also strategic ally of the U.S. in view of its maritime border with Iran in the Caspian Sea.
In this regard, the U.S. Navy is involved in supporting the Azeri Navy, in the area of training.
There is also an agreement to provide US support to refurbish Azeri warships in the Caspian sea.
In 2006, the US Government donated 3 motorboats with the latest technology to the Azerbaijani navy.
In 2007 an agreement between Azeri Navy and one of the US military companies was concluded, which stated that a part of the Azeri Navy would be equipped with advanced laser marksmanship device/system.
The US company specialists were also to give training for the use of new equipment.
As a comment on this Colonel Lieutenant Eldar Safarov said that the work on modernization of warships will continue.

The US has also participated in joint naval exercises with the Azeri Army’s 641st Special Warfare Naval Unit, headquartered at the Azeri Naval Station outside Baku.
The Azerbaijani Air Defense has about 3,500 personnel under service.
There are some installations of the Cold War era left by the Soviets in 1990.
The Gabala OTH Radar in Azerbaijan is the main early warning capability of the Azerbaijan Air Defense Force.
The radar station has a range of up to 6,000 kilometres (3,728 mi), and was designed to detect missile launches as far as from the Indian Ocean.

The U.S. also provided Azerbaijani military with the latest radar technology in 2006.
In the same year, plans were announced for the U.S. to modernize one radar station near the Iranian border at Lerik and another near the border with Georgia at Agstafa.
Joint work has also commenced on two radar stations on the Russia-Azerbaijani border and Iran-Azerbaijani border to monitor Caspian Sea traffic.
In 2007 the U.S. and Russia showed great interests to make the Gabala Radar Station the main anti-missile defense shield for Europe.

Azerbaijan has also a wide missile system covering the Azeri Aerospace.
The NATO designated SA-2 Guideline (original name S-75) has been installed in and around Baku and additional installations are near the border with Iran and Dagestan.
Among them are the medium range SA-4, for short range SA-8 and the SA-13 mobile SAM vehicles.
Azerbaijan also has a lot of lighter AA guns and shoulder launched SAMs.
Azerbaijan’s National Mine Action Authority (ANAMA) is the official mine-cleaning organization of Azerbaijan.
In October 9, 2006 ANAMA confirmed that 36,861,337 sq.
meters of area had been cleared from mines and unexploded ordinances and 70 334 UXO have been neutralized.
194 100 sq.
meters of area were cleared in mechanical way.
The operation took place in 2006; about 25 Dutch trained dogs (each worth $100,000), 156 sappers, 47 UXO operators, 8 paramedics, some 100 assistants and 4 mine detecting vehicles were used in the clearance operations.

ANAMA reports 81 mine explosions have left 51 persons dead and 116 wounded since September, 2001.
Azerbaijan Defense Industry (ADI) headed by Yavar Jamalov of Defense Industries Ministry is the domestic military supplier of Azerbaijan, it was stablished in 2005.
The Defense Industries Ministry is incorporated in the State Departments for Military Industry and for Armaments and the Military Science Center, each of which was formerly a separate agency within the Azerbaijani Defense Ministry.

The defense industry has emerged as an autonomous entity with a growing defense production capability.
The ministry is cooperating with the defense sectors of Ukraine, Belarus and Pakistan.
The major military companies of Azerbaijan are:The defense industry of Azerbaijan manufactures small arms, artillery systems, various military vehicles and military planes and helicopters.
Azerbaijan and Turkey have always been strong with the two often being described as "one nation with two states" due to a common culture and history, and the mutual intelligibility of Turkish and Azerbaijani.

Turkey is the closest ally of Azerbaijan; the two countries cooperate on multiple issues.
Turkey has supported the Azerbaijani military by providing training to Azerbaijani military personnel and delivering military equipment and armaments.
Due to help from Turkish specialists and instructors, thousands of Azerbaijani officers were trained according to western standards and some have even gained field experience by taking part in special-forces operations.

Section 907 of the United States Freedom Support Act bans any kind of direct United States aid to the Azerbaijani government.
This ban makes Azerbaijan the only exception to the countries of the former Soviet Union, to receive direct aid from United States government under the Freedom Support Act to facilitate economic and political stability.
The Act was strongly lobbied for by the Armenian American community in the U.S., and was passed in response to Azerbaijan's blockade of Armenia, however no measures were taken against Armenia regarding its occuapation of some 20% of Azerbaijani territory.

The U.S. also provided Azerbaijani Navy with the latest radar technology and 3 navy boats in 2006.
In the same year the U.S. modernized one radar station near the Iranian border at Lerik and another near the border with Georgia at Agstafa.
Joint work has also commenced on two radar stations on the Russia-Azerbaijani border and Iran-Azerbaijani border to monitor Caspian Sea traffic.

On May 19, 2006 Azerbaijani Defense Minister Safar Abiyev and Commander of U.S. Air Forces in Europe Tom Hobbins met in Baku to discuss military cooperation.
General Hobbins said that the main reason for the lack of peace and stability in South Caucasus was the Armenia-Azerbaijan Upper (Nagorno) Garabagh conflict.
He stated that "Armenia’s destructive policies and its non-constructive stance in the negotiations have been the main reason for the ongoing instability.
Armenia keeps 20% of Azerbaijani land under occupation".

Hobbins pointed to the progress made in the NATO-Azerbaijan relations, saying that the successful implementation of the NATO Partnership for Peace program in Azerbaijan has brought the country even closer to the alliance.
He said the objective of his visit was to become familiar with the state of Azerbaijani armed forces.
He expressed that the two countries' air forces will expand cooperation.

Beyond the focus on reform, another important area of cooperation is the country’s support for NATO-led operations.
Azerbaijan currently contributes peacekeepers the International Security Assistance Force (ISAF) in Afghanistan.
In the past, it also actively supported the peacekeeping operation in Kosovo and Iraq.

In June 5, 2006 the U.S.
Departments of Defense and Homeland Security and the Federal Bureau of Investigation held a training program for about 100 representatives of Azerbaijan Ministry for Emergencies, Republican Prosecutor's Office, Defense Ministry and other law-enforcement bodies.
The objective of the training was to enhance Azerbaijan's ability to prevent the spread of weapon of mass destruction and related materials.
According to a U.S. Embassy official, the program was organized as part of U.S. efforts to help Azerbaijan implement its NATO IPAP, specifically to strengthen Azerbaijan's ability to control its land and sea borders: "This training is being implemented within the frame of International struggle against spread of weapons of mass destruction.
It is a good case that Azerbaijan is our active partner in struggle against spread of weapons of mass destruction".</entry>
  <entry author_id="391474" end="264" start="155">Since the fall of the Soviet Union, Azerbaijan has been trying to further develop its armed forces into a professional, well trained, and mobile military.
Since 2005 Azerbaijan has increased its military budget to $2.46 billion in 2009.
Based on the 2008 statistics the country has over 600 Main Battle Tanks, 900 Armored Combat Vehicles and over 720 Artillery Systems.
Its air force has over 220 aircraft and more than 75 helicopters.

In July 1992, Azerbaijan ratified the Treaty on Conventional Armed Forces in Europe (CFE), which establishes comprehensive limits on key categories of conventional military equipment.
The country approved the CFE flank agreement in May 1997.
It also has acceded to the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty as a non-nuclear weapons state.
Azerbaijan also participates in NATO's Partnership for Peace.

Azerbaijan joined the Coalition of the Willing during Iraq War, and as of 2006, is protecting the northern parts of Iraq.
One hundred soldiers were sent on December 29, 2004 to reinforce the 150 soldiers already in the country.
They provide security for local Turkmen populations, religious sites and convoys.

The history of the modern Azerbaijan army dates back to Azerbaijan Democratic Republic in 1918, when the Armed Forces of Azerbaijan Republic were created in June 26, 1918.
First de facto Minister of Defense of ADR was Dr. Khosrov bey Sultanov.
When the Ministry was formally established Gen. Samedbey Mehmandarov became the minister, and then Lt-Gen. Ali-Agha Shikhlinski his deputy.
Chiefs of Staff of ADR Army were Lt-Gen. Mamedbey Sulkevich (March 1919 - 10 December 1919) and Maj-Gen. Abdulhamid bey Gaitabashi (10 December 1919 – April 1920).

The Red Army invaded Azerbaijan on April 28, 1920.
Although the bulk of the newly formed Azerbaijani army was engaged in putting down an Armenian revolt that had just broken out in Karabakh, the Azeris did not surrender their brief independence of 1918-20 quickly or easily.
As many as 20,000 died resisting what was effectively a Russian reconquest.

Azerbaijan had been the deployment area of units of the Soviet 4th Army that consisted of four motorized rifle divisions (23rd, 60th, 296th and 75th) and prescribed army units that included missile and air defense brigades and artillery and rocket regiments.
It also hosted the 49th arsenal of the Main Agency of Missiles and Artillery of the Ministry of Defense of the Russian Federation, which contained over 7,000 train-car loads of ammunition to the excess of one billion units.
The transfer of the property of the 4th Army (except for part of the property of the 366th motorized rifle regiment of the 23rd division captured by Armenian armed formations in 1992 during the regiment's withdrawal from Stepanakert) and the 49th arsenal was completed in 1992.
Thus, by the end of 1992, Azerbaijan received arms and military hardware sufficient for approximately four motorized rifle divisions with prescribed army units.
It also inherited 50 combat aircraft from the disbanded 19th Air Defense Army and naval ships.

Azerbaijan has been undergoing serious modernization and capacity expanding programs, the military budget alone increased from around $300 million in 2005 to $2.46 billion in 2009.
The Azerbaijani active forces number about 126,000, with an additional National Guard of 575,000.
In addition, the Azeri ground forces have 15,000 paramilitary troops.
Azerbaijan has signed numerous contracts to strengthen its armed forces and to train its military with Turkey's assistance.

Azerbaijan has also implemented a new organizational style in order to modernize its army.
Over the last 15 years, Azerbaijan has been preparing its military for possible action against Armenian forces in Nagorno-Karabakh.
It is feared that Azerbaijan may attempt to retake Karabakh and the surrounding regions by military force because the last negotiations in France were a failure.
Azerbaijan has continually stated that it is interested in a diplomatic and peaceful solution.

Azerbaijani Special Forces or Tigers is the special operations unit of the Azerbaijani Army.
The rising influence and importance of Azerbaijan required the army to create a professional special forces this was established with cooperation with Turkish Navy in 2001.
The training and organisation structure of the Tigers is similar to Turkish special forces, Su Altı Taarruz who have close training relationships with them.
The first Tiger units were in Ganja following a joint training program with Turkey.

According to the European Lateral Treaty on Conventional Arms, Azerbaijan may keep 100 fighter jets and 50 helicopters.
The country has 6 major military airports: There are USSR-made MiG-21, MiG-23, MiG-25, Su-24 and Su-25, as well as fourth generation of MiG-29 purchased from Ukraine in 2006 and Soviet-made Il-76 and military aircraft.
Azerbaijan is holding talks with Pakistan to purchase JF-17 Thunder aircraft.

In June 2008, Azerbaijan acquired six Orbiter, six Aerostar and another three IAI Searcher unmanned aircraft produced by Israel’s Aeronautics Company.
These aircraft were demonstrated for the first time during the military parade in Baku in 2008.
According to the Israeli newspapers, Azerbaijan is holding the talks for purchasing Hermes and Heron-TP unmanned crafts.

The Air Force stockpiles L-29 and L-39 practice fighter jets produced in Czech Republic and Ukraine.
The Azerbaijan Border Guard and Voluntary Society of Defense, Patriotism and Sport have Yakovlev light assault aircraft.
Azerbaijani pilots are trained in the Azerbaijan Air Force School and then developing their skills in the military bases.
Azerbaijan has an experience exchange with Turkey, Ukraine, the United States and number of NATO countries.
Turkish Air Force School has a great role in the training of military pilots.
The Azerbaijani pilots are also trained in the Ukraine’s Pilot Training School.

The helicopter fleet contains Soviet made Mi-24, Mi-8Mi-17 and Mi-6 helicopters.
Last year Azerbaijan signed a deal with Russia to purchase Mi-171 helicopters.
Alongside with the Azerbaijan Air Force, the Border Guard, Interior Guard and Ministry of Emergency Situations have their helicopter squadrons.

The Azerbaijan Navy has about 5,000 personnel in twenty two units including the Caspian Flotilla and a Border Coast Guard.
The navy has 7 patrol boats consisting out of; 2 - OSA-II-Class and 5 - Stenka-Class patrol boats.
There are 7 minesweepers consisting out of; 2 - Sonya-Class and 5 - Yevgenya-Class minesweepers.
There are 6 landing crafts, 2 landing cutters, 1 special purposes warship and 1 special purposes cutter.

Azerbaijan is also strategic ally of the U.S. in view of its maritime border with Iran in the Caspian Sea.
In this regard, the U.S. Navy is involved in supporting the Azeri Navy, in the area of training.
There is also an agreement to provide US support to refurbish Azeri warships in the Caspian sea.
In 2006, the US Government donated 3 motorboats with the latest technology to the Azerbaijani navy.
In 2007 an agreement between Azeri Navy and one of the US military companies was concluded, which stated that a part of the Azeri Navy would be equipped with advanced laser marksmanship device/system.
The US company specialists were also to give training for the use of new equipment.
As a comment on this Colonel Lieutenant Eldar Safarov said that the work on modernization of warships will continue.

The US has also participated in joint naval exercises with the Azeri Army’s 641st Special Warfare Naval Unit, headquartered at the Azeri Naval Station outside Baku.
The Azerbaijani Air Defense has about 3,500 personnel under service.
There are some installations of the Cold War era left by the Soviets in 1990.
The Gabala OTH Radar in Azerbaijan is the main early warning capability of the Azerbaijan Air Defense Force.
The radar station has a range of up to 6,000 kilometres (3,728 mi), and was designed to detect missile launches as far as from the Indian Ocean.

The U.S. also provided Azerbaijani military with the latest radar technology in 2006.
In the same year, plans were announced for the U.S. to modernize one radar station near the Iranian border at Lerik and another near the border with Georgia at Agstafa.
Joint work has also commenced on two radar stations on the Russia-Azerbaijani border and Iran-Azerbaijani border to monitor Caspian Sea traffic.
In 2007 the U.S. and Russia showed great interests to make the Gabala Radar Station the main anti-missile defense shield for Europe.

Azerbaijan has also a wide missile system covering the Azeri Aerospace.
The NATO designated SA-2 Guideline (original name S-75) has been installed in and around Baku and additional installations are near the border with Iran and Dagestan.
Among them are the medium range SA-4, for short range SA-8 and the SA-13 mobile SAM vehicles.
Azerbaijan also has a lot of lighter AA guns and shoulder launched SAMs.
Azerbaijan Defense Industry (ADI) is the domestic military supplier of Azerbaijan, it was stablished in 2005.
The Defense Industries Ministry is incorporated in the State Departments for Military Industry and for Armaments and the Military Science Center, each of which was formerly a separate agency within the Azerbaijani Defense Ministry.

The defense industry has emerged as an autonomous entity with a growing defense production capability.
The ministry is cooperating with the defense sectors of Ukraine, Belarus and Pakistan.
The major military companies of Azerbaijan are:The defense industry of Azerbaijan manufactures small arms, artillery systems, various military vehicles and military planes and helicopters.
Azerbaijan’s National Mine Action Authority (ANAMA) is the official mine-cleaning organization of Azerbaijan.
In October 9, 2006 ANAMA confirmed that 36,861,337 sq.
meters of area had been cleared from mines and unexploded ordinances and 70 334 UXO have been neutralized.
194 100 sq.
meters of area were cleared in mechanical way.
The operation took place in 2006; about 25 Dutch trained dogs (each worth $100,000), 156 sappers, 47 UXO operators, 8 paramedics, some 100 assistants and 4 mine detecting vehicles were used in the clearance operations.

ANAMA reports 81 mine explosions have left 51 persons dead and 116 wounded since September, 2001.
Turkey has supported the Azerbaijani military by providing training to Azerbaijani military personnel and delivering military equipment and armaments.
Due to help from Turkish specialists and instructors, thousands of Azerbaijani officers were trained according to western standards and some have even gained field experience by taking part in special-forces operations.

Section 907 of the United States Freedom Support Act bans any kind of direct United States aid to the Azerbaijani government.
This ban makes Azerbaijan the only exception to the countries of the former Soviet Union, to receive direct aid from United States government under the Freedom Support Act to facilitate economic and political stability.
The Act was strongly lobbied for by the Armenian American community in the U.S., and was passed in response to Azerbaijan's blockade of Armenia, however no measures were taken against Armenia regarding its occuapation of some 20% of Azerbaijani territory.

The U.S. also provided Azerbaijani Navy with the latest radar technology and 3 navy boats in 2006.
In the same year the U.S. modernized one radar station near the Iranian border at Lerik and another near the border with Georgia at Agstafa.
Joint work has also commenced on two radar stations on the Russia-Azerbaijani border and Iran-Azerbaijani border to monitor Caspian Sea traffic.

On May 19, 2006 Azerbaijani Defense Minister Safar Abiyev and Commander of U.S. Air Forces in Europe Tom Hobbins met in Baku to discuss military cooperation.
General Hobbins said that the main reason for the lack of peace and stability in South Caucasus was the Armenia-Azerbaijan Upper (Nagorno) Garabagh conflict.
He stated that "Armenia’s destructive policies and its non-constructive stance in the negotiations have been the main reason for the ongoing instability.
Armenia keeps 20% of Azerbaijani land under occupation".

Hobbins pointed to the progress made in the NATO-Azerbaijan relations, saying that the successful implementation of the NATO Partnership for Peace program in Azerbaijan has brought the country even closer to the alliance.
He said the objective of his visit was to become familiar with the state of Azerbaijani armed forces.
He expressed that the two countries' air forces will expand cooperation.

Beyond the focus on reform, another important area of cooperation is the country’s support for NATO-led operations.
Azerbaijan currently contributes peacekeepers the International Security Assistance Force (ISAF) in Afghanistan.
In the past, it also actively supported the peacekeeping operation in Kosovo and Iraq.

In June 5, 2006 the U.S.
Departments of Defense and Homeland Security and the Federal Bureau of Investigation held a training program for about 100 representatives of Azerbaijan Ministry for Emergencies, Republican Prosecutor's Office, Defense Ministry and other law-enforcement bodies.
The objective of the training was to enhance Azerbaijan's ability to prevent the spread of weapon of mass destruction and related materials.
According to a U.S. Embassy official, the program was organized as part of U.S. efforts to help Azerbaijan implement its NATO IPAP, specifically to strengthen Azerbaijan's ability to control its land and sea borders: "This training is being implemented within the frame of International struggle against spread of weapons of mass destruction.
It is a good case that Azerbaijan is our active partner in struggle against spread of weapons of mass destruction".</entry>
  <entry author_id="13501739" end="297" start="264">Azerbaijan was among the first countries from the former Soviet Union, who joined the Partnership for Peace (PFP) programme of NATO.
The President of Azerbaijan H.E.
Mr. Heydar Aliyev signed the PFP Framework Document on the accession to PFP during his official visit to NATO HQ on 4 May 1994.

Since 1996, on the basis of its Presentation Document and Partnership Work Programme prepared by the NATO, Azerbaijan has been annually adopting Individual Partnership Programme (IPP), which includes all joint activities and events to be attended by national military and civilian representatives.
Annually expanding the scope of its Individual Partnership Programme, Azerbaijan participated in more than 250 NATO/PFP activities and events in 2007.
This number is one of the highest in the ranking among the Partner Nations and the highest one in the South Caucasus.

In 2006, Government of Azerbaijan increased financing of the PFP Programme from 300 000 USD to 850 000 USD.
In 2007 this figure was increased to 1.8 million USD.
In 2008 it was approximately 2 million USD.

In 1997 Azerbaijan joined the Planning and Review Process (PARP).
PARP related activities were aimed at engaging Azerbaijan more closely to NATO's defence planning for operations.
Since then Azerbaijani Armed Forces are undertaking increasing number of so-called Partnership Goals (PG) based on two-year cycles.
PG are focused on achieving military interoperability with NATO troops through introduction of NATO's political-military, military, training and technical standards.

In 2002 NATO/EAPC Prague Summit adopted Individual Partnership Action Plan (IPAP) instrument in order to improve cooperation with the Partner nations.
In May 2003 Azerbaijan formally applied for joining the IPAP.
In May 2004 President of Azerbaijan H.E.
Mr. Ilham Aliyev officially submitted the IPAP Presentation Document to the Alliance, which included comprehensive information on the current status of political, economic and security developments in Azerbaijan.

Azerbaijan and NATO elaborated and approved the Individual Partnership Action Plan (IPAP) in May 2005, on the basis of this Presentation Document.
The IPAP covers all major political, defence, security and security related economic, scientific and environmental spheres.
IPAP implementation and update is based on two-year cycles and annual assessment reports, which are considered at the level of North Atlantic Council +Azerbaijan.

In August 2007 Azerbaijan has completed first IPAP cycle.
The new IPAP document was approved in March 2008.
Since the adoption of the first IPAP of Azerbaijan in May 2005 real steps have been made towards its successful implementation, including in the sphere of security sector reform.
Taking together all the fields of cooperation, progress of Azerbaijan on implementation of IPAP has been considerable.

- Work on the National Security Concept has been completed and it was subsequently endorsed by the Government and Parliament on 19 May 2007.
The work on the Military doctrine is close to finalisation.
These two fundamental documents will guide the Strategic Defence Review of the security sector.

- Despite the on-going conflict, the process of gradual transformation of the Armed Forces of Azerbaijan has been started.
Structural changes on the basis of NATO standarts are under way within MOD, General Staff and army units.
It is planned to complete this process in 2009 integrating needs and requirements identified within the Strategic Defence Review (SDR).

With regard to the future of the Partnership and the policy of NATO in the region, Azerbaijan considers that the security in Euro-Atlantic area depends on improvement of the capacity of crises management, creation of secure transport corridors, and development of energy security.
All of these are essential for the development of Partnership as an institution.
The development of Partnership has to give opportunity for the development of security cooperation with NATO on the basis of 3 pillars: political unanimity, legal harmony, practical interoperability.</entry>
</article>
