<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1098" title="Foreign relations of Armenia" authors="1" lines="82">
  <entry author_id="3302398" end="82" start="0">Armenia's foreign relationships vary from close (with countries like Russia, Iran, France, and Greece) to bitter (with countries like Turkey and Azerbaijan).
Armenia is a member of more than 40 different international organizations including the United Nations, the Council of Europe, the Commonwealth of Independent States, the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe, NATO's Partnership for Peace, the North Atlantic Cooperation Council, the International Monetary Fund, and the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the World Trade Organization.
It is also an observer member of the Eurasian Economic Community, La Francophonie, and the Non-Aligned Movement.
Vardan Oskanyan currently serves as Minister of Foreign Affairs.
ACCT (observer), ADB, BSEC, CE, CIS, Council of Europe, EAPC, EBRD, FAO, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICCt (signatory), ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITU, La Francophonie (observer), MIGA, NAM (observer), OAS (observer), OIF (observer), OPCW, OSCE, PFP, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNIDO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WToO, WTO.
Armenia has currently diplomatic relations with over 80 countries.,,,,,, .
These include: Albania, Andorra, Australia, Austria, Belarus, Belgium, Benin, Brazil, Bulgaria, Canada, Chad, Chile, the People's Republic of China, Cote d'Ivoire, Croatia, Cuba, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Denmark, Egypt, East Timor, Equatorial Guinea, Estonia, Ethiopia, Finland, France, Georgia, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Iceland, India, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Japan, Jordan, Kazakhstan, South Korea, Kyrgyzstan, Latvia, Lebanon, Lithuania, Luxembourg, Libya, Malta, Mexico, Moldova, Montenegro, Norway, Netherlands, Order of Malta, Poland, Portugal, Qatar, Romania, Russia, San Marino, Serbia, Seychelles, Slovakia, Slovenia, South Africa, Spain, Sudan, Sweden, Switzerland, Syria, Tajikistan, Thailand, Turkmenistan, Ukraine, the United Arab Emirates, the United Kingdom, the United States of America, Uruguay, Vatican City and Vietnam.

During the Soviet period, many Armenians and Azeris lived together peacefully.
However, when Mikhail Gorbachev introduced the policies of Glasnost and Perestroika, the majority Armenians from the autonomous area of Nagorno-Karabakh in the Azerbaijan SSR began a peaceful and democratic movement to unify with the Armenian SSR.
In 1988, the Armenians of Karabakh voted to secede and join Armenia.
The reaction was strong and violent from Azerbaijan with anti-Armenian pogroms breaking out in Sumgait, Kirovabad, and Baku.

Tensions continued to escalate into a full-scale armed conflict.
A Russian-brokered cease-fire was declared between Azeri and Nagorno-Karabakh forces in 1994 and has been maintained by both sides since then in spite of occasional disturbances along the line of contact between the two.
The Karabakh Armenians now hold about 14% of Azerbaijan's internationally recognized territory.
They have refused to withdraw until an agreement on the status of Nagorno-Karabakh is reached.
On its turn, Azerbaijan still controls the formerly Armenian-populated and now ethnically cleansed Shahumian district, as well as eastern parts of Mardakert and Martuni districts of Nagorno-Karabakh.
Armenia and Azerbaijan continue to observe the cease-fire which has been in effect since May 1994, and in late 1995 both also agreed to OSCE field representatives being based in Tbilisi, Georgia, to monitor the cease-fire and facilitate the peace process.
Negotiations to peacefully resolve the conflict have been ongoing since, under the aegis of the Minsk Group of the OSCE.
The Minsk Group is currently co-chaired by the U.S., France, and Russia and comprises Armenia, Azerbaijan, Turkey, and several western European nations.
Armenians and Georgians have a lot in common.
Both are ancient Christian civilizations with their own distinct alphabets.
Both use the terms "Apostolic" and "Orthodox" in the full titles of their respective churches.
They also use the term "Catholicos" to refer to their church patriarchs.
Despite all this, however, Armenians and Georgians have tended to have a tenuous relationship (at times, sharing close bonds while at other times regarding each other as rivals).

Today, relations with Georgia are of particular importance for Armenia because, under the economic blockade imposed by Turkey and Azerbaijan due to the ongoing Karabakh conflict, Georgia offers Armenia its only land connection with Europe and access to its Black Sea ports.
However, because of Armenia's reliance on Russia from whose grip Georgia is attempting to free itself, relations have been especially tentative lately.
The development of close relations between Turkey and Georgia (such as the Baku-Tbilisi-Ceyhan oil pipeline and South Caucasus natural gas pipeline) have also weighed on the mutual relations and lead to the prevention of the country recognizing the Armenian Genocide.
On occasion, however, Georgian politicians have sympathized with the Armenian cause.
For example, on March 20, 2006, Georgian Ambassador to Armenia Revaz Gachechiladze stated, "We sympathize with the sister nation but taking decisions of the kind we should take into account the international situation.
When the time comes Georgia will do everything within the limits of the possible for the recognition of the Armenian Genocide by the international community including Georgia."
However, Armenian-Georgian relations have begun to improve.
On May 10, 2006, Armenia and Georgia agreed on the greater part of the lines of the state border between the two countries..
The Javakheti region in southern Georgia contains a large Armenian population and although there have been local civic organizations (such as United Javakhk) pushing for autonomy, there has been no violence between Armenians and Georgians in the area despite Russian efforts to use the situation.
Armenia's most notable recent foreign policy success came with the August 29 treaty with Russia on friendship, cooperation and mutual assistance, in which Moscow committed itself to the defense of Armenia should it be attacked by a third party.
Russia is the key regional security player, and has proved a valuable historical ally for Armenia.
Although it appeared as a response to Aliyev's US trip, the treaty had probably long been under development.
However, it is clear from the wider context of Armenian foreign policy that -- while Yerevan welcomes the Russian security guarantee -- the country does not want to rely exclusively on Moscow, nor to become part of a confrontation between Russian and US-led alliances in the Transcaucasus.

Armenia and Greece share a strong historical and cultural bond.
Both peoples fell under Ottoman rule, oppression, and persecution.
Furthermore, the ancient Kingdom of Armenia exemplied the ideal Hellenistic civilization during its existence.
During the Nagorno-Karabakh War, Greece did not aid Armenia militarily but supplied them with economic resources that would prove to be vital to the war effort.
The illegal Turkish occupation of Northern Cyprus led forced Armenian Cypriots to flee and this mutual victimization of both countries by the Turks have strengthened the bonds between the two nations.

Despite religious and ideological differences, relations between Armenia and the Islamic Republic of Iran remain cordial and both Armenia and Iran are strategic partners in the region.
Armenia and Iran enjoy cultural and historical ties that go back thousands of years.
There are no border disputes between the two countries and the Christian Armenian minority in Iran enjoys official recognition.
Of special importance is the cooperation in the field of energy security which lowers Armenia's dependence on Russia and can in the future also supply Iranian gas to Europe through Georgia and the Black Sea.

Since independence, Armenia has received support from Israel and today remains one of their major trade partners.
While both countries have diplomatic relations, neither maintains an embassy in the other country.
Instead, Ehude Moshe Eytam, the Israeli ambassador to Armenia is based in Tbilisi, Georgia, and visits Yerevan twice a month.

Israel has recognized 10 Armenians as Righteous Among the Nations for risking their lives to save Jews during the Holocaust.
However, because Turkey is one of the few countries in the Middle East that recognizes Israel's right to exist and is a major ally of the Jewish state, Israel has yet to recognize the Armenian Genocide, despite calls by Israeli politicians, Rabbis, and Israel's Armenian population to do so.
Turkey has warned of harming ties with Israel if Israel or the United States recognizes the killings as genocide.

Still, there have been several high-level official visits to Israel by Armenians in the last several years.
In January 2000, President Robert Kocharian traveled to Israel and met with high-ranking Israeli officials, including former Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Barak.
The two sides pledged to strengthen relations and signed agreements on health and bilateral investment.

Yad Vashem, the Holocaust Memorial in Israel, has paid tribute to ten Armenians as “Righteous Among the Nations” for risking their lives during the Holocaust to rescue Jews.
In 1988, Israel Defense Forces were sent to Armenia after a devastating earthquake.
Over the past years, trade between Israel and Armenia has further increased the two nations’ friendship.

Turkey has played an active role in persecuting the Armenian minority within Turkey from the Ottoman Empire till today.Hostile Turkish rhetoric started during the Nagorno-Karabagh War when Turkish politicians threatened to intervene on the side of Azerbajan.
This led Armenia to allow Russia to open an important Russian Base in Gyurmi on the Turkish-Armenian border.Turkey has actively supported Azerbajan in it's embargo of Armenia which is suffocating the country.
The Nagorno- Karabakh conflict and the continued persecution of Armenians inside modern Turkey( such as the assassination of Turkish-Armenian activist Hrant Dink) have kept tensions high.
Honorable Turks such as (Orhan Parmuk and Professor Shafik) who have fought for Armenian Genocide recognition have been prosecuted under Article 301 of the Turkish Penal code silencing any discussions of the Armenian Genocide in Turkey.
However, since Turkey has become a candidate to join the European Union, limited discussion of the event is now taking place in Turkey.
Some in the European Parliament have even suggested that one of the provisions for Turkey to join the E.U.
should be the full recognition of the event as genocide, though this hasn't happened.

Recently, however, relations have begun to ease and both Turkey and Armenia seem to be willing to settle their differences through peaceful talks.
On June 5, 2005, Armenian President Robert Kocharian announced that he was ready to "continue dialogue with Azerbaijan for the settlement of the Nagorno-Karabakh conflict and with Turkey on establishing relations without any preconditions."
The first Armenians migrated to Australia in the 1850s, during the gold rush.
The majority came to Australia in the 1960s, starting with the Armenians of Egypt after Nasser came to power then, in the early 1970s, from Cyprus after the Turkish occupation of the island and from 1975 until 1992, a period of civil unrest in Lebanon.
Person-to person governmental links are increasing although they are still modest.
In September 2003, The Hon Mr Philip Ruddock MP visited Armenia in his former capacity as Australian Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs.
In October 2005, the Armenian Foreign Minister, H.E.
Mr Vardan Oskanyan, visited Australia.
In November 2005, The Hon Mr Joe Hockey MP, Minister for Human Services, visited Armenia.
Till today the Parliament of the Commonwealth of Australia refuses to recognise the mass murder of Armenians in 1915 as Genocide, although the State of N.S.W passed a law recognising this several years earlier.
The Australian Government elections due to take place late 2007, have created an atmosphere in which the Opposition Labor party has declared it will push for the Recognition of the Armenian Genocide in Australian Parliament if Labor wins the Elections.

Armenia has been joined by many nations, in demanding recognition of the Armenian Genocide.
Countries that officially recognize the Armenian genocide include Argentina, Armenia, Australia State of N.S.W, Austria, Belgium, Canada, Chile, Cyprus, France, Germany, Greece, Italy, Lebanon, Lithuania, The Netherlands, Poland, Russia, Slovakia, Sweden, Switzerland, Uruguay, Vatican City and Venezuela.
Although part of the United Kingdom, Wales also officially recognizes the Armenian Genocide.
US House Resolution 106 was introduced on January 30, 2007 later referred to the House Committee on Foreign Affairs.
The bill currently has 225 co-sponsors.
The bill calls for President George W. Bush to recognize and use the word genocide in his annual April 24 speech which he has not yet used.</entry>
</article>
