<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1132" title="The Ashes" authors="5" lines="100">
  <entry author_id="145867" end="30" start="0">There then followed an extended period of English dominance.
They won the 1884 series 1-0.
Then James Lillywhite, Alfred Shaw and Arthur Shrewsbury promoted a professional tour to Australia in 1884/5.
This tour was marred by disputes over umpiring and money.
The Australians objected to Lillywhite umpiring in the first representative match, and then all 11 first-choice Australians withheld their services from the second match over money.
England won the first two matches, but then, back up to full strength, the Aussies took the third and fourth games, before England took the deciding fifth match by a wide margin.

A strong Australian side came over to England in 1886 under the financial aegis of the Melbourne Cricket Club.
However, although the first game was a close one, which England won by 4 wickets, the other two games were innings thrashings to leave England 3-0 winners.
Lillywhite, Shaw and Shrewsbury put together another tour Down Under in 1886/7.
The England team was not a particularly strong one.
Six of the players were from Nottinghamshire, the county of the organisers, Shaw and Shrewsbury.
The side also got a reputation of playing slow, and therefore unattractive cricket, and the games were poorly promoted.
They were poorly attended too.
England won both representative matches, with a putative third match never materialising because of the deep divisions with Australian cricket at the time.

1887/8 saw two English tours to Australia - a professional one promoted by Lillywhite, Shaw and Shrewsbury, and an amateur one led by Lord Hawke.
The two teams combined to play one match against a united Australia, which England one by 126 runs.
In 1888 Australia toured with what some considered to be the weakest side to leave Australia: the touring party lost the three matches they played before leaving Australia.
However, they surprised their critics by winning their first five matches.
In a low-scoring Test series, seven of the ten completed innings were completed for 100 or fewer.
In the first Test, England only needed 124 runs to win after getting 53 in response to Australia's 116 and 60, on a poor pitch at Lord's, but despite the 41 year old WG Grace's admirable 24, fell 61 runs short.
This was Australia's first victory in England since the Test that started the Ashes legend 6 years before.
England, though, playing under Grace's captaincy for the first time, won both other games by more than an innings to take the series 2-1.

Grace's Englishmen then beat Billy Murdoch's Australians 2-0 over what would have been a three Test series had the last one not been abandoned without a ball being bowled because of rain.
Then in 1891/2 the Australians finally won a series, 2-1, against what was considered to be a strong England side.
England restored supremacy at home in 1893, winning the three Test series 1-0 against John Blackham's side, and this supremacy remained in 1894/5 and in 1896, where a dispute over monies played to amateurs, and in particular WG Grace, saw George Lohmann and William Gunn pull out of the third Test, which England nevertheless won to take the series 2-1.

By 1897/8 England had only lost one Ashes series.
The tide, however, changed.
Australia won the 1897/8 series 4-1, a series which was played in great rancour after English players Ranjitsinhji and Andrew Stoddart made disparaging comments about the Australian crowds in the local press.
Joe Darling then led the Australian tourists in 1899, winning the five Test series 1-0.
Darling and Hugh Trumble continued this new Aussie dominance back home in 1901/2 when they again won 4-1.</entry>
  <entry author_id="145867" end="41" start="30">Overall, up to 2002/3 62 Ashes series have been held.
England have won 27 of them, Australia 39 with 5 drawn series.
When a series is drawn, the holders of the Ashes retain them.
The 5 drawn series led to England retaining the Ashes once, and Australia retaining the Ashes four times.

The 2005 Ashes series in England is one of the most eagerly-awaited in years.
Australia remain the dominant force in world cricket.
England have now reached second spot in the LG ICC Test Championship table after they were the only team to go through the 2004 calendar year undefeated.
After coming back to level their series against South Africa at the Oval in 2003, they have only lost one series and two games.
This has led to speculation that the series will be the tightest in years.
Tickets for all games sold out quickly, with the Oval, which will host the fifth and final Test, selling out the fifth day in advance for the first time ever.
According to Ladbrokes.com on 28 May Australia remain 2-5 favourites to win the Ashes outright, England are 11-3, with the draw 5-1.</entry>
  <entry author_id="488652" end="60" start="41">In the 31st August edition of a magazine called “Cricket: A Weekly Record of The Game” there appeared a now forgoten mock obitary to “English Supremacy in the Cricket Field which expired on the 29th day of August at the Oval”.
Two days later, September 2 1882 another mock obituary, written by Reginald Brooks, appeared in The Sporting Times.
The obituary read as follows: The term “The Ashes” then largely disappears from puiblic use for the next twenty years; certainly, there is no suggestion that this was the accepted name for the series.
Then following the successful English tour of 1902-03 the English captain, Pelham Warner published a book called ‘How we Recovered the Ashes”.
Even though the term does not figure in the text, the title was enough to revive public interest in the myth.
The first mention of The Ashes in the Wisden Cricket Almanac occours in 1905 and the first Wisden account of the Ashes story being delayed until 1922.
As it took many years for the name the Ashes to be given to the ongoing series between England and Australia, there was naturally no concept of there being a trophy to be presented to the winners.
As late as 1925, the following verse appeared in The Cricketers Annual

Several attempts had been made over the years to embody The Ashes in a physical memorial.
Examples include one presented to Warner in 1904, another to Australian Captain MA Noble in 1909 and another to Australian Captain WM Woodfall in 1934.
The oldest however, and the one to enjoy enduring fame was the one presented to Hon Ivo Bligh, later Lord Darnley, during the 1882-83 tour.

The precise details of the origin of the urn however is matter of dispute.
Based on a statement by Darnley made in 1894, it was believed that a group of Victorian ladies, including Darnley later wife Florence Morphy, made the presentation after the victory on the third test in 1883.
More recent researchers, in particular Ronald Willis having studied the tour in detail and concluded that the presentation was made after a private cricket match played when, the English team, led by Ivo Bligh were guests of Sir William Clarke, at his property "Rupertswood" at Sunbury, Victoria over Christmas 1882, before the matches had started.
The prime evidence was provided by a descendant of Lord Clarke.

During Darnley’s lifetime, there was little public knowledge of the urn, and no record of a published photograph exists before 1924.
However, when Darnley died in 1927, his widow presented the urn to the Marylebone Cricket Club and that was the key event in establishing the urn as the physical embodiment of the mythical ashes.
MCC first displayed the urn on the Long Room at Lord's Cricket Groundand more recently in the MCC Cricket Museum at the ground.
It is ironic that MCC’s wish to it been seen by wide a range of cricket enthusiasts possible has led to its been mistaken for an official trophy.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1558654" end="73" start="60">In a rain-hit series in 1926, however, England managed to eke out a 1–0 victory with a win in the final Test at The Oval.
Because the series was at stake, the match was to be "timeless", ie played to a finish.
Australia had a narrow first innings lead of 22.
Jack Hobbs and Herbert Sutcliffe took the score to 49-0 at the end of the second day, a lead of 27.
Heavy rain fell overnight, and next day the pitch soon developed into a traditional sticky wicket.
England seemed doomed to be bowled out cheaply and to lose the match.
In spite of the very difficult batting conditions, however, Hobbs and Sutcliffe took their partnership to 172 before Hobbs was out for exactly 100.
Sutcliffe went on to make 161 and in the end England won the game comfortably

In the Headingley Test of 1930, Bradman made 334, reaching 309* at the end of the first day, including reaching his hundred before lunch.
However he himself thought that his 254 in the preceding match, at Lord's, was an even better innings.
England hung on until the final Test, at The Oval, which they went into at 1-1.
However yet another double hundred by Bradman, and 7-92 by Percy Hornibrook in England's second innings, enabled Australia to win by an innings.
Clarrie Grimmett's 29 wickets at 31.89 for Australia in this high-scoring series were also important.</entry>
  <entry author_id="359672" end="84" start="73">On the batting-friendly wickets that prevailed in the late 1930s, most Tests up to the Second World War still gave results.
It should be borne in mind that Tests in Australia prior to the war were all played to a finish.
Many batting records were set in this period.

Len Hutton scored 364 at The Oval to give England a draw in the 1938 series.

England was already in decline and no longer a match for West Indies.
World Series Cricket damaged Australia too and for many years they struggled in Test cricket.
The Ashes had long been seen as a sort of cricket world championship but that view was no longer feasible.

It was the Australia of old who arrived in England in 1989 and proceeded in a determined and professional manner to demolish a poor England team and win the series 4–0.
Allan Border had stood firm through the lean years and now enjoyed the company of some top-class team mates with the arrival on the scene of Mark Taylor, Merv Hughes, David Boon]], Ian Healy and above all Steve Waugh, who was to be a thorn in England's side for years to come.
There can be little doubt that England reached rock-bottom in the 1990s and was at one stage at the foor of the international rankings.
After re-establishing its credibity in 1989, Australia underlined its superiority with a succession of victories in 1990/91, 1993, 1994/95, 1997, 1998/99, 2001 and 2002/03 series — all by convincing margins.</entry>
  <entry author_id="435516" end="100" start="84">The 1938 series was high-scoring affair with many high-scoring draws, resulting in a 1–1 result, Australia retaining the Ashes.
After the first two matches ended in stalemate and the Third Test at Old Trafford never started due to rain.
Australia then scraped home by five wickets inside three days in a low-scoring match at Headingley to retain the urn.
In the timeless Fifth Test at The Oval, the highlight was Len Hutton's then world record score of 364 as England made 7/093 declared.
Bradman and Jack Fingleton injured themselves during Hutton's marathon effort, and with only nine men, Australia fell to defeat by an innings and 578 runs, the heaviest in Test history.

Aged 38 and having been unwell during the war, Bradman had been reluctant to play.
He batted unconvincingly and reached 28 when he hit a ball to Jack Ikin; England believed it was a catch, but Bradman stood his ground, believing it to be a bump ball.
The umpire ruled in the Australian captain's favour and he appeared to regain his fluency of yesteryear, scoring 187.
Australia promptly reached seized the initiative, won the First Test convincingly and inaugurated a dominant post-war era.
The controversy over the Ikin catch was one of the biggest disputes of the era.

Of the 20 Tests played during the four series, Australia won five and England two.
As they held the Ashes, Australian captains Bob Simpson and Bill Lawry were happy to adopt safety-first tactics and their strategy of sedate batting saw many draws.
During this period, spectator attendances dropped and media condemnation increased, but Simpson and Lawry flatly disregarded the public dissatisfaction.

The failure of England to regain the Ashes for 16 years from 1989, coupled with the global dominance of the Australian team, had dulled the lustre of the series in recent years throughout most of the cricketing world, although it has remained the most popular cricketing contest for Australians.
However, the close results in the 2005 Ashes series, and the overall high quality and competitiveness of the cricket greatly boosted the popularity of the sport in Britain and considerably enhanced the profile of the Ashes around the world.
It remains to be seen whether the lopsided results of the 2006-07 Ashes series will have a negative impact on this newly acquired popularity outside of Australia.</entry>
</article>
