<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1171" title="Abbreviation" authors="3" lines="39">
  <entry author_id="136671" end="13" start="0">Questions which arise include the following: After the Second World War, the British greatly reduced their use of the full stop and other punctuations after abbreviations in at last semi-formal writing, while the Americans more readily kept its use until more recently, and still maintain it more than Britons.
The classic example, considered by their American counterparts quite curious, was the maintenance of the internal comma in that for the British organization of secret agents called 'Special Operations, Executive' - specifically, S.O.,E.
- which you will not find in histories written after about 1960.

But before that, many Britons were more scrupulous at maintaining the French form.
In French, the period only follows an abbreviation of the last letter in the abbreviation is not the last letter of its antecedent: M. is the abbreviation for monsieur while Mme is that for Madame and Mademoiselle yields Mlle as its own abbreviation.
Like many other cross-channel linguistic acquisitions, many Britons readily took this up and followed this rule themselves, while the Americans took a more simplistic rule and applied it rigorously.
Another way of forming an abbreviation is syllable by syllable.
This is prefered by the US Navy as it increases readability amidst the large number of initialisms that have to fit into the same letter abbreviation or acronym.
Hence DESRON 6 is used (in the full capital form) to mean "Destroyer Squadron 6," while COMNAVFORLANT would be "Commander, Naval Force (in the) Atlantic."

This method is deprecated in both British and American society in general.
Part of the antipathy toward it was its prevalence in Germany under the Nazis and the Soviet Union.
For example, Gestapo comes from geheime stadt Polizei, or "secret state police" while Comintern for the Communist International is another.
Another reason is that the French do not use it.</entry>
  <entry author_id="348154" end="28" start="13">or "abbrev."
Apart from the common form of shortening one word, there are other types of abbreviations.
These include apocopations, syllabic abbreviations, acronyms, initialisms and portmanteaux.
A syllabic abbreviation is an abbreviation formed from (usually) initial syllables of several words, such as Interpol = International + police.

On the other hand, they prevailed in Germany under the Nazis and in the Soviet Union for naming the plethora of new bureacratic organizations.
For example, Gestapo stands for Geheime Staats-Polizei, or "secret state police".
Similarly, Comintern stands for the Communist International.
This has caused syllabic abbreviations to have negative connotation, notwithstanding that such abbreviations were used in Germany even before the Nazis came to power, e.g., for Schutzpolizei.

East Asian languages whose writing uses Chinese-originated ideograms instead of an alphabet form abbreviations similarly by using key characters from a term or phrase.
For example, in the term for the United Nations, kokusai rengō (国際連合) is often abbreviated to kokuren (国連).
(Such abbreviations are called (略語) in Japanese).
The classic example is, of course, shogun.
The syllabic abbreviation is frequently used for universities: for instance, Beida (北大, Běidà) for Peking University (Beijing) and Tōdai (東大) for the University of Tokyo.
Syllabic abbreviations are prefered by the US Navy as it increases readability amidst the large number of initialisms that would otherwise have to fit into the same acronyms.
Hence DESRON 6 is used (in the full capital form) to mean "Destroyer Squadron 6," while COMNAVFORLANT would be "Commander, Naval Force (in the) Atlantic."</entry>
  <entry author_id="149908" end="39" start="28">An increase in literacy has, historically, sometimes spawned a trend toward abbreviation.
The standardization of English in the 15th through 17th centuries included such a growth in the use of abbreviation.
At first, abbreviations were sometimes represented with various marks, not only periods.
For example, specific phoneme sets like "er" were dropped from words and replaced with ɔ, like "mastɔ" instead of "master" or exacɔbate instead of "exacerbate".
While this seems trivial, it was symptomatic of an attempt by people manually reproducing academic texts to reduce their copy time.

In the 1830 in the United States, starting with Boston, abbreviation became a fad.
For example, during the growth of philological linguistic theory in academic Britain, abbreviating became very trendy.
The use of abbreviation for the names of "Father of modern etymology" J.R.R.
Tolkein and his friend C.S.
Lewis, members of Oxford literary group known as the Inklings, are sometimes cited as symptomatic of this.
Likewise, a century earlier in Boston, a fad of abbreviation started that swept the United States, with the globally popular term OK generally credited as a remnant of its influence.</entry>
</article>
