<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1177" title="Aleister Crowley" authors="10" lines="347">
  <entry author_id="1200" end="17" start="0">Son of a Plymouth Brethren preacher and heir to a small fortune, Crowley spent most of his adult life seeking out, writing about, and teaching a syncretic form of mysticism.
As a young adult, he was involved in the Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn, where he first studied mysticism -- and made enemies of William Butler Yeats and Arthur Edward Waite.
Several years later, and after having set mysticism aside for a matter of years, he had a mystical experience whilst on vacation in Cairo, Egypt which led to his founding of the religious philosophy known as Thelema.

The text Liber AL vel Legis, or The Book of the Law, which Crowley claimed had been dictated to him in Cairo by the spirit Aiwaz or Aiwass, was to form the cornerstone of Thelema.
The book's philosophy is highly opaque, apparently calling in places for peaceful (and erotic) discovery of magick, and in other places for violence and war.
Portions of it are in numerical cipher, which Crowley claimed inability to decode.

Crowley was notorious in his life -- a frequent target of attacks in the tabloid press, which labeled him "The Wickedest Man in the World" to his evident amusement.
The claims made about him by the press range from the realistic if scandalous at the time (that he was an avowed atheist, openly kept mistresses, and had favored the Germans in World War I) to the ridiculous (that he sacrificed hundreds of babies in black magic rituals).
At one point, he was expelled from Fascist Italy after having established a sort of magickal commune at Cefalu, Sicily.
Crowley claimed to use a scientific method to study what people at the time called "spiritual" experiences, making "The Method of Science, the Aim of Religion" the catchphrase of his magazine The Equinox.
By this he meant that mystical experiences should not be taken at face value, but critiqued and experimented with in order to arrive at religious truth.
In this he may be considered to foreshadow Dr. Timothy Leary, who at one point sought to apply the same method to psychedelic drug experiences.
Yet like Leary's, Crowley's method had many evident failings and has received little "scientific" attention outside the circle of Thelema's practitioners.

Needs more information about the initiatory system, GD, OTO, EGC, and AA Within the subject of occultism Crowley wrote widely, penning commentaries on the Tarot (The Book of Thoth), yoga (Book Four), the Kabbalah (Sepher Sephiroth), and numerous other subjects.
Like the Golden Dawn mystics before him, Crowley evidently sought to comprehend the entire human religious and mystical experience in a single philosophy.
Many of his books he published himself, expending the majority of his inheritance disseminating his views.
His prose works, such as the "Simon Iff" detective stories and the mystical novels Diary of a Drug Fiend and Moonchild, have not received significant notice outside of occult circles.</entry>
  <entry author_id="138060" end="48" start="17">Born Edward Alexander Crowley in Leamington, Warwickshire, England, between 11:00pm and 12 midnight on 12 October 1875.
His father Edward Crowley was a retired brewer--a lucrative family business.
His mother, Emily Bertha Bishop draws roots from a Devon and Sommerset family.
Aleister grew up in a staunch Plymouth Brethren household.
His father after retiring from his daily duties as a brewer took up the practice of preaching at a fanatical pace.
Daily bible studies and private tutoring were mainstains in young Aleister's childhood.
The literal translation of the Bible helped pave the way for his Mother, Emily, to coin the moniker, 'The Beast 666', on her son for his often disobedient and promiscuous behavior, which would be considered tame by today's youth.
It is due in part to Edward Senior's insistent that Aleister so thoroughly learn the Bible that he discovered its many inconsistencies.
He even felt compassionately towards the often maligned and one-sided nature of Divinity portraying any and all activities in life worth living as Sinful.
This infuriated Crowley and at the same time drove him to later become the often maligned yet commonly acknowledged most formidable magickian of the twentieth century.
His system of Occult Sciences is best described as a synthesis of various Eastern mystical systems (including Hinduism, Buddhism, Tantra the predecessor to Western Sex Magick, Zoroastrianism and the many systems of Yoga) fused with the Western Occult Sciences of the Golden Dawn and the many reformed rituals of FreeMasonry he later reformulated within the Ordo Templi Orientis (O.T.O).
This system later discussed is founded in scientific skepticism.
His undergraduate studies in Chemistry dutifully helped forge this scientific skepticism which later culminated in the many volumed and unparalleled occult publication, The Equinox.
Today, nearly 60 years since his passing in 1947 his works are becoming more prevalent and prominent, especially with today's current struggle between the dogmatic systems of Christianity and Islam.

This is in no small part due to the fact that within the Book of the Law it is forwarned that the scribe, Ankh-af-na-khonsu!--Aleister Crowley, was never to attempt to decode the ciphers for to do so would only end up in folly.
The later written, "The Law is For All" sees Crowley forwarning all to not discuss the writing amongst fellow critics for fear that Dogmatism would arise within any position taken.
It was years after the original trance sessions in Cairo that Crowley would accept the writing of the Book of the Law and follow it's doctrine.
Only through countless attempt to falsify its writings did he come to embrace them as the official doctrine of the New Aeon of Horus.
The rest of his professional and personal careers were spent expanding the new frontiers of scientific illuminism.
Crowley was very adament about any who chose to read his works, "Don't Believe Me!"
It is from this position of the skeptic he insists any person of common sense and reason will be shielded and protected against the many trappings of egotism that countless seers and prior prophets or holy men have succumb.

Crowley despised Moussolini and in his many writings of the Equinox he reveals that he also worked in the United States as an agent of England to help reveal the latent German fascist support within the United States, at that time.
When asking Scotland Yard if Crowley was an agent they always distanced themselves from him, due in no small part to Crowley being viceral towards the frigid and bigotted social views Victorian England exhibited throughout the first half of the twentieth century.
The Book of Wisdom and Folly, written in 1918 while in New York stands today as one of the most erudite pieces of mysticism ever written.
It has been disputed by many when Crowley layed claim to giving Churchill the mystical V for Victory sigil to help thwart Hitler's Occult practices that were targeted against Churchill and England, during WWII.
This should come as no surprise that Crowley would not be given credit for such work considering England was in the midst of transitioning itself as being a staunchly dogmatic nation to a more secular nation.
Aleister reveled in pushing the envelope of his day.
What is clear from the many biographers of his works is he loved England and through his various personal relationships with various political figures it is clear they valued his insight in matters of Diplomacy.
To his many critics and admirers no one has ever matched the quality and quantity of Occult Scientific work he produced in his over 72 years on this Earth.
Up until his death, Crowley never stopped pointing fun at all matters serious.
This refreshing approach to studying the many paths of occult science should be taken to heart by any serious student, practitioner or even historian of Crowley and other Occult authors.</entry>
  <entry author_id="61" end="68" start="48">Following the death of his father, the young Aleister (then "Alec" or "Alick") turned to a form of Satanism in grief.
However, within a few years he abandoned this for atheism and hedonism, or in his words, "began to behave like a normal, healthy human being."
During the year 1897, he slowly came to view earthly pursuits as useless and began his lifelong exploration of esoteric matters.
A number of events contributed to this change.
(See, for example, Aleister_Crowley#Chess.)

Rose and Aleister had a daughter, who AC named Nuit Ma Ahathoor Hecate Sappho Jezebel Lilith Crowley, in July of 1904.
This child died in 1906.
They had another daughter, Lola Zaza, in the summer of that year, and AC devised a special ritual of thanksgiving for her birth.
He performed a thanksgiving ritual before his first claimed success in the Abramelin operation, on October 9, 1906.
The events of that year gave the Abramelin book a central role in Crowley's system.
He described the primary goal of the "Great Work" using a term from this book, "the Knowledge and Conversation of the Holy Guardian Angel."

Sutin passes on various stories about AC's death and last words.
Frieda Harris supposedly reported him saying, "I am perplexed."
According to John Symonds, a Mr. Rowe witnessed Crowley's death along with a nurse, and reported his last words as, "Sometimes I hate myself."
Biographer Gerald Suster accepted the version of events he received from a "Mr.
W.H."
in which Crowley dies pacing in his living-room.
Supposedly Mr. W.H.
heard a crash while polishing furniture on the floor below, and entered Crowley's rooms to find him dead on the floor.
Patricia "Deirdre" MacAlpine, the mother of his son, denied all this and reports a sudden gust of wind and peal of thunder at the (otherwise quiet) moment of his death.</entry>
  <entry author_id="277465" end="80" start="68">Within the subject of occultism Crowley wrote widely, penning commentaries on the Tarot (The Book of Thoth), yoga (Book Four), the Kabbalah (Sepher Sephiroth), astrology (The General Principles of Astrology), and numerous other subjects.
He also wrote a Thelemic "translation" of the Tao Te Ching, based on earlier English translations since he knew little or no Chinese.
Like the Golden Dawn mystics before him, Crowley evidently sought to comprehend the entire human religious and mystical experience in a single philosophy.
He self-published many of his books, expending the majority of his inheritance to disseminate his views.
Many of his fiction works, such as the "Simon Iff" detective stories and Moonchild have not received significant notice outside of occult circles.
However his fictional work Diary of a Drug Fiend has received acclaim from those involved in the field of substance abuse rehabilitation.

Crowley had a peculiar sense of humour.
In his Book Four he includes a chapter purporting to illuminate the Qabalistic significance of Mother Goose nursery rhymes.
In re Humpty Dumpty, for instance, he recommends the occult authority "Ludovicus Carolus" -- better known as Lewis Carroll.
In a footnote to the chapter he admits that he had invented the alleged meanings, to show that one can find occult "Truth" in everything.
The title to chapter 69 is given as "The Way to Succeed - and the Way to Suck Eggs!"
a pun, as the chapter concerns the 69 sex position as a mystical act.</entry>
  <entry author_id="24902" end="144" start="80">His father, Edward Crowley, once maintained a lucrative family brewery business and was retired when Aleister Crowley was born.
His mother, Emily Bertha Bishop, drew roots from a Devon and Somerset family.
Aleister grew up in a staunch Plymouth Brethren household.
His father, after retiring from his daily duties as a brewer, took up the practice of preaching at a fanatical pace.
Daily Bible studies and private tutoring were mainstays in young Aleister's childhood; however, after his father's death, his mother's efforts at indoctrinating her son in the Christian faith only served to provoke Aleister's skepticism.
As a child, young Aleister's constant rebellious behaviour displeased his devout mother to such an extent she would chastise him by calling him "The Beast" (from the Book of Revelation), an epithet that Crowley would later happily adopt for himself.
He objected to the labelling of what he saw as life's most worthwhile and enjoyable activities as "sinful".

In response, Crowley created his own philosophical system, Scientific Illuminism — a synthesis of various Eastern mystical systems (including Hinduism, Buddhism, Tantra, the predecessor to Western sex magick, Zoroastrianism and the many systems of Yoga) fused with the Western occult sciences of the Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn and the many reformed rituals of Freemasonry he later reformulated within the Ordo Templi Orientis (O.T.O).
Crowley coined the term "Magick" to describe this system, which also appeals to scientific and philosophical skepticism.
His undergraduate studies in chemistry at Trinity College, Cambridge helped forge the scientific scepticism that later culminated in the many-volumed and unparalleled occult publication, The Equinox.

During the year 1897, he slowly came to view earthly pursuits as useless and began his lifelong exploration of esoteric matters.
A number of events contributed to this change.
(The section on chess in this article gives one example.)
Involved as a young adult in the Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn, he first studied mysticism with and made enemies of William Butler Yeats and Arthur Edward Waite.
Like many in occult circles of the time, Crowley voiced the view that Waite was a pretentious bore through searing critiques of Waite's writings and editorials of other authors' writings.

His friend and former Golden Dawn associate Allan Bennett introduced him to the ideas of Buddhism, while Samuel Liddell MacGregor Mathers, acting leader of the Golden Dawn organization, acted as his early mentor in western magick but would later become his enemy.
Several decades after Crowley's participation in the Golden Dawn, Mathers claimed copyright protection over a particular ritual and sued Crowley for infringement after Crowley's public display of the ritual.
While the public trial continued, both Mathers and Crowley claimed to call forth armies of demons and angels to fight on behalf of their summoner.
Both also developed and carried complex Seal of Solomon amulets and talismans.

While he did not officially break with Mathers until 1904, Crowley lost faith in this teacher's abilities soon after the 1900 schism in the Golden Dawn (if not before).
Later that year, Crowley travelled to Mexico and continued his magical studies in isolation.
AC's writings suggest that he discovered the word Abrahadabra during this time.
(The article on this word explains the spelling.)

In October of 1901, after practising Raja Yoga for some time, he said he had reached a state he called dhyana — one of many states of unification in thoughts that are described in Magick (Liber ABA) (See Crowley on egolessness).
1902 saw him writing the essay Berashith (the first word of Genesis), in which he gave meditation (or restraint of the mind to a single object) as the means of attaining his goal.
The essay describes ceremonial magick as a means of training the will, and of constantly directing ones thoughts to a given object through ritual.
In his 1903 essay, Science and Buddhism, Crowley urged an empirical approach to Buddhist teachings.

He said that a mystical experience in 1904 while on vacation in Cairo, Egypt, led to his founding of the religious philosophy known as Thelema.
Aleister's wife Rose started to behave in an odd way, and this led him to think that some entity had made contact with her.
At her instructions, he performed an invocation of the Egyptian god Horus on March 20 with (he wrote) "great success".
According to Crowley, the god told him that a new magical Aeon had begun, and that Crowley would serve as its prophet.
Rose continued to give information, telling Crowley in detailed terms to await a further revelation.
On 8 April and for the following two days at exactly noon he heard a voice, dictating the words of the text, Liber AL vel Legis, or The Book of the Law, which Crowley wrote down.
The voice claimed to be that of Aiwass (or Aiwaz "the minister of Hoor-paar-kraat," or Horus, the god of force and fire, child of Isis and Osiris) and self-appointed conquering lord of the New Aeon, announced through his chosen scribe "the prince-priest the Beast."

Portions of the book are in numerical cipher, which Crowley claimed the inability to decode (Setian Michael Aquino later claimed to be able to decode them).
Thelemic dogma (to the extent that Thelema has dogma) explains this by pointing to a warning within the Book of the Law — the speaker supposedly warned that the scribe, Ankh-af-na-khonsu (Aleister Crowley), was never to attempt to decode the ciphers, for to do so would end only in folly.
The later-written The Law is For All sees Crowley warning everyone not to discuss the writing amongst fellow critics, for fear that a dogmatic position would arise.
While he declared a "new Equinox of the Gods" in early 1904, supposedly passing on the revelation of March 20 to the occult community, it took years for Crowley to fully accept the writing of the Book of the Law and follow its doctrine.
Only after countless attempts to test its writings did he come to embrace them as the official doctrine of the New Aeon of Horus.
The remainder of his professional and personal careers were spent expanding the new frontiers of scientific illuminism.

Rose and Aleister had a daughter, whom Crowley named Nuit Ma Ahathoor Hecate Sappho Jezebel Lilith Crowley, in July of 1904.
This child died in 1906.
They had another daughter, Lola Zaza, in the summer of that year, and Crowley devised a special ritual of thanksgiving for her birth.

He performed a thanksgiving ritual before his first claimed success in what he called the "Abramelin operation," on October 9, 1906.
This was his implementation of a magical work described by medivak [[Jew] named Abraham of Worms in The Book of the Sacred Magic of Abramelin the Mage.
The events of that year gave the Abramelin book a central role in Crowley's system.
He described the primary goal of the "Great Work" using a term from this book: "the Knowledge and Conversation of the Holy Guardian Angel."
An essay in the first number of The Equinox gives several reasons for this choice of names:Crowley was notorious in his lifetime — a frequent target of attacks in the tabloid press, which labelled him "The Wickedest Man in the World" to his evident amusement.
At one point, he was expelled from Italy after having established a sort of commune, the organization of which was based on his personal philosophies, the Abbey of Thelema, at Cefalu, Sicily.

In 1934 Crowley was declared bankrupt after losing a court case in which he sued the artist Nina Hamnett for calling him a black magician in her 1932 book, Laughing Torso.
In addressing the jury, Mr Justice Swift said:  Aleister Crowley died of a respiratory infection in a Hastings boarding house on December 1, 1947, at the age of 72.
According to some accounts he died on December 5, 1947.
He was penniless and addicted to opium, which had been prescribed for his asthma and bronchitis, at the time.

Biographer Lawrence Sutin passes on various stories about Crowley's death and last words.
Frieda Harris supposedly reported him saying, "I am perplexed," though she did not see him at the very end.
According to John Symonds, a Mr Rowe witnessed Crowley's death along with a nurse, and reported his last words as, "Sometimes I hate myself."
Biographer Gerald Suster accepted the version of events he received from a "Mr W.H."
in which Crowley dies pacing in his living-room.
Supposedly Mr W.H.
heard a crash while polishing furniture on the floor below, and entered Crowley's rooms to find him dead on the floor.
Patricia "Deirdre" MacAlpine, the mother of his son, denied all this and reports a sudden gust of wind and peal of thunder at the (otherwise quiet) moment of his death.
According to MacAlpine, Crowley remained bedridden for the last few days of his life, but was in light spirits and conversational.
Readings at the cremation service in nearby Brighton included one of his own works, Hymn to Pan, and newspapers referred to the service as a black mass.
Brighton council subsequently resolved to take all necessary steps to prevent such an incident occurring again.</entry>
  <entry author_id="966462" end="157" start="144">His expressions of gender-bias may have been in part influenced by his failed marriage.
These feelings may have been further advanced by his experiences with pupils who abandoned their studies for women.
Among his beliefs were that women, except "a few rare individuals," care most about having children and will conspire against their husbands if they lack children to whom to devote themselves.
He claimed that their intentions were to force a man to abandon his life's work for their interests.
He only found women "tolerable" when they served the role of solely helping a man in his life's work.
However, he said that they were incapable of actually understanding the work.
He also felt that women did not have individuality and were solely guided by their impulses.

Crowley made racist statements against the Chinese, specifically the lower classes.
Indians, Italians, and Jews.
His derogatory application of the term "nigger" to Indians and Italians suggests he had a prejudice against Africans as well.

After defending the then-current anti-Semitic pogroms in Kishinev Russia, on the grounds that the deaths of thousands of Jews was a rational response to what he saw as the danger of Jewish ritual cannibalism, Crowley rhetorically asked how a system of value such as Qabala could come from "an entirely barbarous race, devoid of any spiritual pursuit."
"Is it to such people, indeed, that we are to look for the highest and subtlest spiritual knowledge?"
He answered his own questions by saying that the immorality of the source is not a valid critique of the material.</entry>
  <entry author_id="277465" end="176" start="157">Crowley was a highly prolific writer, not only on the topic of Thelema and magick, but on philosophy, politics, and culture.
He was also a published poet and playwright and left behind a countless number of personal letters and daily journal entries.
He self-published many of his books, expending the majority of his inheritance to disseminate his views.

Within the subject of occultism Crowley wrote widely, penning commentaries on magick, the Tarot, Yoga, the Kabbalah, astrology, and numerous other subjects.
He also wrote a Thelemic interpolation of the Tao Te Ching, based on earlier English translations since he knew little or no Chinese.
Like the Golden Dawn mystics before him, Crowley evidently sought to comprehend the entire human religious and mystical experience in a single philosophy.

Some of his most influential books include: He also edited and produced a series of publications in book form called The Equinox (subtitled "The Review of Scientific Illuminism"), which served as the voice of his magical order, the A.'.A.'..
Although the entire set is influential and remains one of the definitive works on occultism, some of the more notable issues include: Crowley also wrote fiction and plays, most of which have not received significant notice outside of occult circles.
Some of his fictional/theatrical works include: Crowley also had a peculiar sense of humour.
He wrote a polemic arguing against George Bernard Shaw's interpretation of the Gospels in his preface to Androcles and the Lion, which was edited by Francis King and published as Crowley on Christ, and shows him at his erudite and witty best.
In his Magick, Book 4 he includes a chapter purporting to illuminate the Qabalistic significance of Mother Goose nursery rhymes.
In re Humpty Dumpty, for instance, he recommends the occult authority "Ludovicus Carolus" -- better known as Lewis Carroll.
In a footnote to the chapter he admits that he had invented the alleged meanings, to show that one can find occult "Truth" in everything.
In The Book of Lies, the title to chapter 69 is given as "The Way to Succeed - and the Way to Suck Eggs!"
a pun, as the chapter concerns the 69 sex position as a mystical act.

Crowley was also a published, if minor, poet.
He wrote the 1929 Hymn to Pan, perhaps his most widely read and anthologized poem.
Three pieces by Crowley, "The Quest ", "The Neophyte ", and "The Rose and the Cross ", appear in the 1917 collection The Oxford Book of English Mystical Verse.
Crowley's unusual sense of humour is on display in White Stains, an 1898 collection of pornographic verse pretended to be "the literary remains of George Archibald Bishop, a neuropath of the Second Empire;" the volume is prefaced with a notice that says that " The Editor hopes that Mental Pathologists, for whose eyes alone this treatise is destined, will spare no precaution to prevent it falling into other hands."</entry>
  <entry author_id="1296259" end="191" start="176">Crowley, along with Leah Hirsig, founded the Abbey of Thelema in Cefalu, Sicily in 1920.
The name was borrowed from Rabelais's satire Gargantua, where the "Abbey of Theleme" is described as a sort of anti-monestary where the lives of the inhabitants were "spent not in laws, statutes, or rules, but according to their own free will and pleasure."
This idealistic utopia was to be the model of Crowley's commune, while also being a type of magical school, giving it the designation "Collegium ad Spiritum Sanctum", The College of the Holy Spirit.
The general programme was in line with the A.'.A.'.
course of training, and included daily adorations to the sun, a study of Crowley's writings, regular yogic and ritual practices (which were to be recorded), as well as general domestic labor.
The object, naturally, was for students to devote themselves to the Great Work of disovering and manifesting their True Wills.

In 1923, a 23-year old Oxford undergraduate by the name of Raoul Loveday (or Frederick Charles Loveday) died at the abbey.
His wife, Betty May, originally blamed this on his participation in one of Crowley's rituals.
Later, however, she accepted the doctor's diagnosis of acute enteric fever contracted by drinking from a mountain spring.
(Crowley had warned the couple against drinking the water.
Lawrence Sutin reports all this in his biography of AC.)
When May returned to London, she gave an interview to a tabloid paper.
The Sunday Express included her story in its ongoing attacks on Crowley.
With these and similar rumors about activities at Thelema in mind, Mussolini's government demandd that Crowley leave the country in 1923.
After Crowley's departure, the Abbey of Thelema was eventually abandoned and local residents whitewashed over Crowley's murals.</entry>
  <entry author_id="852732" end="214" start="191">Some of his published poetry includes:  Contrary to popular belief, Aleister Crowley was not a Mason.
It has been said that he is a Freemason, however Freemasonry is an entire organization in itself.
Aleister Crowley is known to have been in the Golden Knights and O.T.O.

“However, O.T.O.
is an offshoot of Freemasonry.
Keep in mind that the two are not the same.
The Ordo Templi Orientis (the Oriental Order of the Templars).
Unlike the Masons, the OTO would allow women as members.
Otherwise, at this stage, the organization was fairly similar to the Masons, and the inner circle of OTO leadership had advanced Masonic degrees as a job requirement.”  Source: http://www.rotten.com/library/conspiracy/oto/

John Hamill.
Transactions of Quatuor Coronati Lodge.
Vol.
109. p. 214.

“Fringe Masonry encompasses those regular freemasons whose interest in mysticism and the occult led them to such organizations as the Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn (HOGD) and the Ordo Templi Orientis.
Neither of these organizations was ever recognized by any regular masonic body.
The Golden Dawn had no masonic pretensions but the fact that the founders of the OTO made such claims opened it to accusations of being clandestine or irregular Freemasonry.
Since 1919 (Equinox Vol.
III, No.
1) they ceased to claim being or having any authority regarding Freemasonry.
Currently most masonic Grand Lodge jurisdictions are unaware of, or indifferent to, the existence or history of the OTO.

It must be stressed that although Freemasonry recognizes many of these men as freemasons, no recognized masonic body, and few freemasons, endorse their opinions and conclusions as an accepted extension or interpretation of the teachings of Freemasonry.
Their published works have had no positive or lasting impact on Freemasonry.
In fact their writings are more often quoted, out of context, by anti-masons attempting to link masonic teachings with these individuals' opinions.</entry>
  <entry author_id="146368" end="233" start="214">Jane Wolfe, who lived with Crowley at his infamous Abbey od Cefalu, also used the Ouija board.
She credits some of her greatest spiritual communications to use of this implement.
Crowley also discussed the Ouija board with another of his students, and the most ardent of them, Frater Achard (Charles Stansfeld Jones): it is freaquently mentioned in their unpublished letters.

Throughout 1917 Achard experimented with the board as a means of summoning Angels, as opposed to Elementals.
In one letter Crowley told Jones:, "Your Ouija board experiment is rather fun.
You see how very satifactory it is, but I believe things improve greatly with practice.
I think you should keep to one angel, and make the magical preparations more elaborate."

Over the years, both became so facinated by the board that they discussed marketing their own design.
Their discourse culminated in a letter, dated February 21, 1919, in which Crowley tells Jones, "Re: Ouija Board.
I offer you the basis of ten percent of my net profit.
You are, if you accept this, responsible for the legal protection of the ideas, and the marketing of the copyright designs.
I trust that this may be satisfactory to you.
I hope to let you have the material in the course of a week."
In March, Crowley wrote to Achard to inform him, "I'll think up another name for Ouija."
But their business venture never came to fruition and Crowley's new design, along with his name for the board, has not survived.

Crowley has stated, of the Ouija Board, that, "Their is, however, a good way of using this instrument to get what you want, and that is to perform the whole operation in a consecrated circle, so that undesirable aliens cannot interfere with it.
You should then employ the proper magical invocation in order to get into your circle just the one spirit you want.
It is comparatively easy to do this.
A few simple instructions are all that is nessesary, and I shall be pleased to give these, free of charge, to any one who cares to apply."</entry>
  <entry author_id="6113152" end="281" start="233">Aleister Crowley was born on October 12th, 1875 e.v.
in Leamington Spa, England.
His family were very strict members of a christist cult named the Plymouth Brethren.
This cult was, in fact, so restricting that an intense hatred and repulsion developed towards the dogma of the christists.
Aleister Crowley was on genius level.
Such unique features in the karma of his life led Mr. Crowley to look closely on what path his life was to take.
What began as boyish rebellion against his restricting religion started a career on the Path of Magick and Initiation.

During this Search for enlightment he was introduced to George Cecil Jones by the Secret Chiefs.
Mr. Jones turned out to be a member of an occult organization named; THE GOLDEN DAWN.
The leader of this organization was a Magician named S.L.
MacGregor Mathers.
In 1898 e.v., Aleister Crowley received his first Initiation in the Golden Dawn on the Path of Western Esoteric Tradition.
Yet A.C. was a member of the old Golden Dawn for only two years before events occurred that forced A.C. to leave.

Around this time, in 1900 e.v., A.C. created in Mexico, his first Magical Order, L.I.L., the Lamp of the Invisible Light.
He left the Order behind and never knew what happened to it.
Another seed planted on his long and exciting career as a Magician.

In 1903 e.v., Aleister Crowley married a woman by the name of Rose Kelly.
Rose Kelly went on the honeymoon to Cairo where the Book of the Law was given by Aiwass the Minister of Hoor-paar-kraat.
And all this is detailed in THE EQUINOX OF THE GODS.

On November 15th, 1907 e.v.
the A.·.A.·.
was Manifested by Triad from the Higher Planes and reestablished.
To this day, it is called by A.·.A.·.
members, THE FEAST OF REFORMULATION where great Invocations and Celebrations are held throughout the world.

Theodor Reuss, of the old O.T.O., tried to forbid Aleister Crowley from using the Law of Θελημα in the O.T.O.. Several days later, on November 27th, he 1921 e.v.
wrote in his diary: "I have proclaimed myself O.H.O., Frater Superior O.T.O.
of the Order of Oriental Templars".
The magical forces of this conquering became a reality when on October 28th, 1923 e.v.
Theodor Reuss was eliminated by the Gods to permit the prophet his Path to World Leadership.
Yea, Aleister Crowley did not inherit the O.T.O.
in the ordinary sense; he took it over.

It was March 14th, 1942 e.v.
when Aleister Crowley made Karl Germer his Successor in the O.T.O..
He never changed his mind and when Aleister Crowley died on December 1st, 1947 e.v Karl Germer took over as Head of the O.T.O.. Karl Germer was Head of the O.T.O.
until his death in 1962 e.v..
When Karl Germer died in the arms of Sasha Germer he stated his last wishes that Marcelo Motta be his Successor.
This is the famous Letter of Succession from Karl Germer to Marcelo Motta.
And this letter that Sasha Germer wrote is dated October 30th, 1962 e.v..
It is absolute proof of the truth of Marcelo Motta being the O.H.O.. (Note that any sanctions from Aleister Crowley to Grady McMurtry were subject to the approval of Karl Germer.
This letter of October 30th makes Grady McMurtry completely deluded to claim the O.H.O.)

This ends the brief history of the O.T.O.
from beginning to present day.
Since the establishment of non-profit religious status we have added Society to the front of O.T.O.
; and for legal purposes we call ourselves Society O.T.O.
or Society Ordo Templi Orientis.

For admission in a Aleister Crowley existing lineage of AA; and to become a Probationer write.
David Bersson P.O.
Box 59326 Pittsburgh, PA 15210 USA</entry>
  <entry author_id="6113152" end="329" start="281">Aleister Crowley was born on October 12th, 1875 e.v.
in Leamington Spa, England.
His family were very strict members of a christist cult named the Plymouth Brethren.
This cult was, in fact, so restricting that an intense hatred and repulsion developed towards the dogma of the christists.
Aleister Crowley was on genius level.
Such unique features in the karma of his life led Mr. Crowley to look closely on what path his life was to take.
What began as boyish rebellion against his restricting religion started a career on the Path of Magick and Initiation.

During this Search for enlightment he was introduced to George Cecil Jones by the Secret Chiefs.
Mr. Jones turned out to be a member of an occult organization named; THE GOLDEN DAWN.
The leader of this organization was a Magician named S.L.
MacGregor Mathers.
In 1898 e.v., Aleister Crowley received his first Initiation in the Golden Dawn on the Path of Western Esoteric Tradition.
Yet A.C. was a member of the old Golden Dawn for only two years before events occurred that forced A.C. to leave.

Around this time, in 1900 e.v., A.C. created in Mexico, his first Magical Order, L.I.L., the Lamp of the Invisible Light.
He left the Order behind and never knew what happened to it.
Another seed planted on his long and exciting career as a Magician.

In 1903 e.v., Aleister Crowley married a woman by the name of Rose Kelly.
Rose Kelly went on the honeymoon to Cairo where the Book of the Law was given by Aiwass the Minister of Hoor-paar-kraat.
And all this is detailed in THE EQUINOX OF THE GODS.

On November 15th, 1907 e.v.
the A.·.A.·.
was Manifested by Triad from the Higher Planes and reestablished.
To this day, it is called by A.·.A.·.
members, THE FEAST OF REFORMULATION where great Invocations and Celebrations are held throughout the world.

Theodor Reuss, of the old O.T.O., tried to forbid Aleister Crowley from using the Law of Θελημα in the O.T.O.. Several days later, on November 27th, he 1921 e.v.
wrote in his diary: "I have proclaimed myself O.H.O., Frater Superior O.T.O.
of the Order of Oriental Templars".
The magical forces of this conquering became a reality when on October 28th, 1923 e.v.
Theodor Reuss was eliminated by the Gods to permit the prophet his Path to World Leadership.
Yea, Aleister Crowley did not inherit the O.T.O.
in the ordinary sense; he took it over.

It was March 14th, 1942 e.v.
when Aleister Crowley made Karl Germer his Successor in the O.T.O..
He never changed his mind and when Aleister Crowley died on December 1st, 1947 e.v Karl Germer took over as Head of the O.T.O.. Karl Germer was Head of the O.T.O.
until his death in 1962 e.v..
When Karl Germer died in the arms of Sasha Germer he stated his last wishes that Marcelo Motta be his Successor.
This is the famous Letter of Succession from Karl Germer to Marcelo Motta.
And this letter that Sasha Germer wrote is dated October 30th, 1962 e.v..
It is absolute proof of the truth of Marcelo Motta being the O.H.O.. (Note that any sanctions from Aleister Crowley to Grady McMurtry were subject to the approval of Karl Germer.
This letter of October 30th makes Grady McMurtry completely deluded to claim the O.H.O.)

This ends the brief history of the O.T.O.
from beginning to present day.
Since the establishment of non-profit religious status we have added Society to the front of O.T.O.
; and for legal purposes we call ourselves Society O.T.O.
or Society Ordo Templi Orientis.

Love is the law, love under will O.T.O.
P.O.
Box 42423 Pittsburgh, PA 15210 USA</entry>
  <entry author_id="61" end="347" start="329">Spence writes in the International Journal of Intelligence and Counterintelligence that Crowley worked for the British intelligence while residing in America from 1914-1918, under a cover of being a German propaganda agent and a supporter of Irish independence.
Crowley's mission was to gather intelligence about the German intelligence network, the Irish independent activists and produce aberrant propaganda, aiming at compromising the German and Irish ideals.
He also used German magazines The Fatherland and The International as outlets for his other writings.

During his time in the U.S., Crowley practiced the task of a Magister Templi in the A∴A∴ as he conceived it, namely interpreting every phenomenon as a particular dealing of "God" with his soul.
He began to see various women he met as officers in his ongoing initiation, associating them with priests wearing animal masks in Egyptian ritual.
A meditation during his relationship with one such woman (Jeanne Robert Foster) led him to claim the title of Magus, also referring to the system of the A∴A∴.

Two periods of magical experimentation followed.
In June 1916, he began the first of these at the New Hampshire cottage of Evangeline Adams, having ghostwritten most of two books on astrology for her.
His diaries at first show discontent at the gap between his view of the grade of Magus and his view of himself: "It is no good making up my mind to do anything material; for I have no means.
But this would vanish if I could make up my mind."
Despite his objections to sacrificing a living animal, he resolved to crucify a frog as part of a rehearsal of the life of Jesus in the Gospels (afterward declaring it his willing familiar), "with the idea...that some supreme violation of all the laws of my being would break down my Karma or dissolve the spell that seems to bind me."
Slightly more than a month later, having taken ethyl oxide, he had a vision of the universe from modern scientific cosmology that he frequently referred to in later writings.

Crowley began another period of magical work on an island in the Hudson River after buying large amounts of red paint instead of food.
Having painted "Do what thou wilt" on the cliffs at both sides of the island, he received gifts from curious visitors.
Here at the island he had visions of seeming past lives, though he refused to endorse any theory of what they meant beyond linking them to his unconscious.
Towards the end of his stay, he also had a shocking experience he linked to "the Chinese wisdom" which made even Thelema appear insignificant.
Nevertheless, he continued in his work.
Before leaving the country he formed a sexual and magical relationship with Leah Hirsig, who he met earlier, and with her help began painting canvases with more creativity and passion.</entry>
</article>
