<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1182" title="Athena" authors="2" lines="81">
  <entry author_id="21492" end="12" start="0">Athena (also transliterated Athene), goddess of wisdom, associated by the Romans with their Etruscan goddess Minerva, was attended by an owl, carried the goatskin called the aegis and was accompanied by the goddess of victory, Nike.
Athena is an armed warrior goddess, never a child, always a virgin, ().
The Parthenon at Athens is her most famous shrine.
She never had a consort or lover.
Athena was already a goddess in the Aegean before the coming of the Greeks.
Her name derives from a pre-Greek language layer earlier than the Mycenaeans and its real meaning is lost.

Athena is classically portrayed wearing full armor, carrying a lance and a shield with the head of the gorgon Medusa mounted on it.
It is in this posture that she was depicted in Phidias's famous gold and ivory statue of her, now lost to history, in the Parthenon on the Athenian Acropolis.

She was often referred to with the epithet "Pallas Athena".
Pallas was an ambiguous figure, sometimes male sometimes female, never imagined apart from Athena.
She killed Pallas in a mistake, and ever after wore her/his goatskin fringed with chthonic serpents, as the protective.
With the epithet "Athena Promachos" she led in battle.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7666744" end="81" start="12">Athena was given many other cult titles.
She had the epithet Athena Ergane as the patron of craftsmen and artisans.
With the epithet Athena Parthenos ("virgin")she was especially worshipped in the festivals of the Panathenaea and Pamboeotia where both militaristic and athletic displays took place.
With the epithet Athena Promachos she led in battle.
With the epithet Athena Polias ("of the city"), Athena was the protector of not only Athens but also of many other cities, including Argos, Sparta, Gortyn, Lindos, and Larisa.

She was given the epithet Athena Hippeia or Athena Hippia, horse as the inventor of the chariot, and was worshipped under this title at Athens, Tegea and Olympia.
As Athena Hippeia she was given an alternative parentage: Poseidon and Polyphe, daughter of Oceanus..
In each of these cities her temple frequently was the major temple on the acropolis.

In classical times the Plynteria, or “Feast of Adorning”, was observed every May, it was a festival lasting five days.
During this period the Priestesses of Athena, or “Plyntrides”, performed a cleansing ritual within “the Erecththeum”, the personal sanctuary of the goddess.
Here Athena's statue was undressed, her clothes washed, and body purified.

Classically, Athena is portrayed wearing full armor, with her helmet raised high on the forehead to reveal the image of Nike.
Her shield bears at its centre the gorgoneion, the head of the gorgon, as does her aegis.
It is in this standing posture that she was depicted in Phidias's famous lost gold and ivory statue of her, 36 m tall, the Athena Parthenos in the Parthenon.
Athena also often is depicted with an owl sitting on one of her shoulders.
The Mourning Athena is a relief sculpture that dates around 460 BC and portrays a weary Athena resting on a staff.In earlier, archaic portraits of Athena in Black-figure pottery, the goddess retains some of her Minoan-Mycenaean character, such as great bird wings although this is not true of archaic sculpture such as those of Aphaean Athena, where Athena has subsumed an earlier, invisibly numinous —Aphaea— goddess with Cretan connections in her mythos.

Apart from her attributes, there seems to be a relative consensus in late sculpture from the Classical period, the fifth century onward, as to what Athena looked like.
Most noticeable in the face is perhaps the full round strong chin with a high nose that has a high bridge as a natural extension of the forehead.
The eyes typically are somewhat deeply set.
The unsmiling lips are usually full, but the mouth is fairly narrow, usually just slightly wider than the nose.
The neck is somewhat long.
The net result is a serene, serious, somewhat aloof beauty.
Athena had a special relationship with Athens, as is shown by the etymological connection of the names of the goddess and the city.
The citizens of Athens built a statue of Athena as a temple to the goddess, which had piercing eyes, a helmet on her head, attired with an aegis or cuirass, and an extremely long spear.
It also had a crystal shield with the head of the Gorgon on it.
A large snake accompanied her and she held the goddess of victory in her hand.

Athena is associated with Athens, a plural name because it was the place where she presided over her sisterhood, the Athenai, in earliest times: " was the city where the Goddess was called Mykene, and Mycenae is named in the plural for the sisterhood of females who tended her there.At Thebes she was called Thebe, and the city again a plural, Thebae (or Thebes, where the "s" is the plural formation).
Similarly, at Athens she was called Athena, and the city Athenae (or Athens, again a plural)."
Whether her name is attested in Eteocretan or not will have to wait for decipherment of Linear A.

Günther Neumann has suggested that Athena's name is possibly of Lydian origin; it may be a compound word derived in part from Tyrrhenian "ati", meaning mother and the name of the Hurrian goddess "Hannahannah" shortened in various places to "Ana".
In Mycenaean Greek, at Knossos a single inscription A-ta-na po-ti-ni-ja /Athana potniya/ appears in the Linear B tablets from the Late Minoan II-era "Room of the Chariot Tablets"; these comprise the earliest Linear B archive anywhere.
Although Athana potniya often is translated Mistress Athena, it literally means "the potnia of At(h)ana", which perhaps, means the Lady of Athens; Any connection to the city of Athens in the Knossos inscription is uncertain.
We also find A-ta-no-dju-wa-ja /Athana diwya/, the final part being the Linear B spelling of what we know from Ancient Greek as Diwia (Mycenaean di-u-ja or di-wi-ja): divine Athena also was a weaver and the deity of crafts.
(see dyeus).

Some authors believe that, in early times, Athena was either an owl herself or a bird goddess in general: in Book 3 of the Odyssey, she takes the form of a sea-eagle.
These authors argue that she dropped her prophylactic owl-mask before she lost her wings.
"Athena, by the time she appears in art," Jane Ellen Harrison had remarked, "has completely shed her animal form, has reduced the shapes she once wore of snake and bird to attributes, but occasionally in black-figure vase-paintings she still appears with wings."
Some authors claim that her tasselled aegis may be the remnants of wings.
Others believe that it is scaly, indicating that it is snakeskin.

A brief summary of Athena's evolution of myriad motifs after her dominance in Greece may be seen as follows: The rise of Christianity in Greece ended the worship of Greek deities and polytheism in general, but she resurfaced in the Middle Ages as a defender of sagacity and virtue so that her masculine warrior status was still intact.
(She may be found on some family crests of nobility.)
During the Renaissance she donned the mantle of patron of the arts and human endeavor and finally although not ultimately, Athena personified the miracles of freedom and republic during the French Revolution.
(A statue of the goddess was centered on the Place de la Revolution in Paris.)

Athena (Minerva) is the subject of the $50 1915-S Panama-Pacific commemorative coin.
At 2.5 troy oz (78 g) gold, this is the largest (by weight) coin ever produced by the U.S. Mint.
This was the first $50 coin issued by the U.S. Mint and no higher was produced until the production of the $100 platinum coins in 1997.
Of course, in terms of face-value in adjusted dollars, the 1915 is the highest denomination ever issued by the U.S. Mint.

For over a century a full-scale replica of the Parthenon has stood in Nashville, Tennessee, which is known as the Athens of the South.
In 1990, a gilded 41 feet (12.5 m) tall replica of Phidias' statue of Athena Parthenos was added.
The state seal of California features an image of Athena (or Minerva) kneeling next to a brown grizzly bear.

The goddess also holds a special place in the traditions at Bryn Mawr College in Pennsylvania.
A statue of Athena (a replica of the original bronze one in the arts and archaeology library) resides in the Great Hall.
It is traditional at exam time for students to leave offerings to the goddess with a note asking for good luck, or to repent for accidentally breaking any of the college's numerous other traditions.
Athena's owl also serves as the mascot of the college, and one of the college hymns is called "Pallas Athena."

Jean Boucher's statue of the seated skeptical thinker Ernest Renan, shown to the left, caused great controversy when it was installed in Tréguier, Brittany in 1902.
Renan's 1862 biography of Jesus had denied his divinity, and he had written the "Prayer on the Acropolis" addressed to the goddess Athena.
The statue was placed in the square fronted by the cathedral.
Renan's head was turned away from the building, while Athena, beside him, was depicted raising her arm, which was interpreted as indicating a challenge to the church during an anti-clerical phase in French official culture.
The installation was accompanied by a mass protest from local Roman Catholics and a religious service against the growth of skepticism and secularism.

Athena has been used numerous times as a symbol of a republic by different countries.
A recent sample is the 60 Years of the Second Republic commemorative coin issued by Austria in 2005.
Athena is depicted in the obverse of the coin, representing the Austrian Republic.
Athena had an "androgynous compromise" that allowed her traits and what she stood for to be attributed to male and female rulers alike over the course of history (such as Marie de Medici, Anne of Austria, Christina of Sweden, and Catherine the Great).

J.J. Bachofen advocated that Athena was originally a maternal figure stable in her security and poise but was caught up and perverted by a patriarchal society; this was especially the case in Athens.
The goddess adapted but could very easily be seen as a god.
He viewed it as "motherless paternity in the place of fatherless maternity" where once altered, Athena's character was to be crystalized as that of a patriarch.

Whereas Bachofen saw the switch to paternity on Athena's behalf as an increase of power, Freud perceived Athena as an "original mother goddess divested of her power".
Instead, Athena was denoted to only be known as Zeus's daughter never to be allowed to expression of motherhood rather but most different from Bachofen's perspective is the lack of role permanency.
Freud knew that time and cultures would mold Athena to stand for what was necessary.</entry>
</article>
