<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1190" title="Alternative history" authors="2" lines="313">
  <entry author_id="225288" end="122" start="0">1914- Assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand in June.
Start of World War I in August.
Invasion of Serbia

1919- Russian Civil War erupts between Imperial and Socialist-Republican troops in Petrograd.
German troops occupy Poland.
Austrian forces invade Russia after major battles near its border.
Fall of Moscow in June, surrender of Russia in August.
Treaty of Vienna signed in November.
Socialist State installed in non-occupied Russia.
Republic installed in Serbia.

1921- Creation of the Austro-Hungarian Parliament, and the Imperial and Royal Senate.
Assembly of Nationalities formed to represent all cultural groups.
Hungary forms its local Parliament.

1923- First Elections, General Franz Herzog of the Austro-Hungarian Democratic Party (AHDP) wins the elections in a close tie against the AHUP.
Creation of the Lower and Upper Houses of Congress.
First elections for Congress, Parliament, and Assemblies.

1924- The Parliament and Congress drafts the Imperial Constitution.
The constitution will give the emperor only limited power.
Hungarian Parliament drafts its own local constitution.
Freedom of speech, press, and petition established by constitution.

1925- Congress and Parliament approve the Constitution.
Treaty of Paris signed with France for further economic exchanges.
Military alliance with Wilhelm III of Germany.

1926- Charles I signs economic treaty with the United States.
Bohemian protests in March, Bohemians demand special status.
Bohemians granted home rule and coronation of Charles I as King of Bohemia.
Charles I introduces literacy reform.

1927- Second Elections for Prime Minister, the AHUP wins.
Parliament elections: AHUP victory.
Charles I visits Spain and signs an alliance with the Spanish Republic.

1930- Charles I die replaced by Hiendrich I (March).
Hiendrich I visits the Colony of Tunisia in May.
He is the first emperor to visit a colony.
Parliament gives Bosnia provincial status, and is attached to Hungary.
Literacy rate reaches 70%

1939- Hiendrich I die replaced by Charles II (May) Trade treaty signed with Siam.
Japan invades French Indochina.
France and Britain declare war on Japan.
Austria-Hungary joins France and Britain.
HIMS Burgenland, Tyrol, Dalmaten, Wien, and Franz Josef I battles Imperial Japanese Navy off China (December)

1940- Olympic Games held in Vienna, Winter Games held in Salzburg.
Japan invades the Philippines and Indonesia.
The Netherlands and the United States declare war.
Austrian troops land in Luzon Island, Philippines.
Imperial Navy defeats Japanese Navy off Luzon in March.

1941- Japanese troops invade Manchuria and mainland China.
Austrian troops invade Singapore Island, occupied by Japan.
Battle of Singapore: British and French planes bombards the city, Austrian troops fight Japanese troops in the northern jungles.
The HIMS Trieste sunk by Japanese air attack off Singapore while fighting Japanese Coast Guard gun boats.
Naval Battle of Kamtchaka Peninsula: 12 Japanese warships sunk by 6 Austrian ships, 10 American ships and 10 Russian ships.
Literacy rate reaches 90%   1945- Limited-self rule given to Serbia.
Air battle over Batavia, Indonesia.
Austrian troops take control of Luzon Island and smaller islands.
Quick progress towards Manila.
Austro-Netherlands troops take control of Java and Timor.
Invasion of Indochina by air and sea.
Austrian troops take Saigon in March.
Bombing raids over Tokyo, Japan.
Surrender of Manila in November.
Surrender of Japan in December

1946- Treaty of Bangkok reduces Japan to the historic islands of before 1910, Formosa or Taiwan becomes a part of the Republic of China.
Korea becomes a Republic.
France, Britain, America, Holland, and Portugal re-gain their pre-1939 colonies.
Austria will occupy Japan until 1947.
Austria will gain no lands in the Pacific.

1947- Visit of Emperor Napoleon V of France to Vienna to thank Austria for its support in the Pacific War of 1939-1945.
Austrian occupation of Japan ends in May.
Austrian troops return home as heroes of the nation.
Charles II signs treaty with Korea.

1949- Formation of the United Nations, The Austro-Hungarian Empire joins as one of the original 51 members.
Civil War erupts in China between Nationalists and Communists.
Austrian troops stationed in Fuzhou attacked by Communist troops.
Austria declares war on Communist Chinese troops.
Austrian re-enforcements arrive in Fuzhou.
Reforms in education and finances.
Creation of the National Bank.
1950- Death of Charles II, replaced by Franz Josef II.
Austrian troops in China defeat Communist troops in Yunnan and Hunan states.
Chinese Communist leader, Mao Zedong captured by Austrian troops, he his handed over to Nationalist troops.

1951- Constitutional monarchy officially established.
Franz Josef II retires all troops from China.
Chinese Communists surrender to Nationalist troops.
UN oversees the establishment of a democratic government.

1960- Treaty of Friendship with the UK and the USA.
Limited self-rule given to colonies in Africa and Asia.
Treaty of Co-Operation signed with Finland.

1967- Death of Maximillian I, replaced by Franz Josef III.
Free speech outlawed.
Censorship of the press.
The USA cuts relations with Austria-Hungary.

1968- Franz Josef III outlaws the constitution.
Civil strife, townspeople march on Schobrunn Palace in Vienna.
1969- Violence erupts in Bohemia and Hungary against Emperor Franz Josef III.
Kaiserjager troops join revolutionaries and march on Vienna.
All major army units turn over to the revolutionaries.
Loyalists of Franz Josef III and sailors fight each other in the city of Trieste.
The HIMS King of Hungary stationed in Trieste fires to mark the beginning of the Revolution against Franz Josef III.
Glorious Revolution against the Emperor: Sailors and soldiers attack Vienna, Imperial stronghold.
Siege of Vienna in November and attack on the Imperial Palace.
Gun fighting between revolutionary soldiers and Imperial Guards outside the Palace.

1970- Abdication of Franz Josef III, rule by Parliament established.
Constitution re-established.
General Karl Albert declared President.

1981- Russia invades Persia, Persian troops routed in battle.
Austria-Hungary and Turkey declare war on Russia.
Austrian Naval forces engage Soviet-Russian Navy in the Black Sea.
Austrian troops enter Russia from Crimea.
Russian troops routed near Azov.
Austrian Air Force bombards Russian positions in Persia.
The dreadnought HMIS Albania engages the Soviet destroyer Bolshevik.
The Bolshevik is sunk.

1982- Austrian Land Forces defeat Russian troops near Samara.
Austrian push towards Moscow.
Siege of Moscow in May and the fall of the Soviet government in November.
The Republic is restored.
Treaty of Prague signed by Russia and Austria-Hungary.
UN troops sent to Russia for peacekeeping.
School made compulsory through age 18.

2002- Peacekeeping mission in Angola and Nigeria.
Limited self-rule given to Trentino and Trieste.
Provincial status given to Albania and Crimea, attached to Hungary.
Literacy Rate reaches monumental 100%.</entry>
  <entry author_id="6174009" end="313" start="122">Alternative history or alternate history is a subgenre of speculative fiction (or some would say science fiction) and historical fiction that is set in a world in which history has diverged from history as it is generally known.
Alternative history literature asks the question, "What if history had developed differently?"
Most works in this genre are based in real historical events, yet feature social, geopolitical, or industrial circumstances that developed differently than our own.
While to some extent all fiction can be described as "alternative history," the subgenre proper comprises fiction in which a change or point of divergence occurs in the past that causes human society to develop in a way that is distinct from our own.

Since the 1950s, this type of fiction has to a large extent merged with science fictional tropes involving (a) cross-time, or paratime, travel between alternative histories/universes (or psychic awareness of the existence of "our" universe by the people in another, as in Vladimir Nabokov and Philip K. Dick; see below); or (b) ordinary voyaging uptime or downtime that results in history splitting into two or more timelines.
Cross-time, time-splitting and alternative history themes have become so closely interwoven that it is impossible to discuss them fully apart from one another.
Thus, cross-time and time-splitting stories will be an important part of this article insofar as they portray one or more alternative histories that diverged from a common past.

In French, alternative history novels are called uchronie.
This neologism is based on the word utopia (a place that does not exist) and the Greek for time, chronos.
An uchronie, then, is defined as a time that does not exist.
Another occasionally-used term for the genre is "allohistory" (lit.
"other history").
The earliest example of alternative history appears to be Book IX, sections 17–19, of Livy's History of Rome from Its Foundation.
Livy contemplates the possibility of Alexander the Great expanding his father's empire westward instead of eastward and attacking Rome in the 4th century BC.
His main question is: "What would have been the results for Rome if she had been engaged in war with Alexander?"

The first novel-length alternative history in English would seem to be Castello Holford's Aristopia (1895).
While not as nationalistic as Napoléon et la conquête du monde, 1812–1823, Aristopia is another attempt to portray a utopian society.
In Aristopia, the earliest settlers in Virginia discover a reef made of solid gold and are able to build a Utopian society in North America.
Although a number of alternative history stories and novels appeared in the late 1800s and early 1900s, the next major work is perhaps the strongest anthology of alternative history ever assembled.
In 1931, British historian Sir John Squire collected a series of essays, many of which could be considered stories, in If It Had Happened Otherwise from some of the leading historians of the period.
In this work, scholars from major universities as well as important non-university-based authors turned their attention to such questions as "If the Moors in Spain Had Won" and "If Louis XVI Had Had an Atom of Firmness."
The essays range from serious scholarly efforts to Hendrik Willem van Loon's fanciful and satiric portrayal of an independent 20th century Dutch city state on the island of Manhattan.

Two popular themes for alternative history seem to be Napoleon's victory and the American civil war.
One of the entries in Squire's volume was Winston Churchill's "If Lee Had Not Won the Battle of Gettysburg", written from the viewpoint of a historian in a world where the Confederacy had won the American Civil War, considering what would have happened if the North had been victorious (in other words, a character from an alternative world imagining a world more like the real one we live in, although not necessarily getting all the details right).
This kind of speculative work which posts from the point of view of an alternative history is variously known as a "recursive alternative history", a "double-blind what-if" or an "alternative-alternative history".
Other authors appearing in Squire's book included Hilaire Belloc and André Maurois.

Another example of alternative history from this period (and arguably the first to explicitly posit cross-time travel from one universe to another as anything more than a visionary experience) was H.G.
Wells' Men Like Gods (1923) in which several Englishmen are transferred via an accidental encounter with a cross-time machine into an alternative universe in which Britain had changed course in earlier centuries and developed into a seemingly pacifistic and utopian society.
When the Englishmen, led by a satiric figure based on Winston Churchill, try to seize power, the utopians simply point a ray gun at them and send them on to someone else's universe.
Wells works out the entire multiverse-pancake framing complete with paratime travel machines that would become popular with U.S. pulp writers (see below), but since his hero experiences only a single alternative world this story is not very different from conventional alternative history (the intruders from our world cause no significant change in the world they enter and are really just a device for examining the results of a past divergence between Wells' utopia and our own world).

The 1930s would see alternative history move into a new arena.
The December 1933 issue of Astounding published Nat Schachner's "Ancestral Voices".
This was quickly followed by Murray Leinster's "Sidewise in Time".
While earlier alternative histories examined reasonably straight-forward divergences, Leinster attempted something completely different.
In his "world gone mad", pieces of Earth traded places with their analogs from different timelines.
The story follows Professor Minott and his students from the fictitious Robinson College as they wander through these dangerous analogs, each of which features remnants of worlds which followed a different history.
This period also saw the publication of the time travel novel Lest Darkness Fall by L. Sprague de Camp, which was similar to Mark Twain's A Connecticut Yankee in King Arthur's Court but sent an American academic to the Italy of the Ostrogoths at the time of the Byzantine invasion led by Belisarius.
De Camp's work is concerned with the historical changes wrought by his time traveler, Martin Padway, thereby making the work an alternative history.
Padway is depicted as making permanent changes and implicitly forming a new time branch (in contrast to Twain's hero, who ultimately fails, with the result that history reverts to its "normal" course — making this book a secret history, though this sub-genre did not exist as such in Twain's time).

Time travel as the cause of a point of divergence (creating two histories where before there was one, or simply replacing the future that existed before the time traveling event) has continued to be a popular theme over the decades.
In Bring the Jubilee, by Ward Moore, the hero, who lives in a world in which the South won the Civil War, travels through time and brings about an alternative history in which the North won at Gettysburg.
Ray Bradbury's A Sound of Thunder creates a scenario in which the time travelers inadvertently destroy all history as we know it.

This can lead to terrible moral dilemmas.
In Delenda Est, the interference of time-travelling outlaws causes Carthage to win the Second Punic War and destroy Rome.
As a result, there is a completely different Twentieth Century — "not better or worse, just completely different".
The hero, Patrol Agent Manse Everard, must return to that period, fight the outlaws and change history back, restoring his (and our) familiar history — but only at the price of totally destroying the world which has taken its place, and which is equally deserving of existence.
The stakes are the highest imaginable: billions of lives balanced against other billions of lives, for one man to decide.
"Risking your neck in order to negate a world full of people like yourself" is how the hero describes what he eventually undertakes.

Of course not all time travel stories involve alternative histories.
The writer may ignore the possibility of change, or have the cause-and-effect work out so that the time traveler's actions cause the future he remembers, as in Harry Harrison's The Technicolor Time Machine.
H.G.
Wells' "cross-time"/"many universes" variant (see above) was fully developed by De Camp in his 1940 short story "The Wheels of If" (Unknown Fantasy Fiction, October 1940), in which the hero is repeatedly shifted from one alternative history to another, each more remote from our own than the last.
This subgenre was used early on for purposes far removed from quasi-academic examination of alternative outcomes to historical events.
Fredric Brown employed it to satirize the s-f pulps and their adolescent readers—and fears of foreign invasion—in the classic What Mad Universe (1949).
In Clifford Simak's Ring Around the Sun (1953), the hero ends up in an alternative earth of thick forests in which humanity never developed (the ultimate divergence) but where a band of mutants is establishing a colony; the story line appears to frame the author's anxieties regarding McCarthyism and the Cold War.
Also in the late 1940s and the 1950s, however, writers such as H. Beam Piper, Sam Merwin, Jr. and Andre Norton wrote thrillers set in a multiverse in which all alternative histories are co-existent and travel between them occurs via a technology involving portals and/or paratime capsules.
These authors established the convention of a secret paratime trading empire that exploits and/or protects worlds lacking the paratime technology via a network of James Bond style secret agents (Piper called them the "paratime police").

The paratime theme is sometimes used without the police; Poul Anderson dreamed up the Old Phoenix tavern as a nexus between alternative histories.
A character from a modern American alternative history Operation Chaos can thus appear in the English Civil War setting of A Midsummer's Tempest.
In this context, the distinction between an alternative history and a parallel universe with some points in common but no common history may not be feasible, as the writer may not provide enough information to distinguish.

Paratime thrillers published in recent decades often cite the many-worlds interpretation of quantum mechanics (first formulated by Hugh Everett III in 1957) to account for the differing worlds.
Some science fiction writers interpret the splitting of worlds to depend on human decision-making and free will, while others rely on the butterfly effect from chaos theory to amplify random differences at the atomic or subatomic level into a macroscopic divergence at some specific point in history; either way, science fiction writers usually have all changes flow from a particular historical point of divergence (often abbreviated as 'POD' by fans of the genre).
Prior to Everett, science-fiction writers drew on higher dimensions and the speculations of P. D. Ouspensky to explain their characters' cross-time jauntings.

While many justifications for alternative histories involve a multiverse, the "many world" theory would naturally involve—many worlds, in fact a continually exploding array of universes.
In quantum theory, new worlds would proliferate with every quantum event, and even if the writer uses human decisions, every decision that could be made differently would result in a different timeline.
A writer's fictional multiverse may, in fact, preclude some decisions as humanly impossible, as when, in Night Watch, Terry Pratchett depicts a character informing Vimes that while anything that can happen, has happened, nevertheless there is no history whatsoever in which Vimes has ever murdered his wife.
When the writer explicitly maintains that all possible decisions are made in all possible ways, one possible conclusion is that the characters were neither brave, nor clever, nor skilled, but simply lucky enough to happen on the universe in which they did not choose the cowardly route, take the stupid action, fumble the crucial activity, etc.; few writers focus on this idea, although it has been explored in stories such as Larry Niven's All the Myriad Ways, where the reality of all possible universes leads to an epidemic of suicide and crime because people conclude their choices have no moral import.

In any case, even if it is true that every possible outcome occurs in some world, it can still be argued that traits such as bravery and intelligence might still affect the relative frequency of worlds in which better or worse outcomes occurred (even if the total number of worlds with each type of outcome is infinite, it is still possible to assign a different measure to different infinite sets).
The physicist David Deutsch, a strong advocate of the many-worlds interpretation of quantum mechanics, has argued along these lines, saying that "By making good choices, doing the right thing, we thicken the stack of universes in which versions of us live reasonable lives.
When you succeed, all the copies of you who made the same decision succeed too.
What you do for the better increases the portion of the multiverse where good things happen."
This view is perhaps somewhat too abstract to be explored directly in science fiction stories, but a few writers have tried, such as Greg Egan in his short story The Infinite Assassin, where an agent is trying to contain reality-scrambling "whirlpools" that form around users of a certain drug, and the agent is constantly trying to maximize the consistency of behavior among his alternative selves, attempting to compensate for events and thoughts he experiences but he guesses are of low measure relative to those experienced by most of his other selves.

The cross-time theme was further developed in the 1960s by Keith Laumer in the first three volumes of his Imperium sequence, which would be completed in Zone Yellow (1990).
Piper's politically more sophisticated variant was adopted and adapted by Michael Kurland and Jack Chalker in the 1980s; Chalker's G.O.D.
Inc trilogy (1987–89), featuring paratime detectives Sam and Brandy Horowitz, marks the first attempt at merging the paratime thriller with the police procedural.
Kurland's Perchance (1988), the first volume of the never completed "Chronicles of Elsewhen", presents a multiverse of secretive cross-time societies that utilize a variety of means for cross-time travel, ranging from high-tech capsules to mutant powers.
Harry Turtledove has launched the Crosstime Traffic series for teenagers that features a variant of H. Beam Piper's paratime trading empire.

Such "paratime" stories may include speculation that the laws of nature can vary from one universe to the next, providing a science fictional explanation—or veneer—for what is normally fantasy.
Aaron Allston's Doc Sidhe and Sidhe Devil take place between our world, the "grim world" and an alternative "fair world" where the Sidhe retreated to.
Although technology is clearly present in both worlds, and the "fair world" parallels our history, about fifty years out of step, there is functional magic in the fair world.
Even with such explanation, the more explicitly the alternative world resembles a normal fantasy world, the more likely the story is to be labeled fantasy, as in Poul Anderson's "House Rule" and "Loser's Night."

In both science fiction and fantasy, whether a given parallel universe is an alternative history may not be clear.
The writer might allude to a POD only to explain the existence and make no use of the concept, or may present the universe without explanation to its existence.
Most of the early cross-time thrillers depicted the multiverse in Euclidean terms (pancake universes stretching to left and right of any given zero universe with the divergence point being earlier and earlier, and the differences greater and greater, the farther one moved in either direction from the zero point).
McCollum and some later writers, however, have posited a pseudo-Einsteinian paratime in which universes are constantly shifting around, moving closer or farther from each other, with time dilating or contracting from one universe to another in unpredictable ways.
This framing device expands the potential for using cross-time fiction to compare different outcomes uptime, downtime and crosstime all at once.
In 1962, Philip K. Dick published The Man in the High Castle, an alternative history in which Nazi Germany and Imperial Japan won World War II.
This book, widely regarded as Dick's masterpiece, has enhanced the prestige of alternative history in mainstream literary circles, although Dick was not yet recognized beyond SF circles when it was first published.
Dick's book also contained an example of "alternative-alternative" history, in that one of its characters is the author of a book in which the Allies won the war.

It was followed by Vladimir Nabokov's Ada or Ardor: A Family Chronicle (1969), a story of incest that takes place within an alternative North America settled in part by Czarist Russia, and that borrows from Dick's idea of "alternative-alternative" history (the world of Nabokov's hero is wracked by rumors of a "counter-earth" that apparently is ours).
Some critics believe that the references to a counter-earth suggest that the world portrayed in Ada is a delusion in the mind of the hero (another favorite theme of Dick's novels).
Strikingly, the characters in Ada seem to acknowledge their own world as the copy or negative version, calling it "Anti-Terra" while its mythical twin is the real "Terra."
Not only history but science has followed a divergent path on Anti-Terra: it boasts all the same technology as our world, but all based on water instead of electricity.
When a character in Ada makes a long-distance call, all the toilets in the house flush at once to provide hydraulic power.

The late 1980s and the 1990s saw a boom in popular-fiction versions of alternative history, fueled by the emergence of Harry Turtledove, the steampunk genre and two series of anthologies — the "What Might Have Been" series edited by Gregory Benford and the "Alternative..." series edited by Mike Resnick.
This period also saw alternative history works by S.M.
Stirling, Kim Stanley Robinson, Harry Harrison, Howard Waldrop and others.

Since the late 1990s, Harry Turtledove has been the most prolific practitioner of alternative history.
His books include a series in which the South won the American Civil War (a massive series of 11 volumes that began in 1997 and completed in 2007) and another in which aliens invade Earth during the Second World War.
Other stories by this author include one with the premise that America had not been colonized from Asia during the last ice age; as a result, the continent still has living mammoths and a hominid species other than homo sapiens, one in which the Nazis won World War Two, as well as one in which the Spanish Armada succeeded in conquering Britain in the Elizabethan era, with William Shakespeare being given the task of writing the play that will motivate the Britons to rise up against their Spanish conquerors.
He also co-authored a book with actor Richard Dreyfuss The Two Georges, which postulates what would have happened if the United Kingdom had retained the American colonies, with George Washington and King George III making peace.
He did a two-volume series in which the Japanese not only bomb Pearl Harbor but also invade and occupy the Hawaiian Islands.
In 2005, he published two short stories set in a world where the east coast of North America exists as an eighth continent in the middle of the Atlantic Ocean.
The first novel of a projected trilogy set in this particular timeline was published in 2007.

Perhaps the most incessantly explored theme in popular alternative history focusses on worlds in which the Nazis won World War Two.
In some versions, the Nazis conquer the entire world; in others, they conquer most of the world but a "Fortress America" exists under siege.
Fatherland (1992) by Robert Harris, set in Europe following the Nazi victory, has been widely praised for portraying a more believable society and series of events than most other novels set in a Nazified world or Nazified Eurasia.
Several writers have posited points of departure for such a world but then have injected time splitters from the future or paratime travel (for instance, James P. Hogan's The Proteus Operation (1986) and Michael P. Kube-McDowell's Alternities (1988)).
Norman Spinrad wrote The Iron Dream in 1972, which is intended to be a science fiction novel written by Adolf Hitler after fleeing from Europe to North America in the 1920s.
Former House Speaker Newt Gingrich and William R. Forstchen have written a novel, 1945, in which the U.S. defeated Japan but not Germany in World War II, resulting in a Cold War with Germany rather than the Soviet Union.
Gingrich and Fortschen neglected to write the promised sequel; instead, they wrote a trilogy about the American Civil War, starting with, in which the Confederates win a victory at Gettysburg.

S.M.
Stirling wrote the Island in the Sea of Time trilogy, in which Nantucket Island and all its modern inhabitants are transported to Bronze Age times to become the world's first superpower.
In Eric Flint's 1632 series, a small town in West Virginia is transported to 17th century Europe and leads a revolution against the Habsburgs.
John Birmingham's Axis of Time trilogy deals with the culture shock when a United Nations naval task force from 2021 finds itself back in 1942 helping the Allies against the Japanese and the Germans (and doing almost as much harm as good in spite of its advanced weapons).
Many fantasies and science fantasies are set in a world that has a history somewhat similar to our own world, but with magic added.
Since the existence of magic implies different laws of nature it is difficult to imagine a credible point of divergence: The effects of divergence would have existed throughout human history and indeed throughout all evolution of life (unless one posits sudden changes in the laws of nature in medieval or modern times brought about by aliens, a time-space warp, etc.).
One example of a universe that is in part historically recognizable but also obeys different physical laws is Poul Anderson's Three Hearts and Three Lions in which the Matter of France is history, and the fairy folk are real and powerful.
A partly familiar European history for which the author provides a point of divergence is Randall Garrett's "Lord Darcy" series: a monk systemizing magic rather than science, so the use of foxglove to treat heart disease is called superstition.

The Tales of Alvin Maker series by Orson Scott Card (a parallel to the life of Joseph Smith, Jr., founder of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints) takes place in an alternative America, beginning in the early 19th century.
Prior to that time, a POD occurred: England, under the control of Oliver Cromwell, had banished "makers", or anyone else demonstrating "knacks" (an ability to perform seemingly supernatural feats) to the North American continent.
Thus the early American colonists embraced as perfectly ordinary these gifts, and counted on them as a part of their daily lives.
The political divisions of the continent is considerably altered, with two large English colonies bookending a smaller "American" nation, one aligned with England, and the other governed by exiled Cavaliers.
Actual historical figures are seen in a much different light: Ben Franklin is revered as the continents's finest "maker", George Washington was executed at the hands of an English army, and "Tom" Jefferson is the first president of "Apallachee", the result of a compromise between the Continentals and the British.

When the magical version of our world's history is set in contemporary times, the distinction becomes clear between alternative history on the one hand and contemporary fantasy, using in effect a form of secret history (as when Josepha Sherman's Son of Darkness has an elf living in New York City, in disguise) on the other.
In works such as Robert A. Heinlein's Magic, Incorporated where a construction company can use magic to rig up stands at a sporting event and Poul Anderson's Operation Chaos and its sequel Operation Luna, where djinns are serious weapons of war — with atomic bombs — the use of magic throughout the United States and other modern countries makes it clear that this is not secret history—although references in Operation Chaos to degaussing the effects of cold iron make it possible that it is the result of a POD.
The sequel clarifies this as the result of a collaboration of Einstein and Planck in 1901, resulting in the theory of "rheatics".
Moseley applies this theory to "degauss the effects of cold iron and release the goetic forces."
This results in the suppression of ferromagnetism and the reemergence of magic and magical creatures.

Terry Pratchett's works includes several references to alternative histories of Discworld.
Men At Arms observes that in millions of universes, Edward d'Eath became an obsessive recluse rather than the instigator of the plot that he is in the novel.
In Jingo, Vimes accidentally picks up a pocket organizer that should have gone down another leg of the Trousers of Time, and so can hear the organizer reporting on the deaths that would have occurred had his decision gone otherwise.
Indeed, Discworld contains an equivalent of the Time Patrol in its History Monks.
Night Watch revolves around a repair of history after a time traveler's murder of an important figure in Vimes's past.
Thief of Time presents them functioning as a fullscale Time Patrol, ensuring that history occurs at all.
There are certain elements which are common to all alternative histories, whether they deal with history on the micro-level (personal alternative histories) or the macro-level (world-changing events).
These elements include:Alternative histories do not:This leads to readers encountering stories which read as though they were alternative history, but which were not written as such.
An example would be Robert A. Heinlein's The Man Who Sold the Moon.
Written in 1949, it posits that the first moon launch is run by a private organization rather than a government agency in the 1960s.
New readers encountering the book may well presume that this is alternative history since it is clearly a counter-factual depiction of the first moon launch, now almost 40 years in the past.
However, when written, the first moon launch was 20 years in the future.
Thus, The Man Who Sold the Moon is out of date science fiction and not true alternative history.

Also one should not confuse the alternative history subgenre with secret history, which gives an account of history at odds with our general understanding—presenting its own account (whether seriously or satirically intended) as having been concealed or suppressed by an elite.
For instance, a story that depicts key events of U.S. history as having been controlled by the Illuminati and the Freemasons—or by aliens—might be secret history.
Writers occasionally unite AH and secret history.
One example is "Dukakis and the Aliens," by Robert Sheckley in which Michael Dukakis defeats George H. W. Bush for the presidency in 1988 and then is taken to a secret saucer base under Area 51 to meet his new masters.

AH also should not be mistaken for fantasy tales that employ a lost history trope, i.e., that assume a stage of human civilization which supposedly has been forgotten through the passage of time, not through conspiratorial suppression.
The works of Robert Howard and J.R.R.
Tolkien are excellent examples of lost history, which generally does not purport to represent a different time-line from our own.

It is also possible to have novels that explore Points of Divergence (the key concept in alternative history) without actually being works of alternative history themselves.
Two good examples are Jack Williamson's influential pulp novel The Legion of Time (1938) and Marge Piercy's critically acclaimed Woman on the Edge of Time (1976).
In the Piercy book, which follows Williamson's basic concept, a patient in a mental hospital is able to travel into two alternative futures—one an ecotopia run by reformed Weather Underground types and the other a fascist dystopia run by people-hating robots.
Decisions she must make to resist a new type of brain operation will determine which future wins.
This is a time travel story, a cross-time story, a Christopher Priest-style delusional alternative reality story, and a POD story all rolled into one but it is not alternative history because the POD occurs in the present (or perhaps the near future) not in the past.

Less obvious is the difference between alternative history and "what if" stories.
The latter subgenre extrapolates, from the present, a concrete near-future possibility that is often an expression of current public fears (hence the alternative term "cautionary tale" used by Vita Sackville-West, see below).
For instance, beginning in the 1870s the British reading public was treated to a number of what-if books about a German or French invasion of an unready British Isles.
During the Great Depression, Sinclair Lewis wrote of a fascist takeover in the United State in his classic It Can't Happen Here (1935).
During the early years of World War II, Sackville-West penned the science fantasy Grand Canyon (1942) in which the Germans invade a woefully unprepared United States.
One could define such tales as borderline alternative history, since they are usually set in a time that is only shortly after the time of writing and the events described could not have occurred without a branching of history before, if only slightly before, the book was written.
In 1953, the NBC radio network aired a show called Stroke of Fate that posited different point of divergence creating an alternative time-line for each episode and dramatized the results along with commentary from various historians.
Episodes included changes in the American Civil War, Alexander the Great surviving his illness, an alternative fate for James Wolfe at Quebec City, no Julius Caesar assassination, a different outcome of Aaron Burr's duel amongst other stories.
All episodes have been preserved.
Several films have been made that exploit the concepts of alternative history, most notably Kevin Brownlow's It Happened Here (1966), depicting a Nazi-occupied Britain.
Other alternative history films include the HBO TV movie Fatherland (1994), set in the 1960s in a world where Germany won WWII and occupied Britain; 2009 Lost Memories (2002), a Korean film supposing that Hirobumi Ito was not assassinated by An Jung-geun in Harbin, China, in 1909; Timequest (2002), in which a time traveler prevents the assassination of John F. Kennedy, resulting in an altered subsequent history; and C.S.A.
: The Confederate States of America (2004), a satirical look at the history of an America where the South won the Civil War, told in the form of a British "documentary."

A few movies about alternative universes focus on individuals rather than historical events, for example, Frank Capra’s It's a Wonderful Life, and more recently the Back to the Future series of films, Blind Chance, Sliding Doors, Run Lola Run, Me Myself I and The Butterfly Effect.
Several TV series also exploit the concept of alternative history.
The science fiction television show Sliders presented alternative histories under the science-inspired guise of quantum-navigating the multiverse.
The alternative Americas in most episodes are nasty dystopias, although sometimes this is not evident at first.
In the Japanese television series, "Zipang" (based on a manga of the same name), a modern Aegis class destroyer of the Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force is thrown back in time to the Battle of Midway in 1942.
The presence of the ship and its crew, their advanced technology and knowledge of the future, change the course of World War II and create an alternative timeline.
Another such television show, a South Korean drama, Gung presents a point of divergence where the Korean monarchy is restored after independence from the Japanese Empire even up to the 21st Century.
The dramatic possibilities of alternative history provide a diverse genre for exploration in role-playing games.
Many games use an alternative historical background for their campaigns.
In particular, the fourth edition of GURPS uses a setting containing multiple different alternative histories as its default campaign setting, with the supplement GURPS Infinite Worlds detailing a large number of alternative worlds included in the setting, many of them carryovers from the third-edition GURPS supplements GURPS Alternative Earths and GURPS Alternative Earths II.
For the same reasons that this genre is explored by role-playing games, alternative history is also an intriguing backdrop for the storylines of many video and computer games.
One of the most famous example of an alternative history game is Command &amp; Conquer: Red Alert.
It presents a point of divergence where Albert Einstein goes back in time to eliminate Adolf Hitler long before he gained power in Germany to prevent World War II from ever taking place.
He is successful in his mission, but in the process allows Joseph Stalin and the Soviet Union to become powerful enough—as a direct result of not having a strong rival dictator like Hitler to keep his power in check—to launch an all out campaign to conquer Europe, sparking an alternative (and ultimately costlier) version of the Second World War and, eventually, a third world war in the 1970s where the USSR invades the U.S..

Crimson Skies is one example of an alternative history spawning multiple interpretations in multiple genres.
The stories and games in Crimson Skies take place in an alternative 1930's United States, where the nation crumbled into many hostile states following the effects of the Great Depression, the Great War, and Prohibition.
With the road and railway system destroyed, commerce took to the skies.
Great cargo zeppelins escorted by fighter squadrons are the targets of many ruthless air pirates and enemy countries.
This world has featured in a board game, a PC game, an Xbox game, a collectible miniatures game and various promotional novels, comics and short stories.
The key change between our history and the alternative history is known as the "point of divergence".
For example, in Philip K. Dick's The Man in the High Castle, the point of divergence is the attempted assassination of Franklin D. Roosevelt in Miami in 1933.
In reality, this attempt failed.

For alternative histories which some assert to be factual rather than speculative, see conspiracy theory and historical revisionism.
In 1995, the Sidewise Award for Alternative History was established to recognize best long form (novels and series) and best short form (stories) within the genres.
The award is named for Murray Leinster's story "Sidewise in Time".</entry>
</article>
