<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1806" title="Arnold Schwarzenegger" authors="5" lines="359">
  <entry author_id="7279" end="13" start="0">In the days and even hours leading up to the show's taping, political experts and insiders concluded that Schwarzenegger was leaning against running.
Even his closest advisors believed he was probably not going to run.
Schwarzenegger stunned the pundits when he announced that he did intended to run in the October 7 recall election.
He said, "The politicians are fiddling, fumbling and failing.
The man that is failing the people more than anyone is Gray Davis.
He is failing them terribly, and this is why he needs to be recalled and this is why I am going to run for governor."
Rumors leading up to the announcement said that his wife, Maria Shriver, a Kennedy family Democrat, was against his running, and he wanted her approval in order to run.
He said, "It's the most difficult I've made in my entire life."
Ultimately, Shriver said she would support Schwarzenegger no matter what he chose, so he decided to run.
Schwarzenegger has the most name recognition in a crowded field of candidates for Governor, but he has never held public office and his political views are unknown to most Californians.

Schwarzenegger's candidacy was immediate national and international news, with media outlets dubbing him the "Governator" and "The Running Man", and calling the recall election "Total Recall" and "Terminator 4: Rise of the Candidate."
Schwarzenegger was quick to use his well-known one-liners, promising to "pump up Sacramento" (the state capital) and tell Gray Davis "hasta la vista".
At the end of his first press conference, he said "I'll be back."</entry>
  <entry author_id="7279" end="31" start="13">Schwarzenegger was appointed Chairman of the President's Council on Physical Fitness and Sports in the administration of George H. W. Bush from 1990 to 1993.
During that time, Schwarzenegger traveled across the U.S. promoting physical fitness to kids.
He later served as Chairman for the California Governor's Council on Physical Fitness and Sports under Governor Pete Wilson.

Schwarzenegger's inauguration was opened by Vanessa Williams, his co-star from Eraser, with the singing of the National Anthem.
He then spoke a few words: "Today is a new day in California.
I did not seek this office to do things the way they've always been done.
What I care about is restoring your confidence in your government...
This election was not about replacing one man.
It was not replacing one party.
It was about changing the entire political climate of our state."

In his first few hours in office Schwarzenegger fulfilled his campaign promise to repeal a 300% increase in vehicle license fees signed by Gov.
Davis to raise $4 billion to close the state's budget deficit.
On his first full day in office, Schwarzenegger proposed a three point plan to fix the budget woes.
First, Schwarzenegger proposed floating $15 billion in bonds.
Second, he urged voters to pass a constitutional amendment to limit state spending.
Third, he sought an overhaul of workers compensation.
Schwarzenegger also called the state legislature into a special session and said that spending cuts would also be necessary.
He initiated the cuts by agreeing to serving with no salary, a savings of $175,000.</entry>
  <entry author_id="134382" end="199" start="31">Arnold Alois Schwarzenegger (born July 30, 1947 in Thal, Styria Austria) is an Austrian-American actor, Republican politician, bodybuilder, and businessman, currently serving as the 38th Governor of California.
He was elected on October 7, 2003 in a special recall election which removed sitting Governor Gray Davis from office.
Schwarzenegger was sworn in on November 17, 2003 to serve the remainder of Davis' term, which lasts until January 2007.

Nicknamed the Austrian Oak in his body-building days, and more recently The Governator and Conan the Republican, Schwarzenegger as a young man gained widespread attention as a highly successful bodybuilder, and later gained worldwide fame as a Hollywood action film star.
His most famous films include The Terminator (and its sequels), Predator, Conan the Barbarian, True Lies, and Total Recall.
Schwarzenegger was born in Thal, Austria, four miles (6 km) from Graz, to a Gendarmerie-Kommandant policeman, Gustav Schwarzenegger (1907-1972) and his wife Aurelia Jadrny (1922-1998).
His parents were members of the Nazi party.

With $20 in his pocket, and not fluent in English, he moved to the U.S. in 1968.
He became a U.S. citizen in 1983, although he has also retained his Austrian nationality.
During this time, he earned a B.A.
from the University of Wisconsin-Superior where he graduated with a major in international marketing of fitness and business administration in 1979.

In 1971 Schwarzenegger's brother Meinhard was killed in an automobile accident, and his father died the following year.
In 1977 his autobiography, was published.
In 1986, Schwarzenegger married TV journalist Maria Shriver, niece of late President John F. Kennedy.
The couple have four children: daughters Katherine and Christina, and sons Patrick and Christopher.
Together, the couple own a home in the fabled Kennedy Compound.

His distinctive and oft-imitated accent has led many entertainers and pundits to refer to him simply as "Ah-nuld".
Schwarzenegger first gained fame as a bodybuilder.
His well-developed physique earned him the moniker "The Austrian Oak"(or "The Styrian Oak") and won him the titles of Junior Mr. Europe, Mr. World, Mr. Universe (five times) and Mr. Olympia (seven times).
The seven wins at Mr. Olympia was a record set in 1980, cementing him as a legend of the sport.
The record would remain until Lee Haney won his eighth straight Olympia in 1991.
Schwarzenegger is considered among the most important figures in the history of bodybuilding, and his legacy is commemorated in the Arnold Classic annual bodybuilding competition.

Schwarzenegger has admitted to using performance-enhancing anabolic steroids, writing in 1977 that " were helpful to me in maintaining muscle size while on a strict diet in preparation for a contest.
I did not use them for muscle growth, but rather for muscle maintenance when cutting up."
However, some bodybuilders who used the same steroid cocktails as Schwarzenegger in the 1970s dispute the notion that they were used merely for "muscle maintenance."
Even Schwarzenegger has called the drugs "tissue building."
In 1999, Schwarzenegger sued Willi Heepe, a German doctor who publicly predicted an early death for the bodybuilder based on a link between steroid use and later heart problems.
Because the doctor had never examined him personally, Schwarzenegger collected a DM20,000 (US$12,000) libel judgement against him in a German court.
In 1999 Schwarzenegger also sued and settled with Globe Magazine, a U.S. tabloid which had made similar predictions about the bodybuilder's future health.
As late as 1996, a year before open heart surgery to replace an aortic valve, Schwarzenegger publicly defended his use of anabolic steroids during his bodybuilding career.
(Schwarzenegger was born with a bicuspid aortic valve; a normal aortic valve is tricuspid.)
According to a spokesman, Schwarzenegger has not used anabolic steroids since 1990 when they were made illegal.
In bodybuilder slang, steroids are sometimes called "Arnolds".

Schwarzenegger has remained a prominent face in the bodybuilding sport long after his retirement, in part due to his ownership of gyms and fitness magazines.
He has presided over numerous contests and awards shows.
For many years he wrote a monthly column for the bodybuilding magazines Muscle &amp; Fitness and Flex.
Shortly after being elected Governor, he was appointed executive editor of both magazines in a largely symbolic capacity.
The magazines agreed to donate $250,000 a year to the Governor's various physical fitness initiatives.
The magazine MuscleMag International has a monthly two page article on him and refers to him as "The King".

Schwarzenegger's first political appointment was to the President's Council on Physical Fitness and Sports, on which he served from 1990 to 1993.
He was nominated by George H. W. Bush, who called him "Conan the Republican".
Growing bored with professional bodybuilding, which he began to view as a "go nowhere" career, Schwarzenegger began to pursue a career as an actor.
His uniquely muscular appearance earned him several movie roles.
His first film appearance was as Hercules in Hercules in New York (1970), credited under the name Arnold Strong, although his accent in the film was so thick that his lines were dubbed.
He appeared in The Long Goodbye, and more notably Stay Hungry, for which he was awarded a Golden Globe.
Schwarzenegger came to the attention of more people in the documentary Pumping Iron (1977), elements of which were dramatized.
In 1991, Schwarzenegger purchased the rights to this film, outtakes, and associated still photography that could be embarrassing politically.
Initially he had trouble breaking into films because agents disliked his surname, muscles and accent.
Though Schwarzenegger refuses to discuss his plastic surgery ("You are confusing me with Cher," he told People Magazine in 2002), citing before and after photos, critics allege he has undergone procedures on his eyes and chin, and has received at least one facelift.

Schwarzenegger's breakthrough film was Conan the Barbarian (1982), and this was cemented by a sequel, Conan the Destroyer (1984).
As an actor, he is most well-known as the title character of James Cameron's android thriller The Terminator (1984).
Schwarzenegger's acting ability (described by one critic as having an emotional range that "stretches from A almost to B") has long been the butt of many jokes; he retains a strong Austrian accent in his speech even in roles which do not call for such an accent.
However, few of the fans of his work seem to care.
He also made a mark for injecting his films with a droll, often self-deprecating sense of humor, setting him apart from more serious action heroes such as Sylvester Stallone, his most prominent contemporary.
(As an aside, his alternative-universe comedy/thriller Last Action Hero featured a poster of the movie Terminator 2: Judgment Day which, in that alternate universe had Sylvester Stallone as its star; a similar in-joke in Twins suggested that the two actors might one day co-star, something which never came to pass).

Following his arrival as a Hollywood superstar, he made a number of commercially successful films: Commando (1985), Raw Deal (1986), The Running Man (1987), and Red Heat (1988).
In Predator (1987), another commercially successful film, Schwarzenegger led a cast which included future Minnesota Governor Jesse Ventura (Ventura also appears in Running Man) and future Kentucky Gubernatorial Candidate Sonny Landham.
Twins, (1988) a comedy with Danny DeVito, was a change of pace.
Total Recall (1990), at that time the most expensive film ever, netted Schwarzenegger $10 millon and 15% of the gross, and was a widely praised, thought-provoking science-fiction script behind his usual violent action.
Kindergarten Cop (1990) was another comedy.

Schwarzenegger's critical and commercial high-water mark was Terminator 2: Judgment Day (1991).
His next film project, the self-aware action comedy Last Action Hero, (1993), had the misfortune to be released opposite Jurassic Park, and suffered accordingly.
Schwarzenegger's career never again achieved quite the same prominence, his aura of box-office invincibility suffering.
True Lies (1994) was a popular sendup of spy films, and saw Schwarzenegger reunited with director James Cameron, whose own career had taken off with The Terminator.
It was followed by the popular, albeit by-the-numbers Eraser (1996), and Batman &amp; Robin (1997), his final film before taking time to recuperate from a back injury.
Although Batman &amp; Robin was a famous disaster, Schwarzenegger emerged largely unscathed.
Several film projects were announced with Schwarzenegger attached to star including the remake of The Planet of the Apes, a new film of I am Legend and a World War II film scripted by Quentin Tarrantino that would have seen Schwarzenegger finally play an Austrian.
Instead he returned with End of Days (1999) - an unsuccessful and atypically dark attempt to broaden his acting range - The 6th Day (2000) and Collateral Damage (2002), none of which came close to recapturing his former prominence.
He starred in Terminator 3: Rise of the Machines (2003) and was slated to star in a possible True Lies 2 and Conan the King, but his duties as California governor have likely put his movie career on hold until at least 2007, though producers repeatedly claim he will make a small appearance in a fourth Terminator film.
His last film appearance to date was a cameo in the 2004 remake of Around the World in 80 Days.

Schwarzenegger is a Republican, unusual among the often heavily Democratic Hollywood community.
He describes himself as fiscally conservative and socially moderate.
Schwarzenegger backed Republican President Ronald Reagan, whose footsteps he's following—movie star turned politician—while Reagan was in office, but chastised fellow Republicans during the impeachment of Bill Clinton.
Sensing an opportunity to affect the outcome of the 2004 Presidential race, Schwarzenegger campaigned in Ohio for Republican George W. Bush in the closing days of the campaign.

Regarding a run for public office, in 1999, he told Talk magazine that "I think about it many times."
He said, "The possibility is there because I feel it inside.
I feel there are a lot of people standing still and not doing enough.
And there's a vacuum."
Schwarzenegger was appointed Chairman of the President's Council on Physical Fitness and Sports in the administration of George H. W. Bush from 1990 to 1993.
During that time, Schwarzenegger traveled across the U.S. promoting physical fitness to kids and lobbying all 50 governors in support of school fitness programs.
"He would hit sometimes two or three governors in a day in his own airplane, at his own expense, somewhere around $4,000 an hour," said George Otott, his chief of staff at the time.
"When he walked in, it wasn't about the governor, it was about Arnold," said Otott, a retired Marine.
"He has what we in the military call a command presence.
He becomes the number one attention-getter."

Schwarzenegger scored his first real political success on November 5, 2002 when Californians approved his personally crafted and sponsored Proposition 49, the "After School Education and Safety Program Act of 2002", an initiative to make state grants available for after-school programs.
For years, Schwarzenegger had discussed with friends, potential donors, advisors and political allies a possible run for high political office; on April 10, 2003, for example, he met with Republican political operative Karl Rove to discuss a future campaign.
In the months leading to the 2003 California recall, Schwarzenegger was widely rumored to be considering a run at becoming Governor of California.
In the July 2003 issue of Esquire magazine, he said, "Yes, I would love to be governor of California...
If the state needs me, and if there's no one I think is better, then I will run."
When a petition to recall Democratic governor Gray Davis qualified for the ballot on July 24, Schwarzenegger left many wondering whether he would jump into the contest.
Schwarzenegger was just wrapping up a promotional tour for Terminator 3 and said he would announce his decision on whether to run on August 6 on The Tonight Show with Jay Leno.

In the days and even hours leading up to the show's taping, political experts and insiders concluded that Schwarzenegger was leaning against running in California's October 7 recall election.
Even his closest advisors said he was probably not going to run.
Rumors leading up to the announcement said that his wife, Maria Shriver, a Kennedy family Democrat, was against his running, and he wanted her approval in order to run.
When announcing his candidacy on the Tonight Show, he joked, "It's the most difficult I've made in my entire life, except the one I made in 1978 when I decided to get a bikini wax."
Ultimately, Shriver said she would support Schwarzenegger no matter what he chose, so he decided to run.
Schwarzenegger told Leno, "The politicians are fiddling, fumbling and failing.
The man that is failing the people more than anyone is Gray Davis.
He is failing them terribly, and this is why he needs to be recalled and this is why I am going to run for governor."

As a candidate in the recall election, Schwarzenegger had the most name recognition in a crowded field of candidates, but he had never held public office and his political views were unknown to most Californians.
His candidacy was immediate national and international news, with media outlets dubbing him the "Governator" (referring to The Terminator movies, see above) and "The Running Man" (the name of another of his movies), and calling the recall election "Total Recall" (ditto) and "Terminator 4: Rise of the Candidate" (referring to his movie Terminator 3: Rise of the Machines).
Schwarzenegger was quick to make use of his well-known one-liners, promising to "pump up Sacramento" (the state capital) and tell Gray Davis "hasta la vista."
At the end of his first press conference, he told the audience "I'll be back."
Schwarzenegger looked to follow in the footsteps of former California governor and one-time movie star Ronald Reagan.
However, due to his status as a naturalized citizen, he would not be eligible to seek the Presidency unless the Constitution were to be amended (as proposed in 2000 by Congressman Barney Frank (D-MA), and in July 2003 (the Equal Opportunity to Govern Amendment) by Senator Orrin Hatch (R-UT)).
Among his campaign team were Rob Lowe, Warren Buffett, and George Shultz.

During the campaign, allegations of sexual and personal misconduct were raised against Schwarzenegger.
Within the last five days before the election, news reports appeared in the Los Angeles Times recounting allegations of sexual misconduct from several individual women, sixteen of whom eventually came forward with their personal stories.
Chronologically, they ranged from Elaine Stockton, who claimed that Schwarzenegger groped her breast at a Gold's Gym in 1975 (she was 19 at the time), to a 51-year-old woman who said that he pinned her to his chest and spanked her shortly after she met him in connection with production of his film, "The Sixth Day," in 2000.
Schwarzenegger admitted that he has "behaved badly sometimes" and apologized, but also stated that "a lot of (what) you see in the stories is not true".
This came after a magazine interview from the same era (1975) surfaced in which Schwarzenegger discussed attending sexual orgies and indulging in drugs like marijuana and cocaine.

Allegations, based on selective quotation, were also made that he at one time admired Adolf Hitler and had praised him as a great propagandist.
However the full text of the statement from which the quotation was taken significantly reduces the credibility of the allegations.
Although Schwarzenegger's father was in fact a member of the Nazi party, Schwarzenegger has been a strong supporter of various Jewish groups, and has denounced the principles of the fascist German regime, saying "I have always despised everything that Hitler stands for."

On October 7, 2003, the 2003 California recall resulted in Governor Gray Davis being recalled with 55.4% of the Yes vote.
Schwarzenegger was elected Governor of California under the second question on the ballot with 48.6% of the vote, defeating Democrat Cruz Bustamante, fellow Republican Tom McClintock and others.
In total, Arnold won the election by about 1.3 million votes.

He was sworn into office on November 17, 2003.
Schwarzenegger's inauguration was opened by Vanessa Williams, his co-star from Eraser singing the National Anthem.
His children joined others in reciting the Pledge of Allegiance, then Maria Shriver spoke and held the Bible while Schwarzenegger was sworn into the office of Governor.
He spoke briefly: "Today is a new day in California.
I did not seek this office to do things the way they've always been done.
What I care about is restoring your confidence in your government...
This election was not about replacing one man.
It was not replacing one party.
It was about changing the entire political climate of our state."

In his first few hours in office Schwarzenegger fulfilled his campaign promise to repeal an unpopular 200% increase in vehicle license fees undertaken to fund the state's budget.
The increase was a restoration to 1998 levels.
On his first full day in office, Schwarzenegger proposed a three-point plan to address the budget woes.
First, Schwarzenegger proposed floating $15 billion in bonds.
Second, he urged voters to pass a constitutional amendment to limit state spending.
Third, he sought an overhaul of workers' compensation.
Schwarzenegger also called the state legislature into a special session and said that spending cuts would also be necessary.
He initiated the cuts by agreeing to serve as governor with no salary, a savings of $175,000 per year.

To fulfill the first two points, he urged California voters to pass Proposition 57 and Proposition 58 in the March 2, 2004 election, which authorized the sale of $15 billion in bonds and mandated balanced budgets, respectively.
Despite initially tepid support from the public, the combination of heavy campaigning by Schwarzenegger, endorsements from a number of leading Democrats, and warnings about the dire consequences should the propositions fail to pass, led to overwhelming votes in favor of the two propositions.
Prop.
57 passed with 63.3% of the votes in favor and Prop.
58 passed with 71.0% in favor.
He accomplished the third point when he signed a workers' compensation reform bill on April 19, 2004.
Schwarzenegger convinced the Democratic-controlled state legislature to approve the package by threatening to take the issue directly to state voters in a November ballot initiative if the legislature did not act.

Schwarzenegger was later criticized for reneging on his campaign pledges not to take money from special interests and for failing to answer directly the sexual harassment allegations raised by the Los Angeles Times immediately preceding the recall election.
However, Schwarzenegger made a point shortly after becoming governor of voluntarily attending a training course conducted by the state Attorney General's office on preventing sexual harassment (along with several members of his senior staff).
Schwarzenegger continues to collect campaign contributions from private interests at a greater rate than any politician in California history.

In February 2004, he declined amnesty to convicted murderer Kevin Cooper who had asked him for clemency in his death penalty sentence.
Nevertheless, Cooper's planned execution was stayed by the Ninth U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals pending a revisiting of evidence.
Austrian Green Party spokesman Peter Pilz later called for Schwarzenegger to be stripped of his Austrian citizenship.
Pilz claimed that Austrian law forbids any Austrian citizen from taking part in or ordering executions.

Despite expectations that Schwarzenegger would be vulnerable to opposition critics once taking office, his early governorship showed some successes.
He has dealt successfully with California politicians as diverse as John Burton on the left to Tom McClintock on the right.
At the end of May, 2004 the Field poll put his popularity at 65%, the highest for a California governor in 45 years, including 41% of Democrats, party adherents of his opposition.
By comparison, former United States President Ronald Reagan, known as "the Great Communicator," never hit 60% approval while serving as California governor.
In March, 2004 libertarian policy research foundation The Cato Institute rated him 1st in their fiscal policy report card of the nation's governors.

In July 2004, however, Schwarzenegger and the state legislature deadlocked, failing to approve the state budget on time.
Trying to rouse public support for his position, he compared lawmakers to kindergartners who need a "timeout," and in a rally of supporters called his budget opponents "girlie men" (a reference to a long-running Saturday Night Live skit parodying Schwarzenegger).
The remark became national news and was not received well by his opponents, including gay advocacy and feminist groups who labeled it homophobic and sexist, not to mention the legislators themselves.
His supporters made "girly men" T-shirts and the Governor continued to use the term, including when he addressed the Republican National Convention, calling critics of the current U.S. economic situation "economic girlie men".

Despite what some viewed as political snags during the summer, the Field polls released in August and October 2004 showed that Schwarzenegger's approval rating remained at 65%.
Additionally, in October, for the first time in four years a plurality of Californians felt the state was "on the right track".

While Arnold Schwarzenegger's height was always believed to be 6 feet, 2 inches (1.88 m), a July 2002 article in US Weekly magazine speculated that Schwarzenegger was actually closer to 5 ft 10 in (1.78 m).
During his campaign for governorship it was noted that Schwarzenegger was considerably shorter than many expected, with others putting his height at around 5 ft 10 in (1.78 m), exactly as reported in US Weekly.
His spokespeople now give his height as 6 ft even (1.83 m).
Assuming his height was ever closer to 6'2", it is possible he may have shrunk slightly with age, although four inches seems too much to lose by the mid-fifties.

In 2005 Peter Pilz from the Austrian Green Party in parliament demanded to revoke Schwarzenegger's Austrian citizenship because of his involvement in the exercise of the death penalty in California.
This demand was based on article 33 of the Austrian citizenship act that states: "A citizen, who is in the public service of a foreign country, shall be deprived of his citizenship, if he heavily damages the reputation or the interests of the Republic".
The European Convention on Human Rights, which bans the death penalty, is part of the Austrian constitution.
Schwarzenegger justified his actions by referring to the fact that his only duty as Governor of California was to prevent an error in the judicial system.</entry>
  <entry author_id="206678" end="303" start="199">However, due to his status as a naturalized citizen, he would not be eligible to seek the Presidency unless the Constitution were to be amended (as proposed in 2000 by Congressman Barney Frank (Democratic - Massachusetts), and in July 2003 (the Equal Opportunity to Govern Amendment) by Senator Orrin Hatch (Republican-Utah)).
(In yet another filmic foreshadowing, in the Stallone film Demolition Man, there is reference made to the Arnold Schwarzenegger Presidential Library, implying that in the future, the naturalization issue was settled, leading to Arnold becoming President.)
Among his campaign team were Democratic actor Rob Lowe, Democratic-sounding billionaire Warren Buffett, and moderate George Shultz (former Nixon and Reagan aide).

An interview that Arnold Schwarzenegger had given to Penthouse magazine received renewed attention.
In the interview, Schwarzenegger described a body-building session in Venice Beach in which a "black chick came downstairs" and participated in a "gang bang" with Arnold and other males exercising in the gym.
While many were revolted by the fact that Schwarzenegger bragged about participating in group sex, others also pointed out that it was very curious that the future governor went out of his way to describe the racial characteristics of the woman.

Allegations printed on the front page of The Los Angeles Times, based on selective quotation, which Schwarzenegger claimed not to recall, were also made that he at one time admired Adolf Hitler and had praised him as a great propagandist.
However the full text of the statement from which the quotation was taken significantly reduces the credibility of the allegations.
Although Schwarzenegger's father was in fact a member of the Nazi party, Schwarzenegger has been a strong supporter of various Jewish groups, and has denounced the principles of the fascist German regime, saying "I have always despised everything that Hitler stands for".
In the uncut version of the film Pumping Iron Arnold was said to have given a Nazi salute and also to have said that he admired Hitler.

Schwarzenegger supported the campaign of his friend, Kurt Waldheim, former UN chief and a former Austrian politician who was accused of war crimes during World War II in Yugoslavia, which resulted in both Waldheim, and his wife, Elisabeth, both of whom belonged to the Nazi Party, being excluded from entering the United States.
Schwarzenegger's name remained on Waldheim's campaign posters, even after allegations of Waldheim's war crimes were brought to light.
Waldheim was also invited to Arnold's wedding with Maria Shriver, but declined (see ).

On October 7, 2003, the 2003 California recall resulted in Governor Gray Davis being recalled with 55.4% of the Yes vote.
Schwarzenegger was elected Governor of California under the second question on the ballot with 48.6% of the vote, defeating Democrat Cruz Bustamante, fellow Republican Tom McClintock and others.
In total, Arnold won the election by about 1.3 million votes.

He was sworn into office on November 17, 2003.
Schwarzenegger's inauguration was opened by Vanessa Lynn Williams, his co-star from Eraser, singing the National Anthem.
Hollywood attendees included Danny DeVito, Rhea Perlman, Dennis Miller and Rob Lowe (only Miller is a Republican).

The Schwarzenegger children joined others in reciting the Pledge of Allegiance, then Maria Shriver spoke and held the Bible while Schwarzenegger was sworn into the office of Governor.
He spoke briefly: "Today is a new day in California.
I did not seek this office to do things the way they've always been done.
What I care about is restoring your confidence in your government...
This election was not about replacing one man.
It was not replacing one party.
It was about changing the entire political climate of our state."

In his first few hours in office Schwarzenegger fulfilled his campaign promise to repeal an unpopular 200% increase in vehicle license fees undertaken to fund the state's budget.
The increase was a restoration to 1998 levels.
On his first full day in office, Schwarzenegger proposed a three-point plan to address the budget woes.
First, Schwarzenegger proposed floating $15,000,000,000 (USD) in bonds.

Second, he urged voters to pass a constitutional amendment to limit state spending.
Third, he sought an overhaul of workers' compensation.
Schwarzenegger also called the state legislature into a special session and said that spending cuts would also be necessary.
He initiated the cuts by agreeing to serve as governor with no salary, a savings of $175,000 (USD) per year.

To fulfill the first two points, he urged California voters to pass Proposition 57 and Proposition 58 in the March 2, 2004, election, which authorized the sale of $15 billion in bonds and mandated balanced budgets, respectively.
Despite initially tepid support from the public, the combination of heavy campaigning by Schwarzenegger, endorsements from a number of leading Democrats, and warnings about the dire consequences should the propositions fail to pass, led to overwhelming votes in favor of the two propositions.
Prop.
57 passed with 63.3% of the votes in favor and Prop.
58 passed with 71.0% in favor.
He accomplished the third point when he signed a workers' compensation reform bill on April 19, 2004.

Schwarzenegger was later criticized for reneging on his campaign pledges not to take money from special interests and for failing to answer directly the sexual harassment allegations raised by the Los Angeles Times immediately preceding the recall election.
However, Schwarzenegger made a point shortly after becoming governor of voluntarily attending a training course conducted by the state Attorney General's office on preventing sexual harassment (along with several members of his senior staff).
Schwarzenegger continues to collect campaign contributions from private interests (see ) at a greater rate than any politician in California history, including Gray Davis, whom he criticized on that very issue (see ).

Also in February 2004, he declined amnesty to convicted murderer Kevin Cooper who had asked him for clemency in his death penalty sentence.
Cooper's planned execution was stayed by the Ninth U.S.
Circuit Court of Appeals pending a revisiting of evidence.
The first execution under his administration was that of Donald Beardslee.

Austrian Green Party spokesman, Peter Pilz, later called for Schwarzenegger to be stripped of his Austrian citizenship.
Pilz claimed that Austrian law forbids any Austrian citizen from taking part in or ordering executions.
However, Schwarzenegger does not appear to be in any danger of losing his Austrian citizenship.

The governor has granted clemency to a number of convicted felons – more than Democrat predecessor Gray Davis, who presided over numerous executions.
The power of clemency is often controversial.
After a longer period of consideration than is usual, on December 12, 2005, Schwarzenegger denied clemency to quadruple murderer Stanley Tookie Williams, who was executed on December 13.

Despite expectations that Schwarzenegger would be vulnerable to opposition critics once taking office, his early governorship showed some successes.
He has dealt successfully with California politicians as diverse as John Burton on the left to Tom McClintock on the right.
At the end of May, 2004, the Field poll put his popularity at 65%, the highest for a California governor in 45 years, including 41% of Democrats, party adherents of his opposition.
By comparison, former United States President Ronald Reagan, known as "the Great Communicator," never hit 60% approval while serving as California governor (see ).

He said about the legislators: "They are part of a bureaucracy that is out of shape, that is out of date, that is out of touch and that is definitely out of control in Sacramento.
They cannot have the guts to come out there in front of you and say, 'I don't want to represent you.
I want to represent those special interests: the unions, the trial lawyers.'...
if they don’t have the guts, I call them girlie-men.
They should get back to the table and they should finish the budget".

The remark became national news and was not received well by his opponents, including gay advocacy and feminist groups who labeled it homophobic and sexist, in spite of his earlier support for gay rights (see the Gavin Newsom incident above), not to mention the legislators themselves.
Others however, were quick to point out that the critics actually were expressing a sentiment of latent homophobia themselves because they automatically connected the phrase "girlie-men" with homosexuals.
The term "girlie-man" was actually the Governor taking a bit of a pot-shot at himself, as the phrase is derived from the popular Saturday Night Live sketch "Pumping Up With Hanz and Franz" where two Austrian bodybuilders chastize those not sufficiently bulked up as "girlie men."

However, when asked if they would support Schwarzenegger if he could run for president, 50% said they would oppose, while only 26% said they would support the governor in a presidential bid (see ).
In the spring of 2005, polls began showing Schwarzenegger's approval ratings had dropped to between 40-49%.
(See, , ,  .)

Schwarzenegger's spokesman responded that Schwarzenegger had not yet had enough time to explain his proposals to voters.
The Legislature also shared low approval ratings, with just 24% of voters saying they approve of the job lawmakers have been doing.
That represents a drop of 10% since February.
The governor has responded that the poll sends a "very clear message to us.
They are saying they want us to work together."
He has also responded "I know popularity goes up and down... as soon as you start making decisions and strong decisions, sometimes they're not popular decisions" (see ).

To some degree, Governor Schwarzenegger's unpopularity has had to do with his confrontations with three popular labor groups: nurses, teachers, and firefighters.
Some unions and activists reacted with anger (see, , , ), and others with humor (, , ).
While governor, Schwarzenegger continued to hold a position of executive editor of two American Media magazines.
He announced in March 2004 that his $250,000 a year salary would be donated to charity.
Schwarzenegger has an extensive history with the magazines and was frequently their star in his body-building days.
As executive editor, he produces monthly columns based on his body-building history.

Schwarzenegger drew fire when a second contract, a consulting position, was subsequently discovered in SEC filings, by the L.A. Times.
This second contract would net him an estimated $8,000,000 (USD) over the next five years (see ).
His consulting duties are not clear, except that the job allegedly "takes up little time".

The New York Times further reported (on July 15) that under the five-year November 2003 contract, signed two days before his inauguration as Governor, Oak Productions, Mr. Schwarzenegger's company, is to receive 1% of the net print advertising revenues of Weider Publications.
But the payment must be at least $1,000,000 (USD) per year.
Mr. Schwarzenegger has also been granted phantom equity, a way of sharing in the growth of the value of the company.
The equity could become worth 1% of the company's value, which was stated at the time of the contract as $520,000,000 (USD)" (see ).

Running up to the November special election, Schwarzenegger campaigned heavily throughout the state for his slate of propositions.
Through an organization called "Join Arnold", tens of millions of dollars were funneled into the state, mostly from corporate interests, to fund the campaign.
Schwarzenegger even reportedly spent 7,000,000 (USD) of his own money.
Schwarzenegger characterized the four propositions as being key to his reform agenda.

Schwarzenegger made personal appearances at numerous so-called "town hall meeting" events throughout the state to promote the measures.
In reality these events were highly choreographed, and typically featured Hollywood-style set lighting and coordinated electronic displays.
A group of four or so "ordinary citizens", pre-selected by local Republican operatives, would appear on stage with Schwarzenegger to ask him questions at the appropriate time.
The time and location of these events would not be released to the public until two hours in advance, to limit the time anti-Schwarzenegger forces had to organize protests.

In the November 8, 2005 special election, California voters dealt a devastating blow to Schwarzenegger by soundly rejecting all four ballot initiatives that Schwarzenegger had proposed to reform the state government.
All propositions were defeated by a margin of at least 7 percentage points.
The two propositions most key to Schwarzenegger's agenda, propositions 76 and 77, were defeated by 24 and 19 points respectively.

However, Governor Schwarzenegger's attempts to redeem his political career via the bond measures fell apart in March 2006, largely due to his inability to gain Republican support for the negotiated bond plan.
Democratic legislators had pressed Schwarzenegger to emphasize in the bond offering those areas that broadly benefitted the population of the state, while the Republican minority in the legislature pushed for the interests of business and agriculture.
The Governor found himself in an impossible situation, as he needed the support of both the Republicans and Democrats to achieve the two-thirds vote to establish the June bond measure.

Both the Governor and Legislature have stated their desire to put some bond measure on the November 2006 ballot, but it remains to be seen if election year politics will bring this to fruition.
On Tuesday, May 2, 2006, Schwarzenegger continued in his quest to get two NFL teams formed in the L.A. area.
According to (), Schwarzenegger's net worth has been under-estimated by conservatively using the usual $100,000,000-$200,000,000 (USD) estimate.</entry>
  <entry author_id="303874" end="331" start="303">However, due to his status as a naturalized citizen, he would not be eligible to seek the Presidency unless the Constitution were to be amended (as proposed in 2000 by Congressman Barney Frank (Democratic - Massachusetts), and in July 2003 (the Equal Opportunity to Govern Amendment) by Senator Orrin Hatch (Republican-Utah)).
(In yet another filmic foreshadowing, in the Stallone film Demolition Man, there is reference made to the Arnold Schwarzenegger Presidential Library, implying that in the future, the naturalization issue was settled, leading to Arnold becoming President.)
Among his campaign team were Democratic actor Rob Lowe, Democratic-sounding billionaire Warren Buffett, and moderate George Shultz (former Nixon and Reagan aide).

An interview that Arnold Schwarzenegger had given to Penthouse magazine received renewed attention.
In the interview, Schwarzenegger described a body-building session in Venice Beach in which a "black chick came downstairs" and participated in a "gang bang" with Arnold and other males exercising in the gym.
While many were revolted by the fact that Schwarzenegger bragged about participating in group sex, others also pointed out that it was very curious that the future governor went out of his way to describe the racial characteristics of the woman.

Allegations printed on the front page of The Los Angeles Times, based on selective quotation, which Schwarzenegger claimed not to recall, were also made that he at one time admired Adolf Hitler and had praised him as a great propagandist.
However the full text of the statement from which the quotation was taken significantly reduces the credibility of the allegations.
Although Schwarzenegger's father was in fact a member of the Nazi party, Schwarzenegger has been a strong supporter of various Jewish groups, and has denounced the principles of the fascist German regime, saying "I have always despised everything that Hitler stands for".
In the uncut version of the film Pumping Iron Arnold was said to have given a Nazi salute and also to have said that he admired Hitler.

Schwarzenegger supported the campaign of his friend, Kurt Waldheim, former UN chief and a former Austrian politician who was accused of war crimes during World War II in Yugoslavia, which resulted in both Waldheim, and his wife, Elisabeth, both of whom belonged to the Nazi Party, being excluded from entering the United States.
Schwarzenegger's name remained on Waldheim's campaign posters, even after allegations of Waldheim's war crimes were brought to light.
Waldheim was also invited to Arnold's wedding with Maria Shriver, but declined.

On October 7, 2003, the recall election resulted in Governor Gray Davis being removed from office with 55.4% of the Yes vote in favor of a recall.
Schwarzenegger was elected Governor of California under the second question on the ballot with 48.6% of the vote to choose a successor to Davis.
Schwarzenegger defeated Democrat Cruz Bustamante, fellow Republican Tom McClintock, and others.
In total, Schwarzenegger won the election by about 1.3 million votes.

Schwarznegger was sworn into office on November 17, 2003.
Schwarzenegger's inauguration was opened by Vanessa Lynn Williams, his co-star from Eraser, singing the National Anthem.
Hollywood attendees included Danny DeVito, Rhea Perlman, Dennis Miller and Rob Lowe (only Miller and Lowe are Republicans).

The Schwarzenegger children joined others in reciting the Pledge of Allegiance, then Maria Shriver spoke and held the Bible while Schwarzenegger was sworn into the office of Governor.
He spoke briefly: "Today is a new day in California.
I did not seek this office to do things the way they've always been done.
What I care about is restoring your confidence in your government...
This election was not about replacing one man.
It was not replacing one party.
It was about changing the entire political climate of our state."
In his first few hours in office Schwarzenegger fulfilled his campaign promise to repeal an unpopular 200% increase in vehicle license fees undertaken to fund the state's budget.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1897072" end="359" start="331">Anabolic steroids like many other drugs have been at the center of a lot of controversy and because of this there are many popular misconceptions and myths concerning their purported effects and side effects.
As with many infamous drugs in popular culture the misconceptions relating to anabolic steroids have likely arisen from misunderstandings of actual side effects of anabolic steroids, one such example might include the myth that anabolic steroids can ‘shrink’ ones penis.
It is likely that this myth came from the real side effect of anabolic steroids known as testicular atrophy in which the use of anabolic steroids will cause natural testosterone levels to decrease, thus reducing testicle size.
This side effect is temporary and testicles return to normal once use is stopped and natural testosterone levels return to normal.

Another common misconceptions purveyed in popular culture and the media include the myth that anabolic steroids are highly dangerous and users mortality rates are high.
Anabolic steroids are used widely in the medical field without any serious health risks to users and no scientific evidence has shown any long term serious health defects from correct use of anabolic steroids.
While risk of death is present in many drugs, the risk of premature death from use of anabolic steroids seems to be extremely low.
It is possible this myth arose from claims that Lyle Alzado died from brain cancer caused by anabolic steroids.
Alzado himself had claimed that his cancer was caused by anabolic steroids.
However, there is no medical evidence anabolic steroids can cause brain cancer and Alzado's own doctors admitted anabolic steroids had nothing to do with his death.

More myths relating to purported side effects include claims that anabolic steroids have caused many teenagers to commit suicide.
While lower levels of testosterone have been known to cause depression, and ending a steroid cycle is known to result in temporarily lower testosterone levels, the claim that anabolic steroids are responsible for specific suicides among teenagers is highly questionable.
In the United states the estimated use of anabolic steroids among high school students was 2.8% in 1999.
On the other hand, in the year 2000 in the United States, suicide was the third leading cause of death among 15- to 24-year-olds.
With the suicide rate this high among teenagers, concluding anabolic steroids are responsible for the suicides of teenagers who happened to be taking them prior to committing suicide is a Post hoc logical fallacy.
Also, even though teen bodybuilders have been using steroids since at least the early 1960's, only a few cases suggesting a link between steroids and suicide have been reported in the medical literature.

One of the most common misconceptions regarding the side effects of anabolic steroids is known as ‘roid rage’.
There seems to be little or no evidence such a condition actually exists.
Most studies done on "angry behavior" and anabolic steroid use show no psychological effect, implying that either "roid rage" doesn't exist or that anabolic steroids effects on aggression are too small to be measured.
Many scientists and medical professionals conclude anabolic steroids have no real effect on increased angry behavior.

Arnold Schwarzenegger is the victim of yet another myth regarding the purported side effects of anabolic steroids.
Arnold Schwarzenegger has admitted to using anabolic steroids during his bodybuilding career for many years and in 1997 he went in for surgery to correct a defect relating to his heart.
So many have concluded that this was due to anabolic steroids.
This claim is false.
Arnold Schwarzenegger was born with a genetic defect in which his heart only had a bicuspid aortic valve.
It was a congenital disorder meaning he was born with it.
Normal hearts have 3 cusps.
However Arnold Schwarzenegger had only 2 cusps which can occasionally cause problems, especially later in life.</entry>
</article>
