<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="1814" title="Adam Smith" authors="4" lines="487">
  <entry author_id="83143" end="11" start="0">The Wealth of Nations also rejects the Physiocratic school's emphasis on the importance of land; instead, Smith believed labour was tantamount, and that a division of labour would effect a great increase in production.
Nations was so successful, in fact, that it led to the abandonment of earlier economic schools, and later economists, such as Thomas Malthus and David Ricardo, focused on refining Smith's theory into what is now known as classical economics.
(Modern economics evolved from this.)
Malthus expanded Smith's ruminations on overpopulation, while Ricardo (and Karl Marx) believed in the "iron law of wages" — that overpopulation would prevent wages from topping the subsistence level.
Smith postulated an increase of wages with an increase in production, a view considered more accurate today.

One of the main points of the The Wealth of Nations is that the free market, while appearing chaotic and unrestrained, is actually guided to produce the right amount and variety of goods by a so-called "invisible hand."
If a product shortage occurs, for instance, its price rises, creating incentive for its production, and eventually curing the shortage.
The increased competition among manufacturers and increased supply would also lower the price of the product to its production cost, the "natural price."

Smith vigourously attacked the antiquated government restrictions which he thought were hindering industrial expansion.
In fact, he attacked most forms of government interference in the economic process, including tariffs, arguing that this creates inefficiency and high prices in the long run.
This theory, now referred to as "laissez-faire," influenced government legislation in later years, especially during the 19th century.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1594915" end="143" start="11">“Invisible hand” appears only once in The Wealth of Nations (WN) by Adam Smith.
It does not appear “with the marketplace.” Yet, the “invisible hand” is listed on the internet 1,650,000 times.
It is listed with “Adam Smith” 259,000 times and with “the marketplace” 106,000 times.

There are other discrepancies.
Untrue is that Smith had endorsed “laissez-faire” which does not appear even once in WN.
but received about four million listings on the internet, 290,000 citing Adam Smith.
Not understood is the reason for his opposition to restraints on trade.
Hardly known is Smith’s The Theory of Moral Sentiments (MS) and its emphasis upon justice and sympathy.
One source for such serious differences between his image and reality began nearly two centuries ago.

Between 1800 and 1850, evangelicals became powerful in England.
They contended that Adam Smith had portrayed an invisible hand of the marketplace.
They also believed that this invisible hand was a perfectly designed instrument to reward good Christian behavior and to punish the sinful.
For such reasons, Britain denied help during the Irish potato famine, resulting in many deaths and emigrations.

The misconceptions and their outcomes need to be compared with the published works of Adam Smith, beginning with his early Lectures on Jurisprudence.
Its index contains many listings for government, education, and wages and none for economy or wealth.
They accord with the final sentence of a lengthy biography by Ian Ross explaining Smith’s aim “to help us to aspire to virtue rather than to wealth.”

Significant for understanding Smith is the era in which he lived from 1723 to 1790.
It was a time throughout Great Britain when important contributions were being made to the modern world in science and capitalism.
Especially relevant for the modern world were a group of scholars, widely identified as Scottish moral philosophers.

In 1764, he became the tutor of a young duke and went with him to France.
He was welcomed especially by its “philosophes,” the eminent men of letters in France He found them to have similar interests and ideas.
Their enthusiasm over MS was very encouraging to him to keep improving it in later editions.

Much has been written about his meetings with “physiocrats” whose belief in “laissez-faire” has been said to have influenced the writing of WN.
To the contrary, however, he questioned their ideas as extremism.
Historian Jerry Muller has repeatedly rejected the notion that Smith endorsed “laissez faire.” Also, according to biographer Ross, Smith viewed leading physiocrat Francois Quesnay as “the doctrine head of a sect.”

Returning to England in 1766, he was assured of a lifetime income by the duke’s family.
He then retired from teaching and concentrated on WN, first printed in 1776, 17 years after MS. Just as in MS, he described human beings as being concerned about others and nowhere did he describe people as naturally selfish.
In reality, to Ross “his writings are a direct challenge to the theories of intrinsic human selfishness advanced by Hobbes and Mandeville.”

Sympathy for workers appears in the WN chapter “On the Wages of Labour.” Central is his emphasis on the great advantage “masters” have over labor.
“We rarely hear of the combinations of masters, though frequently of those of workmen.” Smith offered detailed descriptions of the ways used by masters to keep down the wages of their workers.
To him, “Labour, therefore, is the real measure of the exchangeable value of all commodities.”

Especially notable is that the last three chapters of more than 280 pages in WN dealt with government expenses, revenues, taxes, and public debts.
It is very important, remarkable, and virtually unnoticed.
The first part provided for public works, justice, and various institutions as well as for the “education of youth.”

Chapter II described a wide variety of taxes.
They mentioned taxes on rent, on land, the produce of land, homes, profit, stock, employment, wages, every different species of revenue, capitation taxes, and upon consumable commodities.
Hardly evidence of an anti-tax personna.

Smith favored free trade mainly to replace the then current mercantile system controlled by monarchical governments.
Mercantilism judged a nation's wealth by its stock of gold and silver, rather than by income, productivity, standards of living, or other possible indicators.
Also mercantilists believed the world had a limited supply of wealth--gold and silver--and so one country could grow rich only at the expense of another.

According to mercantilism, a nation that did not have gold or silver mines had to rely on foreign trade to be successful.
That called for an excess of exports over imports, that is, a favorable balance of trade.
During the 15th to 18th centuries, gold served as the chief means of settling international debts.
A nation that exported more than it imported could collect the difference in gold from the importing countries.

From that perspective, imports were undesirable since they had to be paid for in gold.
To Smith, goods not gold were the true measure of wealth.
He opposed what he called mercantilist, “Restraints upon the importation from foreign countries of such goods as can be produced at home.”

Neither mercantilism nor free trade attracted the newly formed United States.
Although largely unnoticed today, it became an industrialized nation by blocking imports from Great Britain.
Alexander Hamilton’s 1791 “Report on Manufactures” proposed tariffs on imports to help finance the new nation and to aid industry.
Protectionism grew greatly during the following century with tariffs as high as 40% on certain manufactured products.

Similar views were appearing elsewhere and soon become dominant.
In the United States, the neoclassical theory of the free market is accepted as though it was ordained by God and confirmed by science.
To Smith, it allows self-interest to override the public interest and public justice.

Contemporary free trade has had little benefit for nearly one third of the world population.
According to the World Bank, one of the most worrisome global trends of the past two decades of international free trade is that countries with around two billion people are in danger of becoming marginal to the world economy.
Among the very poorest of those countries are former colonies, many in Africa.

The beginnings of colonialist trade appear to have grown around the 15th and 16th centuries among the coastal European nations.
Profitable sugar, coffee, cotton, and tobacco plantations in their colonies were enhanced through the slave trade.
Begun during the mercantilist era and continued as free trade, England’s commerce in slaves allowed it to buy cotton cheaply and sell the finished textiles to less developed countries.

The slave trade had become a major enterprise for the American colonists during the 18th century.
While not comparable to the extent of European slavery shipping, New England ships brought hundreds of thousands of slaves from African ports, selling them throughout the Americas.
Only after independence did the northern states oppose slavery which “free trade” southerners defended.

The discussion by Smith of colonies in WN is quite extensive.
Along with scattered references to colonies is a section of about a hundred pages on the topic.
They deal with many historic cases but the main focus is upon his era.
Also, the tone is less detached than that of slavery.

While he seems to approve of colonization as a way of providing new lands for cultivation by emigrants, he barely mentions slavery in this lengthy chapter.
Instead, the discussion is largely of their financial arrangements.
Moreover, he made no effort at considering their outcome.

Its damage is greatest among the former colonies, especially those on the continent of Africa.
Colonizing nations had created new political entities out of diverse tribes, religions, and language groups.
Their divisions have resulted in frequent disagreements and conflicts.
Numerous sellers of armaments urge the many factions in these backward nations to buy large quantities of costly weaponry.
Not only is that very profitable, but it keeps poor nations indebted to and dependent upon rich ones.

Private and governmental gun trade totals about a trillion dollars annually.
Among the largest makers and dealers in selling guns, grenades, tanks, bombers, and other weapons are the five members of the UN security council: Britain, China, France.
Russia, and the United States.

Smith surely would approve of the following conditions described in the British periodical The Economist.
“Looking around the world, you do not see many economies, least of all rich ones, doing as well as America’s.
In the inexhaustible capacity of its private sector to innovate, in the seemingly unquenchable desire to reinvent itself, the United States still leads the world, and reaps the material rewards of that leadership.”

What would he say about America’s lack of sympathy for slums, homeless, handicapped, lower life expectancy, wage-cutting, disappearing pensions, and huge prison population?
How would he respond to 46 million people without national health insurance, unlike other modern nations?
Yet, the United States leads the world in its number of billionaires.

There have been many failed attempts to adopt some form of national health insurance in the United States.
A basic reason is the economic assumption that private health care is better than public health care.
For one thing, it is alleged that the people will go to the doctor too often when the government pays the costs.
Thus, a 2004 report to the president stated this habit is a “moral hazard” of unnecessary medical visits.

In fact, the total per person cost of private health care in the United States is twice the cost of countries with national health care.
Much of our high costs are the result of the more serious illnesses of the uninsured.
They are high because the uninsured don’t get health care until they visit the emergency room for very serious, costly, and charitable treatment.

Moreover, the alleged benefits of the marketplace and free trade has led to increasing “privatization.” Among the latest is the privatizing of prisons which can build and house convicted offenders at lower cost than government.
Since “correction” has long been dropped from the prison agenda, these private jails can hardly be expected to do otherwise.
That would hardly accord with the sympathy and justice of Smith.

Writing during the era of rule by monarchs and nobility, Smith could not have conceived of governments much influenced by wealthy enterprises.
Yet, he was fully aware of the selfishness of enterprisers.
Thus in WN, “People of the same trade meet together, even for merriment or diversion, but the conversation ends in a conspiracy against the public.”

Law violations by leading corporations are not new.
Fifty years ago a noted American criminologist Edwin Sutherland reported that our 70 largest corporations had averaged 14 convictions for law violations in their average 45-year existence.
Many other studies since then have reported similar patterns of law violations by American corporations.

Such corporate law violations are called crimes by criminologists although the American legal system does not do so.
That is because the United States has two separate and unequal justice systems--criminal justice and regulatory justice.
Under regulatory justice, corporate law violations receive scant public notice, neither in official reports nor in the media.

Nationally, the criminal justice system is largely the Department of Justice.
The Federal Bureau of Investigation is its primary branch which obtains data concerning assault, fraud, homicide, and other violations of federal and local laws.
Its reports consist of individual law violations published annually by the FBI--but not corporate violations.
Regulatory justice is the domain of a great variety of independent federal agencies which deal mainly with corporations.

The reason for our regulatory justice system goes back to English law.
Because England does not have a constitution, its laws are based upon precedent.
Those precedents were compiled during the 18th century by Sir William Blackstone, a contemporary of Adam Smith.
Included in the Blackstone’s famed legal commentary is the following: “...a corporation cannot commit treason, felony, or other crime in its corporate capacity; though its members may in their own distinct individual capacity.”

Although Blackstone received several footnotes in WN, his explanation of corporative immunity from criminal prosecution was not cited.
Since corporations then were chartered by British kings, their exemption may have seemed appropriate to Smith.
However, protection of corporations also have found considerable support in American jurisprudence.

As the Constitution of the United States made no chartering provision for corporations, they were established by the various states.
These state charters have varied in many ways.
But commonly they have placed little limits on the actions of their chartered enterprises--and they immunize corporations themselves from criminal penalties though not their employees.
Eventually, the federal government created national agencies or commissions to “regulate” the actions of corporations.

In recent decades, new financial entities have emerged with even less oversight or regulation.
Among them are huge equity funds and hedge funds owned by small numbers of extremely affluent investors.
Acting quietly, often internationally, public safeguards or enforcement are negligible.
A common technique is to buy businesses, withdraw their cash reserves and pension funds, strip them of profitable entities, load them with debt, and then sell them.
In the absence of legal standards, they cannot be called law violators or criminals.

Law violations by corporations and other large financial entities with few moral or legal restraints would have horrified Adam Smith.
To him in WN.
“Society, however, cannot subsist among those who are at all times ready to hurt and injure one another...Justice, on the contrary, is the main pillar that upholds the whole edifice...the immense fabric of society.”

In December, 2005, newspapers reported that Wal-Mart has been ordered to pay $172 million to 116,000 employes for illegally preventing them from taking meal breaks.
Another 40 law suits have been filed against Wal-Mart, the largest private employer in the United States.
Only 30% of its employees are eligible for needs like health insurance and pensions,

Prior commentaries document the discrepancy between widespread images and the reality about Adam Smith, as evidenced in The Theory of Moral Sentiments and The Wealth of Nations.
Overcoming the serious distortions of his views of free trade, invisible hand, and laissez-faire is very unlikely, perhaps impossible.
Still, his advocacy of justice and sympathy can be followed and promoted by those who care for all human bengs.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1594915" end="276" start="143">“Invisible hand” appears only once in The Wealth of Nations (WN) by Adam Smith.
It does not appear “with the marketplace.” Yet, the “invisible hand” is listed on the internet 1,650,000 times.
It is listed with “Adam Smith” 259,000 times and with “the marketplace” 106,000 times.

There are other discrepancies.
Untrue is that Smith had endorsed “laissez-faire” which does not appear even once in WN.
but received about four million listings on the internet, 290,000 citing Adam Smith.
Not understood is the reason for his opposition to restraints on trade.
Hardly known is Smith’s The Theory of Moral Sentiments (MS) and its emphasis upon justice and sympathy.
One source for such serious differences between his image and reality began nearly two centuries ago.

Between 1800 and 1850, evangelicals became powerful in England.
They contended that Adam Smith had portrayed an invisible hand of the marketplace.
They also believed that this invisible hand was a perfectly designed instrument to reward good Christian behavior and to punish the sinful.
For such reasons, Britain denied help during the Irish potato famine, resulting in many deaths and emigrations.

The misconceptions and their outcomes need to be compared with the published works of Adam Smith, beginning with his early Lectures on Jurisprudence.
Its index contains many listings for government, education, and wages and none for economy or wealth.
They accord with the final sentence of a lengthy biography by Ian Ross explaining Smith’s aim “to help us to aspire to virtue rather than to wealth.”

Significant for understanding Smith is the era in which he lived from 1723 to 1790.
It was a time throughout Great Britain when important contributions were being made to the modern world in science and capitalism.
Especially relevant for the modern world were a group of scholars, widely identified as Scottish moral philosophers.

In 1764, he became the tutor of a young duke and went with him to France.
He was welcomed especially by its “philosophes,” the eminent men of letters in France He found them to have similar interests and ideas.
Their enthusiasm over MS was very encouraging to him to keep improving it in later editions.

Much has been written about his meetings with “physiocrats” whose belief in “laissez-faire” has been said to have influenced the writing of WN.
To the contrary, however, he questioned their ideas as extremism.
Historian Jerry Muller has repeatedly rejected the notion that Smith endorsed “laissez faire.” Also, according to biographer Ross, Smith viewed leading physiocrat Francois Quesnay as “the doctrine head of a sect.”

Returning to England in 1766, he was assured of a lifetime income by the duke’s family.
He then retired from teaching and concentrated on WN, first printed in 1776, 17 years after MS. Just as in MS, he described human beings as being concerned about others and nowhere did he describe people as naturally selfish.
In reality, to Ross “his writings are a direct challenge to the theories of intrinsic human selfishness advanced by Hobbes and Mandeville.”

Sympathy for workers appears in the WN chapter “On the Wages of Labour.” Central is his emphasis on the great advantage “masters” have over labor.
“We rarely hear of the combinations of masters, though frequently of those of workmen.” Smith offered detailed descriptions of the ways used by masters to keep down the wages of their workers.
To him, “Labour, therefore, is the real measure of the exchangeable value of all commodities.”

Especially notable is that the last three chapters of more than 280 pages in WN dealt with government expenses, revenues, taxes, and public debts.
It is very important, remarkable, and virtually unnoticed.
The first part provided for public works, justice, and various institutions as well as for the “education of youth.”

Chapter II described a wide variety of taxes.
They mentioned taxes on rent, on land, the produce of land, homes, profit, stock, employment, wages, every different species of revenue, capitation taxes, and upon consumable commodities.
Hardly evidence of an anti-tax personna.

Smith favored free trade mainly to replace the then current mercantile system controlled by monarchical governments.
Mercantilism judged a nation's wealth by its stock of gold and silver, rather than by income, productivity, standards of living, or other possible indicators.
Also mercantilists believed the world had a limited supply of wealth--gold and silver--and so one country could grow rich only at the expense of another.

According to mercantilism, a nation that did not have gold or silver mines had to rely on foreign trade to be successful.
That called for an excess of exports over imports, that is, a favorable balance of trade.
During the 15th to 18th centuries, gold served as the chief means of settling international debts.
A nation that exported more than it imported could collect the difference in gold from the importing countries.

From that perspective, imports were undesirable since they had to be paid for in gold.
To Smith, goods not gold were the true measure of wealth.
He opposed what he called mercantilist, “Restraints upon the importation from foreign countries of such goods as can be produced at home.”

Neither mercantilism nor free trade attracted the newly formed United States.
Although largely unnoticed today, it became an industrialized nation by blocking imports from Great Britain.
Alexander Hamilton’s 1791 “Report on Manufactures” proposed tariffs on imports to help finance the new nation and to aid industry.
Protectionism grew greatly during the following century with tariffs as high as 40% on certain manufactured products.

Similar views were appearing elsewhere and soon become dominant.
In the United States, the neoclassical theory of the free market is accepted as though it was ordained by God and confirmed by science.
To Smith, it allows self-interest to override the public interest and public justice.

Contemporary free trade has had little benefit for nearly one third of the world population.
According to the World Bank, one of the most worrisome global trends of the past two decades of international free trade is that countries with around two billion people are in danger of becoming marginal to the world economy.
Among the very poorest of those countries are former colonies, many in Africa.

The beginnings of colonialist trade appear to have grown around the 15th and 16th centuries among the coastal European nations.
Profitable sugar, coffee, cotton, and tobacco plantations in their colonies were enhanced through the slave trade.
Begun during the mercantilist era and continued as free trade, England’s commerce in slaves allowed it to buy cotton cheaply and sell the finished textiles to less developed countries.

The slave trade had become a major enterprise for the American colonists during the 18th century.
While not comparable to the extent of European slavery shipping, New England ships brought hundreds of thousands of slaves from African ports, selling them throughout the Americas.
Only after independence did the northern states oppose slavery which “free trade” southerners defended.

The discussion by Smith of colonies in WN is quite extensive.
Along with scattered references to colonies is a section of about a hundred pages on the topic.
They deal with many historic cases but the main focus is upon his era.
Also, the tone is less detached than that of slavery.

While he seems to approve of colonization as a way of providing new lands for cultivation by emigrants, he barely mentions slavery in this lengthy chapter.
Instead, the discussion is largely of their financial arrangements.
Moreover, he made no effort at considering their outcome.

Its damage is greatest among the former colonies, especially those on the continent of Africa.
Colonizing nations had created new political entities out of diverse tribes, religions, and language groups.
Their divisions have resulted in frequent disagreements and conflicts.
Numerous sellers of armaments urge the many factions in these backward nations to buy large quantities of costly weaponry.
Not only is that very profitable, but it keeps poor nations indebted to and dependent upon rich ones.

Private and governmental gun trade totals about a trillion dollars annually.
Among the largest makers and dealers in selling guns, grenades, tanks, bombers, and other weapons are the five members of the UN security council: Britain, China, France.
Russia, and the United States.

Smith surely would approve of the following conditions described in the British periodical The Economist.
“Looking around the world, you do not see many economies, least of all rich ones, doing as well as America’s.
In the inexhaustible capacity of its private sector to innovate, in the seemingly unquenchable desire to reinvent itself, the United States still leads the world, and reaps the material rewards of that leadership.”

What would he say about America’s lack of sympathy for slums, homeless, handicapped, lower life expectancy, wage-cutting, disappearing pensions, and huge prison population?
How would he respond to 46 million people without national health insurance, unlike other modern nations?
Yet, the United States leads the world in its number of billionaires.

There have been many failed attempts to adopt some form of national health insurance in the United States.
A basic reason is the economic assumption that private health care is better than public health care.
For one thing, it is alleged that the people will go to the doctor too often when the government pays the costs.
Thus, a 2004 report to the president stated this habit is a “moral hazard” of unnecessary medical visits.

In fact, the total per person cost of private health care in the United States is twice the cost of countries with national health care.
Much of our high costs are the result of the more serious illnesses of the uninsured.
They are high because the uninsured don’t get health care until they visit the emergency room for very serious, costly, and charitable treatment.

Moreover, the alleged benefits of the marketplace and free trade has led to increasing “privatization.” Among the latest is the privatizing of prisons which can build and house convicted offenders at lower cost than government.
Since “correction” has long been dropped from the prison agenda, these private jails can hardly be expected to do otherwise.
That would hardly accord with the sympathy and justice of Smith.

Writing during the era of rule by monarchs and nobility, Smith could not have conceived of governments much influenced by wealthy enterprises.
Yet, he was fully aware of the selfishness of enterprisers.
Thus in WN, “People of the same trade meet together, even for merriment or diversion, but the conversation ends in a conspiracy against the public.”

Law violations by leading corporations are not new.
Fifty years ago a noted American criminologist Edwin Sutherland reported that our 70 largest corporations had averaged 14 convictions for law violations in their average 45-year existence.
Many other studies since then have reported similar patterns of law violations by American corporations.

Such corporate law violations are called crimes by criminologists although the American legal system does not do so.
That is because the United States has two separate and unequal justice systems--criminal justice and regulatory justice.
Under regulatory justice, corporate law violations receive scant public notice, neither in official reports nor in the media.

Nationally, the criminal justice system is largely the Department of Justice.
The Federal Bureau of Investigation is its primary branch which obtains data concerning assault, fraud, homicide, and other violations of federal and local laws.
Its reports consist of individual law violations published annually by the FBI--but not corporate violations.
Regulatory justice is the domain of a great variety of independent federal agencies which deal mainly with corporations.

The reason for our regulatory justice system goes back to English law.
Because England does not have a constitution, its laws are based upon precedent.
Those precedents were compiled during the 18th century by Sir William Blackstone, a contemporary of Adam Smith.
Included in the Blackstone’s famed legal commentary is the following: “...a corporation cannot commit treason, felony, or other crime in its corporate capacity; though its members may in their own distinct individual capacity.”

Although Blackstone received several footnotes in WN, his explanation of corporative immunity from criminal prosecution was not cited.
Since corporations then were chartered by British kings, their exemption may have seemed appropriate to Smith.
However, protection of corporations also have found considerable support in American jurisprudence.

As the Constitution of the United States made no chartering provision for corporations, they were established by the various states.
These state charters have varied in many ways.
But commonly they have placed little limits on the actions of their chartered enterprises--and they immunize corporations themselves from criminal penalties though not their employees.
Eventually, the federal government created national agencies or commissions to “regulate” the actions of corporations.

In recent decades, new financial entities have emerged with even less oversight or regulation.
Among them are huge equity funds and hedge funds owned by small numbers of extremely affluent investors.
Acting quietly, often internationally, public safeguards or enforcement are negligible.
A common technique is to buy businesses, withdraw their cash reserves and pension funds, strip them of profitable entities, load them with debt, and then sell them.
In the absence of legal standards, they cannot be called law violators or criminals.

Law violations by corporations and other large financial entities with few moral or legal restraints would have horrified Adam Smith.
To him in WN.
“Society, however, cannot subsist among those who are at all times ready to hurt and injure one another...Justice, on the contrary, is the main pillar that upholds the whole edifice...the immense fabric of society.”

In December, 2005, newspapers reported that Wal-Mart has been ordered to pay $172 million to 116,000 employes for illegally preventing them from taking meal breaks.
Another 40 law suits have been filed against Wal-Mart, the largest private employer in the United States.
Only 30% of its employees are eligible for needs like health insurance and pensions,

Prior commentaries document the discrepancy between widespread images and the reality about Adam Smith, as evidenced in The Theory of Moral Sentiments and The Wealth of Nations.
Overcoming the serious distortions of his views of free trade, invisible hand, and laissez-faire is very unlikely, perhaps impossible.
Still, his advocacy of justice and sympathy can be followed and promoted by those who care for all human bengs.
There has been considerable controversy as to whether there is a contradiction between Smith's emphasis on sympathy in his Theory of Moral Sentiments and the key role of self-interest in The Wealth of Nations.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1594915" end="408" start="276">“Invisible hand” appears only once in The Wealth of Nations (WN) by Adam Smith.
It does not appear “with the marketplace.” Yet, the “invisible hand” is listed on the internet 1,650,000 times.
It is listed with “Adam Smith” 259,000 times and with “the marketplace” 106,000 times.

There are other discrepancies.
Untrue is that Smith had endorsed “laissez-faire” which does not appear even once in WN.
but received about four million listings on the internet, 290,000 citing Adam Smith.
Not understood is the reason for his opposition to restraints on trade.
Hardly known is Smith’s The Theory of Moral Sentiments (MS) and its emphasis upon justice and sympathy.
One source for such serious differences between his image and reality began nearly two centuries ago.

Between 1800 and 1850, evangelicals became powerful in England.
They contended that Adam Smith had portrayed an invisible hand of the marketplace.
They also believed that this invisible hand was a perfectly designed instrument to reward good Christian behavior and to punish the sinful.
For such reasons, Britain denied help during the Irish potato famine, resulting in many deaths and emigrations.

The misconceptions and their outcomes need to be compared with the published works of Adam Smith, beginning with his early Lectures on Jurisprudence.
Its index contains many listings for government, education, and wages and none for economy or wealth.
They accord with the final sentence of a lengthy biography by Ian Ross explaining Smith’s aim “to help us to aspire to virtue rather than to wealth.”

Significant for understanding Smith is the era in which he lived from 1723 to 1790.
It was a time throughout Great Britain when important contributions were being made to the modern world in science and capitalism.
Especially relevant for the modern world were a group of scholars, widely identified as Scottish moral philosophers.

In 1764, he became the tutor of a young duke and went with him to France.
He was welcomed especially by its “philosophes,” the eminent men of letters in France He found them to have similar interests and ideas.
Their enthusiasm over MS was very encouraging to him to keep improving it in later editions.

Much has been written about his meetings with “physiocrats” whose belief in “laissez-faire” has been said to have influenced the writing of WN.
To the contrary, however, he questioned their ideas as extremism.
Historian Jerry Muller has repeatedly rejected the notion that Smith endorsed “laissez faire.” Also, according to biographer Ross, Smith viewed leading physiocrat Francois Quesnay as “the doctrine head of a sect.”

Returning to England in 1766, he was assured of a lifetime income by the duke’s family.
He then retired from teaching and concentrated on WN, first printed in 1776, 17 years after MS. Just as in MS, he described human beings as being concerned about others and nowhere did he describe people as naturally selfish.
In reality, to Ross “his writings are a direct challenge to the theories of intrinsic human selfishness advanced by Hobbes and Mandeville.”

Sympathy for workers appears in the WN chapter “On the Wages of Labour.” Central is his emphasis on the great advantage “masters” have over labor.
“We rarely hear of the combinations of masters, though frequently of those of workmen.” Smith offered detailed descriptions of the ways used by masters to keep down the wages of their workers.
To him, “Labour, therefore, is the real measure of the exchangeable value of all commodities.”

Especially notable is that the last three chapters of more than 280 pages in WN dealt with government expenses, revenues, taxes, and public debts.
It is very important, remarkable, and virtually unnoticed.
The first part provided for public works, justice, and various institutions as well as for the “education of youth.”

Chapter II described a wide variety of taxes.
They mentioned taxes on rent, on land, the produce of land, homes, profit, stock, employment, wages, every different species of revenue, capitation taxes, and upon consumable commodities.
Hardly evidence of an anti-tax personna.

Smith favored free trade mainly to replace the then current mercantile system controlled by monarchical governments.
Mercantilism judged a nation's wealth by its stock of gold and silver, rather than by income, productivity, standards of living, or other possible indicators.
Also mercantilists believed the world had a limited supply of wealth--gold and silver--and so one country could grow rich only at the expense of another.

According to mercantilism, a nation that did not have gold or silver mines had to rely on foreign trade to be successful.
That called for an excess of exports over imports, that is, a favorable balance of trade.
During the 15th to 18th centuries, gold served as the chief means of settling international debts.
A nation that exported more than it imported could collect the difference in gold from the importing countries.

From that perspective, imports were undesirable since they had to be paid for in gold.
To Smith, goods not gold were the true measure of wealth.
He opposed what he called mercantilist, “Restraints upon the importation from foreign countries of such goods as can be produced at home.”

Neither mercantilism nor free trade attracted the newly formed United States.
Although largely unnoticed today, it became an industrialized nation by blocking imports from Great Britain.
Alexander Hamilton’s 1791 “Report on Manufactures” proposed tariffs on imports to help finance the new nation and to aid industry.
Protectionism grew greatly during the following century with tariffs as high as 40% on certain manufactured products.

Similar views were appearing elsewhere and soon become dominant.
In the United States, the neoclassical theory of the free market is accepted as though it was ordained by God and confirmed by science.
To Smith, it allows self-interest to override the public interest and public justice.

Contemporary free trade has had little benefit for nearly one third of the world population.
According to the World Bank, one of the most worrisome global trends of the past two decades of international free trade is that countries with around two billion people are in danger of becoming marginal to the world economy.
Among the very poorest of those countries are former colonies, many in Africa.

The beginnings of colonialist trade appear to have grown around the 15th and 16th centuries among the coastal European nations.
Profitable sugar, coffee, cotton, and tobacco plantations in their colonies were enhanced through the slave trade.
Begun during the mercantilist era and continued as free trade, England’s commerce in slaves allowed it to buy cotton cheaply and sell the finished textiles to less developed countries.

The slave trade had become a major enterprise for the American colonists during the 18th century.
While not comparable to the extent of European slavery shipping, New England ships brought hundreds of thousands of slaves from African ports, selling them throughout the Americas.
Only after independence did the northern states oppose slavery which “free trade” southerners defended.

The discussion by Smith of colonies in WN is quite extensive.
Along with scattered references to colonies is a section of about a hundred pages on the topic.
They deal with many historic cases but the main focus is upon his era.
Also, the tone is less detached than that of slavery.

While he seems to approve of colonization as a way of providing new lands for cultivation by emigrants, he barely mentions slavery in this lengthy chapter.
Instead, the discussion is largely of their financial arrangements.
Moreover, he made no effort at considering their outcome.

Its damage is greatest among the former colonies, especially those on the continent of Africa.
Colonizing nations had created new political entities out of diverse tribes, religions, and language groups.
Their divisions have resulted in frequent disagreements and conflicts.
Numerous sellers of armaments urge the many factions in these backward nations to buy large quantities of costly weaponry.
Not only is that very profitable, but it keeps poor nations indebted to and dependent upon rich ones.

Private and governmental gun trade totals about a trillion dollars annually.
Among the largest makers and dealers in selling guns, grenades, tanks, bombers, and other weapons are the five members of the UN security council: Britain, China, France.
Russia, and the United States.

Smith surely would approve of the following conditions described in the British periodical The Economist.
“Looking around the world, you do not see many economies, least of all rich ones, doing as well as America’s.
In the inexhaustible capacity of its private sector to innovate, in the seemingly unquenchable desire to reinvent itself, the United States still leads the world, and reaps the material rewards of that leadership.”

What would he say about America’s lack of sympathy for slums, homeless, handicapped, lower life expectancy, wage-cutting, disappearing pensions, and huge prison population?
How would he respond to 46 million people without national health insurance, unlike other modern nations?
Yet, the United States leads the world in its number of billionaires.

There have been many failed attempts to adopt some form of national health insurance in the United States.
A basic reason is the economic assumption that private health care is better than public health care.
For one thing, it is alleged that the people will go to the doctor too often when the government pays the costs.
Thus, a 2004 report to the president stated this habit is a “moral hazard” of unnecessary medical visits.

In fact, the total per person cost of private health care in the United States is twice the cost of countries with national health care.
Much of our high costs are the result of the more serious illnesses of the uninsured.
They are high because the uninsured don’t get health care until they visit the emergency room for very serious, costly, and charitable treatment.

Moreover, the alleged benefits of the marketplace and free trade has led to increasing “privatization.” Among the latest is the privatizing of prisons which can build and house convicted offenders at lower cost than government.
Since “correction” has long been dropped from the prison agenda, these private jails can hardly be expected to do otherwise.
That would hardly accord with the sympathy and justice of Smith.

Writing during the era of rule by monarchs and nobility, Smith could not have conceived of governments much influenced by wealthy enterprises.
Yet, he was fully aware of the selfishness of enterprisers.
Thus in WN, “People of the same trade meet together, even for merriment or diversion, but the conversation ends in a conspiracy against the public.”

Law violations by leading corporations are not new.
Fifty years ago a noted American criminologist Edwin Sutherland reported that our 70 largest corporations had averaged 14 convictions for law violations in their average 45-year existence.
Many other studies since then have reported similar patterns of law violations by American corporations.

Such corporate law violations are called crimes by criminologists although the American legal system does not do so.
That is because the United States has two separate and unequal justice systems--criminal justice and regulatory justice.
Under regulatory justice, corporate law violations receive scant public notice, neither in official reports nor in the media.

Nationally, the criminal justice system is largely the Department of Justice.
The Federal Bureau of Investigation is its primary branch which obtains data concerning assault, fraud, homicide, and other violations of federal and local laws.
Its reports consist of individual law violations published annually by the FBI--but not corporate violations.
Regulatory justice is the domain of a great variety of independent federal agencies which deal mainly with corporations.

The reason for our regulatory justice system goes back to English law.
Because England does not have a constitution, its laws are based upon precedent.
Those precedents were compiled during the 18th century by Sir William Blackstone, a contemporary of Adam Smith.
Included in the Blackstone’s famed legal commentary is the following: “...a corporation cannot commit treason, felony, or other crime in its corporate capacity; though its members may in their own distinct individual capacity.”

Although Blackstone received several footnotes in WN, his explanation of corporative immunity from criminal prosecution was not cited.
Since corporations then were chartered by British kings, their exemption may have seemed appropriate to Smith.
However, protection of corporations also have found considerable support in American jurisprudence.

As the Constitution of the United States made no chartering provision for corporations, they were established by the various states.
These state charters have varied in many ways.
But commonly they have placed little limits on the actions of their chartered enterprises--and they immunize corporations themselves from criminal penalties though not their employees.
Eventually, the federal government created national agencies or commissions to “regulate” the actions of corporations.

In recent decades, new financial entities have emerged with even less oversight or regulation.
Among them are huge equity funds and hedge funds owned by small numbers of extremely affluent investors.
Acting quietly, often internationally, public safeguards or enforcement are negligible.
A common technique is to buy businesses, withdraw their cash reserves and pension funds, strip them of profitable entities, load them with debt, and then sell them.
In the absence of legal standards, they cannot be called law violators or criminals.

Law violations by corporations and other large financial entities with few moral or legal restraints would have horrified Adam Smith.
To him in WN.
“Society, however, cannot subsist among those who are at all times ready to hurt and injure one another...Justice, on the contrary, is the main pillar that upholds the whole edifice...the immense fabric of society.”

In December, 2005, newspapers reported that Wal-Mart has been ordered to pay $172 million to 116,000 employes for illegally preventing them from taking meal breaks.
Another 40 law suits have been filed against Wal-Mart, the largest private employer in the United States.
Only 30% of its employees are eligible for needs like health insurance and pensions,

Prior commentaries document the discrepancy between widespread images and the reality about Adam Smith, as evidenced in The Theory of Moral Sentiments and The Wealth of Nations.
Overcoming the serious distortions of his views of free trade, invisible hand, and laissez-faire is very unlikely, perhaps impossible.
Still, his advocacy of justice and sympathy can be followed and promoted by those who care for all human bengs.</entry>
  <entry author_id="178836" end="451" start="408">Smith was a son of the controller of the customs at Kirkcaldy, Fife, Scotland.
The exact date of his birth is unknown, but he was baptised at Kirkcaldy on June 5, 1723, his father having died some six months previously.
At around the age of 4, he was kidnapped by a band of Gypsies, but he was quickly rescued by his uncle and returned to his mother.
Smith recovered from this ordeal quickly and resumed his close relationship with his mother on his safe return home.
Smith's biographer, John Rae, commented wryly that he feared Smith would have made "a poor Gypsy."
He is thought to have been an only child as there is no record of him having had siblings.

At the age of fourteen, Smith proceeded to the University of Glasgow, studying moral philosophy under "the never-to-be-forgotten" (as Smith called him) Francis Hutcheson.
Here Smith developed his strong passion for liberty, reason, and free speech.
In 1740 he entered Balliol College, Oxford, but as William Robert Scott has said, "the Oxford of his time gave little if any help towards what was to be his lifework," and he left the university in 1746, becoming a public critic of its process of tenure.
In 1748 he began delivering public lectures in Edinburgh under the patronage of Lord Kames.
Some of these dealt with rhetoric and belles-lettres, but later he took up the subject of "the progress of opulence," and it was then, in his middle or late 20s, that he first expounded the economic philosophy of "the obvious and simple system of natural liberty" which he was later to proclaim to the world in his Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations.
In about 1750 he met David Hume, who was his senior by over a decade.
The alignments of opinion that can be found within the details of their respective writings covering history, politics, philosophy, economics, and religion indicate that they both shared a closer intellectual alliance and friendship than with the others who were to play important roles during the emergence of what has come to be known as the Scottish Enlightenment; he frequented The Poker Club of Edinburgh.

Smith's father had a strong interest in Christianity and belonged to the moderate wing of the Church of Scotland (the national church of Scotland since 1690).
Smith may have gone to England with the intention of a career in the Church of England: this is controversial and depends on the status of the Snell Scholarship.
How he lost belief and why remains uncertain.
But it is definite that he returned to Scotland as a Deist.

Coase, Professor of Economics and journal editor, challenged the view that Smith was a Deist, stating that, whilst Smith may have referred to the "Great Architect of the Universe", other scholars have "very much exaggerated the extent to which Adam Smith was committed to a belief in a personal God".
He based this on analysis of a remark in The Wealth of Nations where Smith writes that the curiosity of mankind about the "great phenomena of nature" such as "the generation, the life, growth and dissolution of plants and animals" has led men to "enquire into their causes".
Coase notes Smith's observation that: "Superstition first attempted to satisfy this curiosity, by referring all those wonderful appearances to the immediate agency of the gods.
Philosophy afterwards endeavoured to account for them, from more familiar causes, or from such as mankind were better acquainted with than the agency of the gods."
Coase argues that this is "hardly a remark which would have been made by a strong, or even a mild, deist".

In 1751 Smith was appointed chair of logic at the University of Glasgow, transferring in 1752 to the chair of moral philosophy.
His lectures covered the fields of ethics, rhetoric, jurisprudence, political economy, and "police and revenue".
In 1759 he published his The Theory of Moral Sentiments, embodying some of his Glasgow lectures.
This work, which established Smith's reputation in his day, was concerned with how human communication depends on sympathy between agent and spectator (that is, the individual and other members of society).
His analysis of language evolution was somewhat superficial, as shown only 14 years later by a more rigorous examination of primitive language evolution by Lord Monboddo in his Of the Origin and Progress of Language.
Smith's capacity for fluent, persuasive, if rather rhetorical argument, is much in evidence.
He bases his explanation, not as the third Lord Shaftesbury and Hutcheson had done, on a special "moral sense", nor (as Hume did) on utility, but on sympathy.

Smith now began to give more attention to jurisprudence and economics in his lecture and less to his theories of morals.
An impression can be obtained as to the development of his ideas on political economy from the notes of his lectures taken down by a student in about 1763 which were later edited by Edwin Cannan, and from what Scott, its discoverer and publisher, describes as "An Early Draft of Part of The Wealth of Nations", which he dates about 1763.
Cannan's work appeared as Lectures on Justice, Police, Revenue and Arms.
A fuller version was published as Lectures on Jurisprudence in the Glasgow Edition of 1976.

At the end of 1763 Smith obtained a lucrative offer from Charles Townshend (who had been introduced to Smith by David Hume), to tutor his stepson, the young Duke of Buccleuch.
Smith subsequently resigned from his professorship and from 1764-66 traveled with his pupil, mostly in France, where he came to know intellectual leaders such as Turgot, Jean D'Alembert, André Morellet, Helvétius and, in particular, Francois Quesnay, the head of the Physiocratic school whose work he respected greatly.
On returning home to Kirkcaldy he devoted much of the next ten years to his magnum opus, An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations, which appeared in 1776.
It was very well-received and popular, and Smith became famous.
In 1778 he was appointed to a comfortable post as commissioner of customs in Scotland and went to live with his mother in Edinburgh.
He died there on July 17, 1790, after a painful illness and was buried in the Canongate Kirkyard, Royal Mile, Edinburgh.
He had apparently devoted a considerable part of his income to numerous secret acts of charity.

Smith's literary executors were two old friends from the Scottish academic world; physicist/chemist Joseph Black and pioneering geologist James Hutton.
Smith left behind many notes and some unpublished material, but gave instructions to destroy anything that was not fit for publication.
He mentioned an early unpublished History of Astronomy as probably suitable, and it duly appeared in 1795, along with other material, as Essays on Philosophical Subjects.</entry>
  <entry author_id="4379273" end="487" start="451">Shortly before his death, Smith had nearly all his manuscripts destroyed.
In his last years he seemed to have been planning two major treatises, one on the theory and history of law and one on the sciences and arts.
The posthumously published Essays on Philosophical Subjects (1795) probably contain parts of what would have been the latter treatise.

The Wealth of Nations was his most influential work, and is considered to be very important in the creation of the field of economics and its development into an autonomous systematic discipline.
In the Western world, it is arguably the most influential book on the subject ever published.
When the book, which has become a classic manifesto against mercantilism (the theory that large reserves of bullion are essential for economic success), appeared in 1776, there was a strong sentiment for free trade in both Britain and America.
This new feeling had been born out of the economic hardships and poverty caused by the American War of Independence.
However, at the time of publication, not everybody was immediately convinced of the advantages of free trade: the British public and Parliament still clung to mercantilism for many years to come.

The Wealth of Nations also rejects the Physiocratic school's emphasis on the importance of land; instead, Smith believed labour was paramount, and that a division of labour would effect a great increase in production.
One example he used was the making of pins.
One worker could probably make only twenty pins per day.
But if ten people divided up the eighteen steps required to make a pin, they could make a combined amount of 48,000 pins in one day.
However, it is less well known that Smith also concluded that excessive division of labor would lead man to his most ignorant state possible.Nations was so successful, in fact, that it led to the abandonment of earlier economic schools, and later economists, such as Thomas Malthus and David Ricardo, focused on refining Smith's theory into what is now known as classical economics.
Both Modern economics and, separately, Marxian economics owe significantly to classical economics.
Malthus expanded Smith's ruminations on overpopulation, while Ricardo believed in the "iron law of wages" — that overpopulation would prevent wages from topping the subsistence level.
Smith postulated an increase of wages with an increase in production, a view considered more accurate today.

One of the main points of The Wealth of Nations is that the free market, while appearing chaotic and unrestrained, is actually guided to produce the right amount and variety of goods by a so-called "invisible hand" (an image that Smith had previously employed in Theory of Moral Sentiments, but which has its original use in his essay, "The History of Astronomy").
If a product shortage occurs, for instance, its price rises, creating a profit margin that creates an incentive for others to enter production, eventually curing the shortage.
If too many producers enter the market, the increased competition among manufacturers and increased supply would lower the price of the product to its production cost, the "natural price".
Even as profits are zeroed out at the "natural price," there would be incentives to produce goods and services, as all costs of production, including compensation for the owner's labour, are also built into the price of the goods.
If prices dip below a zero profit, producers would drop out of the market; if they were above a zero profit, producers would enter the market.
Smith believed that while human motives are often selfishness and greed, the competition in the free market would tend to benefit society as a whole by keeping prices low, while still building in an incentive for a wide variety of goods and services.
Nevertheless, he was wary of businessmen and argued against the formation of monopolies.

Smith vigorously attacked the antiquated government restrictions which he thought were hindering industrial expansion.
In fact, he attacked most forms of government interference in the economic process, including tariffs, arguing that this creates inefficiency and high prices in the long run.
This theory, now referred to as "laissez-faire", which means "let them do" or more relevant to the study of economics, "let the market set supply and demand with no interference".
It is believed that this theory influnced government legislation in later years, especially during the 19th century.
(However this was not opposition to government.
Smith advocated a Government that was active in sectors other than the economy: he advocated public education of poor adults; institutional systems that were not profitable for private industries; a judiciary; and a standing army.)

Two of the most famous and often-quoted passages in The Wealth of Nations are: Another favorite quote, usually recited by economists, also from The Wealth of Nations is: A critical but rarely-quoted passage in The Wealth of Nations is: Herbert Stein, in a frequently-quoted article, "Adam Smith did not wear an Adam Smith necktie," wrote that the people who wear the Adam Smith tie do it "to make a statement of their devotion to the idea of free markets and limited government.
What stands out in WofN, however, is that their patron saint was not pure or doctrinaire about this idea.
He viewed government intervention in the market with great skepticism.
He regarded his exposition of the virtues of the free market as his main contribution to policy, and the purpose for which his economic analysis was developed."

"Yet he was prepared to accept or propose qualifications to that policy in the specific cases where he judged that their net effect would be beneficial and would not undermine the basically free character of the system," wrote Stein.
"He did not wear the Adam Smith necktie."
In Stein's reading, The Wealth of Nations could justify the Food and Drug Administration, The Consumer Product Safety Commission, mandatory employer health benefits, environmentalism, and "discriminatory taxation to deter improper or luxurious behavior."</entry>
</article>
