<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="2122" title="Astrology" authors="8" lines="726">
  <entry author_id="3814" end="15" start="0">Astrology originated in Mesopotamia in the second millennium B.C.E., whence it spread to much of the world.
In medieval Europe before the scientific method was better understood, there was no distinction between astrology and astronomy, and those who studied the sky were often called upon as counselors to make astrological predictions, or to determine the best times to take important actions.
Today, astrology is seen as pseudoscience, and is practised primarily for personal counselling.

Astrological charts or horoscopes based on a person's birth will show where the stars and planets were in relation to each other at the moment of birth, and the person's specific latitude and longitude at that time.
The most prominent of these features is the position of the sun in relation to the signs of the zodiac.
From these planetary positions some people believe that certain conclusions can be made about the person.
Similarly, a horoscope may be prepared to reflect circumstances of an event.

Newspapers often print astrology columns, but these are a highly generalized presentation of astrology.
They purport to provide guidance on what challenges might be found in a day, as determined by where planets and stars are on that day, in relation to the sign of the zodiac that included the sun when the person was born.
This is correctly known as the "sun sign", but is often incorrectly referred to as the "star sign" in such newspapers.
Typically these predictions, an innovation of 20th century newspapers, are so vague or general as to be useless even to most practising astrologers.
People presented with randomly-chosen newspaper column report the same degree of accuracy as those given specifically prepared ones.

As the Earth spins on its axis, it "wobbles" like a top, causing the vernal equinox to move gradually backwards against the star background, (a phenomenon known as the Precession of the equinoxes) at a rate of about 30 degrees (one Zodiacal sign length) every 2160 years.
Thus the two Zodiacs are aligned only once every 26,000 years, with the most recent alignment being about 2000 years ago when the zodiac was principally established.
This phenomenon gives us the conceptual basis for the Age of Aquarius, whose "dawning" coincides with the movement of the vernal equinox across the cusp from Pisces to Aquarius in the star background.</entry>
  <entry author_id="40648" end="53" start="15">The case of Platonic and Neo-Platonic astrology should be of particular interest.
Here one can easily observe both the strong motivations towards the establishment of an astrological science, and the collapse of the bulk of these motivations in the post-Galilean world.
We shall begin by following a line of thought that was very strong in many parts of the classical world.
So strong, it was the reason for the deportation of Anaxagoras from Athens (he was advocating the stars were nothing but “hot stones in the sky”), and the Epicureans made the fight against this view the main point of their moral philosophy.

So, imagine you live in a society with a technology that is less than modern: no cars, planes, etc.
The only things you would observe that have the capacity to move on their own are living things.
Hence only living things have what Aristotle calls (potential) "innate movement".
But all living things decease (given enough time).
All?
Well, look at the sky - there you will find heavenly bodies moving perpetually in well-ordered paths.
If living things are the only candidates for self-induced movement, then the heavenly bodies must be alive.
They are also perpetual, hence immortal.
They also seem to be moving in a nice circular fashion; hence they must be highly intelligent sentient beings (circles being the most perfect of geometric forms).
What would you call a super-intelligent, immortal sentient being?
A god.
So the heavenly bodies are gods.
That's well enough.
But there are two other things you should notice about these gods: 1.
They seem to be unbound by earthly physics: they float high above, unaffected by gravity, and they also move in circular motion - a type of motion that is not very common down here on earth.
So the rules that work in the heavens are not the same as the terrestrial laws of physics.
2.
We already know that the heavens directly affect our lives.
Think about the weather: rain, snow, light, heat, cold, clouds... the different seasons... all these things govern our lives (esp. if we live in an agricultural society).
Let us sum things up.
We have seen that: -	Heavenly things govern life here on earth.
-	Heavenly things do not abide by earthly laws.
-	Heavenly things are gods.

It is very easy to see how Astrology and Alchemy stem from this view.
It would be only rational to try and consult the heavenly bodies - concerning almost everything – from the conception of babies to the signing of political and commercial treaties – hence Astrology.
It would also be very tempting to utilize the forces governing the heavens down here.
If you could “make” Mars work for you, you would be free from the confines of terrestrial physics – hence Alchemy.
It is also very easy to see why the Galilean views were so intimidating in the eyes of many renaissance scientists and policy-makers: Galileo’s observations were deadly to the dichotomy between earth and the heavens.
He was showing that the stars were merely natural phenomena, rather then super-natural super-intelligent perpetually unchanging beings.

So, in the classical world, the case for astrology was almost trivial.
The connections between heaven and earth are everywhere you look, and the heavens are clearly something supernatural.
In the post Galilean world, however, advocates for Astrology face an excruciating task.
The easy-to-observe influences of heaven are dealt with within the framework of sciences e.g. Meteorology and Solar Astronomy.
Further influences are no longer deemed trivial, and are usually very hard to show.</entry>
  <entry author_id="23657" end="77" start="53">Many people use the fact that there are 13 constellations, of unequal size, along the astronomical ecliptic, and not twelve equally-sized constellations, to try and discredit or otherwise disprove astrology.
In astrology, the size of the actual astronomical constellations is a non-issue because most Western astrologers use the tropical zodiac, where the ecliptic is divided into 12 equal portions exactly 30 degrees each to get the 12 astrological signs.
(12 signs x 30 degrees each sign = the 360 degrees of the ecliptic).
The beginning of the astrological year is the beginning of Spring in the Northern Hemisphere (the vernal equinox - usually around March 21), and not when the Sun crosses an arbitrary dividing line drawn up in modern times to denote where the constellation of Aries begins.
The time of the vernal equinox, therefore, is the definition of the start of the astrological sign of Aries, even though the Sun is well within the astronomical constellation of Pisces at that time of year.
See also the First Point of Aries.
Jyotish and western Siderial astrologers avoid this criticism by using a closer approximation of the true astronomical positions of the stars.

Some believers in astrology consult a horoscope published in a newspaper, which claims to make predictions for the coming day.
Newspapers often publish horoscope columns with the title "Astrological Forecast," perhaps implying that they should be considered on the same footing with weather forecasts.
However, astrology has failed carefully designed empirical tests of its predictive claims, unlike meteorology, which, although not always correct, has been proved to be statistically more accurate than random guessing.

If, on the other hand, the scientific method is to be rejected entirely, many skeptics believe the problem is that astrologers do not agree on any alternative method of determining whether a particular astrological method is any more or less objectively correct than any other.
Astrology is a controversial subject.
The case for and the case against astrology's objective validity are presented here: Many astrologers do not believe that gravitational or tidal forces are the mechanism behind astrology supposedly working, but, the idea that tidal forces affect biological organisms in some way has some scientific support.

Dr. Brown placed his oysters in a controlled environment, and at first they responded as expected, opening and closing their shells in accord with the tide in New Haven.
However, within a week, they began to get out of sync.
Within two weeks, they had once again settled on a unanimous rhythm - opening and closing in correlation with the tidal forces of Evanston, despite the fact that there was no physical motion of the water to prompt their action.
Clearly, some mechanism in the oyster was "detecting" the tidal force.

Dr. Percy Seymour, an astronomer/astrophysicist at Plymouth University, UK, has published several books in which he tries to find scientific explanations for astrology.
For more information, see the External links section below.
He focuses on the electromagnetic changes induced by tidal forces and the so-called Mars effect.

In 1997, Dr. Percy Seymour was Principal Lecturer in Astronomy at the University of Plymouth, where he taught astronomy and astrophysics to undergraduates and carried out research on magnetic fields in astronomy.
Given that astrology claims to be able to make predictions about future events, it should be possible to construct an experiment that measures its accuracy.
No such experiment has ever been able to clearly demonstrate the objective validity of astrology.
In addition, scientific double blind tests (example) have shown that even the best astrologers fare no better than random chance when matching astrological charts to personalities.</entry>
  <entry author_id="680483" end="126" start="77">Detractors say there is no evidence for the claims that astrologers can predict the future and maintain that astrology is a "pseudo-science" at best.
Astrologers claim that the centuries of astrological history proves otherwise.
And the great debate on the validity of astrology continues into the 21st century.
Astrology can be defined as the serious observations and studies of planetary and stellar cycles and their mathematical patterns in time as they affect life on Earth.
Professional astrologers apply mathematical aspects such as the conjunction, sextile, square, trine, and opposition to form complex calculations of activity between celestial objects in constant motion among the constellations relative to the Earth's position using charts called horoscopes to examine planetary transits at any given moment.
Spans of time and space where a person is born is charted through the application of a horoscope to forecast potential future events.
Free will is a given in true astrological practice, but destiny is within the principles of universal laws - and not outside of it.

The earliest knowledge of astrology dates back to antiquity and required constant renewing through presentation because of the growth of the many branches of astrological practice.
This development can be compared to that of the medical sciences, with the many special branches over time.
Some professional astrologers say that one of the handicaps of astrology as practiced in the late 20th century, is that much of the expansion has been done by groups of isolated reseachers that has limited the opportunities for building astrological work into a more solid body of work and consensus.

In the United States, a great surge of popular interest in astrology took place between 1900 through 1949.
A very popular astrologer based in New York City named Evangeline Adams help feed the public's thirst for astrology readings with many accurate forecasts, her biographers say.
A famous court case involving Adams, who was arrested and charged with illegal fortune-telling in 1914 - was later dismissed when Adams correctly read the horoscope of the judge's son with only a birthdate.
Her acquital set an American precedent that if astrologer's practiced in a professional manner that they were not guilty of any wrong-doing.

The serious and complex writings on astrological practice and concepts in America progressed from the turn-of-the-century years and into a new period of popular expansion in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s.
Many complex astrological materials were simplified to attempt to carve a clear line through points of contention and controversy.
The result of this attempt was to "simplify astrology" in the minds of professionals and gave the impression of settled and agreed positions on many points that were not resolved.

The period between 1920-1940 gave way to the popular media jumping on board the great public interest in astrology.
Publishers realized that millions of readers were interested in astrological forecasts and the interest grew ever more intense with the advent of America's entry into the First World War.
The war heightened interest in astrology.
Journalists began to write articles based on character descriptions and astrological "forecasts" were published in newspapers based on the one and only factor known to the public: the month and day of birth, as taken from the position of the Sun when a personis born.
The result of this practice led to modern-day publishing of Sun-Sign astrology columns and expanded to some astrological books and magazines in later decades of the 20th century.

Professional astrologers say that the average educated adult or beginner should not be misled by false astrological statements, or over-simplifying by the biased opinions of those who have academic status in other fields of learning while using their positions to direct others to believe that their ideas on astrology are valid.
Such examples exist of somw writers of books on astrology who have admitted that that they did not know how to cast an astrological horoscope or to interpret one.
Astrologers state that writers and detractors who possess no practical knowledge of the workings of astrological principles, its history, and techniques are not qualified to state that astrology is a pseudo-science.

Seeking to protect serious astrology from the perceived attacks of conventional scientists - astrologers in the latter half of the 20th century have fought to protect themselves against Sun-Sign "pseudo-astrologers" in much the same way the medical profession has sought to protect itself from "quacks."
With the advent of computer technology, astrological work has had great benefit with the speed and accuracy of complex calucations.
But the downside has been that those who buy such astrological software believe that with the ability to print out a horoscope that they qualify as professional astrologers and can give "readings" to clients.

As with any profession, only true scholarship, study and practical application can successfully attain the proper professional status to become a true astrologer.
It takes years to learn the most basic principles and apply them practically.
And decades to master many astrological techniques and branches.
Many professional astrologers are self-taught, or have taken correspondence courses with professional tutors in the global astrological community.
Many new schools of astrology led by responsible leadership have opened their doors in the latter half of the 20th century, and teaching schools now offer diplomas after rigorous examination courses are passed by students.
As in medicine, passing an examination cannot always mean that the candidate is an expert in the subject.
However, it can show that a successful student has assimilated what they have studied and is fit to produce practical and accurate astrological work for clients that will give them the experience where, in time, they may eventually become expert.
The oldest known form of astrology, classical, or judicial astrology, practiced by ancient astrologers who made calculations of their direct view of the constellational night skies.
Judicial astrology as many branches (see below) such as Mundane astrology a branch that uses mathematical calculations of the celestial bodies to forecast future world events.

The origin of astrology included astronomy; as both were combined as one applied science before the emergence of conventional scientific practice in the 18th Century.
Judicial astrologers were considered masters of the celestial sciences and were much sought-after mathematicians and forecasters by royalty and the wealthy.
One of the first uses of astrology was accurately predicting the weather using meteorological astrology - a another branch of judicial astrology which Ptolemy first mastered.

Many judicial astrologers practiced as teachers, medicial doctors and strategists and were known for their strict astrological principles and ability to forecast the future.
Today, judicial astrologers are rare due to the false popularization of sun-sign astrology; however, those who do practice judicial astrology are known to be very accurate forecasters and astute observers of celestial movements relative to the Earth.
It is said that nothing forecasted by a judicial astrologer should ever be taken lightly due to the seriousness and many years of practice to become a judicial astrologer.
The average span of learning and professional astrological practice to reach the experience qualification level of judicial astrologer is said to be over 20 years.

The opinion of the conventional scientific community is that astrology is superstition, with no actual ability; yet, conventional scientists cannot account for the numerous accurate forecasts of astrologers throughout the centuries using astrological principles.
For examples, the world forecasts of judicial astrologers like Nostradamus hundreds of years prior to world events cannot be disputed as false since many of his predictions did come true.
However, skpetics claim that seeing into the future is not possible.

Astrologers rely on data drawn set out in a set of tables called an ephemeris, which shows the changing positions of the heavenly bodies through time.
It is the interpretation of these science based tables that astrologers use to make predictions - including long-term weather forecasts.</entry>
  <entry author_id="680483" end="175" start="126">Detractors say there is no evidence for the claims that astrologers can predict the future and maintain that astrology is a "pseudo-science" at best.
Astrologers claim that the centuries of astrological history proves otherwise.
And the great debate on the validity of astrology continues into the 21st century.
Astrology can be defined as the serious observations and studies of planetary and stellar cycles and their mathematical patterns in time as they affect life on Earth.
Professional astrologers apply mathematical aspects such as the conjunction, sextile, square, trine, and opposition to form complex calculations of activity between celestial objects in constant motion among the constellations relative to the Earth's position using charts called horoscopes to examine planetary transits at any given moment.
Spans of time and space where a person is born is charted through the application of a horoscope to forecast potential future events.
Free will is a given in true astrological practice, but destiny is within the principles of universal laws - and not outside of it.

The earliest knowledge of astrology dates back to antiquity and required constant renewing through presentation because of the growth of the many branches of astrological practice.
This development can be compared to that of the medical sciences, with the many special branches over time.
Some professional astrologers say that one of the handicaps of astrology as practiced in the late 20th century, is that much of the expansion has been done by groups of isolated reseachers that has limited the opportunities for building astrological work into a more solid body of work and consensus.

In the United States, a great surge of popular interest in astrology took place between 1900 through 1949.
A very popular astrologer based in New York City named Evangeline Adams help feed the public's thirst for astrology readings with many accurate forecasts, her biographers say.
A famous court case involving Adams, who was arrested and charged with illegal fortune-telling in 1914 - was later dismissed when Adams correctly read the horoscope of the judge's son with only a birthdate.
Her acquital set an American precedent that if astrologer's practiced in a professional manner that they were not guilty of any wrong-doing.

The serious and complex writings on astrological practice and concepts in America progressed from the turn-of-the-century years and into a new period of popular expansion in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s.
Many complex astrological materials were simplified to attempt to carve a clear line through points of contention and controversy.
The result of this attempt was to "simplify astrology" in the minds of professionals and gave the impression of settled and agreed positions on many points that were not resolved.

The period between 1920-1940 gave way to the popular media jumping on board the great public interest in astrology.
Publishers realized that millions of readers were interested in astrological forecasts and the interest grew ever more intense with the advent of America's entry into the First World War.
The war heightened interest in astrology.
Journalists began to write articles based on character descriptions and astrological "forecasts" were published in newspapers based on the one and only factor known to the public: the month and day of birth, as taken from the position of the Sun when a personis born.
The result of this practice led to modern-day publishing of Sun-Sign astrology columns and expanded to some astrological books and magazines in later decades of the 20th century.

Professional astrologers say that the average educated adult or beginner should not be misled by false astrological statements, or over-simplifying by the biased opinions of those who have academic status in other fields of learning while using their positions to direct others to believe that their ideas on astrology are valid.
Such examples exist of somw writers of books on astrology who have admitted that that they did not know how to cast an astrological horoscope or to interpret one.
Astrologers state that writers and detractors who possess no practical knowledge of the workings of astrological principles, its history, and techniques are not qualified to state that astrology is a pseudo-science.

Seeking to protect serious astrology from the perceived attacks of conventional scientists - astrologers in the latter half of the 20th century have fought to protect themselves against Sun-Sign "pseudo-astrologers" in much the same way the medical profession has sought to protect itself from "quacks."
With the advent of computer technology, astrological work has had great benefit with the speed and accuracy of complex calucations.
But the downside has been that those who buy such astrological software believe that with the ability to print out a horoscope that they qualify as professional astrologers and can give "readings" to clients.

As with any profession, only true scholarship, study and practical application can successfully attain the proper professional status to become a true astrologer.
It takes years to learn the most basic principles and apply them practically.
And decades to master many astrological techniques and branches.
Many professional astrologers are self-taught, or have taken correspondence courses with professional tutors in the global astrological community.
Many new schools of astrology led by responsible leadership have opened their doors in the latter half of the 20th century, and teaching schools now offer diplomas after rigorous examination courses are passed by students.
As in medicine, passing an examination cannot always mean that the candidate is an expert in the subject.
However, it can show that a successful student has assimilated what they have studied and is fit to produce practical and accurate astrological work for clients that will give them the experience where, in time, they may eventually become expert.
The oldest known form of astrology, classical, or judicial astrology, practiced by ancient astrologers who made calculations of their direct view of the constellational night skies.
Judicial astrology as many branches (see below) such as Mundane astrology a branch that uses mathematical calculations of the celestial bodies to forecast future world events.

The origin of astrology included astronomy; as both were combined as one applied science before the emergence of conventional scientific practice in the 18th Century.
Judicial astrologers were considered masters of the celestial sciences and were much sought-after mathematicians and forecasters by royalty and the wealthy.
One of the first uses of astrology was accurately predicting the weather using meteorological astrology - a another branch of judicial astrology which Ptolemy first mastered.

Many judicial astrologers practiced as teachers, medicial doctors and strategists and were known for their strict astrological principles and ability to forecast the future.
Today, judicial astrologers are rare due to the false popularization of sun-sign astrology; however, those who do practice judicial astrology are known to be very accurate forecasters and astute observers of celestial movements relative to the Earth.
It is said that nothing forecasted by a judicial astrologer should ever be taken lightly due to the seriousness and many years of practice to become a judicial astrologer.
The average span of learning and professional astrological practice to reach the experience qualification level of judicial astrologer is said to be over 20 years.

The opinion of the conventional scientific community is that astrology is superstition, with no actual ability; yet, conventional scientists cannot account for the numerous accurate forecasts of astrologers throughout the centuries using astrological principles.
For examples, the world forecasts of judicial astrologers like Nostradamus hundreds of years prior to world events cannot be disputed as false since many of his predictions did come true.
However, skpetics claim that seeing into the future is not possible.

Astrologers rely on data drawn set out in a set of tables called an ephemeris, which shows the changing positions of the heavenly bodies through time.
It is the interpretation of these science based tables that astrologers use to make predictions - including long-term weather forecasts.</entry>
  <entry author_id="733550" end="205" start="175">Only Propitiation &amp; Election branches of Hindu astrology are advised in Vedas, which has withstood test of time for the last 5 millenniums.
Other branches of Hindu astrology have been subsequently derived thereafter.
Electional astrology, called Muhurtha or Muhurt, is indeed the most useful predictive, preventive &amp; prescriptive branch of Hindu astrology capable of guiding aspirants for fruition of their activities &amp; desires.
The fundamental challenge &amp; aim before a human being is improvement in his existing status &amp; to attain fruition of individual desires to the maximum extent, simultaneously warding off visible &amp; invisible obstacles.

VEDIC DIRECTIONS - Hindu sages through their intuitive foresight (trikaal darshita) had in-depth knowledge of election (called Muhurt / Muhurtha – in Vedic astrology) &amp; had prescribed propitiations through incantation of Mantras (recitation of sacred hymns), Yagna (oblation through fire), ritual bathing, gem therapy, donations &amp; various other modes in Vedas.
The knowledge has with stood test of the time for the last over 5 millenniums, &amp; is still followed without modifications.
Vedic dictums deal with election &amp; not other branches of present day astrology, which have been subsequently derived from Vedic spiritualism.

It is not thought possible in any other branch of knowledge other than available in the Vedic election, which can render advice to an aspirant to initiate any life activity, for the best fruition of the event.
Even in the modern day branches of different knowledges have not been able to render such guidance to cull out a propitious time to initiate an activity.
Only knowledge available in Vedas about election can guide an aspirant in this direction, &amp; does render predictive, preventive &amp; prescriptive advises, not only for spiritual uplift but for mundane benefits also.

HIGHEST EXPERTISE REQUIRED – No activity used to be performed by the kings in historic era without elections.
To cite an example; the India’s first great emperor, Chanragupta Maurya ( 4th century B C) had 3 cabinet members ( Navrantanas) out of the total 9 cabinet ministers, who had expertise in the field of astrology.
One of them was Acharya Kalidas, who was expert in election astrology, to render astro advices on day-to-day governmental activities.

Only after in-depth study of astrology, one can venture into the field of election astrology.
There were exponents in Vedic electional astrology who have written treatises only on electional astrology.
This establishes the fact that in the history of Indian astrology we had specialist in the different fields of astrology – not like now-a-days we have astrologers who claim specialization in all the fields of astrology claiming to render astro advice in all the fields.

The subject is so deep &amp; intricate which requires huge efforts to cull out a figure of heaven for birth of a life activity for an aspirant.
Perhaps only one in over 10,000 Hindu astrologers ventures to study &amp; master the subject to guide aspirants achieve the desired eventual outcome of an undertaking.
The fact the readers shall like to digest from information that in the last over 100 years, there has been no compilation / addition / research work in the field of electional astrology even in form of a commentary / compendium / treatise, yet thousands of books on predictive branch of Hindu astrology have been published.
In Indian / Vedic system of astrology, predictive part has been given much lesser importance compared to advisory role expected to be played by an astrologer.

The unsullied Muhurt – without any maleficence is the best but is rarely available.
Next middling Muhurt having more beneficence &amp; less maleficence is used by specialist astrologer through his expertise after balancing the election &amp; examining the antidotes.
The Muhurt having lesser beneficence is used in emergency.
In Hindu system, other styles of Muhurtas like Do Ghati Muhurt, Shiv prokat Muhurt, Chaughadia Muhurt &amp; Brihaspati Muhurtas are also in vogue.

Antidotes: No election is feasible unless antidotes to the maleficence is available &amp; is balanced by specialist astrologer.
He has to examine compliance to the laid down logics, purification of divisional charts; arriving at the precise moment to start the event for the best benefits of the aspirants explaining him the limitations &amp; constraints, as perceived by the specialist.
It is not feasible to concise all the factors considered in selection of an election.

N.B.
Learned readers may note that Muhurt / election is available to lucky individuals who have done meritorious deeds in this as well as in their past births; and even if such a propitious time is prescribed to him, he may not be able to fully utilize for his benefits.
Purity of mind &amp; consciousness are essential to comply &amp; reap benefits from expert guidance in election.</entry>
  <entry author_id="733550" end="235" start="205">SUBTLETIES OF VEDIC ELECTION / MUHURTHA – HINDU ELECTIONAL ASTROLOGY               Only Propitiation &amp; Election branches of Hindu astrology are advised in Vedas, which has withstood test of time for the last 5 millenniums.
Other branches of Hindu astrology have been subsequently derived thereafter.
Electional astrology, called Muhurtha or Muhurt, is indeed the most useful predictive, preventive &amp; prescriptive branch of Hindu astrology capable of guiding aspirants for fruition of their activities &amp; desires.
The fundamental challenge &amp; aim before a human being is improvement in his existing status &amp; to attain fruition of individual desires to the maximum extent, simultaneously warding off visible &amp; invisible obstacles.

VEDIC DIRECTIONS - Hindu sages through their intuitive foresight (trikaal darshita) had in-depth knowledge of election (called Muhurt / Muhurtha – in Vedic astrology) &amp; had prescribed propitiations through incantation of Mantras (recitation of sacred hymns), Yagna (oblation through fire), ritual bathing, gem therapy, donations &amp; various other modes in Vedas.
The knowledge has with stood test of the time for the last over 5 millenniums, &amp; is still followed without modifications.
Vedic dictums deal with election &amp; not other branches of present day astrology, which have been subsequently derived from Vedic spiritualism.

It is not thought possible in any other branch of knowledge other than available in the Vedic election, which can render advice to an aspirant to initiate any life activity, for the best fruition of the event.
Even in the modern day branches of different knowledges have not been able to render such guidance to cull out a propitious time to initiate an activity.
Only knowledge available in Vedas about election can guide an aspirant in this direction, &amp; does render predictive, preventive &amp; prescriptive advises, not only for spiritual uplift but for mundane benefits also.

HIGHEST EXPERTISE REQUIRED – No activity used to be performed by the kings in historic era without elections.
To cite an example; the India’s first great emperor, Chanragupta Maurya ( 4th century B C) had 3 cabinet members ( Navrantanas) out of the total 9 cabinet ministers, who had expertise in the field of astrology.
One of them was Acharya Kalidas, who was expert in election astrology, to render astro advices on day-to-day governmental activities.

Only after in-depth study of astrology, one can venture into the field of election astrology.
There were exponents in Vedic electional astrology who have written treatises only on electional astrology.
This establishes the fact that in the history of Indian astrology we had specialist in the different fields of astrology – not like now-a-days we have astrologers who claim specialization in all the fields of astrology claiming to render astro advice in all the fields.

The subject is so deep &amp; intricate which requires huge efforts to cull out a figure of heaven for birth of a life activity for an aspirant.
Perhaps only one in over 10,000 Hindu astrologers ventures to study &amp; master the subject to guide aspirants achieve the desired eventual outcome of an undertaking.
The fact the readers shall like to digest from information that in the last over 100 years, there has been no compilation / addition / research work in the field of electional astrology even in form of a commentary / compendium / treatise, yet thousands of books on predictive branch of Hindu astrology have been published.
In Indian / Vedic system of astrology, predictive part has been given much lesser importance compared to advisory role expected to be played by an astrologer.

The unsullied Muhurt – without any maleficence is the best but is rarely available.
Next middling Muhurt having more beneficence &amp; less maleficence is used by specialist astrologer through his expertise after balancing the election &amp; examining the antidotes.
The Muhurt having lesser beneficence is used in emergency.
In Hindu system, other styles of Muhurtas like Do Ghati Muhurt, Shiv prokat Muhurt, Chaughadia Muhurt &amp; Brihaspati Muhurtas are also in vogue.

Antidotes: No election is feasible unless antidotes to the maleficence is available &amp; is balanced by specialist astrologer.
He has to examine compliance to the laid down logics, purification of divisional charts; arriving at the precise moment to start the event for the best benefits of the aspirants explaining him the limitations &amp; constraints, as perceived by the specialist.
It is not feasible to concise all the factors considered in selection of an election.

N.B.
Learned readers may note that Muhurt / election is available to lucky individuals who have done meritorious deeds in this as well as in their past births; and even if such a propitious time is prescribed to him, he may not be able to fully utilize for his benefits.
Purity of mind &amp; consciousness are essential to comply &amp; reap benefits from expert guidance in election.</entry>
  <entry author_id="680483" end="284" start="235">Detractors say there is no evidence for the claims that astrologers can predict the future and maintain that astrology is a "pseudo-science" at best.
Astrologers claim that the centuries of astrological history proves otherwise.
And the great debate on the validity of astrology continues into the 21st century.
Astrology can be defined as the serious observations and studies of planetary and stellar cycles and their mathematical patterns in time as they affect life on Earth.
Professional astrologers apply mathematical aspects such as the conjunction, sextile, square, trine, and opposition to form complex calculations of activity between celestial objects in constant motion among the constellations relative to the Earth's position using charts called horoscopes to examine planetary transits at any given moment.
Spans of time and space where a person is born is charted through the application of a horoscope to forecast potential future events.
Free will is a given in true astrological practice, but destiny is within the principles of universal laws - and not outside of it.

The earliest knowledge of astrology dates back to antiquity and required constant renewing through presentation because of the growth of the many branches of astrological practice.
This development can be compared to that of the medical sciences, with the many special branches over time.
Some professional astrologers say that one of the handicaps of astrology as practiced in the late 20th century, is that much of the expansion has been done by groups of isolated reseachers that has limited the opportunities for building astrological work into a more solid body of work and consensus.

In the United States, a great surge of popular interest in astrology took place between 1900 through 1949.
A very popular astrologer based in New York City named Evangeline Adams help feed the public's thirst for astrology readings with many accurate forecasts, her biographers say.
A famous court case involving Adams, who was arrested and charged with illegal fortune-telling in 1914 - was later dismissed when Adams correctly read the horoscope of the judge's son with only a birthdate.
Her acquital set an American precedent that if astrologer's practiced in a professional manner that they were not guilty of any wrong-doing.

The serious and complex writings on astrological practice and concepts in America progressed from the turn-of-the-century years and into a new period of popular expansion in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s.
Many complex astrological materials were simplified to attempt to carve a clear line through points of contention and controversy.
The result of this attempt was to "simplify astrology" in the minds of professionals and gave the impression of settled and agreed positions on many points that were not resolved.

The period between 1920-1940 gave way to the popular media jumping on board the great public interest in astrology.
Publishers realized that millions of readers were interested in astrological forecasts and the interest grew ever more intense with the advent of America's entry into the First World War.
The war heightened interest in astrology.
Journalists began to write articles based on character descriptions and astrological "forecasts" were published in newspapers based on the one and only factor known to the public: the month and day of birth, as taken from the position of the Sun when a personis born.
The result of this practice led to modern-day publishing of Sun-Sign astrology columns and expanded to some astrological books and magazines in later decades of the 20th century.

Professional astrologers say that the average educated adult or beginner should not be misled by false astrological statements, or over-simplifying by the biased opinions of those who have academic status in other fields of learning while using their positions to direct others to believe that their ideas on astrology are valid.
Such examples exist of somw writers of books on astrology who have admitted that that they did not know how to cast an astrological horoscope or to interpret one.
Astrologers state that writers and detractors who possess no practical knowledge of the workings of astrological principles, its history, and techniques are not qualified to state that astrology is a pseudo-science.

Seeking to protect serious astrology from the perceived attacks of conventional scientists - astrologers in the latter half of the 20th century have fought to protect themselves against Sun-Sign "pseudo-astrologers" in much the same way the medical profession has sought to protect itself from "quacks."
With the advent of computer technology, astrological work has had great benefit with the speed and accuracy of complex calucations.
But the downside has been that those who buy such astrological software believe that with the ability to print out a horoscope that they qualify as professional astrologers and can give "readings" to clients.

As with any profession, only true scholarship, study and practical application can successfully attain the proper professional status to become a true astrologer.
It takes years to learn the most basic principles and apply them practically.
And decades to master many astrological techniques and branches.
Many professional astrologers are self-taught, or have taken correspondence courses with professional tutors in the global astrological community.
Many new schools of astrology led by responsible leadership have opened their doors in the latter half of the 20th century, and teaching schools now offer diplomas after rigorous examination courses are passed by students.
As in medicine, passing an examination cannot always mean that the candidate is an expert in the subject.
However, it can show that a successful student has assimilated what they have studied and is fit to produce practical and accurate astrological work for clients that will give them the experience where, in time, they may eventually become expert.
The oldest known form of astrology, classical, or judicial astrology, practiced by ancient astrologers who made calculations of their direct view of the constellational night skies.
Judicial astrology as many branches (see below) such as Mundane astrology a branch that uses mathematical calculations of the celestial bodies to forecast future world events.

The origin of astrology included astronomy; as both were combined as one applied science before the emergence of conventional scientific practice in the 18th Century.
Judicial astrologers were considered masters of the celestial sciences and were much sought-after mathematicians and forecasters by royalty and the wealthy.
One of the first uses of astrology was accurately predicting the weather using meteorological astrology - a another branch of judicial astrology which Ptolemy first mastered.

Texts show that judicial astrologers practiced as teachers, medicial doctors and strategists and were known for their strict astrological principles and ability to forecast the future.
Today, judicial astrologers are rare due to the false popularization of sun-sign astrology; however, those who do practice judicial astrology are known to be very accurate forecasters, and astute observers of celestial movements relative to the Earth.
It is said that nothing forecasted by a judicial astrologer should ever be taken lightly due to the seriousness and many years of practice to become a judicial astrologer.
The average span of learning and professional astrological practice to reach the experience qualification level of judicial astrologer is said to be over 20 years.

The opinion of the conventional scientific community is that astrology is superstition, with no actual ability; yet, conventional scientists cannot account for the numerous accurate forecasts of astrologers throughout the centuries using astrological principles.
For examples, the world forecasts of judicial astrologers like Nostradamus hundreds of years prior to world events cannot be disputed as false since many of his predictions did come true.
However, skpetics claim that seeing into the future is not possible.

Astrologers rely on data drawn set out in a set of tables called an ephemeris, which shows the changing positions of the heavenly bodies through time.
It is the interpretation of these science based tables that astrologers use to make predictions - including long-term weather forecasts.</entry>
  <entry author_id="680483" end="337" start="284">Detractors say there is no evidence for the claims that astrologers can predict the future and maintain that astrology is a "pseudo-science" at best.
Astrologers claim that the centuries of astrological history proves otherwise.
And the great debate on the validity of astrology continues into the 21st century.
Astrology can be defined as the serious observations and studies of planetary and stellar cycles and their mathematical patterns in time as they affect life on Earth.
Professional astrologers apply mathematical aspects such as the conjunction, sextile, square, trine, and opposition to form complex calculations of activity between celestial objects in constant motion among the constellations relative to the Earth's position using charts called horoscopes to examine planetary transits at any given moment.
Spans of time and space where a person is born is charted through the application of a horoscope to forecast potential future events.
Free will is a given in true astrological practice, but destiny is within the principles of universal laws - and not outside of it.

The earliest knowledge of astrology dates back to antiquity and required constant renewing through presentation because of the growth of the many branches of astrological practice.
This development can be compared to that of the medical sciences, with the many special branches over time.
Some professional astrologers say that one of the handicaps of astrology as practiced in the late 20th century, is that much of the expansion has been done by groups of isolated reseachers that has limited the opportunities for building astrological work into a more solid body of work and consensus.

Many prior astrological works were contained in the almanac form in Europe in the Middle Ages.
These almanacs were popular throughout western Europe, and were also published in the United States in the mid-1700s.
One of the most famous was penned by Benjamin Franklin, who created Poor Richard's Almanac under one of his pen names (Richard Saunders, a destitute astrologer.)
Franklin's almanac was immensely popular and maintained a circulation over 10,000 a year for 25 years.

A great surge of popular interest in astrology also took place between 1900 through 1949 in America.
A very popular astrologer based in New York City named Evangeline Adams help feed the public's thirst for astrology readings with many accurate forecasts, her biographers say.
A famous court case involving Adams, who was arrested and charged with illegal fortune-telling in 1914 - was later dismissed when Adams correctly read the horoscope of the judge's son with only a birthdate.
Her acquital set an American precedent that if astrologer's practiced in a professional manner that they were not guilty of any wrong-doing.

The serious and complex writings on astrological practice and concepts in America progressed from the turn-of-the-century years and into a new period of popular expansion in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s.
Many complex astrological materials were simplified to attempt to carve a clear line through points of contention and controversy.
The result of this attempt was to "simplify astrology" in the minds of professionals and gave the impression of settled and agreed positions on many points that were not resolved.

The period between 1920-1940 gave way to the popular media jumping on board the great public interest in astrology.
Publishers realized that millions of readers were interested in astrological forecasts and the interest grew ever more intense with the advent of America's entry into the First World War.
The war heightened interest in astrology.
Journalists began to write articles based on character descriptions and astrological "forecasts" were published in newspapers based on the one and only factor known to the public: the month and day of birth, as taken from the position of the Sun when a personis born.
The result of this practice led to modern-day publishing of Sun-Sign astrology columns and expanded to some astrological books and magazines in later decades of the 20th century.

Professional astrologers say that the average educated adult or beginner should not be misled by false astrological statements, or over-simplifying by the biased opinions of those who have academic status in other fields of learning while using their positions to direct others to believe that their ideas on astrology are valid.
Such examples exist of somw writers of books on astrology who have admitted that that they did not know how to cast an astrological horoscope or to interpret one.
Astrologers state that writers and detractors who possess no practical knowledge of the workings of astrological principles, its history, and techniques are not qualified to state that astrology is a pseudo-science.

Seeking to protect serious astrology from the perceived attacks of conventional scientists - astrologers in the latter half of the 20th century have fought to protect themselves against Sun-Sign "pseudo-astrologers" in much the same way the medical profession has sought to protect itself from "quacks."
With the advent of computer technology, astrological work has had great benefit with the speed and accuracy of complex calucations.
But the downside has been that those who buy such astrological software believe that with the ability to print out a horoscope that they qualify as professional astrologers and can give "readings" to clients.

As with any profession, only true scholarship, study and practical application can successfully attain the proper professional status to become a true astrologer.
It takes years to learn the most basic principles and apply them practically.
And decades to master many astrological techniques and branches.
Many professional astrologers are self-taught, or have taken correspondence courses with professional tutors in the global astrological community.
Many new schools of astrology led by responsible leadership have opened their doors in the latter half of the 20th century, and teaching schools now offer diplomas after rigorous examination courses are passed by students.
As in medicine, passing an examination cannot always mean that the candidate is an expert in the subject.
However, it can show that a successful student has assimilated what they have studied and is fit to produce practical and accurate astrological work for clients that will give them the experience where, in time, they may eventually become expert.
The oldest known form of astrology, classical, or judicial astrology, practiced by ancient astrologers who made calculations of their direct view of the constellational night skies.
Judicial astrology as many branches (see below) such as Mundane astrology a branch that uses mathematical calculations of the celestial bodies to forecast future world events.

The origin of astrology included astronomy; as both were combined as one applied science before the emergence of conventional scientific practice in the 18th Century.
Judicial astrologers were considered masters of the celestial sciences and were much sought-after mathematicians and forecasters by royalty and the wealthy.
One of the first uses of astrology was accurately predicting the weather using meteorological astrology - a another branch of judicial astrology which Ptolemy first mastered.

Texts show that judicial astrologers practiced as teachers, medicial doctors and strategists and were known for their strict astrological principles and ability to forecast the future.
Today, judicial astrologers are rare due to the false popularization of sun-sign astrology; however, those who do practice judicial astrology are known to be very accurate forecasters, and astute observers of celestial movements relative to the Earth.
It is said that nothing forecasted by a judicial astrologer should ever be taken lightly due to the seriousness and many years of practice to become a judicial astrologer.
The average span of learning and professional astrological practice to reach the experience qualification level of judicial astrologer is said to be over 20 years.

The opinion of the conventional scientific community is that astrology is superstition, with no actual ability; yet, conventional scientists cannot account for the numerous accurate forecasts of astrologers throughout the centuries using astrological principles.
For examples, the world forecasts of judicial astrologers like Nostradamus hundreds of years prior to world events cannot be disputed as false since many of his predictions did come true.
However, skpetics claim that seeing into the future is not possible.

Astrologers rely on data drawn set out in a set of tables called an ephemeris, which shows the changing positions of the heavenly bodies through time.
It is the interpretation of these science based tables that astrologers use to make predictions - including long-term weather forecasts.</entry>
  <entry author_id="680483" end="390" start="337">Detractors say there is no evidence for the claims that astrologers can predict the future and maintain that astrology is a "pseudo-science" at best.
Astrologers claim that the centuries of astrological history proves otherwise.
And the great debate on the validity of astrology continues into the 21st century.
Astrology can be defined as the serious observations and studies of planetary and stellar cycles and their mathematical patterns in time as they affect life on Earth.
Professional astrologers apply mathematical aspects such as the conjunction, sextile, square, trine, and opposition to form complex calculations of activity between celestial objects in constant motion among the constellations relative to the Earth's position using charts called horoscopes to examine planetary transits at any given moment.
Spans of time and space where a person is born is charted through the application of a horoscope to forecast potential future events.
Free will is a given in true astrological practice, but destiny is within the principles of universal laws - and not outside of it.

The earliest knowledge of astrology dates back to antiquity and required constant renewing through presentation because of the growth of the many branches of astrological practice.
This development can be compared to that of the medical sciences, with the many special branches over time.
Some professional astrologers say that one of the handicaps of astrology as practiced in the late 20th century, is that much of the expansion has been done by groups of isolated reseachers that has limited the opportunities for building astrological work into a more solid body of work and consensus.

Many prior astrological works were contained in the almanac form in Europe in the Middle Ages.
These almanacs were popular throughout western Europe, and were also published in the United States in the mid-1700s.
One of the most famous was penned by Benjamin Franklin, who created Poor Richard's Almanac under one of his pen names (Richard Saunders, a destitute astrologer.)
Franklin's almanac was immensely popular and maintained a circulation over 10,000 a year for 25 years.

A great surge of popular interest in astrology also took place between 1900 through 1949 in America.
A very popular astrologer based in New York City named Evangeline Adams help feed the public's thirst for astrology readings with many accurate forecasts, her biographers say.
A famous court case involving Adams, who was arrested and charged with illegal fortune-telling in 1914 - was later dismissed when Adams correctly read the horoscope of the judge's son with only a birthdate.
Her acquital set an American precedent that if astrologer's practiced in a professional manner that they were not guilty of any wrong-doing.

The serious and complex writings on astrological practice and concepts in America progressed from the turn-of-the-century years and into a new period of popular expansion in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s.
Many complex astrological materials were simplified to attempt to carve a clear line through points of contention and controversy.
The result of this attempt was to "simplify astrology" in the minds of professionals and gave the impression of settled and agreed positions on many points that were not resolved.

The period between 1920-1940 gave way to the popular media jumping on board the great public interest in astrology.
Publishers realized that millions of readers were interested in astrological forecasts and the interest grew ever more intense with the advent of America's entry into the First World War.
The war heightened interest in astrology.
Journalists began to write articles based on character descriptions and astrological "forecasts" were published in newspapers based on the one and only factor known to the public: the month and day of birth, as taken from the position of the Sun when a personis born.
The result of this practice led to modern-day publishing of Sun-Sign astrology columns and expanded to some astrological books and magazines in later decades of the 20th century.

Professional astrologers say that the average educated adult or beginner should not be misled by false astrological statements, or over-simplifying by the biased opinions of those who have academic status in other fields of learning while using their positions to direct others to believe that their ideas on astrology are valid.
Such examples exist of somw writers of books on astrology who have admitted that that they did not know how to cast an astrological horoscope or to interpret one.
Astrologers state that writers and detractors who possess no practical knowledge of the workings of astrological principles, its history, and techniques are not qualified to state that astrology is a pseudo-science.

Seeking to protect serious astrology from the perceived attacks of conventional scientists - astrologers in the latter half of the 20th century have fought to protect themselves against Sun-Sign "pseudo-astrologers" in much the same way the medical profession has sought to protect itself from "quacks."
With the advent of computer technology, astrological work has had great benefit with the speed and accuracy of complex calucations.
But the downside has been that those who buy such astrological software believe that with the ability to print out a horoscope that they qualify as professional astrologers and can give "readings" to clients.

As with any profession, only true scholarship, study and practical application can successfully attain the proper professional status to become a true astrologer.
It takes years to learn the most basic principles and apply them practically.
And decades to master many astrological techniques and branches.
Many professional astrologers are self-taught, or have taken correspondence courses with professional tutors in the global astrological community.
Many new schools of astrology led by responsible leadership have opened their doors in the latter half of the 20th century, and teaching schools now offer diplomas after rigorous examination courses are passed by students.
As in medicine, passing an examination cannot always mean that the candidate is an expert in the subject.
However, it can show that a successful student has assimilated what they have studied and is fit to produce practical and accurate astrological work for clients that will give them the experience where, in time, they may eventually become expert.
The oldest known form of astrology, classical, or judicial astrology, practiced by ancient astrologers who made calculations of their direct view of the constellational night skies.
Judicial astrology as many branches (see below) such as Mundane astrology a branch that uses mathematical calculations of the celestial bodies to forecast future world events.

The origin of astrology included astronomy; as both were combined as one applied science before the emergence of conventional scientific practice in the 18th Century.
Judicial astrologers were considered masters of the celestial sciences and were much sought-after mathematicians and forecasters by royalty and the wealthy.
One of the first uses of astrology was accurately predicting the weather using meteorological astrology - a another branch of judicial astrology which Ptolemy first mastered.

Texts show that judicial astrologers practiced as teachers, medicial doctors and strategists and were known for their strict astrological principles and ability to forecast the future.
Today, judicial astrologers are rare due to the false popularization of sun-sign astrology; however, those who do practice judicial astrology are known to be very accurate forecasters, and astute observers of celestial movements relative to the Earth.
It is said that nothing forecasted by a judicial astrologer should ever be taken lightly due to the seriousness and many years of practice to become a judicial astrologer.
The average span of learning and professional astrological practice to reach the experience qualification level of judicial astrologer is said to be over 20 years.

The opinion of the conventional scientific community is that astrology is superstition, with no actual ability; yet, conventional scientists cannot account for the numerous accurate forecasts of astrologers throughout the centuries using astrological principles.
For examples, the world forecasts of judicial astrologers like Nostradamus hundreds of years prior to world events cannot be disputed as false since many of his predictions did come true.
However, skpetics claim that seeing into the future is not possible.

Astrologers rely on data drawn set out in a set of tables called an ephemeris, which shows the changing positions of the heavenly bodies through time.
It is the interpretation of these science based tables that astrologers use to make predictions - including long-term weather forecasts.</entry>
  <entry author_id="680483" end="443" start="390">Detractors say there is no evidence for the claims that astrologers can predict the future and maintain that astrology is a "pseudo-science" at best.
Astrologers claim that the centuries of astrological history proves otherwise.
And the great debate on the validity of astrology continues into the 21st century.
Astrology can be defined as the serious observations and studies of planetary and stellar cycles and their mathematical patterns in time as they affect life on Earth.
Professional astrologers apply mathematical aspects such as the conjunction, sextile, square, trine, and opposition to form complex calculations of activity between celestial objects in constant motion among the constellations relative to the Earth's position using charts called horoscopes to examine planetary transits at any given moment.
Spans of time and space where a person is born is charted through the application of a horoscope to forecast potential future events.
Free will is a given in true astrological practice, but destiny is within the principles of universal laws - and not outside of it.

The earliest knowledge of astrology dates back to antiquity and required constant renewing through presentation because of the growth of the many branches of astrological practice.
This development can be compared to that of the medical sciences, with the many special branches over time.
Some professional astrologers say that one of the handicaps of astrology as practiced in the late 20th century, is that much of the expansion has been done by groups of isolated reseachers that has limited the opportunities for building astrological work into a more solid body of work and consensus.

Many prior astrological works were contained in the almanac form in Europe in the Middle Ages.
These almanacs were popular throughout western Europe, and were also published in the United States in the mid-1700s.
One of the most famous was penned by Benjamin Franklin, who created Poor Richard's Almanac under one of his pen names (Richard Saunders, a destitute astrologer.)
Franklin's almanac was immensely popular and maintained a circulation over 10,000 a year for 25 years.

A great surge of popular interest in astrology also took place between 1900 through 1949 in America.
A very popular astrologer based in New York City named Evangeline Adams help feed the public's thirst for astrology readings with many accurate forecasts, her biographers say.
A famous court case involving Adams, who was arrested and charged with illegal fortune-telling in 1914 - was later dismissed when Adams correctly read the horoscope of the judge's son with only a birthdate.
Her acquital set an American precedent that if astrologer's practiced in a professional manner that they were not guilty of any wrong-doing.

The serious and complex writings on astrological practice and concepts in America progressed from the turn-of-the-century years and into a new period of popular expansion in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s.
Many complex astrological materials were simplified to attempt to carve a clear line through points of contention and controversy.
The result of this attempt was to "simplify astrology" in the minds of professionals and gave the impression of settled and agreed positions on many points that were not resolved.

The period between 1920-1940 gave way to the popular media jumping on board the great public interest in astrology.
Publishers realized that millions of readers were interested in astrological forecasts and the interest grew ever more intense with the advent of America's entry into the First World War.
The war heightened interest in astrology.
Journalists began to write articles based on character descriptions and astrological "forecasts" were published in newspapers based on the one and only factor known to the public: the month and day of birth, as taken from the position of the Sun when a personis born.
The result of this practice led to modern-day publishing of Sun-Sign astrology columns and expanded to some astrological books and magazines in later decades of the 20th century.

Professional astrologers say that the average educated adult or beginner should not be misled by false astrological statements, or over-simplifying by the biased opinions of those who have academic status in other fields of learning while using their positions to direct others to believe that their ideas on astrology are valid.
Such examples exist of somw writers of books on astrology who have admitted that that they did not know how to cast an astrological horoscope or to interpret one.
Astrologers state that writers and detractors who possess no practical knowledge of the workings of astrological principles, its history, and techniques are not qualified to state that astrology is a pseudo-science.

Seeking to protect serious astrology from the perceived attacks of conventional scientists - astrologers in the latter half of the 20th century have fought to protect themselves against Sun-Sign "pseudo-astrologers" in much the same way the medical profession has sought to protect itself from "quacks."
With the advent of computer technology, astrological work has had great benefit with the speed and accuracy of complex calucations.
But the downside has been that those who buy such astrological software believe that with the ability to print out a horoscope that they qualify as professional astrologers and can give "readings" to clients.

As with any profession, only true scholarship, study and practical application can successfully attain the proper professional status to become a true astrologer.
It takes years to learn the most basic principles and apply them practically.
And decades to master many astrological techniques and branches.
Many professional astrologers are self-taught, or have taken correspondence courses with professional tutors in the global astrological community.
Many new schools of astrology led by responsible leadership have opened their doors in the latter half of the 20th century, and teaching schools now offer diplomas after rigorous examination courses are passed by students.
As in medicine, passing an examination cannot always mean that the candidate is an expert in the subject.
However, it can show that a successful student has assimilated what they have studied and is fit to produce practical and accurate astrological work for clients that will give them the experience where, in time, they may eventually become expert.
The oldest known form of astrology, classical, or judicial astrology, practiced by ancient astrologers who made calculations of their direct view of the constellational night skies.
Judicial astrology as many branches (see below) such as Mundane astrology a branch that uses mathematical calculations of the celestial bodies to forecast future world events.

The origin of astrology included astronomy; as both were combined as one applied science before the emergence of conventional scientific practice in the 18th Century.
Judicial astrologers were considered masters of the celestial sciences and were much sought-after mathematicians and forecasters by royalty and the wealthy.
One of the first uses of astrology was accurately predicting the weather using meteorological astrology - a another branch of judicial astrology which Ptolemy first mastered.

Texts show that judicial astrologers practiced as teachers, medicial doctors and strategists and were known for their strict astrological principles and ability to forecast the future.
Today, judicial astrologers are rare due to the false popularization of sun-sign astrology; however, those who do practice judicial astrology are known to be very accurate forecasters, and astute observers of celestial movements relative to the Earth.
It is said that nothing forecasted by a judicial astrologer should ever be taken lightly due to the seriousness and many years of practice to become a judicial astrologer.
The average span of learning and professional astrological practice to reach the experience qualification level of judicial astrologer is said to be over 20 years.

The opinion of the conventional scientific community is that astrology is superstition, with no actual ability; yet, conventional scientists cannot account for the numerous accurate forecasts of astrologers throughout the centuries using astrological principles.
For examples, the world forecasts of judicial astrologers like Nostradamus hundreds of years prior to world events cannot be disputed as false since many of his predictions did come true.
However, skpetics claim that seeing into the future is not possible.

Astrologers rely on data drawn set out in a set of tables called an ephemeris, which shows the changing positions of the heavenly bodies through time.
It is the interpretation of these science based tables that astrologers use to make predictions - including long-term weather forecasts.</entry>
  <entry author_id="680483" end="496" start="443">Detractors say there is no evidence for the claims that astrologers can predict the future and maintain that astrology is a "pseudo-science" at best.
Astrologers claim that the centuries of astrological history proves otherwise.
And the great debate on the validity of astrology continues into the 21st century.
Astrology can be defined as the serious observations and studies of planetary and stellar cycles and their mathematical patterns in time as they affect life on Earth.
Professional astrologers apply mathematical aspects such as the conjunction, sextile, square, trine, and opposition to form complex calculations of activity between celestial objects in constant motion among the constellations relative to the Earth's position using charts called horoscopes to examine planetary transits at any given moment.
Spans of time and space where a person is born is charted through the application of a horoscope to forecast potential future events.
Free will is a given in true astrological practice, but destiny is within the principles of universal laws - and not outside of it.

The earliest knowledge of astrology dates back to antiquity and required constant renewing through presentation because of the growth of the many branches of astrological practice.
This development can be compared to that of the medical sciences, with the many special branches over time.
Some professional astrologers say that one of the handicaps of astrology as practiced in the late 20th century, is that much of the expansion has been done by groups of isolated reseachers that has limited the opportunities for building astrological work into a more solid body of work and consensus.

Many prior astrological works were contained in the almanac form in Europe in the Middle Ages.
These almanacs were popular throughout western Europe, and were also published in the United States in the mid-1700s.
One of the most famous was penned by Benjamin Franklin, who created Poor Richard's Almanac under one of his pen names (Richard Saunders, a destitute astrologer.)
Franklin's almanac was immensely popular and maintained a circulation over 10,000 a year for 25 years.

A great surge of popular interest in astrology also took place between 1900 through 1949 in America.
A very popular astrologer based in New York City named Evangeline Adams help feed the public's thirst for astrology readings with many accurate forecasts, her biographers say.
A famous court case involving Adams, who was arrested and charged with illegal fortune-telling in 1914 - was later dismissed when Adams correctly read the horoscope of the judge's son with only a birthdate.
Her acquital set an American precedent that if astrologer's practiced in a professional manner that they were not guilty of any wrong-doing.

The serious and complex writings on astrological practice and concepts in America progressed from the turn-of-the-century years and into a new period of popular expansion in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s.
Many complex astrological materials were simplified to attempt to carve a clear line through points of contention and controversy.
The result of this attempt was to "simplify astrology" in the minds of professionals and gave the impression of settled and agreed positions on many points that were not resolved.

The period between 1920-1940 gave way to the popular media jumping on board the great public interest in astrology.
Publishers realized that millions of readers were interested in astrological forecasts and the interest grew ever more intense with the advent of America's entry into the First World War.
The war heightened interest in astrology.
Journalists began to write articles based on character descriptions and astrological "forecasts" were published in newspapers based on the one and only factor known to the public: the month and day of birth, as taken from the position of the Sun when a personis born.
The result of this practice led to modern-day publishing of Sun-Sign astrology columns and expanded to some astrological books and magazines in later decades of the 20th century.

Professional astrologers say that the average educated adult or beginner should not be misled by false astrological statements, or over-simplifying by the biased opinions of those who have academic status in other fields of learning while using their positions to direct others to believe that their ideas on astrology are valid.
Such examples exist of somw writers of books on astrology who have admitted that that they did not know how to cast an astrological horoscope or to interpret one.
Astrologers state that writers and detractors who possess no practical knowledge of the workings of astrological principles, its history, and techniques are not qualified to state that astrology is a pseudo-science.

Seeking to protect serious astrology from the perceived attacks of conventional scientists - astrologers in the latter half of the 20th century have fought to protect themselves against Sun-Sign "pseudo-astrologers" in much the same way the medical profession has sought to protect itself from "quacks."
With the advent of computer technology, astrological work has had great benefit with the speed and accuracy of complex calucations.
But the downside has been that those who buy such astrological software believe that with the ability to print out a horoscope that they qualify as professional astrologers and can give "readings" to clients.

As with any profession, only true scholarship, study and practical application can successfully attain the proper professional status to become a true astrologer.
It takes years to learn the most basic principles and apply them practically.
And decades to master many astrological techniques and branches.
Many professional astrologers are self-taught, or have taken correspondence courses with professional tutors in the global astrological community.
Many new schools of astrology led by responsible leadership have opened their doors in the latter half of the 20th century, and teaching schools now offer diplomas after rigorous examination courses are passed by students.
As in medicine, passing an examination cannot always mean that the candidate is an expert in the subject.
However, it can show that a successful student has assimilated what they have studied and is fit to produce practical and accurate astrological work for clients that will give them the experience where, in time, they may eventually become expert.
The oldest known form of astrology, classical, or judicial astrology, practiced by ancient astrologers who made calculations of their direct view of the constellational night skies.
Judicial astrology as many branches (see below) such as Mundane astrology a branch that uses mathematical calculations of the celestial bodies to forecast future world events.

The origin of astrology included astronomy; as both were combined as one applied science before the emergence of conventional scientific practice in the 18th Century.
Judicial astrologers were considered masters of the celestial sciences and were much sought-after mathematicians and forecasters by royalty and the wealthy.
One of the first uses of astrology was accurately predicting the weather using meteorological astrology - a another branch of judicial astrology which Ptolemy first mastered.

Texts show that judicial astrologers practiced as teachers, medicial doctors and strategists and were known for their strict astrological principles and ability to forecast the future.
Today, judicial astrologers are rare due to the false popularization of sun-sign astrology; however, those who do practice judicial astrology are known to be very accurate forecasters, and astute observers of celestial movements relative to the Earth.
It is said that nothing forecasted by a judicial astrologer should ever be taken lightly due to the seriousness and many years of practice to become a judicial astrologer.
The average span of learning and professional astrological practice to reach the experience qualification level of judicial astrologer is said to be over 20 years.

The opinion of the conventional scientific community is that astrology is superstition, with no actual ability; yet, conventional scientists cannot account for the numerous accurate forecasts of astrologers throughout the centuries using astrological principles.
For examples, the world forecasts of judicial astrologers like Nostradamus hundreds of years prior to world events cannot be disputed as false since many of his predictions did come true.
However, skpetics claim that seeing into the future is not possible.

Astrologers rely on data drawn set out in a set of tables called an ephemeris, which shows the changing positions of the heavenly bodies through time.
It is the interpretation of these science based tables that astrologers use to make predictions - including long-term weather forecasts.</entry>
  <entry author_id="680483" end="549" start="496">Detractors say there is no evidence for the claims that astrologers can predict the future and maintain that astrology is a "pseudo-science" at best.
Astrologers claim that the centuries of astrological history proves otherwise.
And the great debate on the validity of astrology continues into the 21st century.
Astrology can be defined as the serious observations and studies of planetary and stellar cycles and their mathematical patterns in time as they affect life on Earth.
Professional astrologers apply mathematical aspects such as the conjunction, sextile, square, trine, and opposition to form complex calculations of activity between celestial objects in constant motion among the constellations relative to the Earth's position using charts called horoscopes to examine planetary transits at any given moment.
Spans of time and space where a person is born is charted through the application of a horoscope to forecast potential future events.
Free will is a given in true astrological practice, but destiny is within the principles of universal laws - and not outside of it.

The earliest knowledge of astrology dates back to antiquity and required constant renewing through presentation because of the growth of the many branches of astrological practice.
This development can be compared to that of the medical sciences, with the many special branches over time.
Some professional astrologers say that one of the handicaps of astrology as practiced in the late 20th century, is that much of the expansion has been done by groups of isolated reseachers that has limited the opportunities for building astrological work into a more solid body of work and consensus.

Many prior astrological works were contained in the almanac form in Europe in the Middle Ages.
These almanacs were popular throughout western Europe, and were also published in the United States in the mid-1700s.
One of the most famous was penned by Benjamin Franklin, who created Poor Richard's Almanac under one of his pen names (Richard Saunders, a destitute astrologer.)
Franklin's almanac was immensely popular and maintained a circulation over 10,000 a year for 25 years.

A great surge of popular interest in astrology also took place between 1900 through 1949 in America.
A very popular astrologer based in New York City named Evangeline Adams help feed the public's thirst for astrology readings with many accurate forecasts, her biographers say.
A famous court case involving Adams, who was arrested and charged with illegal fortune-telling in 1914 - was later dismissed when Adams correctly read the horoscope of the judge's son with only a birthdate.
Her acquital set an American precedent that if astrologer's practiced in a professional manner that they were not guilty of any wrong-doing.

The serious and complex writings on astrological practice and concepts in America progressed from the turn-of-the-century years and into a new period of popular expansion in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s.
Many complex astrological materials were simplified to attempt to carve a clear line through points of contention and controversy.
The result of this attempt was to "simplify astrology" in the minds of professionals and gave the impression of settled and agreed positions on many points that were not resolved.

The period between 1920-1940 gave way to the popular media jumping on board the great public interest in astrology.
Publishers realized that millions of readers were interested in astrological forecasts and the interest grew ever more intense with the advent of America's entry into the First World War.
The war heightened interest in astrology.
Journalists began to write articles based on character descriptions and astrological "forecasts" were published in newspapers based on the one and only factor known to the public: the month and day of birth, as taken from the position of the Sun when a personis born.
The result of this practice led to modern-day publishing of Sun-Sign astrology columns and expanded to some astrological books and magazines in later decades of the 20th century.

Professional astrologers say that the average educated adult or beginner should not be misled by false astrological statements, or over-simplifying by the biased opinions of those who have academic status in other fields of learning while using their positions to direct others to believe that their ideas on astrology are valid.
Such examples exist of somw writers of books on astrology who have admitted that that they did not know how to cast an astrological horoscope or to interpret one.
Astrologers state that writers and detractors who possess no practical knowledge of the workings of astrological principles, its history, and techniques are not qualified to state that astrology is a pseudo-science.

Seeking to protect serious astrology from the perceived attacks of conventional scientists - astrologers in the latter half of the 20th century have fought to protect themselves against Sun-Sign "pseudo-astrologers" in much the same way the medical profession has sought to protect itself from "quacks."
With the advent of computer technology, astrological work has had great benefit with the speed and accuracy of complex calucations.
But the downside has been that those who buy such astrological software believe that with the ability to print out a horoscope that they qualify as professional astrologers and can give "readings" to clients.

As with any profession, only true scholarship, study and practical application can successfully attain the proper professional status to become a true astrologer.
It takes years to learn the most basic principles and apply them practically.
And decades to master many astrological techniques and branches.
Many professional astrologers are self-taught, or have taken correspondence courses with professional tutors in the global astrological community.
Many new schools of astrology led by responsible leadership have opened their doors in the latter half of the 20th century, and teaching schools now offer diplomas after rigorous examination courses are passed by students.
As in medicine, passing an examination cannot always mean that the candidate is an expert in the subject.
However, it can show that a successful student has assimilated what they have studied and is fit to produce practical and accurate astrological work for clients that will give them the experience where, in time, they may eventually become expert.
The oldest known form of astrology, classical, or judicial astrology, practiced by ancient astrologers who made calculations of their direct view of the constellational night skies.
Judicial astrology as many branches (see below) such as Mundane astrology a branch that uses mathematical calculations of the celestial bodies to forecast future world events.

The origin of astrology included astronomy; as both were combined as one applied science before the emergence of conventional scientific practice in the 18th Century.
Judicial astrologers were considered masters of the celestial sciences and were much sought-after mathematicians and forecasters by royalty and the wealthy.
One of the first uses of astrology was accurately predicting the weather using meteorological astrology - a another branch of judicial astrology which Ptolemy first mastered.

Texts show that judicial astrologers practiced as teachers, medicial doctors and strategists and were known for their strict astrological principles and ability to forecast the future.
Today, judicial astrologers are rare due to the false popularization of sun-sign astrology; however, those who do practice judicial astrology are known to be very accurate forecasters, and astute observers of celestial movements relative to the Earth.
It is said that nothing forecasted by a judicial astrologer should ever be taken lightly due to the seriousness and many years of practice to become a judicial astrologer.
The average span of learning and professional astrological practice to reach the experience qualification level of judicial astrologer is said to be over 20 years.

The opinion of the conventional scientific community is that astrology is superstition, with no actual ability; yet, conventional scientists cannot account for the numerous accurate forecasts of astrologers throughout the centuries using astrological principles.
For examples, the world forecasts of judicial astrologers like Nostradamus hundreds of years prior to world events cannot be disputed as false since many of his predictions did come true.
However, skpetics claim that seeing into the future is not possible.

Astrologers rely on data drawn set out in a set of tables called an ephemeris, which shows the changing positions of the heavenly bodies through time.
It is the interpretation of these science based tables that astrologers use to make predictions - including long-term weather forecasts.</entry>
  <entry author_id="680483" end="602" start="549">Detractors say there is no evidence for the claims that astrologers can predict the future and maintain that astrology is a "pseudo-science" at best.
Astrologers claim that the centuries of astrological history proves otherwise.
And the great debate on the validity of astrology continues into the 21st century.
Astrology can be defined as the serious observations and studies of planetary and stellar cycles and their mathematical patterns in time as they affect life on Earth.
Professional astrologers apply mathematical aspects such as the conjunction, sextile, square, trine, and opposition to form complex calculations of activity between celestial objects in constant motion among the constellations relative to the Earth's position using charts called horoscopes to examine planetary transits at any given moment.
Spans of time and space where a person is born is charted through the application of a horoscope to forecast potential future events.
Free will is a given in true astrological practice, but destiny is within the principles of universal laws - and not outside of it.

The earliest knowledge of astrology dates back to antiquity and required constant renewing through presentation because of the growth of the many branches of astrological practice.
This development can be compared to that of the medical sciences, with the many special branches over time.
Some professional astrologers say that one of the handicaps of astrology as practiced in the late 20th century, is that much of the expansion has been done by groups of isolated reseachers that has limited the opportunities for building astrological work into a more solid body of work and consensus.

Many prior astrological works were contained in the almanac form in Europe in the Middle Ages.
These almanacs were popular throughout western Europe, and were also published in the United States in the mid-1700s.
One of the most famous was penned by Benjamin Franklin, who created Poor Richard's Almanac under one of his pen names (Richard Saunders, a destitute astrologer.)
Franklin's almanac was immensely popular and maintained a circulation over 10,000 a year for 25 years.

A great surge of popular interest in astrology also took place between 1900 through 1949 in America.
A very popular astrologer based in New York City named Evangeline Adams help feed the public's thirst for astrology readings with many accurate forecasts, her biographers say.
A famous court case involving Adams, who was arrested and charged with illegal fortune-telling in 1914 - was later dismissed when Adams correctly read the horoscope of the judge's son with only a birthdate.
Her acquital set an American precedent that if astrologer's practiced in a professional manner that they were not guilty of any wrong-doing.

The serious and complex writings on astrological practice and concepts in America progressed from the turn-of-the-century years and into a new period of popular expansion in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s.
Many complex astrological materials were simplified to attempt to carve a clear line through points of contention and controversy.
The result of this attempt was to "simplify astrology" in the minds of professionals and gave the impression of settled and agreed positions on many points that were not resolved.

The period between 1920-1940 gave way to the popular media jumping on board the great public interest in astrology.
Publishers realized that millions of readers were interested in astrological forecasts and the interest grew ever more intense with the advent of America's entry into the First World War.
The war heightened interest in astrology.
Journalists began to write articles based on character descriptions and astrological "forecasts" were published in newspapers based on the one and only factor known to the public: the month and day of birth, as taken from the position of the Sun when a personis born.
The result of this practice led to modern-day publishing of Sun-Sign astrology columns and expanded to some astrological books and magazines in later decades of the 20th century.

Professional astrologers say that the average educated adult or beginner should not be misled by false astrological statements, or over-simplifying by the biased opinions of those who have academic status in other fields of learning while using their positions to direct others to believe that their ideas on astrology are valid.
Such examples exist of somw writers of books on astrology who have admitted that that they did not know how to cast an astrological horoscope or to interpret one.
Astrologers state that writers and detractors who possess no practical knowledge of the workings of astrological principles, its history, and techniques are not qualified to state that astrology is a pseudo-science.

Seeking to protect serious astrology from the perceived attacks of conventional scientists - astrologers in the latter half of the 20th century have fought to protect themselves against Sun-Sign "pseudo-astrologers" in much the same way the medical profession has sought to protect itself from "quacks."
With the advent of computer technology, astrological work has had great benefit with the speed and accuracy of complex calucations.
But the downside has been that those who buy such astrological software believe that with the ability to print out a horoscope that they qualify as professional astrologers and can give "readings" to clients.

As with any profession, only true scholarship, study and practical application can successfully attain the proper professional status to become a true astrologer.
It takes years to learn the most basic principles and apply them practically.
And decades to master many astrological techniques and branches.
Many professional astrologers are self-taught, or have taken correspondence courses with professional tutors in the global astrological community.
Many new schools of astrology led by responsible leadership have opened their doors in the latter half of the 20th century, and teaching schools now offer diplomas after rigorous examination courses are passed by students.
As in medicine, passing an examination cannot always mean that the candidate is an expert in the subject.
However, it can show that a successful student has assimilated what they have studied and is fit to produce practical and accurate astrological work for clients that will give them the experience where, in time, they may eventually become expert.
The oldest known form of astrology, classical, or judicial astrology, practiced by ancient astrologers who made calculations of their direct view of the constellational night skies.
Judicial astrology as many branches (see below) such as Mundane astrology a branch that uses mathematical calculations of the celestial bodies to forecast future world events.

The origin of astrology included astronomy; as both were combined as one applied science before the emergence of conventional scientific practice in the 18th Century.
Judicial astrologers were considered masters of the celestial sciences and were much sought-after mathematicians and forecasters by royalty and the wealthy.
One of the first uses of astrology was accurately predicting the weather using meteorological astrology - a another branch of judicial astrology which Ptolemy first mastered.

Texts show that judicial astrologers practiced as teachers, medicial doctors and strategists and were known for their strict astrological principles and ability to forecast the future.
Today, judicial astrologers are rare due to the false popularization of sun-sign astrology; however, those who do practice judicial astrology are known to be very accurate forecasters, and astute observers of celestial movements relative to the Earth.
It is said that nothing forecasted by a judicial astrologer should ever be taken lightly due to the seriousness and many years of practice to become a judicial astrologer.
The average span of learning and professional astrological practice to reach the experience qualification level of judicial astrologer is said to be over 20 years.
The calculations performed in applied Astrology involve complex arithmetic that include Algebra, Geometry and Trigonometry - mathematical techniques invented by astrologers.
They calculate the positions of the planets and stars relative to the Earth and serve to locate the apparent location of heavenly bodies on desired dates and times based on tables of planets - also known as an scientific ephemeris.

The opinion of the conventional scientific community is that astrology is superstition, with no actual ability; yet, conventional scientists cannot account for the numerous accurate forecasts of astrologers throughout the centuries using astrological principles.
For examples, the world forecasts of judicial astrologers like Nostradamus hundreds of years prior to world events cannot be disputed as false since many of his predictions did come true.
However, skpetics claim that seeing into the future is not possible while astrologers maintain that predicting future events using astrological techniques is more than possible.</entry>
  <entry author_id="194262" end="655" start="602">According to Geoffrey Cornelius, astrology (and divinatory practices in general) do not so much predict as put the questioner in a position where he or she may discover the means to make something significant come about (See katarche.)
This view has been increasingly adopted by influential astrologers (see for instance, Robert Hand.)
There are other astrologers (for example, Robert Zoller) who feel that our lives are, in the main, predestined.

The core principles of astrology reflect a general principle, which was accepted in some parts of the ancient world, that events in the heavens should have analogies on Earth.
In some places, such as ancient India, China and Babylon, the apparently untoward movement of a comet across the otherwise orderly movement of the heavens was taken as a portent of disaster.
Such ancient beliefs are epitomized in the Hermetic maxim: As Above, So Below.
The famous astronomer/astrologer Tycho Brahe also used a similar phrase to justify his studies in astrology: Suspiciendo despicio — "By looking up I see downward."

Astrology can be defined as the serious observations and studies of planetary and stellar cycles and their mathematical patterns in time as they affect life on Earth.
Professional astrologers apply simple geometric constructs (known in astrology as "aspects") such as the conjunction, sextile, square, trine, and opposition to form calculations of activity between celestial objects in constant motion among the constellations relative to the Earth's position using charts called horoscopes to examine planetary transits at any given moment.
Spans of time and space where a person is born is charted through the application of a horoscope to forecast potential future events.
Free will is a given in true astrological practice, but destiny is within the principles of universal laws - and not outside of it.

The earliest knowledge of astrology dates back to antiquity and required constant renewing through presentation because of the growth of the many branches of astrological practice.
The structure of this development can be compared to the structure of the medical sciences, with the many special branches over time.
Some professional astrologers say that one of the handicaps of astrology as practiced in the late 20th century, is that much of the expansion has been done by groups of isolated reseachers that has limited the opportunities for building astrological work into a more solid body of work and consensus.

Many prior astrological works were contained in the almanac form in Europe in the Middle Ages.
These almanacs were popular throughout western Europe, and were also published in the United States in the mid-1700s.
One of the most famous was penned by Benjamin Franklin, who created Poor Richard's Almanac under one of his pen names (Richard Saunders, a destitute astrologer.)
Franklin's almanac was immensely popular and maintained a circulation over 10,000 a year for 25 years.

A great surge of popular interest in astrology also took place between 1900 through 1949 in America.
A very popular astrologer based in New York City named Evangeline Adams help feed the public's thirst for astrology readings with many accurate forecasts, her biographers say.
A famous court case involving Adams, who was arrested and charged with illegal fortune-telling in 1914 - was later dismissed when Adams correctly read the horoscope of the judge's son with only a birthdate.
Her acquital set an American precedent that if astrologer's practiced in a professional manner that they were not guilty of any wrong-doing.

The serious and complex writings on astrological practice and concepts in America progressed from the turn-of-the-century years and into a new period of popular expansion in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s.
Many complex astrological materials were simplified to attempt to carve a clear line through points of contention and controversy.
The result of this attempt was to "simplify astrology" in the minds of professionals and gave the impression of settled and agreed positions on many points that were not resolved.

The period between 1920-1940 gave way to the popular media jumping on board the great public interest in astrology.
Publishers realized that millions of readers were interested in astrological forecasts and the interest grew ever more intense with the advent of America's entry into the First World War.
The war heightened interest in astrology.
Journalists began to write articles based on character descriptions and astrological "forecasts" were published in newspapers based on the one and only factor known to the public: the month and day of birth, as taken from the position of the Sun when a person is born.
The result of this practice led to modern-day publishing of Sun-Sign astrology columns and expanded to some astrological books and magazines in later decades of the 20th century.

Professional astrologers say that the average educated adult or beginner should not be misled by false astrological statements, or over-simplifying by the biased opinions of those who have academic status in other fields of learning while using their positions to direct others to believe that their ideas on astrology are valid.
Such examples exist of somw writers of books on astrology who have admitted that that they did not know how to cast an astrological horoscope or to interpret one.
Astrologers state that writers and detractors who possess no practical knowledge of the workings of astrological principles, its history, and techniques are not qualified to state that astrology is a pseudo-science.

Seeking to protect serious astrology from the perceived attacks of conventional scientists - astrologers in the latter half of the 20th century have fought to protect themselves against Sun-Sign "pseudo-astrologers" in much the same way the medical profession has sought to protect itself from "quacks."
With the advent of computer technology, astrological work has had great benefit with the speed and accuracy of complex calucations.
But the downside has been that those who buy such astrological software believe that with the ability to print out a horoscope that they qualify as professional astrologers and can give "readings" to clients.

It takes about six months to learn the basics of astrology, but much longer to develop a deeper, more professional skill.
Many professional astrologers are self-taught, or have taken correspondence courses with professional tutors in the global astrological community.
Many new schools of astrology led by responsible leadership have opened their doors in the latter half of the 20th century, and teaching schools now offer diplomas after rigorous examination courses are passed by students.
The oldest known form of astrology, classical, or judicial astrology, practiced by ancient astrologers who made calculations of their direct view of the constellational night skies.
Judicial astrology as many branches (see below) such as Mundane astrology a branch that uses mathematical calculations of the celestial bodies to forecast future world events.

The origin of astrology included astronomy; as both were combined as one applied science before the emergence of conventional scientific practice in the 18th Century.
Judicial astrologers were considered masters of the celestial sciences and were much sought-after mathematicians and forecasters by royalty and the wealthy.
One of the first uses of astrology was accurately predicting the weather using meteorological astrology - a another branch of judicial astrology which Ptolemy first mastered.

Texts show that judicial astrologers practiced as teachers, medicial doctors and strategists and were known for their strict astrological principles and ability to forecast the future.
Today, judicial astrologers are rare due to the false popularization of sun-sign astrology; however, those who do practice judicial astrology are known to be very accurate forecasters, and astute observers of celestial movements relative to the Earth.
It is said that nothing forecasted by a judicial astrologer should ever be taken lightly due to the seriousness and many years of practice to become a judicial astrologer.
The average span of learning and professional astrological practice to reach the experience qualification level of judicial astrologer is said to be over 20 years.
The calculations performed in applied Astrology involve complex arithmetic that include Algebra, Geometry and Trigonometry - mathematical techniques invented by astrologers.
They calculate the positions of the planets and stars relative to the Earth and serve to locate the apparent location of heavenly bodies on desired dates and times based on tables of planets - also known as an scientific ephemeris.

The opinion of the conventional scientific community is that astrology is superstition, with no actual ability; yet, conventional scientists cannot account for the numerous accurate forecasts of astrologers throughout the centuries using astrological principles.
For examples, the world forecasts of judicial astrologers like Nostradamus hundreds of years prior to world events cannot be disputed as false since many of his predictions did come true.
However, skpetics claim that seeing into the future is not possible while astrologers maintain that predicting future events using astrological techniques is more than possible.</entry>
  <entry author_id="733550" end="680" start="655">Seven days of the week are created on the basis of 24 (Hora) divisions of the day and heliocentric order of the planets.
In Hindu system of astrology, a weekday starts from local Sunrise &amp; ends at the following Sunrise, which is distinct from the Georgian calendar in which a weekday along with date starts at expiry of 1200 a.m. of the Zonal Standard Time.
Julian day begins at noon, whereas the Julian calendar begins at preceding midnight.
Georgian calendar is worldwide used for civil purpose.

A day is divided in 24 divisions called “Hora” in Hindu system.
The order of Hora is based on heliocentric order of the planets which is; Saturn, Jupiter, Mars, Sun, (Earth), Venus, Mercury, &amp; Moon.
It is said that the world started on Sunday.
And the first Hora of the Sunday is ruled by the Sun.
Second Hora of Sunday is ruled by Venus, followed by Mercury, Moon, Saturn, Jupiter &amp; Mars.
Thus Sunday has three cycles of the above Horas &amp; its 25th Hora is of Moon.
Thus at the next Sunrise time Hora of Moon shall prevail.
Therefore, the following day is ruled by the Moon.
Similarly 25th Hora of Monday shall be of Mars, &amp; the day shall be ruled by Mars.
In the same way following days shall be ruled by Mercury, Jupiter, Venus &amp; Saturn.
Thus order of the weekdays are ruled by Sun, Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus &amp; Saturn.
This logic has already been mentioned in Hindu astrology treatises.

In Hindu system the Sun is called Ravi; The Moon – Soma; Mars – Mangal; Mercury- Budh; Jupiter – Brishapati; Venus – Shukar; &amp; Saturn – Shani.
The day is called “Vaar”.
Thus weekdays in order have been named as Ravi Vaar, Soma Vaar, Mangal Vaar, Budh Vaar, Brihaspati Vaar, Shukar Vaar, and Shani Vaar.

In electional astrology, weekday &amp; Hora of the specific planet has special significance.
Hora is also used in calculation of planetary strength in a nativity.
In general, a work which fructifies in a particular weekday, also can be performed during Hora of the weekday lord falling in another weekday.
For example, it is recommended to solemnize marriage on Thursday, also can be done during Hora of Jupiter falling in Friday (a weekday ruled by a benefic planet).
This usage of Hora in electional astrology is also applied by western astrologers.
More information about planetary linguistics can be found on this site.</entry>
  <entry author_id="619904" end="698" start="680">1.
Of Vishnu now I declare the mighty works, who has measured out the earthly worlds and that higher seat of our self-accomplishing he supports, he the wide-moving, in the threefold steps of his universal movement.
2.
That Vishnu affirms on high by his mightiness and he is like a terrible Lion LEO that ranges in the difficult places, yea, his lair is on the mountain-tops, he in whose three wide movements all the worlds find their dwelling-place.
3.
Let our strength and our thought go forward to Vishnu the all-pervading, the wide-moving Bull TAURUS whose dwelling- place is on the mountain, he who being One has measured all this long and far-extending seat of our self-accomplishing by only three of his strides.
4.
He whose three steps are full of the honey- wine and they perish not but have ecstasy by the self-harmony of their nature; yea, he being One holds the triple principle and earth and heaven also, even all the worlds.
5.
May I attain to and enjoy that goal of his movement, the Delight, where souls that seek the godhead have the rapture; for there in that highest step of the wide-moving Vishnu is that Friend of men Aquarius who is the fount of the sweetness.
6.
Those are the dwellings-places of ye twain which we desire as the goal of our journey, where the many-horned herds of Light go traveling; the highest step of wide-moving Vishnu shines down on us here in its manifold vastness.
(RigVeda 1.154)

This appearance of the Zodiac in the Rig Veda was first noted by controversial cosmologist Patrizia Norelli-Bachelet, who writes that these "Steps of Vishnu" start from Scorpio and proceed in the direction of the Precession of the Equinoxes (i.e. backwards through the zodiac).
The same author writes that the Vedic gunas of Rajas, Sattva, and Tamas (corresponding to the Gods Brahma - the creative principle of the universe, Vishnu - the Preserver, and Shiva - the Destroyer) are identical to western astrologies energy flows of Creation, Preservation and Destruction.
The ramification of these assertions are inconcievable to many Western and Modern Vedic Astrologers.
For one, it suggests that Western Astrology came from Vedic India, putting into question the common story of the origin of astrology, mentioned above in the "History of Astrology" section.
Norelli-Bachelet also claims that the authors of the Rig Veda did not discount the Tropical Zodiac as an important basis of Astrological knowledge.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1136066" end="726" start="698">There are only a handful of journals dealing with scientific research into astrology (i.e. astrological journals directed towards scientific research or scientific journals publishing astrological research).
As Mike Harding noted, "it is unlikely that any pro-astrology research, however impeccably presented would ever have been published in Nature, whose editor, John Maddox, had this to say on the subject: 'It is a plain fact that astrology is a pack of lies in the literal sense.'"
Few practitioners today feel the need to pursue scientific testing of astrology in order to prove its objective validity since they feel that working with clients on a daily basis provides personal validation.

Some supporters of astrology also argue that the prevailing attitudes and motives of many opponents of astrology introduce conscious or unconscious bias in the formulation of hypotheses to be tested, the conduct of the tests, and the reporting of results.
Tests of astrology by its critics has sometimes taken the form of debunking campaigns or contests with offers of prize money.
Additionally, some researchers from within the scientific community itself have been critical of the way that the organization CSICOP has conducted certain research experiments involved in replicating astrological claims.
Philip Julian Klass, a member of CSICOP has replied to these criticisms.
Critics object to the lack of an accepted astrological mechanism that would account for the supposed effects of celestial bodies on terrestrial affairs.
Similar objections have been made against a number of new theories at the time (e.g. Alfred Wegener's 'continental drift' idea leading to plate tectonics), but later research confirmed these hypotheses.
While few modern astrologers believe that the planets literally cause things to happen on Earth through a direct causal relationship between heavenly bodies and earthly events, physical mechanisms are still among the proposed theories of astrology.
Some have posited acausal purely correlative relationships between astrological observations and events, such as the theory of synchronicity proposed by Jung.
Victor Mansfield, an astrophysicist, while acknowledging that within currently accepted science, there is little support for a physical mechanism for astrological influence, also suggested that astrology draw inspiration from quantum physics, which is radically acausal but is highly accurate and vastly applicable.
Others have posited a basis in divination.
Still others have argued that empirical correlations can stand on their own epistemologically and do not need the support of any theory or mechanism.
Some of these concepts raise serious questions about the feasibility of validating astrology through scientific testing, and some have gone so far as to reject the applicability of the scientific method to astrology almost entirely.
However, a number of researchers and astrologers have called for or advocated continuing studies of astrology based on statistical validation.

Several individuals, most notably French psychologist and statistician Michel Gauquelin, claimed to have found correlations between some planetary positions and certain human traits such as vocations.
Gauquelin's most widely known but controversial claim is known as the Mars effect, which is said to demonstrate a correlation between the planet Mars occupying certain positions in the sky more often at the birth of eminent sports champions than at the birth of ordinary people.
Since its original publication in 1955, the Mars effect has been the subject of numerous studies claiming either to replicate or refute it.
In 1988, 1997 and 2000, German Professor of psychology Suitbert Ertel published the latest claims for a Mars effect, suggesting that it increased in proportion to the eminence of the athletes.

Besides the Mars-athletes claims, astrological researchers claim to have found statistical correlations for physical and behavioural attributes, special events, social trends such as economics and large geophysical patterns.. One of these claims was published in a mainstream scientific journal.
Critics contend meanwhile that, where tested against personality tests, astrologers have shown a consistent lack of agreement with these tests.
One such double-blind study, which was published in the scientific journal Nature, claimed to refute astrologers assertions that they can solve clients' personal problems by reading natal charts.
The study concluded that astrologers had no special ability to interpret personality from astrological readings.
Another study contended that astrologers tested, failed to predict objective facts about people or agree with each others interpretations.
Astrologers claim that disproof is made more difficult because astrology makes no claim of correlation to the personality tests used and individuals' self-reported views of themselves in questionnaires (as reported in some personality tests not used in the above examples) may be flawed.
When testing for cognitive, behavioral, physical and other variables, one study of astrological "time twins" found no support for the hypothesis that two people born at nearly the same time and place would necessarily have similar outcomes in behavior.
Skeptics of astrology also suggest that the perceived accuracy of astrological interpretations and descriptions of one's personality can be accounted for by the fact that we tend to exaggerate positive 'hits' and overlook whatever does not really fit, especially when vague language is used (see Forer effect).</entry>
</article>
