<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="2154" title="African American" authors="10" lines="680">
  <entry author_id="72454" end="14" start="0">In the South, during the brief period of black progress after the Civil War called Reconstruction, some strides were made toward equal rights for African-Americans.
Black legislators were elected to the U.S. Congress and held local public office, established schools and built towns and businesses.
However, in the face of southern violence and intimidation directed at blacks as well as whites sympathetic to their cause, the U.S. government refused to step in to guarantee constitutional protections to freedmen and women.
The pattern of de facto and de jure racial segregation, discrimination and oppression against blacks and a system of white power and privilege continued to pervade virtually all facets of American life.
The groundbreaking gains of Reconstruction were reversed, and white mob violence against African-Americans escalated.

After its founding in 1867, the Ku Klux Klan, a clandestine organization sworn to perpetuate white supremacy through violence and intimidation, became a power in the South and beyond, eventually establishing a northern headquarters in Greenfield, Indiana.
Lynchings escalated dramatically in a period that marked the bleakest period in U.S. black-white race relations.
It was reported that nearly 3,600 blacks were lynched from 1889 to 1930, virtually all victims of white, racially motivated violence.
The victims were often tortured, castrated and otherwise mutilated, and burned, their body parts often distributed as souvenirs.
Postcards featuring smiling, white onlookers and black bodies hanging from trees limbs, or heaps of charred human remains for a time became the subject of photographs which were mass produced as popular postcards -- until the U.S. Post Office banned them in the 1930s.
Of the tens of thousands of lynchers and onlookers during this period, it is reported that less than 50 whites were ever indicted for their crimes, and only 4 sentenced.

Other racial violence also marked the period.
The "Red Summer" of 1919 an orgy of white-on-black violence erupted in the form of race riots in 26 cities across the nation, among them Chicago; Washington, D.C.; Charleston, South Carolina; Nashville and Knoxville, Tennessee; Omaha, Nebraska; Longview, Texas; and Elaine, Arkansas.
Over 100 African-Americans were killed, and thousands wounded, their homes, churches, schools and businesses destroyed.</entry>
  <entry author_id="114032" end="32" start="14">African Americans (American Blacks or Black Americans), racial group in the United States whose dominant ancestry is from sub-Saharan West Africa.
Many African Americans also claim European, Native American, or Asian ancestors.
A variety of names have been used for African Americans at various points in history.
African Americans have been referred to as Negroes, colored, blacks, and Afro-Americans, as well as lesser-known terms, such as the 19th-century designation Anglo-African.
The terms Negro and colored are now rarely used.
African American, black, and to a lesser extent Afro-American, are used interchangeably today.

Recent black immigrants from Africa and the islands of the Caribbean are sometimes classified as African Americans.
However, these groups, especially first- and second-generation immigrants, often have cultural practices, histories, and languages that are distinct from those of African Americans born in the United States.
For example, Caribbean natives may speak French, British English, or Spanish as their first language.
Emigrants from Africa may speak a European language other than English or any of a number of African languages as their first language.
Caribbean and African immigrants often have little knowledge or experience of the distinctive history of race relations in the United States.
Thus, Caribbean and African immigrants may or may not choose to identify with the African American community.

According to 2003 U.S. census, some 36.4 million African Americans live in the United States, making up 12.9 percent of the total population.
2000 census shows that 54.8 percent African Americans lived in the South.
In that year, 17.6 percent of African Americans lived in the Northeast and 18.7 percent in the Midwest, while only 8.9 percent lived in the Western states.
Almost 88 percent of African Americans lived in metropolitan areas in 2000.
With over 2 million African American residents, New York City had the largest black urban population in the United States in 2000.
Washington, D.C., had the highest proportion of black residents of any U.S. city in 2000, with African Americans making up almost 60 percent of the population.</entry>
  <entry author_id="114032" end="69" start="32">African American history is intertwined with that of blacks in Latin America and the Caribbean.
Like other blacks in the western hemisphere, the overwhelming majority of African Americans were brought to North America as slaves between the 1700s and the early 1800s.
As slaves, they were considered the property of their owners and had no rights.
African slaves could be found in all 13 of the British colonies, as well as the Spanish colony of Florida and the French colony of Louisiana.

After the American Revolution (1775-1783), changing economic conditions resulted in the decline of slavery in the North.
However, the spread of cotton cultivation encouraged the growth of slavery in the South.
By 1860, 4 million slaves accounted for one-third of the total population of the southern states.
About 500,000 free blacks lived throughout the United States, slightly more than half residing in the southern states.
In the North, many free blacks became abolitionists, activists dedicated to ending slavery and bringing about black equality.

In 1863, during the American Civil War (1861-1865), U.S. president Abraham Lincoln issued the Emancipation Proclamation, freeing slaves in the southern states at war with the North.
The 13th amendment to the Constitution of the United States, ratified in 1865, outlawed slavery in the United States.
In 1868 the 14th amendment granted full U.S. citizenship to African Americans.
The 15th amendment, ratified in 1870, extended the right to vote to black males.

In the South, such rights were enforced only by the presence of Union troops, who occupied the region during the period known as Reconstruction.
When Union troops withdrew from the South in 1877, white Southerners quickly reversed these advances.
Racist groups, such as the Ku Klux Klan, used terrorism to keep blacks from voting, holding office, and enforcing labor contracts.
Whites also began establishing a thorough system of segregation in the United States.
Laws limiting blacks’ access to transportation, schools, restaurants, and other public facilities, sprang up throughout the South.
Although legal systems of segregation were not established in the North or West, informal segregation was enforced in both of these regions.

Blacks responded to these setbacks by forming the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) in 1910.
The NAACP mounted legal challenges to segregation and lobbied legislatures on behalf of black Americans.
African Americans also created an independent community and institutional life.
They established schools, banks, newspapers, and small businesses to serve the needs of their community.

Between 1910 and 1950, in the largest internal migration in U.S. history, over 5 million African Americans moved from southern plantations to northern cities in hopes of finding better jobs and greater equality.
In the 1920s the concentration of blacks in urban areas led to the cultural movement known as the Harlem Renaissance, which used art, music, and literature to demonstrate the creative abilities of African Americans.
A new generation of African American political leaders, such as black nationalist Marcus Garvey and union organizer A. Philip Randolph, also found support among urban African Americans.

In 1954 the U.S. Supreme Court handed down a landmark decision in the case of Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka.
This decision led to the dismantling of legal segregation in all areas of southern life, from schools to restaurants to public restrooms.
Energized by leaders such as Martin Luther King Jr., the civil rights movement in the United States gained new momentum in the mid-1950s.
Civil rights groups organized nonviolent protests, such as marches and sit-ins, to rally the black community.

Many Southern whites attempted to hold onto segregation through continued violence.
By the mid-1960s some African Americans began to question the effectiveness of nonviolent protest.
More militant black leaders, such as Malcolm X of the Nation of Islam and Eldridge Cleaver of the Black Panther Party, called for blacks to defend themselves, using violence if necessary.
From the mid-1960s to the mid-1970s, the Black Power movement urged African Americans to look to Africa for inspiration and emphasized African American solidarity rather than integration.

Responding to pressure from the civil rights movement, the U.S. government sought to open up political and economic opportunities for black Americans.
The 1965 Civil Rights Act banned discrimination in public accommodations, employment, and labor unions.
The 1965 Voting Rights Act, which brought equality to black voters throughout the South, was the capstone to more than a decade of major civil rights legislation.</entry>
  <entry author_id="72454" end="84" start="69">Christianity was used as a tool to subjugate slaves and make them submissive, easier to control.
Whites emphasized passages of the Bible which urged obedience to one's master and piety.
However, slaves seized upon and held dear the story of Moses leading the "children of Israel" out of Egypt to the "Promised Land," and the Old Testament notions of a fierce, warrior God who protected and avenged his "chosen people."
They crafted these and other elements of Christian dogma, Protestant and Catholic, into a kind of syncretic liberation theology that included elements of African religions such as, the Kalunga Line and related river cults, ring shouts, ancestor reverence, call and response, shape-shifting spirits and magic.
Some of these African influences persist today in mainstream African-American religious worship.
The "amen corner"; the resonance of the Jordan River in spirituals and liturgical imagery, including river and full-immersion baptism; praise shouts and gospel music; and altered states of consciousness and speaking in tongues.

Today, the vast majority of African Americans practice some form of Protestantism, with evangelical churches, such as the Church of God in Christ (COGIC); Baptist and Methodist churches accounting for the majority of church membership.
Because of the persistence of segregation, and because of fundamentally more African styles of worship, generally, African Americans historically have established and maintained churches separate from whites.
The comment by Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr, that, "...eleven o'clock Sunday morning is the most segregated hour, and Sunday school is still the most segregated school of the week," remains true today.
The polarization of American society along racial lines is, perhaps, starkest when it comes to religious worship.

Richard Allen was a former slave and an influential deacon and elder at the integrated and affluent St. George's Methodist Church in Philadelphia.
In 1787, Allen founded the all-black Mother Bethel African Methodist Episcopal Church after St. George's white members, increasingly uncomfortable with the large number of blacks the charismatic Allen had attracted to the church, began relegating black worshipers to the church balcony.
Over time, growing numbers of African-American congregations withdrew from the Methodist Episcopal Church.
In 1816, representatives of these congregations convened to establish the African Methodist Episcopal Church, consecrating Allen is their bishop.
The AME Church became the first national black Church in U.S. history.</entry>
  <entry author_id="72454" end="99" start="84">The ruling also brought new momentum to the Civil Rights Movement.
Boycotts against segregated public transportation systems sprang up in the South, the most notable of which was the Montgomery bus boycott.
Civil rights groups organized other boycotts, voter registration campaigns, freedom rides and other nonviolent direct action, such as marches, pickets, boycotts and sit-ins, to mobilize around issues of equal access and voting rights.

Perhaps, the high point of the Civil Rights Movement was the 1963 "March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom," which brought more than 200,000 marchers to the grounds of the Lincoln Memorial and the National Mall in Washington, D.C., to speak out for an end to southern racial violence and police brutality, equal opportunity in employment, equal access in education and public accommodations.
The organizers of the march were the "Big Six" of the Civil Rights Movement: labor organizer and initiator of the march, A. Phillip Randolph; Roy Wilkins of the NAACP; Whitney Young, Jr., of the National Urban League; Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC); James Farmer of the Congress on Racial Equality (CORE); and John Lewis of the Student Non-violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
Also active behind the scenes and sharing the podium with Dr. King was Dorothy Height, head of the National Council of Negro Women.
It was at this event, on the steps of the Lincoln Memorial that King delivered his "I Have a Dream" speech.
This march and the conditions which brought it into being are credited with putting pressure on President John F. Kennedy and then Lyndon B. Johnson]] that culminated in the passage the Civil Rights Act of 1964 that banned discrimination in public accommodations, employment, and labor unions.

The "Mississippi Freedom Summer" of 1964 brought thousands of idealistic youth, black and white, to the state to run "freedom schools," to teach basic literacy, history and civics.
Other volunteers were involved in voter registration drives.
The season was marked by sporadic harassment, intimidation and violence directed at Civil Rights workers and their host families.
The disappearance of three youth, James Chaney, Andrew Goodman and Michael Schwerner in Philadelphia, Mississippi, captured the attention of the nation.
Six weeks later, searchers found the brutally beaten body of Chaney, a black man, in a muddy dam alongside the remains of his two white companions, who had been shot to death.
Outrage at the escalating violence in Mississippi during the "Mississippi Blood Summer" as it had come to be called, and at brutality of these murders brought about the passage of the Voting Rights Act of 1965.
The Act struck down barriers to black enfranchisement and was the capstone to more than a decade of major civil rights legislation.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7068" end="140" start="99">It is important to note that use of this term carries important political overtones.
Previous terms used to identify American blacks were conferred upon the group by whites and were included in the wording of various laws and legal decisions which became tools of white supremacy and oppression.
There developed among blacks in America a growing desire for a term of their own choosing.

With the political consciousness that emerged from the political and social ferment of the late 1960s and early 1970s, Negro fell into disfavor among many American blacks.
It had taken on a moderate, accommodationist, even Uncle Tomish, connotation.
The period was a time when growing numbers of blacks in the U.S., particularly black youth, celebrated their blackness and their historical and cultural ties with the African continent.
They defiantly embraced black as a group identifier, a term often associated in English with things negative and undesirable -- a term they themselves had repudiated only two decades earlier -- proclaiming, "Black is beautiful."

By the 1990s, the terms Afro-American and African-American began to reemerge, this time for many as self-referential terms of choice.
Just as other ethnic groups in American society historically had adopted names descriptive of their families' geographical points of origin (such as Italian-American, Irish-American, Polish-American), many blacks in America expressed a preference for a similar term.
Because of the historical circumstances surrounding the capture, enslavement and systematic attempts to de-Africanize blacks in the U.S. under chattel slavery, most American blacks are unable to trace their ancestry to a specific African nation; hence, the entire continent serves as a geographic marker.

For many, African-American is more than a name expressive of cultural and historical roots.
The term expresses black pride and a sense of kinship and solidarity with others of the black African diaspora -- an embracing of the notion of pan-Africanism earlier enunciated by prominent black thinkers such as Marcus Garvey, W.E.B.
Dubois and, later, George Padmore.

A discussion of the term African-American and related terms can be found in the journal article "The Politicization of Changing Terms of Self Reference Among American Slave Descendants" in American Speech v 66 is 2 Summer 1991 p. 133-46.
To be considered African-American in the United States of America, not even half of one's ancestry must be black.
But will one quarter do, or one-eighth, or less?
The nation's answer to the question "Who is black?"
long has been that a black is any person with any known African black ancestry.
This definition reflects the long experience with racism; white supremacy; slavery; and, later, with Jim Crow laws.

In the southern United States, it became known as the one-drop rule, meaning that a single drop of "black blood" makes a person black.
Some courts have called it the traceable amount rule, and anthropologists call it the hypo-descent rule, meaning that racially mixed persons are assigned the status of the subordinate group.
This definition emerged from the American South to become America's national definition, generally accepted by whites and blacks -- but for different reasons.
White supremacists, whose motivation was racist, considered anyone with black ancestry tainted,inherently inferior morally and intellectually and, thus, subordinate.
Blacks, on the other hand, generally shared a common lot in society and, therefore, common cause -- regardless of their ethnic mixture.

In the last decade, a growing movement has developed, spearheaded mostly by white mothers of African-American children, towards the adoption and acceptance of the term bi-racial.
Some bi-racial blacks also refer to themselves as mixed, when, in fact, virtually all African-Americans are mixed.
In the mid 1970s, New York's New Amsterdam News reported that African-Americans with Native American ancestry numbered in the upper 80th percentile.
Native Americans often took in runaway bondsmen and women and accepted them as members of their tribes, and there is a lengthy history of peaceful coexistence and fighting alliances against whites between Native Americans and African-Americans.
Some Native American tribes, notably, the Cherokee, held African-American slaves.
Further, recent genetic tests on a small population of African-Americans revealed their ancestry to be, on average, approximately 19 percent white.

Additionally, throughout U.S. history, very fair persons with straight hair sometimes chose to "pass" as white to escape racism and discrimination, oftentimes completely separating themselves from contact with darker members of their family.
This was a dangerous action, in light of anti-miscegenation laws, social attitudes and lynch mobs.
Many lived in constant fear of producing children with telltale African features or being otherwise discovered.
The term Negro, which was widely used until the 1960s, today generally is considered inappropriate and derogatory.
Once widely considered acceptable, it fell into disfavor for reasons already herein stated.
The self-referential term of preference for Negro became black.
Another objection to the term is that it too easily can be misprounced unintentionally or by design to sound like nigra a Southern euphemism for nigger, the much-detested slur.

Other largely defunct, seldom used terms to refer to African-Americans are mulatto and colored.
The term mulatto originally was used to mean the offspring of a "pure African black" and a "pure European white".
The Latin root of the word is mulo, as in "mule", implying incorrectly that, like mules, which are horse-donkey hybrids, mulattoes are sterile crosses of two different species.
For example, in the early twentieth century, African-American leaders such as Booker T. Washington and Frederick Douglass, who had slaves as mothers and white fathers, were referred to as mulattoes.</entry>
  <entry author_id="72454" end="151" start="140">A variety of names have been used for African Americans at various points in history.
African Americans have been referred to as Negroes, colored, blacks and Afro-Americans, as well as lesser-known terms, such as the 19th-century designation Anglo-African.
The terms Negro and colored are now rarely used except in the South.
African American, black, and to a lesser extent Afro-American, are used interchangeably today but often incorrectly.
The term African-American refers only to American citizens, but is often applied to black residents from other countries who do not hold American citizenship.

Recent black immigrants from Africa and the islands of the Caribbean are sometimes classified as African Americans.
However, these groups, especially first- and second-generation immigrants, often have cultural practices, histories, and languages that are distinct from those of African Americans born in the United States.
For example, Caribbean natives may speak French, British English, Creole, or Spanish.
Africans may speak a European language other than English or any of a number of African languages as their first language.
Caribbean and African immigrants often have little knowledge or experience of the distinctive history of race relations in the United States.
Thus, Caribbean and African immigrants may or may not choose to call themselves African American.</entry>
  <entry author_id="624663" end="238" start="151">But this definition was not always the case.
Before 1690 or so, colonial social divisions reflected class (planters, craftsmen, forced laborers) and religion (Christians, "heathens") but did not emphasize ethnic origin.
Afro-European intermarriage was common.
The endogamous color line was invented in 1691 Virginia, when intermarriage was legislated to be a crime.
Over the next 30 years, Afro-European intermarriage was outlawed throughout 12 of the 13 colonies (SC being the exception) and the terms Black and White took on today's meaning.

For the next century and a half, as reflected in U.S. literature, popular culture, and court cases, Americans defined which side of the color line you were on by three rules: appearance, association, and blood fraction.
Appearance meant that you would not be accepted as White if you looked African.
Association meant that if your all friends were Black, then you would not be accepted as White even if you looked European.
Blood fraction meant that if you had more than a statutory fraction of Black ancestry, then you could not become legally White even if you looked European and associated only with Whites.
Although the three rules were formally documented and enforced by the courts, each rule’s details varied from state to state.
For example, the same biracial person of mostly European ancestry might be seen as a light-skinned Black in Virginia, but White-looking in Spanish Florida and the French Gulf Coast.
In Barbadian South Carolina, the rule of association was heavily influenced by wealth; money whitened as in today's Brazil.
And the legal blood fraction limit ranged from 1/8 (as in North Carolina) to 1/2 (Ohio).
During this period, hundreds of individuals, including famous ones like Jefferson's son Eston Hemmings, painter John James Audubon, and Florida's first U.S. senator David Levy Yulee, were socially accepted as White despite acknowledging slight Black ancestry (rather like Carol Channing today).
The one-drop rule of invisible Blackness arose in the mid-1830s in the Ohio Valley and spread to the south after the Civil War.
Those who advocated the notion that you could look completely European and self-identify as White, but still be involuntarily Black due to an undetectable trace of Black ancestry, were a minority at first, and the idea was rejected both by popular culture and the law.
But as 19th century was ending, the one-drop rule became increasingly accepted in the South.
By 1900 it had become the law of the land in court cases.
In the 1910-1930 period its acceptance spread throughout the nation, and it was made statutory and enforced in most states.

Incidentally, not everyone uses the term one-drop rule thus.
To some, the term is synonymous with Marvin Harris’s “hypodescent,” meaning that Americans who look slightly African are considered Black, even if their African admixture is less than 50 percent.
This differs from the Caribbean, where you are White if you look preponderantly European.
To others, one-drop rule refers to the U.S. folkloric belief that anyone who has even one drop of African blood in his veins is marked by some subtle physical trait, a clue that reveals the African ancestry.
Some say that it is revealed in the color of the half-moons at the base of the thumbnails, or in the shape of the heels, or in blue or purple marks at specific locations on the body.
To them, one-drop rule is the belief that no matter how diluted African blood may be, a residue of visible evidence will always remain, generation after generation.
This is nonsense, of course, since about one-third of White Americans have detectable recent African genetic admixture in their DNA from ancestors who passed through the color line.
The one-drop rule, on the other hand, is the idea that you can look completely European and self-identify as White, but still be involuntarily Black due to an undetectable trace of Black ancestry.

Why were Americans the only society to adopt such a strange rule of group membership (undetectable and intangible by definition)?
The question has interested anthropologists and historians.
The four most popular theories are: that it maintained and expanded the agricultural labor force, that it was embraced by Black leadership to enhance ethnic solidarity, that it was used by White supremacists to support the notion of White racial purity, and that it was wielded as a threat to keep compassionate White families in line by exiling them to Blackness if they defended or befriended Blacks during the Jim Crow period of White-on-Black terror and oppression.
Of course, these explanations are not mutually exclusive, and may have operated in combination.

The first theory is that the one-drop rule maintained or expanded the labor force by subjecting those of mixed ancestry to forced labor.
Its strength lies in explaining why the one-drop rule triumphed in the early 20th century.
This was the very period when much of the South's Black agricultural labor force fled to the North in the Great Migration.
The one-drop rule shifted the color line pale-wards, trapping many who had been previously seen as White.
The theory's weakness is that it is sometimes erroneously applied to slavery.
This is an error because no court case ever ruled that someone was a slave merely because of his or her "race."
Slavery was matrilineal.
Hundreds of people of sub-Saharan phenotype were routinely freed following case law set by Higgins v. Allen, 1796 Maryland by proving that a matrilineal ancestor was free.
Indeed, having mixed ancestry was useful because, ever since Gobu v. Gobu, 1802 North Carolina; Hudgins v. Wrights, 1806 Virginia; and Adelle v. Beauregard, 1810 Louisiana, the law of the land (subsequently followed in hundreds of cases) was that biracial individuals were presumed to be free unless proven otherwise.
But most importantly, the one-drop rule was not adopted—indeed, it was virtually unknown—in the South until long after slavery was dead.
(See Race.)

The explanation that the one-drop rule was embraced by Black leadership in order to enhance ethnic solidarity matches the timing and direction of the rule's spread.
The rule was advocated by both Martin R. Delany (1812-1885) and Frederick Douglass (1818-1895) before the Civil War.
It was carried south after the war by the Black Yankees who built the schools, printed the newspapers, and opened the businesses that taught the newly freed to flourish as Americans.
It was defended and supported by Black political leadership throughout the Jim Crow terror.
The one-drop system of racial designation was a significant factor in African-American ethnic solidarity since antebellum times.
African Americans generally shared a common lot in society and, therefore, common cause—regardless of their ethnic admixture and social and economic stratification.
This theory's weakness is that it cannot stand alone.
It seems unlikely that a minority population (Black) could somehow cause mainstream society (White) to adopt and impose a law that helped only Blacks.
After all, one-drop rule was enforced by White elites through the judicial system.

The theory that the one-drop rule was used to keep compassionate White families in line is psychologically compelling and matches court evidence of how the rule was enforced.
Between 1900 and 1920, over a hundred court cases were held to decide whether an accused family was truly White or unknowingly Black.
About forty of those cases were then appealed to state supreme courts.
In not one of those forty cases was any genealogical evidence produced.
In no case did an accuser reveal an ancient birth certificate, marriage license, school record, or the like.
Instead, the testimony was that: An aunt was seen laughing at a joke told by a Black maid.
An uncle was seen shaking hands with a Black carpenter who had been hired to build a chicken-coop.
A 15-year-old niece was seen flirting with a Black boy of the same age.
The testimony that banished families to Blackness was always about establishing one-on-one family-to-family relationships across the color line.
The theory is compelling because it is a well-known law of group psychology that when a powerful group bullies a weak group, any member of the bullying group who befriends and tries to defend a victim will be expelled to the bullied group and become a victim himself.
During the Jim Crow wave of terror, the White community bullied the Black community.
And so, any White family that befriended a Black family was expelled from Whiteness and made legally Black.
In 1896, the United States Supreme Court missed an opportunity to stifle the one-drop rule before it became the law of the land two decades later.

Ironically, the Justices wanted to consider the issue of Plessy's "race" and encouraged Plessy's lawyers to argue the point.
But Plessy's legal strategy was to stipulate that he was Black in order to focus on refuting the public benefit of segregation.
Like Walter White a generation later, his goal was not to redefine himself as White (he could easily have done that without court permission); it was to kill segregation.

With the advent of Affirmative Action and other entitlement programs, some have seen it advantageous to be accepted as African-American.
The claims to Blackness by individuals who look White and were raised as White, have been rejected by some courts but upheld by others.
It apparently depends upon community acceptance.
The firefighter Malone brothers of 1985 Boston were convicted of "racial fraud" for acquiring Affirmative Action points added to test scores by claiming that a great-grandmother was Black—a claim that was violently opposed by the local Black community.
On the other hand, the employers of Mary Walker of 1988 Denver, a schoolteacher of fair complexion, green eyes, light brown hair, and no documented Black ancestry, were court-ordered to accept her as Black because she was supported by the local Black community.
Conversely, Mustapha Henry of 1997 Detroit, a Black-looking immigrant from Africa (Egypt), was denied benefits because he was not "ethnically" African-American.
And yet Mark Stebbins, a Stockton California councilman of African heritage and African-American ethnicity lost his seat due to a recall vote paid for by an equally African-American (but Black separatist) opponent on the grounds that Stebbins's integrationist political agenda had made him no longer African-American enough.
Again, whether you can benefit from entitlement programs meant for African Americans seems to depend on the support of the local African-American community.

Some recent evidence suggests that the one-drop rule may be waning in America's popular culture.
One way of measuring the tenacity of the one-drop-rule is by examining how Black/White interracial parents identify their children on the census “race” question.
Such couples are not typical of most Americans.
Nevertheless, if interracial parents accept the legitimacy of African-American ethnic self-identity while simultaneously rejecting the one-drop rule, you would expect half of their children to be identified as White and half as Black.
That the children of Black/White interracial parents have been more often identified as Black than as White since 1880 demonstrates that the one-drop rule has been accepted for many decades.
In fact, the fraction of such children labeled as unmixed White has fallen steadily from 50 percent in 1940 to 13 percent in 2000.
This suggests that the one-drop rule continues to grow stronger among Black/White interracial parents.
On the other hand, the fraction of such children labeled as unmixed Black dropped abruptly from 62 percent in 1990 to 31 percent in 2000.
This suggests that it has recently become unfashionable to make first-generation biracial children deny their European ancestry.
Whether this portends a crack in the one-drop rule remains to be seen.

On the other hand, some recent evidence suggests that the one-drop rule is still invoked by Americans whenever it seems useful.
As recently as 1986, the U.S. Supreme Court upheld the one-drop rule by refusing to hear a case against Louisiana’s “racial” classification criteria as applied to Susie Phipps (479 U.S. 1002).</entry>
  <entry author_id="864816" end="252" start="238">African-Americans have a higher prevalence of some chronic health conditions.
They also have an out-of-wedlock birth rate relative to the general population that greatly exceeds any other ethnic group.
This rate has been almost 70% for years.
Rates of marriage and out-of-wedlock births are highly correlated to levels of poverty.
These problems and potential remedies have been the subject of intense public policy debate in the United States in general, and within the African-American community in particular.
Main article: African American culture

African American culture, especially African American music, is one of the most pervasive cultural influences in the United States today.
Hip hop, rock, R&amp;B, funk, and other contemporary American musical forms evolved from blues, jazz, and gospel music.
African American culture also gave rise to pop culture notions cool that have transcended American culture to become an international phenomenon.
African American Vernacular English (AAVE) is a dialect of English spoken by many African Americans to varying degrees.

Many African American authors have written stories, poems, and essays influenced by their experiences as African Americans, and African American literature is a major genre in American literature, notable among them Langston Hughes, James Baldwin, Richard Wright, Zora Neale Hurston, Jessie Redmond Fauset, Ralph Ellison, Gwendolyn Brooks, Alice Walker, Toni Morrison, Maya Angelou, Gayle Jones and Walter Mosley.
The term African American has important political overtones.
Previous terms used to identify Americans of African ancestry were conferred upon the group by whites and were included in the wording of various laws and legal decisions which became tools of white supremacy and oppression.
There developed among blacks in America a growing desire for a term of their own choosing.</entry>
  <entry author_id="864816" end="320" start="252">(the Department of Justice figures cited here conflate Hispanics with European-Americans).
Furthermore, the absolute number of African-American murderers has exceeded the absolute number of European-American murderers in every year since 1986.
The victim rate for African-Americans is also high, with African-Americans six times more likely to be murdered than European-Americans.

These problems and potential remedies have been the subject of intense public policy debate in the United States in general, and within the African American community in particular.
Historically, Booker T. Washington said that the situation can only be remedied by African Americans themselves, and that African Americans should not expect whites or the government to solve African Americans' problems for them.
In 1865, Frederick Douglass echoed the same sentiments when he said, "The American people have always been anxious to know what they shall do with us....
I have had but one answer from the beginning.
Do nothing with us!"
These approaches contrast with modern policies of affirmative action, welfare, and other social programs designed for the benefit of African Americans.
Main article: African American culture

African American foods reflect creative responses to racial and economic oppression.
Under slavery, African Americans were not allowed to eat better cuts of meat, and after Emancipation many often were too poor to afford them.
Soul food, a hearty cuisine commonly associated with African Americans in the South (but also common among blacks in the North), makes creative use of inexpensive products procured through farming and subsistence hunting and fishing.
Pig intestines are boiled and sometimes battered and fried to make “chitterlings,” or "chitlins."
Ham hocks and neck bones provide seasoning to soups; beans and boiled turnip, collard and mustard greens.
Other common foods, such as fried chicken and fish, cornbread and “hoppin’ John,” (black-eyed peas and rice), are prepared simply.

African American music is one of the most pervasive African American cultural influences in the United States today and is among the most dominant in mainstream popular music.
Hip hop, rock, R&amp;B, funk, soul, techno and other contemporary American musical forms originated in black communities and evolved from blues, jazz, and gospel music.
These musical forms have also influenced and been incorporated into nearly every other popular musical genre.

African Americans have had a tremendous impact on left-wing politics in the United States.
From liberalism to progressivism, from communism to socialism, to anarchism, African Americans have been a major part of leftist struggles throughout U.S. history.
Like most Leftists, the majority of the African-Americans are in favor of workers rights, pacifism, equality, equal distribution of wealth, and a color-blind society.
Far-left groups would include organizations such as the Black Panther Party.

African American inventors have created some of the most widely used devices in the world and have contributed to great medical innovations internationally, a few notable examples including the first successful open heart surgery, performed by Dr. Daniel Hale Williams, the conceptualization and establishment of blood banks around the world by Dr. Charles Drew,the air conditioner, patented by Frederick Jones in 1949, the creation of the gas mask and automatic traffic signal by Garrett A. Morgan, the refrigerator, patented by John Standard in 1894 and the cellular phone, created by Henry Sampson.
The term African American carries important political overtones.
Previous terms used to identify Americans of African ancestry were conferred upon the group by whites and were included in the wording of various laws and legal decisions which became tools of white supremacy and oppression.
There developed among blacks in America a growing desire for a term of their own choosing.

With the political consciousness that emerged from the political and social ferment of the late 1960s and early 1970s, Negro fell into disfavor among many African Americans.
It had taken on a moderate, accommodationist, even Uncle Tomish, connotation.
In this period, a growing number of blacks in the U.S., particularly African American youth, celebrated their blackness and their historical and cultural ties with the African continent.
The Black Power movement defiantly embraced black as a group identifier—a term they themselves had repudiated only two decades earlier—a term often associated in English with things negative and undesirable, proclaiming, "Black is beautiful."

In this same period, others favored the term Afro-American; this particular term never gained much traction, but by the 1990s, the term African American had emerged as the leading choice of self-referential term.
Just as other ethnic groups in American society historically had adopted names descriptive of their families' geographical points of origin (such as Italian-American, Irish-American, Polish-American), many blacks in America expressed a preference for a similar term.
Because of the historical circumstances surrounding the capture, enslavement and systematic attempts to de-Africanize blacks in the U.S. under chattel slavery, most African Americans are unable to trace their ancestry to a specific African nation; hence, the entire continent serves as a geographic marker.

For many, African American is more than a name expressive of cultural and historical roots.
The term expresses African pride and a sense of kinship and solidarity with others of the African diaspora—an embracing of the notion of pan-Africanism earlier enunciated by prominent African thinkers such as Marcus Garvey, W.E.B.
Dubois and, later, George Padmore.

A discussion of the term African American and related terms can be found in the journal article "The Politicization of Changing Terms of Self Reference Among American Slave Descendants" in American Speech v 66 is 2 Summer 1991 p. 133-46.
To be considered African American in the United States of America, not even half of one's ancestry need be black African.
The nation's answer to the question "Who is black?"
long has been that a "black" is any person with any known African ancestry.
This definition reflects the long experience with racism, white supremacy, slavery, and, later, with Jim Crow laws.

In the Southern United States, it became known as the one-drop rule, meaning that a single drop of "black blood" makes a person "black".
Some courts have called it the traceable amount rule, and anthropologists call it the hypo-descent rule, meaning that racially mixed persons are assigned the status of the subordinate group.
This definition emerged from the American South to become America's national definition, generally accepted by whites and blacks -- but for different reasons.

White supremacists, whose motivation was racist, considered anyone with African ancestry tainted, inherently inferior morally and intellectually and, thus, subordinate.
During slavery, there was also a strong economic incentive to maximize the number of individuals who could be owned, bred, worked, traded and sold outright as human chattel.
The designation of anyone possessing any trace of African ancestry as "black", and, therefore, of subordinate status to whites, guaranteed a source of free or cheap labor during slavery and for decades afterward.

In the 1980s, parents of mixed-race children began to organize and lobby for the addition of a more inclusive term of racial designation that would reflect the heritage of their offspring.
As a result, the term biracial has become more widely used and accepted to classify people of mixed race.
The term Negro, which was widely used until the 1960s, today increasingly is considered passé and inappropriate or derogatory.
It is still fairly commonly used by older individuals and in the Deep South.
Once widely considered acceptable, Negro fell into disfavor for reasons already herein stated.
The self-referential term of preference for Negro became black.

Negroid is a term used by European anthropologists first in the 18th century to describe indigenous Africans and their descendants throughout the African diaspora.
As with most descriptors of race based on inconsistent, unscientific phenotypical standards, the term is controversial and imprecise.
Because of its similarity to Negro, growing numbers of blacks have substituted the term Africoid which, unlike Negroid, encompasses the phenotypes of all indigenous African peoples.

Other largely defunct, seldom used terms to refer to African Americans are mulatto and colored.
Even so, the use of the word "colored" can still be found today in the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, or NAACP.
The American use of the term mulatto originally was used to mean the offspring of a "pure African black" and a "pure European white".

The Latin root of the word is mulo, as in "mule", implying incorrectly that, like mules, which are horse-donkey hybrids, mulattoes are sterile crosses of two different species.
For example, in the early 20th century, African American leaders such as Booker T. Washington and Frederick Douglass, who had slaves as mothers and white fathers, were referred to as mulattoes.
While not as common as "mixed" or "biracial," or even "multiracial," mulatto is still sometimes used to refer to people of mixed parentage and, despite its origin, is not considered inherently derogatory.

Mulatto and terms with the -roon suffix persisted in a social context for a number of decades, but by the mid twentieth century, they no longer were in common use.
With the end of slavery, there was no longer a strong commercial incentive to classify blacks by their African-European ancestral admixture.
The occasional use of these terms, however, does still persist in electronic media, literature and in some social settings.
The following gives the black population in the U.S. over time, based on U.S. Census figures.
(Numbers from years 1920 to 2000 are based on U.S. Census figures as given by the Time Almanac of 2005, p 377)</entry>
  <entry author_id="864816" end="331" start="320">Some criticize the term African American.
To be African-American, some would argue that an individual would have to be born in Africa, then immigrate to U.S., and then obtain citizenship.
By this definition, an overwhelming majority of black Americans would not be African-American, but of African American descent.

Some counter that "hyphenated American" terms are used to describe one's national origin, so any person born in Africa would take on the name of their country.
For example, individuals from Nigeria would be called Nigerian-American, as it describes their national origin, as opposed to African-American.
The term African-American is preferred by many because although the national origin of the majority of black Americans is not traceable, the continent of Africa provides a descriptive term of themselves.
However, this is criticized by some because the hyphenated terms put one's heritage at the center of one's identity, rather than identifying as Americans first and of whatever national or ethnic background secondarily.

The term has also been criticized on the grounds that since "African American" has largely replaced "black," there is no term in U.S. English to describe blacks who are not of African descent, or those who are not American.
For example, during the 2005 civil unrest in France, CNN reporter Carol Lin referred to the rioters as "African Americans."
While the majority of rioters are of North African background, none are known to be U.S. citizens.
Without a "politically correct" alternative, Lin used the only term available, but the term clearly does not cover the same semantic ground as black does.</entry>
  <entry author_id="864816" end="412" start="331">(the Department of Justice figures cited here conflate Hispanics with whites).
Furthermore, the absolute number of African-American murderers has exceeded the absolute number of white murderers in every year since 1986.
The victim rate for African-Americans is also high, with African-Americans six times more likely to be murdered than whites.
African-Americans have a higher prevalence of some chronic health conditions.
The out-of-wedlock birth rate for African-Americans, at 70%, greatly exceeds that of any other group, as well as the population as a whole.. Rates of marriage and out-of-wedlock births are highly correlated to levels of poverty.

These problems and potential remedies have been the subject of intense public policy debate in the United States in general, and within the African American community in particular.
Historically, Booker T. Washington said that the situation can only be remedied by African Americans themselves, and that African Americans should not expect whites or the government to solve African Americans' problems for them.
In 1865, Frederick Douglass echoed the same sentiments when he said, "The American people have always been anxious to know what they shall do with us....
I have had but one answer from the beginning.
Do nothing with us!"
These approaches contrast with modern policies of affirmative action, welfare, and other social programs designed for the benefit of African Americans.
Main article: African American culture

African American foods reflect creative responses to racial and economic oppression.
Under slavery, African Americans were not allowed to eat better cuts of meat, and after Emancipation many often were too poor to afford them.
Soul food, a hearty cuisine commonly associated with African Americans in the South (but also common among blacks in the North), makes creative use of inexpensive products procured through farming and subsistence hunting and fishing.
Pig intestines are boiled and sometimes battered and fried to make “chitterlings,” or "chitlins."
Ham hocks and neck bones provide seasoning to soups; beans and boiled turnip, collard and mustard greens.
Other common foods, such as fried chicken and fish, cornbread and “hoppin’ John,” (black-eyed peas and rice), are prepared simply.

African American music is one of the most pervasive African American cultural influences in the United States today and is among the most dominant in mainstream popular music.
Hip hop, rock, R&amp;B, funk, soul, techno and other contemporary American musical forms originated in black communities and evolved from blues, jazz, and gospel music.
These musical forms have also influenced and been incorporated into nearly every other popular musical genre.

African Americans have had a tremendous impact on left-wing politics in the United States.
From liberalism to progressivism, from communism to socialism, to anarchism, African Americans have been a major part of leftist struggles throughout U.S. history.
Like most Leftists, the majority of the African-Americans are in favor of workers rights, pacifism, equality, equal distribution of wealth, and a color-blind society.
Far-left groups would include organizations such as the Black Panther Party.

African American inventors have created some of the most widely used devices in the world and have contributed to great medical innovations internationally, a few notable examples including the first successful open heart surgery, performed by Dr. Daniel Hale Williams, the conceptualization and establishment of blood banks around the world by Dr. Charles Drew,the air conditioner, patented by Frederick Jones in 1949, the creation of the gas mask and automatic traffic signal by Garrett A. Morgan, the refrigerator, patented by John Standard in 1894 and the cellular phone, created by Henry Sampson.
The term African American carries important political overtones.
Previous terms used to identify Americans of African ancestry were conferred upon the group by whites and were included in the wording of various laws and legal decisions which became tools of white supremacy and oppression.
There developed among blacks in America a growing desire for a term of their own choosing.

With the political consciousness that emerged from the political and social ferment of the late 1960s and early 1970s, Negro fell into disfavor among many African Americans.
It had taken on a moderate, accommodationist, even Uncle Tomish, connotation.
In this period, a growing number of blacks in the U.S., particularly African American youth, celebrated their blackness and their historical and cultural ties with the African continent.
The Black Power movement defiantly embraced black as a group identifier—a term they themselves had repudiated only two decades earlier—a term often associated in English with things negative and undesirable, proclaiming, "Black is beautiful."

In this same period, others favored the term Afro-American; this particular term never gained much traction, but by the 1990s, the term African American had emerged as the leading choice of self-referential term.
Just as other ethnic groups in American society historically had adopted names descriptive of their families' geographical points of origin (such as Italian-American, Irish-American, Polish-American), many blacks in America expressed a preference for a similar term.
Because of the historical circumstances surrounding the capture, enslavement and systematic attempts to de-Africanize blacks in the U.S. under chattel slavery, most African Americans are unable to trace their ancestry to a specific African nation; hence, the entire continent serves as a geographic marker.

For many, African American is more than a name expressive of cultural and historical roots.
The term expresses African pride and a sense of kinship and solidarity with others of the African diaspora—an embracing of the notion of pan-Africanism earlier enunciated by prominent African thinkers such as Marcus Garvey, W.E.B.
Dubois and, later, George Padmore.

A discussion of the term African American and related terms can be found in the journal article "The Politicization of Changing Terms of Self Reference Among American Slave Descendants" in American Speech v 66 is 2 Summer 1991 p. 133-46.
To be considered African American in the United States of America, not even half of one's ancestry need be black African.
The nation's answer to the question "Who is black?"
long has been that a "black" is any person with any known African ancestry.
This definition reflects the long experience with racism, white supremacy, slavery, and, later, with Jim Crow laws.

In the Southern United States, it became known as the one-drop rule, meaning that a single drop of "black blood" makes a person "black".
Some courts have called it the traceable amount rule, and anthropologists call it the hypo-descent rule, meaning that racially mixed persons are assigned the status of the subordinate group.
This definition emerged from the American South to become America's national definition, generally accepted by whites and blacks -- but for different reasons.

White supremacists, whose motivation was racist, considered anyone with African ancestry tainted, inherently inferior morally and intellectually and, thus, subordinate.
During slavery, there was also a strong economic incentive to maximize the number of individuals who could be owned, bred, worked, traded and sold outright as human chattel.
The designation of anyone possessing any trace of African ancestry as "black", and, therefore, of subordinate status to whites, guaranteed a source of free or cheap labor during slavery and for decades afterward.

In the 1980s, parents of mixed-race children began to organize and lobby for the addition of a more inclusive term of racial designation that would reflect the heritage of their offspring.
As a result, the term biracial has become more widely used and accepted to classify people of mixed race.
The term Negro, which was widely used until the 1960s, today increasingly is considered passé and inappropriate or derogatory.
It is still fairly commonly used by older individuals and in the Deep South.
Once widely considered acceptable, Negro fell into disfavor for reasons already herein stated.
The self-referential term of preference for Negro became black.

Negroid is a term used by European anthropologists first in the 18th century to describe indigenous Africans and their descendants throughout the African diaspora.
As with most descriptors of race based on inconsistent, unscientific phenotypical standards, the term is controversial and imprecise.
Because of its similarity to Negro, growing numbers of blacks have substituted the term Africoid which, unlike Negroid, encompasses the phenotypes of all indigenous African peoples.

Other largely defunct, seldom used terms to refer to African Americans are mulatto and colored.
Even so, the use of the word "colored" can still be found today in the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, or NAACP.
The American use of the term mulatto originally was used to mean the offspring of a "pure African black" and a "pure European white".

The Latin root of the word is mulo, as in "mule", implying incorrectly that, like mules, which are horse-donkey hybrids, mulattoes are sterile crosses of two different species.
For example, in the early 20th century, African American leaders such as Booker T. Washington and Frederick Douglass, who had slaves as mothers and white fathers, were referred to as mulattoes.
While not as common as "mixed" or "biracial," or even "multiracial," mulatto is still sometimes used to refer to people of mixed parentage and, despite its origin, is not considered inherently derogatory.

Mulatto and terms with the -roon suffix persisted in a social context for a number of decades, but by the mid twentieth century, they no longer were in common use.
With the end of slavery, there was no longer a strong commercial incentive to classify blacks by their African-European ancestral admixture.
The occasional use of these terms, however, does still persist in electronic media, literature and in some social settings.
Some criticize the term African American.
To be African-American, some argue that an individual would have to be born in Africa, then immigrate to U.S., and then obtain citizenship.
By this definition, an overwhelming majority of black Americans would not be African-American, but of African American descent.

Others counter that "hyphenated American" terms are used to describe one's national origin, so any person born in Africa would take on the name of their country.
For example, individuals from Nigeria would be called Nigerian-American, as it describes their national origin, as opposed to African-American.
The term African-American is preferred by many because although the national origin of the majority of black Americans is not traceable, the continent of Africa provides a geographic point of origin and a descriptive term of themselves.

The term has also been criticized on the grounds that since "African American" has largely replaced "black," there is no term in U.S. English to describe blacks who are not of African descent, or those who are not American.
For example, during the 2005 civil unrest in France, CNN reporter Carol Lin referred to the rioters as "African Americans."
While the majority of rioters are of North African background, none are known to be U.S. citizens.
Without a "politically correct" alternative, Lin used the only term available, but the term clearly does not cover the same semantic ground as black does.

By this argument, "black" is an all-encompassing term that could be applied to many different cultures in the United States, while "African American" could be applied specifically to native-born blacks whose African diasporic ancestry lies primarily in the United States.
The following gives the black population in the U.S. over time, based on U.S. Census figures.
(Numbers from years 1920 to 2000 are based on U.S. Census figures as given by the Time Almanac of 2005, p 377)</entry>
  <entry author_id="1596019" end="430" start="412">Within African American families, the formation of a household often begins not with marriage, but with the birth of a child.
The importance of extended family and kin in maintaining family cohesion is often overshadowed by negative portrayals of African American family life, however, studies have found that African American families display about 70 various structural formations, versus about 40 among white families.
This comparison points to the variability of the African American family structure and to the flexibilty of family roles.

African American families tend to be more hierarchical are more likely to be strict, to hold demanding behavioral standards and to use physical discipline.
Such strictness is, however, balanced within a context of strong support and affection.
Physical punishment among African American children usually doesn't result in the same negative outcomes as it does for white children.

Grandparents, especially African American grandmothers, often play a crucial role role in the maintenance of the family.
When mothers cannot fulfill their roles, grandmothers often step in to parent children.
In 1998, 1.4 million African American children (12%) lived in their grandparents' home (either with or without their parents).
Grandparents care is often reciprocated in old age - African American families are much more likely to care for aging or dying family members.

African American foods reflect creative responses to racial and economic oppression.
Under slavery, African Americans were not allowed to eat better cuts of meat, and after Emancipation many often were too poor to afford them.
Soul food, a hearty cuisine commonly associated with African Americans in the South (but also common among blacks nationwide), makes creative use of inexpensive products procured through farming and subsistence hunting and fishing.
Pig intestines are boiled and sometimes battered and fried to make “chitterlings,” or "chitlins."
Hamhocks and neck bones provide seasoning to soups; beans and boiled greens (turnip greens, collard greens, and mustard greens).
Other common foods, such as fried chicken and fish, cornbread and “hoppin’ John” (black-eyed peas and rice), are prepared simply.
When the African-American population was considerably more rural than it generally is today, rabbit, possum, and squirrel, as well as waterfowl, were important additions to the diet.
Many of these food traditions are especially predominant in many parts of the rural South.</entry>
  <entry author_id="553435" end="450" start="430">At the same time, current information points to a continuation of a long-term trend toward parity with national levels and absolutely higher levels of affluence than those experienced by most populations outside the United States.
By 2003, sex had replaced race as the primary factor in life expectancy in the United States, with African American females expected to live longer than white males born in that year.
In the same year, the gap in life expectancy between American whites (78.0) and blacks (72.8) had decreased to 5.2 years, reflecting a long term trend of this phenomenon.
The current life expectancy of African Americans as a group is comparable to those of other groups who live in developed nations.
In 2004, African American workers had the second-highest median earnings of American minority groups after Asian Americans, and African Americans had the highest level of male-female income parity of all ethnic groups in the United States.
Also, among American minority groups, only Asian Americans were more likely to hold white collar occupations (management, professional, and related fields), and African Americans were no more or less likely than whites to work in the service industry.
In 2002, African American women had a lower fertility rate than the US average.
In 2001, over half of African American households of married couples earned $50,000 or more.
Although in the same year African Americans were over-represented among the nation's poor, this was directly related to the disproportionate percentage of African American families headed by single women; such families are collectively poorer, regardless of ethnicity.
Collectively, African Americans are more involved in the American politcal process than other minority groups in the US, indicated by the highest level of voter registration and participation in elections among these groups in 2004.
African Americans collectively attain higher levels of education than immigrants to the United States (despite conventional discourse that suggests that groups "fresh off the boat" arrive with higher value placed on education than African Americans).
Although the unemployment rate among African Americans (in 2002, approximately 11% has typically been twice the rate among European Americans(app.
5% in the same year, ), it is still at or below rates found in France and Spain,, and is slightly higher than the overall rate of the European Union.
When compared to populations outside of the United States and European Union, the collective affluence of African Americans is even more striking and disproportionate.
Based on worker income alone, African Americans produced $586 billion in 2004,, slightly smaller than the GDP of Brazil in 2006 (even though Brazil's population is about 5 times the size of the African American one), and approximately 80% the size of Russia's 2005 GDP (even though Russia's population is nearly 4 times the size of the African American one.
In 2004 this amount would have been ranked as the 15th largest GDP internationally (out of 177 ranked), compared to a population ranking of 33 in 2005.
In 2005, the populations of Poland and African Americans were roughly equal, but the 2004 earnings of the latter group would have been nearly 2.5 times the size of the former's GDP in 2005.
In 2005, the Ukraine's population was approximately 10% larger than the African American population, but its GDP was over 8 times smaller than the 2004 earnings of the latter group.
In Argentina, arguably the most developed Latin American country whose population is predominantly of European origin (97%), the unemployment rate is slightly higher than that of African Americans as a group, the poverty rate is almost twice the rate, and the 2004 earnings of African American workers were nearly 3.5 times the size of Argentina's 2005 GDP, even though Argentina's population is slightly larger than the African American population.
In Mexico, whose human development index is comparable to those of most former Second World countries, and whose economy ranks as a mid-income one, the poverty rate is twice the rate of African Americans as a group, and even though its 2005 population was nearly 3 times the population of African Americans, Mexico's GDP from the same year exceeded the 2004 earnings of African American workers by only 25%.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1802979" end="466" start="450">Although the unemployment rate among African Americans (in 2002, approximately 11% has typically been twice the rate among European Americans (app.
5% in the same year, ), it is still at or below rates found in France and Spain,, and is slightly higher than the overall rate of the European Union.
Main article: African American culture

note: The CIA World Factbook gives the current 2005 figure as 13.5%  Colon cleansing is becoming increasingly popular in the African-American Community.
Negro people are the major customers of colon cleansing producers.
Nobody is sure about why blacks are obsessed with the cleanliness of their colons.
Some speculate that it is a superstition brought over from Africa by the slaves.
Perhaps it has something to do with the emancipation proclamation.
Every negro deserves a donkey and a bucket of KFC to shit in, according to the Articles of Reconstruction.
This lead to the binge and purge mentality of blacks.
In some health food stores, black women are called "Saturday Night Specials," because they love to come in on Saturday night to get their colon cleansers.
A week of KFC has them plugged up, and they need to eliminate the greasy waste so their shacked up boyfriends can have better anal sex, unless they are planning on having another welfare baby.
Many nutritionists, including Mike Hunt attribute this phenomena to the typical diet of fried chicken, and the increasing price of watermelon.
Economist Raj Sahib says has indicated that watermelon sales in the inner-city have an inverse relationship to prices, and that as watermelon consumption declines, the use of habit forming colon cleansers increases.
Mike Hunt states that Afro-Americans have a higher risk of colon cancer as a direct result of their consumption of mass quantities fried chicken, literally buckets full per household on a daily basis in the typical negro apartment.
Combine this with drinking a forty of Eight-Ball (malt liquor sold by "the man" in our communities to enslave our brothers) on the porch, smokin some menthols, and some chronic, and you have a receipe for disaster.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1596019" end="558" start="466">In 1790, when the first census was taken, African Americans numbered about 760,000—about 19% of the population.
In 1860, at the start of the Civil War, the African-American population increased to 4.4 million, but the percentage rate dropped to 14% of the overall population of the country.
The vast majority were slaves, with only 488,000 counted as “freemen.” By 1900, the black population had doubled and reached 8.8 million.
In 1910, about 90% of African Americans lived in the South, but large numbers began migrating north looking for better job opportunities and living conditions, and to escape Jim Crow and racial violence.
The Great Migration, as it was called, spanned the 1890s to the 1970s.
From 1916 through the 1960s, more than 6 million black people moved north.
But in the 1970s and 1980s, that trend reversed, with more African Americans moving south to the Sunbelt than leaving it.
By 1990, the African American population reached about 30 million and represented 12% of the U.S. population, roughly the same proportion as in 1900.

Among the most notable inventors were Jan Matzeliger, who developed the first machine to mass-produce shoes, and Elijah McCoy, who invented automatic lubrication devices for steam engines.
Granville Woods had 35 patents to improve electric railway systems including the first system to allow moving trains to communicate.
He even sued Alexander Graham Bell and Thomas Edison for stealing his patents and won both cases.
Garrett Morgan developed the first automatic traffic signal and gas mask, and Norbert Rilleux who created the technique for converting sugar cane juice into white sugar crystals.
Moreover, Rillieux was so brilliant that in 1854 he left Louisiana and went to France where he spent ten years working with the Champollions deciphering Egyptian hieroglyphics from the Rosetta Stone.

Lewis Latimer created an inexpensive cotton-thread filament, which made electric light bulbs practical because Edison's original light bulb only burned for a few minutes.
More recent inventors include McKinley Jones, who invented the movable refrigeration unit for food transport in trucks and trains and Lloyd Quarterman who with six other Black scientists, worked on the creation of the atomic bomb along (code named the Manhattan Project.)
Quaterman also helped develop the first nuclear reactor, which was used in the atomically powered submarine called the Nautilus.

More current contributors include Otis Bodkin, who invented an electrical device used in all guided missiles and all IBM computers, and Colonel Frederick Gregory, who was not only the first Black astronaut pilot but the person who also redesigned the cockpits for the last three space shuttles.
Gregory was also on the team that pioneered the microwave instrumentation landing system.
In 2000, Bendix Aircraft Company began a worldwide promotion of this microwave instrumentation landing system that can land planes without a pilot.
*Excerpt from Black People &amp; Their Place In World History By: Dr. Leroy Vaughn, MD, MBA*

Though the majority of contemporary African Americans are the descendents of enslaved Africans from West and Central Africa, there has been research indicating the African presence in North America predates the arrival of Christopher Columbus.
According to Ivan Van Sertima, "The African presence in America before Columbus is of importance not only to African and American history, but to the history of world civilizations.
The African presence is proven by stone heads, terra cottas, skeletons, artifacts, techniques and inscriptions, by oral traditions and documented history, by botanical, linguistic and cultural data."

In 1862, an immense carved head with African-like features was found in Central America.
Similar carvings dating back to around 800 B.C have been found since.
Step pyramids, such as were built in Egypt, and Peruvian looms resembling those found in Africa have also been found.
Certain species of plants once only indigenous to Africa, including strains of cotton and bananas, appear to have been introduced into the Americas from Africa prior to 1492.
Early European explorers such as Balboa wrote of seeing African was captives in Indian villages and of hearing of isolated tribes of blacks.

Many people have written on the African presence in pre-Columbian America, including Ivan Van Sertima, Leo Wiener, Kofi Wangara,R.A.
Jairazbhoy, Legrand H. Clegg II, and Floyd W. Hayes III.
In his own words, author Ivan Van Sertima notes that:

Recent research indicates that one of the most famous landmarks in the United States, the Statue of Liberty was originally intended to represent the end of American slavery and originally modeled after a black woman.
According to various research, including research by indepedent scholars and acclaimed publications such as the New York Times and the New York Post, the liberation of African American slaves was the primary inspiration for the creation of a Statue of Liberation for Edouard Rene LeFebvre DeLaboulaye.
He recruited a young sculptor, Frederick Auguste Bartholdi, to create a Black female slave statue holding a broken chain in her left hand and with broken chains of slavery at her feet.

The official web site of the Statue of Liberty states that the statue was given to the people of the United States by the people of France as an expression of friendship and to commemorate the centennial of American Independence (1776).
The Encyclopedia Britannica states Bartholdi designed the Statue of Liberty as a monument to the Franco-American alliance of 1778.
However, there is controversy by some scholars that this is a false paradigm.
Edouard Rene LeFebvre DeLaboulaye, an internationally renowned lawyer and author of a three-volume history of the United States, first discussed the idea of a symbol to represent the end of U.S. slavery at a dinner party in 1865, at his country home near Versailles, France.
In attendance at the dinner party were many abolitionists including Victor Hugo and Frederick Auguste Bartholdi, who had initially been retained to create a sculptured bust of Mr. DeLaboulaye.

Victor Hugo and Edouard DeLaboulaye were leaders of the French abolitionist movement.
They hated slavery and were in strong support of John Brown when he attempted to arm slaves in West Virginia for rebellion by raiding the armory at Harpers Ferry in 1859.
After John Brown failed and was hanged, Hugo and DeLaboulaye took up a collection among the French people and presented a gold metal to John Brown’s widow.

After Abraham Lincoln was elected president of the United States in 1861, the French liberals and abolitionists including Hugo, Bartholdi, and DeLaboulaye urged Lincoln to free the slaves even if civil war resulted.
Lincoln was told: “You would become the first country in history to have fought a war against itself to free the internal slave and you would go down in history as a truly great country and a beacon of light to all freedom loving people.” The French abolitionists saw the Emancipation Proclamation of 1863 as a worthless piece of paper since it only freed slaves in the Confederate controlled states where Lincoln had no jurisdiction and not in Union controlled states where Lincoln was still in authority.
When the war ended in 1865, French abolitionists were extremely happy and in addition to again urging Lincoln to free all slaves, DeLaboulaye and Bartholdi requested permission to build and dedicate a monument or colossal statuary to that freeing of all slaves in America.
When Abraham Lincoln was assassinated, DeLaboulaye again headed the abolitionists’ committee that presented a gold metal to Mrs. Lincoln, just as he had done for the widow of John Brown.

In 1871, Frederic Bartholdi at the urging of DeLaboulaye undertook a voyage to America to sale his idea of a colossal statue clearly symbolizing the end of chattel slavery in the United States.
He was armed with a large terracotta statue and numerous drawings to clearly illustrate his proposed Statue of Liberty.
The original African face of the Statue of Liberty was published in The New York Post dated June 17, 1986 as part of the centennial celebration.
Bartholdi found little American support for his African slave model.
In 1878, as the African head of Miss Liberty first went on display at the Universal Exposition in Paris, France, rampant reaction raged throughout the American South.

Bartholdi finally had to abandon his original ideas and changed the Statue of Liberty to the features the United States is now familiar with.
The African face was re-sculptured into the face of his mother Madame Bartholdi.
A tablet of law tucked into her folded arm that bears the date July 4, 1776, replaced the broken chains in the slave’s left hand.
Ironically, the chains were left at the feet but the meaning changed from broken American slavery to broken English tyranny.

On May 18, 1986 during the centennial celebration, The New York Times joined The New York Post in describing the original Statue of Liberty and the intention of DeLaboulaye and Bartholdi in presenting this statue to America.
Dr. Jack Felder sums it up clearly: “Once in place, Miss Liberty received a new meaning.
She was hailed as the ‘Mother of White Exiles,’ greeting European immigrants seeking freedom in America.
Nothing in the original conceptions of Bartholdi or DeLaboulaye envisioned this role for their statue.”  *Excerpt from Black People &amp; Their Place In World History By: Dr. Leroy Vaughn, MD, MBA*

"Joel A. Rogers and Dr. Auset Bakhufu have both written books documenting that at least five former presidents of the United States had Black people among their ancestors.
If one considers the fact that European men far outnumbered European women during the founding of this country, and that the rape and impregnation of an African female slave was not considered a crime, it is even more surprising that these two authors could not document Black ancestors among an ever larger number of former presidents.
The presidents they name include Thomas Jefferson, Andrew Jackson, Abraham Lincoln, Warren Harding, and Calvin Coolidge."

One of the best cases for black ancestry was against Warren G. Harding, the 29th President of the United States from 1921 to 1923, who never denied his ancestry.
When Republican leaders called on Harding to deny the "Negro" history, he said, "How should I know whether or not one of my ancestors might have jumped the fence."
William Chancellor, a White professor of economics and politics at Wooster College in Ohio, wrote a book on the Harding family genealogy and identified Black ancestors among both parents of President Harding.
Justice Department agents allegedly bought and destroyed all copies of this book.
Chancellor also said that Harding's only academic credentials included education at Iberia College, which was founded in order to educate fugitive slaves.

Andrew Jackson was the 7th president of the United States from 1829 to 1837.
The Virginia Magazine of History, Volume 29, says that Jackson was the son of a White woman from Ireland who had intermarried with a Negro.
The magazine also said that his eldest brother had been sold as a slave in Carolina.
Joel Rogers says that Andrew Jackson Sr. died long before President Andrew Jackson Jr. was born.
He says the president's mother then went to live on the Crawford farm where there were Negro slaves and that one of these men was Andrew Jr's father.
Another account of the "brother sold into slavery” story can be found in David Coyle's book entitled "Ordeal of the Presidency" (1960).

Thomas Jefferson was the 3rd president of the United States from 1801 to 1809.
The chief attack on Jefferson was in a book written by Thomas Hazard in 1867 called "The Johnny Cake Papers."
Hazard interviewed Paris Gardiner, who said he was present during the 1796 presidential campaign, when one speaker states that Thomas Jefferson was “a mean-spirited son of a half-breed Indian squaw and a Virginia mulatto father.” In his book entitled "The Slave Children of Thomas Jefferson," Samuel Sloan wrote that Jefferson destroyed all of the papers, portraits, and personal effects of his mother, Jane Randolph Jefferson, when she died on March 31, 1776.
He even wrote letters to every person who had ever received a letter from his mother, asking them to return that letter.
Sloan says, "There is something strange and even psychopathic about the lengths to which Thomas Jefferson went to destroy all remembrances of his mother, while saving over 18,000 copies of his own letters and other documents for posterity."

Abraham Lincoln was the 16th president of the United States from 1861 to 1865.
J.
A. Rogers quotes Lincoln's mother, Nancy Hanks, as saying that Abraham Lincoln was the illegitimate son of an African man.
William Herndon, Lincoln's law partner, said that Lincoln had very dark skin and coarse hair and that his mother was from an Ethiopian tribe.
In Herndon's book entitled "The Hidden Lincoln" he says that Thomas Lincoln could not have been Abraham Lincoln's father because he was sterile from childhood mumps and was later castrated.
Lincoln's presidential opponents made cartoon drawings depicting him as a Negro and nicknamed him “Abraham Africanus the First."

Calvin Coolidge was the 30th president of the United States, and he succeeded Warren Harding.
He proudly admitted that his mother was dark because of mixed Indian ancestry.
However, Dr. Bakhufu says that by 1800 the New England Indian was hardly any longer pure Indian, because they had mixed so often with Blacks.
Calvin Coolidge's mother's maiden name was "Moor."
In Europe the name "Moor" was given to all Black people just as the name Negro was used in America.

All of the presidents mentioned were able to pass for White and never acknowledged their Black ancestry.
Millions of other children who were descendants of former slaves have also been able to pass for White.
*Excerpt from Black People &amp; Their Place In World History By: Dr. Leroy Vaughn, MD, MBA*</entry>
  <entry author_id="1596019" end="584" start="558">"My father was a slave and my people died to build this country, and I'm going to stay right here and have a part of it, just like you.
And no fascist-minded people like you will drive me from it.
Is that clear?"
Paul Robeson (1898-1976) testimony before the House Un-American Activities Committee, June 12, 1956

"Tears will get you sympathy.
Sweat will get you change."
-- Jesse Jackson, minister and activist

"I am America.
I am the part you won't recognize.
But get used to me.
Black, confident, cocky; my name, not yours; my religion, not yours; my goals, my own; get used to me".
--Muhammad Ali(1942- )The Greatest (1975)

"If we accept and acquiesce in the face of discrimination, we accept the responsibility ourselves and allow those responsible to salve their conscience by believing that they have our acceptance and concurrence.
We should, therefore, protest openly everything... that smacks of discrimination or slander."
-- Mary McLeod Bethune (1875-1955) "Certain Unalienable Rights," What the Negro Wants, edited by Rayford W. Logan (1944)

"It is a peculiar sensation, this double-consciousness, this sense of always looking at one's self through the eyes of others.... One ever feels his twoness,—an American, a Negro; two souls, two thoughts, two unreconciled strivings; two warrings ideals in one dark body, whose dogged strength alone keeps it from being torn asunder."
--W.E.B.
Du Bois (1868-1963) The Souls of Black Folk (1903)

We should emphasize not Negro History, but the Negro in history.
What we need is not a history of selected races or nations, but the history of the world void of national bias, race hate, and religious prejudice.
-- Carter Woodson (1875-1950) on founding Negro History Week, 1926

"The common goal of 22 million Afro-Americans is respect as human beings, the God-given right to be a human being.
Our common goal is to obtain the human rights that America has been denying us.
We can never get civil rights in America until our human rights are first restored.
We will never be recognized as citizens there until we are first recognized as humans."
-- Malcolm X "Racism: the Cancer that is Destroying America," in Egyptian Gazette (Aug. 25 1964).</entry>
  <entry author_id="440983" end="596" start="584">Prior to the adoption of the term African American, several other terms had been used at various points in American history.
These included Negro, colored, Afro-Americans, and black.
To some extent, the history of these names can be found in the names of various organizations founded over the course of American history.
The "National Association for the Advancement of Colored People" is significantly older than the "United Negro College Fund", because the term "colored" had come to be seen as condenscending by the time of the UNCF's founding.
Nontheless, both Negro and colored remained common until the late 1960s.

During the 1960s, the terms "black" and "Afro-American" both came into vogue, with first "colored", and then later, Negro, both becoming viewed as derogatory.
However, by the mid-1970s, only "black" remained in widespread usage.
The reasons for this are unclear; perhaps it was the success of the "Black is beautiful" movement, or a rejection of the perceived militancy of the term "Afro American" (which many whites associated with such figures as Malcom X and Angela Davis).
For whatever reason, by 1980, "black" was accepted not only by a majority of persons of African descent, but also by virtually all white Americans.

During the 1980s, a popular movement to designate "African American" as the preferred term began.
The most influential proponent of this term during the 80s was Jesse Jackson and like-minded persons argued that "African American" was more in keeping with the United States immigrant tradition of "hyphenated Americans", which link people with their ancestors' geographic points of origin, and allowed people to assert cultural pride in the same way that, say, "Greek Americans", or "Polish Americans" did.
Using language that could have been borrowed from Malcolm X, Jackson successfully effected the change, first in the media, and then in the popular culture.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1596019" end="608" start="596">The term "African American" has been in common usage in the United States since the late 1980s, when large numbers of African Americans began to adopt the term self-referentially.
Black nationalist Malcolm X had favored the descriptive term "African American" as more historically and culturally defining over "Negro" and "black", and used the term at an OAAU (Organization of Afro American Unity) meeting in the mid-1960s, saying, "Twenty-two million African Americans - that's what we are - Africans who are in America."
Prior to the adoption of the term African American, several other terms had been used at various points in American history.
These included Negro, colored, Afro-American, and black.
To some extent, the history of these names can be found in the names of various organizations founded over the course of American history.
Civil rights organization the "National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP)", founded 1909, is significantly older than the philanthropic organization the "United Negro College Fund", founded 1944, because the term "colored" had come to be seen as condescending by the time of the UNCF's founding.
Nonetheless, both Negro and colored remained common until the late 1960s, especially is the southern United States.

Some African Americans began to abandon the terms "Black" and "Afro-American", which had become popular during the Black Power movement of the 1960s, adopting the autonym "African American" instead, some out of desire for an unabbreviated expression of their African heritage that could not be mistaken or derided as an allusion to the afro hairstyle, and some rejecting the perceived militancy of the term "Afro American" (which many whites associated with such figures as Malcolm X and Angela Davis).
Due to the legacy of the Black Power/black is beautiful movement, by 1980, the term "black" was accepted as a term of pride by a majority of Americans of African descent, but also became the referential term applied by white Americans in general.
In addition to black, the term African American slowly became increasingly popular, and during the 1980's, a popular movement to designate "African American" as the preferred term for American blacks began.
Jackson and like-minded persons argued that "African American" was more in keeping with the United States immigrant tradition of "hyphenated Americans", which link people with their ancestors' geographic points of origin, and allowed people to assert cultural pride in addition to maintaining their American national identity.
Using language reminiscent of Malcolm X, Jackson successfully effected the change, first in the media, and then in the popular culture.</entry>
  <entry author_id="28107" end="680" start="608">The term "African American" has been in common usage in the United States since the late 1980s.
Large numbers of African Americans began to adopt the term self-referentially in preference to "Negro", which was popular before the mid 1960s and "black" since the late 1960s.
Black nationalist Malcolm X had favored the descriptive term "African American" as more historically and culturally defining over either prior term, and used the term at an OAAU (Organization of Afro American Unity) meeting in the mid-1960s, saying, "Twenty-two million African Americans - that's what we are - Africans who are in America."
Asian Americans had also standardized on combining the name of a continent and nationality in preference to "oriental" after the 1970s.
Prior to the adoption of the term African American, several other terms had been used at various points in American history.
These included Negro, colored, Afro-American, and black.
To some extent, the history of these names can be found in the names of various organizations founded over the course of American history.
Civil rights organization the "National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP)", founded 1909, is significantly older than the philanthropic organization the "United Negro College Fund", founded 1944, because the term "colored" had come to be seen as condescending by the time of the UNCF's founding.
Nonetheless, both Negro and colored remained common until the late 1960s, especially in the southern United States.

Some African Americans began to abandon the terms "Black" and "Afro-American", which had become popular during the Black Power movement of the 1960s, adopting the autonym "African American" instead, some out of desire for an unabbreviated expression of their African heritage that could not be mistaken or derided as an allusion to the afro hairstyle, and some rejecting the perceived militancy of the term "Afro American" (which many whites associated with such figures as Malcolm X and Angela Davis).
Due to the legacy of the Black Power/black is beautiful movement, by 1980, the term "black" was accepted as a term of pride by a majority of Americans of African descent, but also became the referential term applied by white Americans in general.
In addition to black, the term African American slowly became increasingly popular, and during the 1980s, a popular movement to designate "African American" as the preferred term for American blacks began.
The most influential proponent of this term during the 1980s was Jesse Jackson.
Jackson and like-minded persons argued that "African American" was more in keeping with the United States immigrant tradition of "hyphenated Americans", which link people with their ancestors' geographic points of origin, and allowed people to assert cultural pride in addition to maintaining their American national identity.
Using language reminiscent of Malcolm X, Jackson successfully effected the change, first in the media, and then in the popular culture.

During the Progressive Era, black members of the middle class attempted improving the conditions of their ethnicity.
This movement was strongest in the Southern United States and it often revolved around black southern universities such as Tuskegee University or Atlanta University, academic journals, and the Episcopal Church.
Like white progressives, black progressives helped the working class through charitable means while supporting political changes that increased the role of the state in creating socioeconomic equity, as opposed to equality.
Many black progressives] were elitist and often condescending towards those they were intent on helping, akin to white progressives' attitudes and actions towards European immigrants.
Black progressives were successful in their charitable efforts, but often were not concerned with issues like racial segregation.
Instead, they supported a social darwinist mentality with the hope that blacks through hardwork and education could accelerate their social evolution.
The plight of most black people did not improve during this time due to racist policies supported by many whites and white vigilante action.

Though the majority of contemporary African Americans are the descendents of enslaved Africans from West and Central Africa, some researchers have claimed that African presence in North America predates the arrival of Christopher Columbus.
Writers on the African presence in pre-Columbian America include Ivan van Sertima, Leo Wiener, Kofi Wangara, R.A. Jairazbhoy, Legrand H. Clegg II, and Floyd W. Hayes III.
According to Van Sertima, "The African presence in America before Columbus is of importance not only to African and American history, but to the history of world civilizations.
The African presence is proven by stone heads, terra cottas, skeletons, artifacts, techniques and inscriptions, by oral traditions and documented history, by botanical, linguistic and cultural data."
Among the evidence commonly cited is an immense carved head with supposedly African-like features found in Central America in 1862.
Similar carvings dating back to around 800 B.C have been found since.
Step pyramids, such as were built in Egypt, and Peruvian looms resembling those found in Africa have also been found.
Certain species of plants once only indigenous to Africa, including strains of cotton and bananas, appear to have been introduced into the Americas from Africa prior to 1492.
Numerous Native American words are similar to African ones, and early European explorers such as Vasco Núñez de Balboa wrote of seeing African captives in Indian villages and of hearing of isolated tribes of blacks.
These theories are considered inaccurate by some mainstream historians who find the evidence unpersuasive.
Van Sertima has also suggested that Malian prince Abubakari II may have led a voyage to the New World around 1312; Abubakari certainly did abdicate the Malian throne to explore the Atlantic, but there is no proof he made it to the Americas.
Recent research indicates that one of the most famous landmarks in the United States, the Statue of Liberty was originally intended to represent the end of American slavery and originally modeled after a black woman.
According to various studies, including research by indepedent scholars and acclaimed publications such as the New York Times and the New York Post, the liberation of African American slaves may have been the primary inspiration for the creation of a Statue of Liberation for Edouard Rene LeFebvre DeLaboulaye.
He recruited a young sculptor, Frederic Auguste Bartholdi, to create a Black female slave statue holding a broken chain in her left hand and with broken chains of slavery at her feet.
The official web site of the Statue of Liberty states that the statue was given to the people of the United States by the people of France as an expression of friendship and to commemorate the centennial of American Independence (1776).
The Encyclopedia Britannica states Bartholdi designed the Statue of Liberty as a monument to the Franco-American alliance of 1778.
However, there is controversy by some scholars about whether this is true.

Edouard Rene LeFebvre DeLaboulaye, an internationally renowned lawyer and author of a three-volume history of the United States, first discussed the idea of a symbol to represent the end of U.S. slavery at a dinner party in 1865, at his country home near Versailles, France.
In attendance at the dinner party were many abolitionists including Victor Hugo and Frederick Auguste Bartholdi, who had initially been retained to create a sculptured bust of Mr. DeLaboulaye.
Victor Hugo and Edouard DeLaboulaye were leaders of the French abolitionist movement.
They hated slavery and were in strong support of John Brown when he attempted to arm slaves in West Virginia for rebellion by raiding the armory at Harpers Ferry in 1859.
After John Brown failed and was hanged, Hugo and DeLaboulaye took up a collection among the French people and presented a gold medal to John Brown’s widow.

After Abraham Lincoln was elected president of the United States in 1861, the French liberals and abolitionists including Hugo, Bartholdi, and DeLaboulaye urged Lincoln to free the slaves even if civil war resulted.
Lincoln was told: "You would become the first country in history to have fought a war against itself to free the internal slave and you would go down in history as a truly great country and a beacon of light to all freedom loving people."
The French abolitionists saw the Emancipation Proclamation of 1863 as a worthless piece of paper since it only freed slaves in the Confederate controlled states where Lincoln had no jurisdiction and not in Union controlled states where Lincoln was still in authority.
When the war ended in 1865, French abolitionists were extremely happy and in addition to again urging Lincoln to free all slaves, DeLaboulaye and Bartholdi requested permission to build and dedicate a monument or colossal statuary to that freeing of all slaves in America.
When Abraham Lincoln was assassinated, DeLaboulaye again headed the abolitionists’ committee that presented a gold medal to Mrs. Lincoln, just as he had done for the widow of John Brown.

In 1871, Frederic Bartholdi at the urging of DeLaboulaye undertook a voyage to America to sale his idea of a colossal statue clearly symbolizing the end of chattel slavery in the United States.
He was armed with a large terracotta statue and numerous drawings to clearly illustrate his proposed Statue of Liberty.
The original African face of the Statue of Liberty was published in The New York Post dated June 17, 1986 as part of the centennial celebration.
Bartholdi found little American support for his African slave model.
In 1878, as the African head of Miss Liberty first went on display at the Universal Exposition in Paris, France, rampant reaction raged throughout the American South.
Bartholdi finally had to abandon his original ideas and changed the Statue of Liberty to the features the United States is now familiar with.
The African face was re-sculptured into the face of his mother Madame Bartholdi.
A tablet of law tucked into her folded arm that bears the date July 4, 1776, replaced the broken chains in the slave’s left hand.
Ironically, the chains were left at the feet but the meaning changed from broken American slavery to broken English tyranny.

On May 18, 1986 during the centennial celebration, The New York Times joined The New York Post in describing the original Statue of Liberty and the intention of DeLaboulaye and Bartholdi in presenting this statue to America.
Dr. Jack Felder sums it up clearly: "Once in place, Miss Liberty received a new meaning.
She was hailed as the ‘Mother of White Exiles,’ greeting European immigrants seeking freedom in America.
Nothing in the original conceptions of Bartholdi or DeLaboulaye envisioned this role for their statue."
*Excerpt from Black People &amp; Their Place In World History By: Dr. Leroy Vaughn, MD, MBA*

Other research suggests that Bartholdi's creation was inspired by his trip to Egypt with four artist friends, and there he developed the idea of creating a gigantic statue to embellish the entrance to the Suez Canal (the construction of which began around 1859).
Upon his return, he created a model and presented it to a friend, who described it as follows: "It was a beautiful woman clothed in the ancient style, with a headdress in the style of the Egyptian sphinx…The right arm carried the lamp of a lighthouse, the left arm fell along the side of the body.
In the mind of the young artist, this statue was to serve as a lighthouse at Suez, at the precise point where the canal opens into the Red Sea."
Controversy to the historical roots and intentions of the Statue of Liberty lies in whether it was intended as popularly professed, or was it inspired by the then newfound freedom of slaves.
Lack of documentation as to who served as the model for the statue (if, indeed, Bartholdi even used a model) has prompted speculation about her identity.
Conjecture about the identity includes Bartholdi’s mother, his wife, his mistress, a glove shop owner in Nancy, and the manager of a brothel in Paris.
Apocrypha circulating on the Internet claim that the model was a black woman.
There have been some claims that the research into this matter is not legitimate, and that the whole controversy began as an urban legend circulated through the internet and that while freed slaves may have played a role in the French inspiration for the Statue, the primary issue was the representation of the freedoms of the United States in general and that many statements in the past regarding this matter have been misinterpreted.
Whoever the original model was or whatever the true origins of the statue may be, the statue stands today as a symbol of liberty.</entry>
</article>
