<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="307" title="Abraham Lincoln" authors="6" lines="338">
  <entry author_id="21013" end="19" start="0">Only one survived into adulthood.In the years following his death, attempts were made to steal the Lincoln's body and hold it for ransom.
Around 1900, Tad Lincoln decided that, in order to prevent body theft, it was necessary to build a permanent crypt for his father.
Lincoln's coffin would be encased in concrete several feet thick, and surronded by a cage, and burried beneath a rock slab.
On September 26, 1901, Lincoln's body was exhumed so that it could be reinterred in the newly built crypt.
However, those present (there were 23 of them, including Tad Lincoln) feared that his body might have been stolen in the intervening years.
They decided to open the coffin and check.

When they did, they were amazed at the sight.
Lincoln's body was almost perfectly preserved.
It had been embalmed so many times following his death that his body had not decayed.
In fact, he was perfectly recognizable, even more than thirty years after his death.
On his chest, they could see red, white, and blue specs - remanents of the American flag he was buried with, which had since disintegrated.

"All 23 of the people who viewed the remains of Mr. Lincoln have long since passed away.
The last one was Fleetwood Lindley who died on February 1, 1963.
Three days before he died, Mr. Lindley was interviewed.
He said, "Yes, his face was chalky white.
His clothes were mildewed.
And I was allowed to hold one of the leather straps as we lowered the casket for the concrete to be poured.
I was not scared at the time but I slept with Lincoln for the next six months."
" ()</entry>
  <entry author_id="6523" end="90" start="19">Lincoln was born on February 12, 1809, on a farm in LaRue County, Kentucky (* then Hardin Co., three miles south of the town of Hodgenville), to Thomas Lincoln and Nancy Hanks.
Lincoln moved at a young age to Indiana, then later to New Salem, Illinois.He served as a captain in the U.S. Army during the Black Hawk War.
He later tried his hand at several business and political ventures.
He was highly regarded as a practicing lawyer.
Lincoln served four terms in the Illinois State Legislature, was briefly elected to Congress (1846), and had a successful law practice in Illinois both before and after his single term in the House of Representatives.
It is commonly held that Lincoln had bipolar disorder, which greatly moderated after his marriage to Mary Ann Todd in 1842.
Some scholars have suggested that Lincoln enjoyed a romantic relationship with his roommate and longtime friend, shopkeeper Joshua Speed.

Another important example of Lincoln's skills as a railroad lawyer was a lawsuit over a tax exemption that the state granted to the Illinois Central Railroad.
McLean County argued that the state had no authority to grant such an exemption, and it sought to impose taxes on the railroad notwithstanding.
In January 1856, the Illinois Supreme Court delivered its opinion upholding the tax exemption, accepting Lincoln's arguments.

During his unsuccessful 1858 campaign for the United States Senate against Stephen A. Douglas, Lincoln debated Douglas in a series of events which represented a national discussion on the issues that were about to split the nation in two.
The Lincoln-Douglas debates presaged the Presidential election of 1860, in which Douglas and Lincoln were once again opponents.
On November 6, 1860, Lincoln was elected as the 16th President of the United States, the first Republican to hold that office.

Shortly after his election, the South made it clear that secession was inevitable, which greatly increased tension across the nation.
President-elect Lincoln survived an assassination attempt in Baltimore, Maryland, and on February 23, 1861 arrived secretly in disguise to Washington, DC.
The South ridiculed Lincoln for this seemingly cowardly act, but the efforts at security may have been prudent.

At Lincoln's inauguration on March 4, 1861, the Turners formed Lincoln's bodyguard; and a sizable garrison of federal troops was always present, ready to protect the president and the capital from rebel invasion.
Lincoln's actual position on freeing enslaved African-Americans is controversial today, despite the frequency and clarity with which he stated it both before his election to president (i.e. Lincoln-Douglas Debates of 1858) and after (see Lincoln's First Inaugural) He stated his position forcefully and succinctly in a letter to Horace Greeley of August 22, 1862.
However, at the time of the writing this letter, Lincoln was already leaning towards emancipation, which would lead to the Emancipation Proclamation.

Also revealing was his letter a year later to James Conkling of August 26, 1863, which included the following excerpt: Lincoln is often credited with freeing enslaved African-Americans with the Emancipation Proclamation, though this only freed the slaves in areas of the Confederacy not yet controlled by the Union; in occupied and northern territories, slaves were not freed.
However, the proclamation made abolishing slavery in the rebel states an official war goal and it did become the impetus for the enactment of the 13th and 14th Amendments of the United States Constitution which respectively abolished slavery and established the federal enforcement of civil rights.
He showed tremendous leadership to the Union populace during the war as evidenced by the Gettysburg Address, a speech dedicating a cemetery of Union soldiers from the Battle of Gettysburg in 1863.
While most of the speakers—e.g.
Edward Everett—at the event spoke at length, some for hours, Lincoln's few choice words resonated across the nation and across history, defying Lincoln's own prediction that "The world will little note, nor long remember what we say here."
While there is little documentation of the other speeches of the day, Lincoln's address is regarded as one of the great speeches in history.
The war was a source of constant frustration for the president, and it occupied nearly all of his time.
After repeated frustrations with General George McClellan and a string of other unsuccessful commanding generals, Lincoln made the fateful decision to appoint a radical and somewhat scandalous army commander: General Ulysses S. Grant.
Grant would apply his military knowledge and leadership talents to bring about the close of the Civil War.

In 1864, Lincoln was the first and only President to face a presidential election during a civil war.
The long war and the issue of emancipation appeared to be severely hampering his prospects and an electoral defeat appeared likely against the Democratic nominee, George McClellan.
However, a series of timely Union victories shortly before election day changed the situation dramatically and Lincoln was reelected.

During the Civil War, Lincoln held powers no previous president had wielded; he suspended the writ of habeas corpus and frequently imprisoned Southern spies and sympathizers without trial.
On the other hand, he often commuted executions.Lincoln met frequently with Grant as the war ended.
The two men planned matters of reconstruction, and it was evident to all that the two men held one another in high regard.
During their last meeting, on April 14, 1865 (Good Friday), Lincoln invited General Grant to a social engagement for that evening.
Grant declined (his wife was not eager to spend time with Mary Todd Lincoln).

Without the General and his wife, or his bodyguard Ward Hill Lamon, to whom he related his famous dream of his own assassination, the Lincolns left to attend a play at Ford's Theater.
The play was Our American Cousin, a musical comedy by the British writer Tom Taylor (1817-1880).
As Lincoln sat in the balcony, John Wilkes Booth, an actor and Southern sympathizer from Virginia, crept up behind Lincoln in his State Box and aimed a single-shot, round-slug.44 caliber derringer at the President's head, firing at point-blank range.
He shouted "Sic semper tyrannis!"
(Latin: "Thus always to tyrants," and Virginia's state motto; some versions say he said "The south is avenged!")
and jumped from the balcony to the stage below, breaking his leg in the fall.

The conspirators had planned to kill a number of other government officials at the same time, but for various reasons Lincoln's was the only assassination actually carried out.
Booth managed to limp to his horse and escape, and the mortally wounded president was taken to a house across the street, now called the Petersen House, where he lay in a coma for some time before he quietly expired.
Abraham Lincoln was officially pronounced dead at 7:21 AM, in April 15, 1865.

Booth and several of his companions were eventually captured and either hanged or imprisoned.
Booth himself was shot when discovered holed up in a barn.
Four people were tried by military tribunal and hanged for the assassination (David Herold, George Atzerodt, Lewis Powell (aka Lewis Payne), and Mary Surratt, the first woman ever executed in the United States.)
Three people were sentenced to life imprisonment (Michael O'Laughlin, Samuel Arnold, and Samuel Mudd).
Edman Spangler was sentenced to six years imprisonment.
John Surratt, tried later by a civilian court, was acquitted.
The fairness of the convictions, particularly of Mary Surratt, have been called into question, and there are doubts as to the exact degree of her involvement, if any, in the conspiracy.

Lincoln's body was carried by train in a grand funeral procession through several states on its way back to Illinois.
The nation mourned a man who many viewed as the savior of the United States, and protector and defender of what Lincoln himself called "the government of the people, by the people, and for the people."
Critics say that in fact the Confederates were the ones defending the right to self-governance and Lincoln was suppressing that right.
They further insist that Lincoln only preserved the union in a geographical sense while destroying its voluntary nature.
President Lincoln and Mary Todd Lincoln had four sons.
Only one survived into adulthood.Lincoln has no living descendants.
Lincoln was buried in Oak Ridge Cemetery in Springfield where a 177-foot tall granite tomb surmounted with several bronze statues of Lincoln was constructed by 1874.
Lincoln's wife and three of his four sons are also buried there (Robert is buried in Arlington National Cemetery).
In the years following his death, attempts were made to steal Lincoln's body and hold it for ransom.
Around 1900, Robert Todd Lincoln decided that, in order to prevent body theft, it was necessary to build a permanent crypt for his father.
Lincoln's coffin would be encased in concrete several feet thick, surrounded by a cage, and buried beneath a rock slab.
On September 26, 1901, Lincoln's body was exhumed so that it could be reinterred in the newly built crypt.
However, those present (there were 23 of them, including Robert Lincoln) feared that his body might have been stolen in the intervening years.
They decided to open the coffin and check.

When they did, they were amazed at the sight.
Lincoln's body was almost perfectly preserved.
It had been embalmed so many times following his death that his body had not decayed.
In fact, he was perfectly recognizable, even more than thirty years after his death.
On his chest, they could see red, white, and blue specs — remnants of the American flag with which he was buried, which had by then disintegrated.</entry>
  <entry author_id="12028" end="113" start="90">The two men planned matters of reconstruction, and it was evident to all that the two men held one another in high regard.
During their last meeting, on April 14, 1865 (Good Friday), Lincoln invited General Grant to a social engagement for that evening.
Grant declined (his wife was not eager to spend time with Mary Todd Lincoln).

Without the General and his wife, or his bodyguard Ward Hill Lamon, to whom he related his famous dream of his own assassination, the Lincolns left to attend a play at Ford's Theater.
The play was Our American Cousin, a musical comedy by the British writer Tom Taylor (1817-1880).
As Lincoln sat in the balcony, John Wilkes Booth, an actor and Southern sympathizer from Virginia, crept up behind Lincoln in his State Box and aimed a single-shot, round-slug.44 caliber Deringer at the President's head, firing at point-blank range.
He shouted "Sic semper tyrannis!"
(Latin: "Thus always to tyrants," and Virginia's state motto; some versions say he added "The south is avenged!")
and jumped from the balcony to the stage below, breaking his leg in the fall.

The conspirators had planned to kill a number of other government officials at the same time, but for various reasons Lincoln's was the only assassination actually carried out.
Booth managed to limp to his horse and escape, and the mortally wounded president was taken to a house across the street, now called the Petersen House, where he lay in a coma for some time before he quietly expired.
Abraham Lincoln was officially pronounced dead at 7:21 AM, in April 15, 1865.

Booth and several of his companions were eventually captured and either hanged or imprisoned.
Booth himself was shot when discovered holed up in a barn.
Four people were tried by military tribunal and hanged for the assassination (David Herold, George Atzerodt, Lewis Powell (aka Lewis Payne), and Mary Surratt, the first woman ever executed in the United States.)
Three people were sentenced to life imprisonment (Michael O'Laughlin, Samuel Arnold, and Samuel Mudd).
Edman Spangler was sentenced to six years imprisonment.
John Surratt, tried later by a civilian court, was acquitted.
The fairness of the convictions, particularly of Mary Surratt, have been called into question, and there are doubts as to the exact degree of her involvement, if any, in the conspiracy.

Lincoln's body was carried by train in a grand funeral procession through several states on its way back to Illinois.
The nation mourned a man who many viewed as the savior of the United States, and protector and defender of what Lincoln himself called "the government of the people, by the people, and for the people."
Critics say that in fact the Confederates were the ones defending the right to self-governance and Lincoln was suppressing that right.
They further insist that Lincoln only preserved the union in a geographical sense while destroying its voluntary nature.</entry>
  <entry author_id="231620" end="139" start="113">Lincoln had a contentious relationship with General George McClellan, who led the Northern war effort after the retirement of Winfield Scott in late 1861.
Lincoln wished to take an active part in planning the Northern war strategy despite his inexperience in military affairs.
Lincoln's strategic priorities were two-fold: First, to ensure that Washington, DC, was well-defended; and second, to conduct an aggressive war effort in hopes of ending the war sooner and appeasing the Northern public, who rabidly pushed for an offensive war.
McClellan, a career military man and West Point graduate, took a more cautious approach.
McClellan took several months to plan and execute his Seven Days campaign to invade Richmond by moving the Army of the Potomac by boat to the peninsula between the James and York Rivers.
McClellan's delay irritated Lincoln, as did McClellan's calculation that the entire Confederate army would be required to fight off his attack, and that thus no troops were needed to defend Washington, D.C. Lincoln insisted on holding some of McClellan's troops to defend Washington, a decision McClellan blamed for the ultimate failure of his Peninsular Campaign.

McClellan, a lifelong Democrat who was tempermentally conservative, was fired after releasing his Harrison's Landing Letter, where he offered unsolicited political advice to Lincoln urging caution in the war effort.
McClellan's letter incensed Radical Republicans, who succesfully pressured Lincoln to appoint fellow Republican John Pope as head of the Army of the Potomac.
Pope complied with Lincoln's strategic desire for the Army of the Potomac to take Richmond from the North, thus guarding the Washington, DC.
However, Pope was soundly defeated st Second Bull Run during the summer of 1862, forcing the Army of the Potomac to abandon Virginia for the time being, leading to Pope's being sent West to command against the American Indians.
Lincoln restored McClellan to effective command in time for the Battle of Antietam in September of that year.
It was Union victory in that battle that allowed Lincoln to release his Emancipation Proclamation.
Lincoln relieved McClellan of command shortly after the 1862 midterm elections and appointed Republican Ambrose Burnside to head the Army of the Potomac, who promised to follow through on Lincoln's strategic vision for a sack of Richmond from the North.
After Burnside was embarrassingly routed at Fredericksburg, John Hooker assumed command, but was routed at Chancellorsville and also relieved of command.

After Union victory at Gettysburg and months of inactivity for the Army of the Potomac, Lincoln made the fateful decision to appoint a radical and somewhat scandalous army commander: General Ulysses S. Grant, who was disfavored by Republican hardliners because he had been a Democrat.
Grant would daringly wage his bloody Wilderness campaign, characterized by shockingly high Union losses at battles such as Cold Harbor and the Crater.
Grant's aggressive campaign, however, would eventually result in the Union taking Richmond and bringing the war to a close in Spring 1865.

Lincoln, perhaps reflecting his lack of military experience, developed a keen curiosity with military campaigning during the war.
Lincoln continually visited battle sights and seemed fascinated by watching scenes of war.
During Jubal Early's raid into Washington, DC, in 1864, Lincoln had to be told to duck his head to avoid being shot observing the scenes of battle.
Lincoln was more successful in giving the war meaning to Northern civilians through his oratorical skills.

On the other hand, he often commuted executions.

He was determined to take a course that would not permanently alienate the former Confederate states, and throughout the war Lincoln urged speedy elections under generous terms in areas behind Union lines.
This irritated congressional Republicans, who urged a more stringent Reconstruction policy.
One of Lincoln's few vetoes during his term was of the Wade-Davis bill, an effort by congressional Republicans to impose harsher Reconstruction terms on the Confederate areas.
Republicans in Congress retaliated by refusing to seat representatives elected from Louisiana, Arkansas, and Tennessee during the war under Lincoln's generous terms.</entry>
  <entry author_id="252510" end="152" start="139">Later, when Lincoln became more renown, reporters and storytellers often exaggerated the poverty and obscurity of Lincoln's birth.
In fact, Lincoln's father Thomas was a respected and relatively affluent citizen of the Kentucky backcountry.
He had purchased the Sinking Spring Farm in December 1808 for $200 cash and assumption of a debt.

In 1811, a prior land claim filed in Hardin Circuit Court forced the Lincolns to move from what had been their property.
Thomas continued legal action until he lost the case in 1815.
Money spent on the lawsuit contributed to family difficulties.
They were able to lease 30 acres of a 230-acre farm on Knob Creek a few miles away, where they then moved.
In a valley of the Rolling Fork River, this was some of the best farmland in the area.
At this time, Lincoln's father was a respected community member and a successful farmer and carpenter.
Lincoln's earliest recollections are from this farm.
In 1815, another claimant sought to eject the family from the Knob Creek farm.
Frustrated with litigation and lack of security provided by Kentucky courts, Thomas decided to move to Indiana, which had been surveyed by the federal government, making land titles more secure.
Historians believe that these problems motivated Abraham to later learn surveying and become an attorney.</entry>
  <entry author_id="725770" end="338" start="152">We've taken this small selection of Lincoln quotations from the letters, speeches and other documents on this Web site.
Every quotation includes a link to its original source for further reading.
You can also see a Quote of the Week page, featuring quotations which once appeared on the home page, which are usually different from those below.

"Every blade of grass is a study; and to produce two, where there was but one, is both a profit and a pleasure."
--From the September 30, 1859 Address before the Wisconsin State Agricultural Society "This leads to the further reflection, that no other human occupation opens so wide a field for the profitable and agreeable combination of labor with cultivated thought, as agriculture.
I know of nothing so pleasant to the mind, as the discovery of anything which is at once new and valuable -- nothing which so lightens and sweetens toil, as the hopeful pursuit of such discovery.
And how vast, and how varied a field is agriculture, for such discovery.
The mind, already trained to thought, in the country school, or higher school, cannot fail to find there an exhaustless source of profitable enjoyment."
--From the September 30, 1859 Address before the Wisconsin State Agricultural Society

"Every man is said to have his peculiar ambition.
Whether it be true or not, I can say for one that I have no other so great as that of being truly esteemed of my fellow men, by rendering myself worthy of their esteem.
How far I shall succeed in gratifying this ambition, is yet to be developed."
--From the March 9, 1832 First Political Announcement "You are ambitious, which, within reasonable bounds, does good rather than harm."
--From the January 26, 1863 Letter to Joseph Hooker

"There is no grievance that is a fit object of redress by mob law."
--From the January 27, 1838 Lyceum Address "Plainly, the central idea of secession, is the essence of anarchy."
--From the March 4, 1861 Inaugural Address

"At what point then is the approach of danger to be expected?
I answer, if it ever reach us, it must spring up amongst us.
It cannot come from abroad.
If destruction be our lot, we must ourselves be its author and finisher.
As a nation of freemen, we must live through all time, or die by suicide."
--From the January 27, 1838 Lyceum Address

"I have never had a feeling politically that did not spring from the sentiments embodied in the Declaration of Independence."
--From the February 22, 1861 Address in Independence Hall "Four score and seven years ago our fathers brought forth on this continent, a new nation, conceived in Liberty, and dedicated to the proposition that all men are created equal."
--From the November 19, 1863 Gettysburg Address

"If you are resolutely determined to make a lawyer of yourself, the thing is more than half done already."
--From the November 5, 1855 Letter to Isham Reavis "I know not how to aid you, save in the assurance of one of mature age, and much severe experience, that you can not fail, if you resolutely determine, that you will not."
--From the July 22, 1860 Letter to George Latham

"The dogmas of the quiet past, are inadequate to the stormy present.
The occasion is piled high with difficulty, and we must rise -- with the occasion.
As our case is new, so we must think anew, and act anew.
We must disentrall ourselves, and then we shall save our country."
--From the December 1, 1862 Message to Congress

"The leading rule for the lawyer, as for the man of every other calling, is diligence.
Leave nothing for to-morrow which can be done to-day."
--From the July 1, 1850 Notes for a Law Lecture

"Neither let us be slandered from our duty by false accusations against us, nor frightened from it by menaces of destruction to the Government nor of dungeons to ourselves.
LET US HAVE FAITH THAT RIGHT MAKES MIGHT, AND IN THAT FAITH, LET US, TO THE END, DARE TO DO OUR DUTY AS WE UNDERSTAND IT."
--From the February 27, 1860 Cooper Union Address

"Upon the subject of education, not presuming to dictate any plan or system respecting it, I can only say that I view it as the most important subject which we as a people can be engaged in."
--From the March 9, 1832 First Political Announcement "Mr. Clay's lack of a more perfect early education, however it may be regretted generally, teaches at least one profitable lesson; it teaches that in this country, one can scarcely be so poor, but that, if he will, he can acquire sufficient education to get through the world respectably."
--From the July 6, 1852 Eulogy on Henry Clay

"A capacity, and taste, for reading, gives access to whatever has already been discovered by others.
It is the key, or one of the keys, to the already solved problems.
And not only so.
It gives a relish, and facility, for successfully pursuing the unsolved ones."
--From the September 30, 1859 Address before the Wisconsin State Agricultural Society

"The old general rule was that educated people did not perform manual labor.
They managed to eat their bread, leaving the toil of producing it to the uneducated.
This was not an insupportable evil to the working bees, so long as the class of drones remained very small.
But now, especially in these free States, nearly all are educated--quite too nearly all, to leave the labor of the uneducated, in any wise adequate to the support of the whole.
It follows from this that henceforth educated people must labor.
Otherwise, education itself would become a positive and intolerable evil.
No country can sustain, in idleness, more than a small percentage of its numbers.
The great majority must labor at something productive."
--From the September 30, 1859 Address before the Wisconsin State Agricultural Society

"And by virtue of the power, and for the purpose aforesaid, I do order and declare that all persons held as slaves within said designated States, and parts of States, are, and henceforward shall be free; and that the Executive government of the United States, including the military and naval authorities thereof, will recognize and maintain the freedom of said persons."
--From the January 1, 1863 Final Emancipation Proclamation "You dislike the emancipation proclamation; and, perhaps, would have it retracted.
You say it is unconstitutional -- I think differently."
--From the August 26, 1863 Letter to James Conkling

"But the proclamation, as law, either is valid, or is not valid.
If it is not valid, it needs no retraction.
If it is valid, it can not be retracted, any more than the dead can be brought to life."
--From the August 26, 1863 Letter to James Conkling

"Those who deny freedom to others, deserve it not for themselves; and, under a just God, can not long retain it."
--From the April 6, 1859 Letter to Henry Pierce "I have here stated my purpose according to my view of official duty; and I intend no modification of my oft-expressed personal wish that all men everywhere could be free."
--From the August 22, 1862 Letter to Horace Greeley

"In giving freedom to the slave, we assure freedom to the free -- honorable alike in what we give, and what we preserve.
We shall nobly save, or meanly lose, the last best, hope of earth."
--From the December 1, 1862 Message to Congress

"We have, as all will agree, a free Government, where every man has a right to be equal with every other man.
In this great struggle, this form of Government and every form of human right is endangered if our enemies succeed."
--From the August 22, 1864 Speech to the One Hundred Sixty-fourth Ohio Regiment

"Towering genius distains a beaten path.
It seeks regions hitherto unexplored."
--From the January 27, 1838 Lyceum Address

"In the untimely loss of your noble son, our affliction here, is scarcely less than your own.
So much of promised usefulness to one's country, and of bright hopes for one's self and friends, have rarely been so suddenly dashed, as in his fall."
--From the May 25, 1861 Letter to Ephraim D. and Phoebe Ellsworth "In this sad world of ours, sorrow comes to all; and, to the young, it comes with bitterest agony, because it takes them unawares."
--From the December 23, 1862 Letter to Fanny McCullough

"I believe it is an established maxim in morals that he who makes an assertion without knowing whether it is true or false, is guilty of falsehood; and the accidental truth of the assertion, does not justify or excuse him."
--From the August 11, 1846 Letter to Allen N. Ford "Let no young man choosing the law for a calling for a moment yield to the popular belief -- resolve to be honest at all events; and if in your own judgment you cannot be an honest lawyer, resolve to be honest without being a lawyer."
--From the July 1, 1850 Notes for a Law Lecture

"John Brown's effort was peculiar.
It was not a slave insurrection.
It was an attempt by white men to get up a revolt among slaves, in which the slaves refused to participate."
--From the February 27, 1860 Cooper Union Address

"Every man is proud of what he does well; and no man is proud of what he does not do well.
With the former, his heart is in his work; and he will do twice as much of it with less fatigue.
The latter performs a little imperfectly, looks at it in disgust, turns from it, and imagines himself exceedingly tired.
The little he has done, comes to nothing, for want of finishing."
--From the September 30, 1859 Address before the Wisconsin State Agricultural Society "By the 'mud-sill' theory it is assumed that labor and education are incompatible; and any practical combination of them impossible.
According to that theory, a blind horse upon a tread-mill, is a perfect illustration of what a laborer should be -- all the better for being blind, that he could not tread out of place, or kick understandingly.
According to that theory, the education of laborers, is not only useless, but pernicious, and dangerous.
In fact, it is, in some sort, deemed a misfortune that laborers should have heads at all."
--From the September 30, 1859 Address before the Wisconsin State Agricultural Society

"Let every American, every lover of liberty, every well wisher to his posterity, swear by the blood of the Revolution, never to violate in the least particular, the laws of the country; and never to tolerate their violation by others."
--From the January 27, 1838 Lyceum Address "Let reverence for the laws, be breathed by every American mother, to the lisping babe, that prattles on her lap -- let it be taught in schools, in seminaries, and in colleges; let it be written in Primers, spelling books, and in Almanacs; -- let it be preached from the pulpit, proclaimed in legislative halls, and enforced in courts of justice.
And, in short, let it become the political religion of the nation; and let the old and the young, the rich and the poor, the grave and the gay, of all sexes and tongues, and colors and conditions, sacrifice unceasingly upon its altars."
--From the January 27, 1838 Lyceum Address

"Discourage litigation.
Persuade your neighbors to compromise whenever you can.
Point out to them how the nominal winner is often a real loser -- in fees, expenses, and waste of time.
As a peacemaker the lawyer has a superior opportunity of being a good man.
There will still be business enough."
--From the July 1, 1850 Notes for a Law Lecture "Never stir up litigation.
A worse man can scarcely be found than one who does this.
Who can be more nearly a fiend than he who habitually overhauls the register of deeds in search of defects in titles, whereon to stir up strife, and put money in his pocket?"
--From the July 1, 1850 Notes for a Law Lecture

"The man does not live who is more devoted to peace than I am.
None who would do more to preserve it."
--From the February 21, 1861 Address to the New Jersey General Assembly "Peace does not appear so distant as it did.
I hope it will come soon, and come to stay; and so come as to be worth the keeping in all future time."
--From the August 26, 1863 Letter to James Conkling

" When the conduct of men is designed to be influenced, persuasion, kind, unassuming persuasion, should ever be adopted.
It is an old and a true maxim, that a 'drop of honey catches more flies than a gallon of gall.'"
--From the February 22, 1842 Temperance Address

"It is not merely for to-day, but for all time to come that we should perpetuate for our children's children this great and free government, which we have enjoyed all our lives."
--From the August 22, 1864 Speech to the One Hundred Sixty-sixth Ohio Regiment "There is more involved in this contest than is realized by every one.
There is involved in this struggle the question whether your children and my children shall enjoy the privileges we have enjoyed."
--From the August 22, 1864 Speech to the One Hundred Sixty-fourth Ohio Regiment

"To His care commending you, as I hope in your prayers you will commend me, I bid you an affectionate farewell."
--From the February 11, 1861 Farewell Address "I am much indebted to the good Christian people of the country for their constant prayers and consolations; and to no one of them, more than to yourself."
--From the September 4, 1864 Letter to Eliza Gurney

"Both read the same Bible, and pray to the same God; and each invokes His aid against the other.
It may seem strange that any men should dare to ask a just God's assistance in wringing their bread from the sweat of other men's faces; but let us judge not that we be not judged.
The prayers of both could not be answered; that of neither has been answered fully."
--From the March 4, 1865 Inaugural Address

"That I am not a member of any Christian Church, is true; but I have never denied the truth of the Scriptures; and I have never spoken with intentional disrespect of religion in general, or any denomination of Christians in particular."
--From the July 31, 1846 Handbill Replying to Charges of Infidelity "I do not think I could myself, be brought to support a man for office, whom I knew to be an open enemy of, and scoffer at, religion."
--From the July 31, 1846 Handbill Replying to Charges of Infidelity

"The will of God prevails.
In great contests each party claims to act in accordance with the will of God.
Both may be, and one must be, wrong."
--From the September 1862 Meditation on the Divine Will

"We hoped for a happy termination of this terrible war long before this; but God knows best, and has ruled otherwise.
We shall yet acknowledge His wisdom and our own error therein."
--From the September 4, 1864 Letter to Eliza Gurney

"Passion has helped us; but can do so no more.
It will in future be our enemy.
Reason, cold, calculating, unimpassioned reason, must furnish all the materials for our future support and defence."
--From the February 22, 1842 Temperance Address "Happy day, when, all appetites controlled, all poisons subdued, all matter subjected, mind, all conquering mind, shall live and move the monarch of the world.
Glorious consummation!
Hail fall of Fury!
Reign of Reason, all hail!"
--From the February 22, 1842 Temperance Address

"Fellow-citizens, we cannot escape history.
We of this Congress and this administration, will be remembered in spite of ourselves.
No personal significance, or insignificance, can spare one or another of us.
The fiery trial through which we pass, will light us down, in honor or dishonor, to the latest generation."
--From the December 1, 1862 Message to Congress "I freely acknowledge myself the servant of the people, according to the bond of service -- the United States Constitution; and that, as such, I am responsible to them."
--From the August 26, 1863 Letter to James Conkling

"The Autocrat of all the Russias will resign his crown, and proclaim his subjects free republicans sooner than will our American masters voluntarily give up their slaves."
--From the August 15, 1855 Letter to George Robertson "You know I dislike slavery; and you fully admit the abstract wrong of it."
--From the August 24, 1855 Letter to Joshua Speed

"I am naturally anti-slavery.
If slavery is not wrong, nothing is wrong.
I can not remember when I did not so think, and feel.
And yet I have never understood that the Presidency conferred upon me an unrestricted right to act officially upon this judgment and feeling."
--From the April 4, 1864 Letter to Albert Hodges

"One eighth of the whole population were colored slaves, not distributed generally over the Union, but localized in the Southern part of it.
These slaves constituted a peculiar and powerful interest.
All knew that this interest was, somehow, the cause of the war."
--From the March 4, 1865 Inaugural Address

"Then came the Black-Hawk war; and I was elected a Captain of Volunteers -- a success which gave me more pleasure than any I have had since."
--From the December 20, 1859 Autobiography "I would like to speak in terms of praise due to the many brave officers and soldiers who have fought in the cause of the war."
--From the July 7, 1863 Response to a Serenade

"You say you will not fight to free negroes.
Some of them seem willing to fight for you; but, no matter.
Fight you, then exclusively to save the Union."
--From the August 26, 1863 Letter to James Conkling

"I do not expect the Union to be dissolved -- I do not expect the house to fall -- but I do expect it will cease to be divided."
--From the June 16, 1858 House Divided Speech "I hold, that in contemplation of universal law, and of the Constitution, the Union of these States is perpetual."
--From the March 4, 1861 Inaugural Address

"The Union is much older than the Constitution.
It was formed in fact, by the Articles of Association in 1774.
It was matured and continued by the Declaration of Independence in 1776."
--From the March 4, 1861 Inaugural Address

"I would save the Union.
I would save it the shortest way under the Constitution.
The sooner the national authority can be restored; the nearer the Union will be 'the Union as it was.'"
--From the August 22, 1862 Letter to Horace Greeley

"Now we are engaged in a great civil war, testing whether that nation, or any nation so conceived and so dedicated, can long endure."
--From the November 19, 1863 Gettysburg Address "Both parties deprecated war; but one of them would make war rather than let the nation survive; and the other would accept war rather than let it perish.
And the war came.... Fondly do we hope -- fervently do we pray -- that this mighty scourge of war may speedily pass away."</entry>
</article>
