<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="308" title="Aristotle" authors="8" lines="187">
  <entry author_id="198" end="44" start="0">His father, Nicomachus, was court physician to King Amyntas of Macedonia.
This position, we have reason to believe, was held under various predecessors of Amyntas by Aristotle's ancestors, so that the profession of medicine was in a sense hereditary in the family.
Whatever early training Aristotle received was probably influenced by this circumstance; when, therefore at the age of eighteen he went to Athens his mind was already determined in the direction which it afterwards took, the investigation of natural phenomena.

From his eighteenth to his thirty-seventh year he remained at Athens as pupil of Plato and was, we are told, distinguished among those who gathered for instruction in the Grove of Academus, adjoining Plato's house.
The relations between the renowned teacher and his illustrious pupil have formed the subject of various legends, many of which represent Aristotle in an unfavourable light.
No doubt there were divergencies of opinion between the master, who took his stand on sublime, idealistic principles, and the scholar, who, even at that time, showed a preference for the investigation of the facts and laws of the physical world.
It is probable that Plato did, indeed, declare that Aristotle needed the curb rather than the spur; but we have no reason to believe that there was an open breach of friendship.
In fact, Aristotle's conduct after the death of Plato, his continued association with Xenocrates and other Platonists, and his allusions in his writings to Plato's doctrines, prove that while there were differences of opinion between teacher and pupil, there was no lack of cordial appreciation, or of that mutual forbearance which one would expect from men of lofty character.
Besides this, the legends, so far as they reflect unfavourably on Aristotle, are traceable to the Epicureans who were known to antiquity as calumnators by profession; and if such legends were given wide circulation by patristic writers, such as Justin Martyr and Gregory Nazianzen, the reason is to be sought not in any well-grounded historical tradition, but in the exaggerated esteem in which Aristotle was held by the heretics of the early Christian period.

After the death of Plato (347 B.C.), Aristotle went, in company with Xenocrates, to the court of Hermias ruler of Atarneus in Asia Minor, whose niece and adopted daughter, Pythias, he married.
In 344 Hermias having been murdered in a rebellion of his subjects, Aristotle went with his family to Mytilene and thence, one or two years later, he was summoned to his native Stagira by King Philip of Macedon, to become the tutor of Alexander, who was then in his thirteenth year.
Whether or not we believe Plutarch when he tells us that Aristotle not only imparted to the future world-conqueror a knowledge of ethics and politics, but also initiated him into the most profound secrets of philosophy, we have positive proof, on the one hand, that the royal pupil profited by contact with the philosopher, and, on the other hand, that the teacher made prudent and beneficial use of his influence over the mind of the young prince.
It was due to this influence that Alexander placed at the disposal of his teacher ample means for the acquisition of books and the pursuit of his scientific investigation, and history is not wrong in tracing to the intercourse with Aristotle those singular gifts of mind and heart which almost up to the very last distinguished Alexander among the few who have known how to make moderate and intelligent use of victory.
About the year 335 Alexander departed for his Asiatic campaign; thereupon Aristotle, who, since his pupil's accession to the throne of Macedonia had occupied the position of a more or less informal adviser, returned to Athens and there opened a school of philosophy.
He may, as Gellius says, have conducted a school of rhetoric during his former residence in the city; but now, following the example of Plato, he gave regular instruction in philosophy choosing for that purpose a gymnasium dedicated to Apollo Lyceios, from which his school has come to be known as the Lyceum.
It was also called the Peripatetic School because it was the master's custom to discuss problems of philosophy with his pupils while walking up and down (peripateo) the shaded walks (peripatoi) around the gymnasium.

During the thirteen years (335-322) which he spent as teacher at the Lyceum, Aristotle composed the greater number of his writings.
Imitating the example of his master, he placed in the hands of his pupils "Dialogues" in which his doctrines were expounded in somewhat popular language.
Besides he composed the several treatises (of which mention will be made below) on physics, metaphysics, and so forth, in which the exposition is more didactic and the language more technical than in the "Dialogues".
These writings show to what good use he put the means placed at his disposal by Alexander.
They show in particular how he succeeded in bringing together the works of his predecessors in Greek philosophy, and how he spared neither pains nor expense in pursuing, either personally or through others, his investigations in the realm of natural Phenomena.
When we read the works treating of zoology we are quite prepared to believe Pliny's statement that Alexander placed under Aristotle's orders all the hunters, fishermen, and fowlers of the royal kingdom and all the overseers of the royal forests, lakes, ponds and cattle-ranges, and when we observe how fully Aristotle is informed concerning the doctrines of those who preceded him, we are prepared to accept Strabo's assertion that he was the first who accumulated a great library.
During the last years of Aristotle's life the relations between him and his former royal pupil became very much strained, owing to the disgrace and punishment of Callisthenes whom he had recommended to the King.
Nevertheless, he continued to be regarded at Athens as a friend of Alexander and a representative of the Macedonian dominion.
Consequently, when Alexander's death became known at Athens, and the outbreak occurred which led to the Lamian war, Aristotle was obliged to share in the general unpopularity of the Macedonians.
The charge of impiety, which had been brought against Anaxagoras and Socrates, was now, with even less reason, brought against him.
He left the city, saying (according to many ancient authorities) that he would not give the Athenians a chance to sin a third time against Philosophy.
He took up his residence at his country house, at Chalcis, in Euboea, and there he died the following year, 322 B.C. His death was due to a disease from which he had long suffered.
The story that his death was due to hemlock poisoning, as well as the legend, according to which he threw himself into the sea "because he could not explain the tides" are absolutely without historical foundation.

Very little is known about Aristotle's personal appearance except from sources manifestly hostile.
There is no reason, however, to doubt the faithfulness of the statues and busts coming down to us, possibly from the first years of the Peripatetic School, which represent him as sharp and keen of countenance, and somewhat below the average height.
His character, as revealed by his writings, his will (which is undoubtedly genuine), fragments of his letters and the allusions of his unprejudiced contemporaries, was that of a high-minded, kind-hearted man, devoted to his family and his friends, kind to his slaves, fair to his enemies and rivals, grateful towards his benefactors -- in a word, an embodiment of those moral ideals which he outlined in his ethical treatises, and which we recognize to be far above the concept of moral excellence current in his day and among his people.
When Platonism ceased to dominate the world of Christian speculation, and the works of the Stagirite began to be studied without fear and prejudice, the personality of Aristotle appeared to the Christian writers of the thirteenth century, as it had to the unprejudiced pagan writers of his own day, calm, majestic, untroubled by passion, and undimmed by any great moral defects, "the master of those who know".

Aristotle defines philosophy in terms of essence, saying that philosophy is "the science of the universal essence of that which is actual".
Plato had defined it as the "science of the idea", meaning by idea what we should call the unconditional basis of phenomena.
Both pupil and master regard philosophy as concerned with the universal; the former however, finds the universal in particular things, and calls it the essence of things, while the latter finds that the universal exists apart from particular things, and is related to them as their prototype or exemplar.
For Aristotle, therefore, philosophic method implies the ascent from the study of particular phenomena to the knowledge of essences, while for Plato philosophic method means the descent from a knowledge of universal ideas to a contemplation of particular imitations of those ideas.
In a certain sense, Aristotle's method is both inductive and deductive, while Plato's is essentially deductive.
In other words, for Plato's tendency to idealize the world of reality in the light of intuition of a higher world, Aristotle substituted the scientific tendency to examine first the phenomena of the real world around us and thence to reason to a knowledge of the essences and laws which no intuition can reveal, but which science can prove to exist.
In fact, Aristotle's notion of philosophy corresponds, generally speaking, to what was later understood to be science, as distinct from philosophy.
In the larger sense of the word, he makes philosophy coextensive with science, or reasoning: "All science (dianoia) is either practical, poetical or theoretical."
By practical science he understands ethics and politics; by poetical, he means the study of poetry and the other fine arts; while by theoretical philosophy he means physics, mathematics, and metaphysics.
The last, philosophy in the stricter sense, he defines as "the knowledge of immaterial being," and calls it "first philosophy", "the theologic science" or of "being in the highest degree of abstraction."
If logic, or, as Aristotle calls it, Analytic, be regarded as a study preliminary to philosophy, we have as divisions of Aristotelean phllosophy (1) Logic; (2) Theoretical Philosophy, including Metaphysics, Physics, Mathematics, (3) Practical Philosophy; and (4) Poetical Philosophy.</entry>
  <entry author_id="16" end="75" start="44">He left the city, saying (according to many ancient authorities) that he would not give the Athenians a chance to sin a third time against Philosophy.
He took up his residence at his country house, at Chalcis, in Euboea, and there he died the following year, 322 BC.
His death was due to a disease from which he had long suffered.
The story that his death was due to hemlock poisoning, as well as the legend, according to which he threw himself into the sea "because he could not explain the tides" are absolutely without historical foundation.

Very little is known about Aristotle's personal appearance except from sources manifestly hostile.
There is no reason, however, to doubt the faithfulness of the statues and busts coming down to us, possibly from the first years of the Peripatetic School, which represent him as sharp and keen of countenance, and somewhat below the average height.
His character, as revealed by his writings, his will (which is undoubtedly genuine), fragments of his letters and the allusions of his unprejudiced contemporaries, was that of a high-minded, kind-hearted man, devoted to his family and his friends, kind to his slaves, fair to his enemies and rivals, grateful towards his benefactors -- in a word, an embodiment of those moral ideals which he outlined in his ethical treatises, and which we recognize to be far above the concept of moral excellence current in his day and among his people.
When Platonism ceased to dominate the world of Christian speculation, and the works of the Stagirite began to be studied without fear and prejudice, the personality of Aristotle appeared to the Christian writers of the thirteenth century, as it had to the unprejudiced pagan writers of his own day, calm, majestic, untroubled by passion, and undimmed by any great moral defects, "the master of those who know".
Aristotle defines philosophy in terms of essence, saying that philosophy is "the science of the universal essence of that which is actual".
Plato had defined it as the "science of the idea", meaning by idea what we should call the unconditional basis of phenomena.
Both pupil and master regard philosophy as concerned with the universal; the former however, finds the universal in particular things, and calls it the essence of things, while the latter finds that the universal exists apart from particular things, and is related to them as their prototype or exemplar.
For Aristotle, therefore, philosophic method implies the ascent from the study of particular phenomena to the knowledge of essences, while for Plato philosophic method means the descent from a knowledge of universal ideas to a contemplation of particular imitations of those ideas.
In a certain sense, Aristotle's method is both inductive and deductive, while Plato's is essentially deductive.

In Aristotle's terminology, the term natural philosophy corresponds to the phenomenon of the natural world: motion, light, the laws of physics.
Many centuries later these subjects would later become the basis of modern science, as studied through the scientific method.
The term philosophy is distinct from metaphysics, which is what moderns term philosophy.

In the larger sense of the word, he makes philosophy coextensive with reasoning, which he also called "science".
Note, however, that his use of the term science carries a different meaning that that which is covered by the scientific method.
"All science (dianoia) is either practical, poetical or theoretical."
By practical science he understands ethics and politics; by poetical, he means the study of poetry and the other fine arts; while by theoretical philosophy he means physics, mathematics, and metaphysics.

The last, philosophy in the stricter sense, he defines as "the knowledge of immaterial being," and calls it "first philosophy", "the theologic science" or of "being in the highest degree of abstraction."
If logic, or, as Aristotle calls it, Analytic, be regarded as a study preliminary to philosophy, we have as divisions of Aristotelian philosophy (1) Logic; (2) Theoretical Philosophy, including Metaphysics, Physics, Mathematics, (3) Practical Philosophy; and (4) Poetical Philosophy.
Aristotelian discussions about science had only been qualitative, not quantitative.
By the modern definition of the term, Aristotelian philosophy was not science, as this worldview did not atempt to probe how the world actually worked through experiment.
Rather, based on what one's senses told one, Aristotelian philosophy then depended upon the assumption that man's mind could elucidate all the laws of the universe, based on simple observation (without experimentation) through reason alone.

In contrast, today the term science refers to the position that thinking alone often leads people astray, and therefore one must compare one's ideas to the actual world through experimentation; only then can one see if one's ideas are based in reality.
Aristotle has been criticised on several grounds.
In any case, Aristotle was regarded as, not a great philosopher, but as "The Philosopher" by Scholastic dogmatists.
It required a repudiation of Aristotelian principles for the sciences and the arts to free themselves for the discovery of modern scientific laws and empirical methods.
This is not a complete list of Aristotle's works, but it does provide links to translations of those works which still exist.
Please update any links that you find to be broken.</entry>
  <entry author_id="14998" end="86" start="75">The history of Aristotle's works from the time of his death until the 1st century BC is obscure.
Legend has it that Aristotle's personal library, including the manuscripts of his works, was left to his successor Theophrastus and that later it was hidden to avoid confiscation or destruction; finally the manuscripts were rediscovered in 70 BC.
Andronicus of Rhodes then (in fact) edited and published the works.
In the interim, however, the works could hardly have been forgotten, as Aristotle's school, the Lyceum, was in operation at the time.

The majority of Aristotle's work has been lost, some since Classical times.
There is a glimpse of what we have lost in the praise given by Cicero to the eloquence of Aristotle's dialogues.
The surviving works are known and respected for a plain an unadorned (though not easy) style; none is a dialogue,

In late antiquity Aristotle fell nearly out of sight.
Early Christian writers such as Tertullian rejected philosophy altogether as a pagan study that was made obsolete by the Gospels.
In the 5th century Saint Augustine used Platonic and Noe-Platonic philosophy in his theology, but had no use for Aristotle.
At the end of the century, however, Boethius undertook to translate the works of Aristotle and other Greeks into Latin, as the teaching of Greek was being lost in the West; his translations and commentaries were nearly all that was known of Greek philosophy in the West for several centuries.</entry>
  <entry author_id="150236" end="108" start="86">The history of Aristotle's works from the time of his death until the 1st century BC is obscure.
Legend has it that Aristotle's personal library, including the manuscripts of his works, was left to his successor Theophrastus and was later hidden to avoid confiscation or destruction; finally the manuscripts were rediscovered in 70 BC.
Andronicus of Rhodes then edited and published the works.
In the interim, however, the works could hardly have been forgotten, since Aristotle's school, the Lyceum, was in operation the whole time.

The majority of Aristotle's work has been lost, some since Classical times.
There is a glimpse of what we have lost in the praise given by Cicero to the eloquence of Aristotle's dialogues.
The surviving works are known and respected for a plain and unadorned (though not easy) style; not one is a dialogue.
Some lost works of Aristotle may have survived in hard-to-restore carbonised form at the Villa of the Papyri in Herculaneum, currently under excavation.

In late antiquity Aristotle fell nearly out of sight.
Early Christian writers such as Tertullian rejected philosophy altogether as a pagan study that was made obsolete by the Gospels.
In the 5th century Saint Augustine used Platonic and Neo-Platonic philosophy in his theology, but had no use for Aristotle.
At the end of the century, however, Boethius undertook to translate the works of Aristotle and other Greeks into Latin, as the teaching of Greek was being lost in the West; his translations and commentaries were nearly all that was known of Greek philosophy in the West for several centuries.
They were little missed, as the hostility of early Christianity to pagan philosophy continued.

Aristotle's works were read during the Umayyad and Abbasid caliphates, however, and the Islamic philosopher Averroes commented extensively on it and attempted to fuse it with Islamic theology.
Maimonides also tried this with Judaism.
By the 12th century there was a great revival of interest in Aristotle in Christian Europe, and the great translator William of Moerbeke worked from both Greek and Arabic manuscripts to produce Latin translations.
Aristotle's works were commented on by Thomas Aquinas and became the standard philosophical approach of the high and later middle ages.
Aristotle's works were held in such esteem that he was known as The Philosopher.

Aristotle's theories about drama, in particular the idea of the dramatic unities, also influenced later playwrights, especially in France.
He claimed to be describing the Greek theater, but his work was taken as prescriptive.
In more recent times there has been a new revival of interest in Aristotle.
His ethical views in particular remain influential.</entry>
  <entry author_id="498138" end="121" start="108">Main article: Aristotelian theory of gravity Aristotle states two modes of causation:Proper CausationChance lies in the realm of accidental causes.
It is "from what is spontaneous" (but note that what is spontaneous does not come from chance).
For a better understanding of Aristotle's conception of "chance" it might be better to think of "coincidence": Something takes place by chance if a person sets out with the intent of having one thing take place, but with the result of another thing (not intended) taking place.
For example: A person seeks donations.
That person may find another person willing to donate a substantial sum.
However, if the person seeking the donations met the person donating, not for the purpose of collecting donations, but for some other purpose, Aristotle would call the collecting of the donation by that particular donator a result of chance.

However, chance can only apply to human beings.
According to Aristotle, chance must involve choice (and thus deliberation), and only humans are capable of deliberation and choice.
"What is not capable of action cannot do anything by chance" (Physics, 2.6).
These four elements interchange (i.e. Fire&lt;--&gt;Air&lt;--&gt;Water&lt;--&gt;Earth&lt;--&gt;Fire, etc.).
The Sun keeps this cycle going.
God keeps the Sun going (and thus the Sun is eternal).
Main article: Nicomachean Ethics</entry>
  <entry author_id="270261" end="143" start="121">Aristotle believed that ethical knowledge is not certain knowledge (like metaphysics and epistemology) but is general knowledge.
Also, as it is not a theoretical discipline, he thought a person had to study in order to become "good."
Thus, if a person was to become virtuous, they could not simply study what virtue is, they had to actually do virtuous activity.
In order to do this, Aristotle had to first establish what was virtuous.
He began by determining that everything was done with some goal in mind and that goal is 'good': But, if action A is done with the goal B, the goal B would also have a goal, goal C. Goal C would also have a goal and this would continue until something stopped the infinite regress.
This was the Highest Good.
Aristotle said the Highest Good must have three characteristics:Aristotle resolves this Highest Good in eudaemonia, which is usually translated as "happiness," but could also be "well-being" or "flourishing."
Aristotle contested that happiness could not be found only in pleasure, as "it would be absurd if the end were amusement and if trouble and hardship throughout life would all be for the sake of amusing oneself."
He also surmised that it was not in only fame and honor, as "it seems to be more superficial than what we are looking for, since it rests in the man who gives the honor rather than in him who receives it."
He finally finds happiness "by ascertaining the specific function of man.
In the case of flute players, sculptors, and all craftsmen - indeed all who have some function and activity - 'good' and 'excellent' reside in their function.
Now the same will be true of man, if he has a peculiar function to himself."

But what is this function that will bring happiness?
To determine this, Aristotle analyzed the nature of the soul.
He saw it as existing in three parts, each of which had a specific function:

Aristotle saw the soul as existing in three parts, each of which had a specific funtion:Thus, a human's function is to do what makes it human, to be good at what sets it apart from everything else: the ability to reason or Nous.
Or, as Aristotle concludes, "The function of man is activity of soul in accordance with reason, or at least not without reason."
He identifies two different ways in which the soul can engage in: reasoning (both practical and theoretical) and following reasoning.
A person that does this is the happiest because they are fulfulling their purpose or nature as found in the rational soul.
In other words, the thinker is not only the 'best' person, but is also most like God.
Contrary to the teachings of Plato, his teacher, Aristotle firmly believed that all human beings (then interpreted as free males) are born with the potential to become ethically virtuous and practically wise.
To acheive these goals, they must go through two stages:Aristotle believes that every ethical virtue is an intermediate condition between behaving]] virtuously and developing virtue rather than committing specific good actions.</entry>
  <entry author_id="285257" end="158" start="143">One story of the original manuscripts of his treatises is described by Strabo in his Geography and Plutarch in his Parallel Lives.
The manuscripts were left from Aristotle to his successor Theophrastus, who in turn willed them to Neleus of Scepsis.
Neleus supposedly took from from Athens to Scepsis, where his heirs let them languish in a cellar until the first century BCE, when Apellicon of Teos discovered and purchased the manuscripts, bringing them back to Athens.

Carnes Lord attributes the popular belief in this story to the fact that it provides "the most plausible explanation for the rapid eclipse of the Peripatetic school after the middle of the third century, and for the absence of widespread knowledge of the specialized treatises of Aristotle throughout the Hellenistic period, as well as for the sudden reappearance of a flourishing Aristotelianism during the first century B.C." Lord voices a number of reservations concerning this story, however.
First, the condition of the texts is far too good for them to have suffered considerable damage followed by Apellicon's inexpert attempt at repair.
Second, there is "incontrovertible evidence," Lord says, that the treatises were in circulation during the time in which Strabo and Plutarch suggest they were confined the the cellar in Scepsis.
Third, the definitive edition of Aristotle's texts seems to have been made in Athens some fifty years before Andronicus supposedly compiled his.
And fourth, ancient library catalogues predating Andronicus' intervention list an Aristotelean corpus quite similar to the one we currently possess.
Lord sees a number of post-Aristotelean interpolations in the Politics, for example, but is generally confident that the work has come down to us relatively intact.

After the Roman period, Aristotle's works were by and large lost to the West for a second time.
They were, however, preserved in the East by various Muslim scholars and philosophers, many of whom wrote extensive commentaries on his works.
Aristotle lay at the foundation of the falsafa movement in Islamic philosophy, stimulating the thought of Al-Farabi, Ibn Sina, Ibn Rushd and others.

As the influence of the falsafa grew in the West, in part due to Gerard of Cremona's translations and the spread of Averroism, the demand for Aristotle's works grew.
William of Moerbeke translated a number of them into Latin.
When Thomas Aquinas wrote his theology, working from Moerbeke's translations, the demand for Aristotle's writings grew and the Greek manuscripts returned to the West, stimulating a revival of Aristotelianism in Europe.</entry>
  <entry author_id="3217849" end="187" start="158">One day Dylan was chillin with his dog Crazy Rumpkins.
They heard a loud thump and they went to see what it was.
They were sad to find out that Nate had died in a copying accident.
Crazy Rumpkins was not happy because Dylan made him dig the grave.
Then Dylan found a new friend named Aristotle.
Crazy Rumpkins ran away from home and he met a witch named Dylan.
Crazy Rumpkins was happy because his old owners name who hated him was named Dylan also.
The witch told Crazy Rumpkins that she knew how to bring people back to life as long as they didn’t die in a copying accident.
Crazy Rumpkins was out of luck because he wanted Nate to come back to life but Nate had died in a copying accident.
So Dylan the witch said “There is one way I can bring him back.
But you have to bungee jump in the nude over a waterfall of candy.” Crazy Rumpkins thought that was impossible but then he remembered that his favorite Uncle Cracker had a candy waterfall in his back yard.
So he went to Cavalier Barbers to get a hair cut but the people shot at him.
So we went to Tracy’s Hair and Nail Salon and they accepted him with warm hearts.
He now had all of his hair cut off and he was in the nude.
But the real question was, where was he going to get a bungee chord?
He went to the first place that popped into his mind.
Freestyle, which had once been Starbase Alpha.
He knew that the aliens who ran Starbase Alpha lived in the dumpster behind freestyle and they had a bungee chord.
He asked them where it was and they said “We took it to Pluto but since that’s not a planet anymore we cried a lot and now we don’t know where it is.
But I think it might be at Burger King.” Crazy Rumpkins then headed over to Burger King, only to find that the King was evil and he wanted to put all the bungee chords in the sandwichs so that people would eat bungee chords instead of sandwichs.
Crazy Rumpkins had to save the day.
So he peed on the Kings rug and the King got so mad that he jumped off a cliff.
Now Crazy Rumpkins had a bungee chord, he was in the nude, and he knew where the candy waterfall was.
He went to his Uncle Crackers house and did all the things that Dylan the witch told him to do.
When he returned to Dylan the witchs house, she greeted him by saying, “Hola amigo, donde esta la bibliotecha?” Crazy Rumpkins didn’t understand so he told Dylan the witch all the things he did and Dylan the witch said “I was just kidding about all of that.” So Crazy Rumpkins cried so much that his eyes turned into peas.
Then Dylan the witch said “I was just kidding about just kidding.” So Crazy Rumpkins was happy that Nate had come back to life and he went back to Dylan, who was chillin with Aristotle.
Crazy Rumpkins pooped in Aristotles bed and when Aristotle got in his bed he ran away and back to his castle made out of bee’s knees.
So in the end Dylan and Crazy Rumpkins were best friends and Nate ended up wasting 20 minutes of his life writing a paper.
And everyone lived happily ever after.</entry>
</article>
