<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="336" title="Altruism" authors="5" lines="90">
  <entry author_id="5364" end="28" start="0">Theories of eusociality and the undoubted advantages of kin selection have made good progress in this direction, but they are far from unproblematic.
Altruistic behaviour isn't soley a case of 'tit for tat' or 'benefit related genes'.
Humans are exclusively altruistic towards family members, previous co-operators or potential future allies, but can be altruistic towards people they don't know and will never meet.
Humans donate to international charities, volunteer our time to help society's less fortunate.
According to this postulate, it strains plausibility to claim that these altruistic deeds are done in the hope of a return favour.
This 'just in case' strategy where the principle would be 'always help everyone in case you need to pull in a favour in return' is a decidedly non-optimal strategy, where the net expenditure of effort (tit) is far greater than the net profit when it occasionally pays off (tat).

However, some point out that the conscience is just another aspect of our mental behaviour, so there must be some evolutionary explanation for their existence.
One recent suggestion, proposed most eloquently by the philosopher Daniel Dennett, was initially developed when considering the problem of so-called 'free riders' in the problem of the commons, a larger-scale version of the Prisoner's Dilemma.
In game theory terms, a free rider is an agent who draws benefits from a co-operative society without contributing.
In a one-to-one situation, free riding can easily be discouraged by a tit-for-tat strategy.
But in a larger-scale society, where contributions and benefits are pooled and shared, they can be incredibly difficult to shake off.

Imagine an elementary society of co-operative organisms.
Co-operative agents interact with each other, each contributing resources and each drawing on the common good.
Now imagine a rogue free rider, an agent who draws a favour (you scratch my back) and later refuses to return it.
The problem is that free riding is always going to be beneficial to individuals at cost to society.
How can well-behaved co-operative agents avoid being cheated?

Over many generations, one obvious solution is for co-operators to evolve the ability to spot potential free riders in advance and refuse to enter into reciprocal arrangements with them.
Then, the canonical free rider response is to evolve a more convincing disguise, fooling co-operators into co-operating after all.
This can lead to an evolutionary arms races, with ever-more-sophisticated disguises and ever-more-sophisticated detectors.
This may be how some societies have evolved, but it seems a far cry from a genuine altruistic conscience.

In this evolutionary arms race, how best might an agent convince his comrades that he really is a genuine co-operator, not a free rider in disguise?
One answe is by actually making himself a genuine co-operator, by erecting psychological barriers to breaking his own promises, and by advertising this fact to everyone else.
In other words, a good solution is for organisms to evolve things that everyone knows will force them to be co-operators - and to make it obvious that they've evolved these things.
And we ought to expect evolution to find good solutions.
So evolution will produce organisms who are sincerely moral and who wear their hearts on their sleeves; in short, evolution will give rise to the phenomenon of conscience.

If all this is true, and altruism (read: morality) has just evolved as an optimum solution to a game-theoretic problem, what then for ethics?
Is right and wrong just an illusion fobbed off on us by our genes so they can survive and reproduce in a society of self-interested agents?
This is a meta-ethical question that straddles the boundary between biology and philosophy.</entry>
  <entry author_id="141644" end="39" start="28">If one is an adherent to the ethical doctrine called altruism (that people have an ethical obligation to help or further the welfare of others), it can become a moral justification for forcing, or advocating forcing individuals to help others.
In the realm of politics, the altruist may employ an agent in the form of government to enforce this supposed moral obligation.
This is not to say that an ethical altruist will necessarily force this on anyone.
An altruist may allow others the freedom to behave in a manner they believe to be immoral or selfish.
In other words, their ethical doctrine would not manifest itself politically.

Finally, many believe that helping others or serving society is not a moral obligation at all, but that altrusm is an arbitrary pronouncement not philosophically derivable.
These oppose all government-enforced charity.
Individualist anarchist Pierre-Joseph Proudhon in 1847 warns of enforcing charity: "That is why charity, the prime virtue of the Christian, the legitimate hope of the socialist, the object of all the efforts of the economist, is a social vice the moment it is made a principle of constitution and a law; that is why certain economists have been able to say that legal charity had caused more evil in society than proprietary usurpation" (The Philosophy of Poverty).

Comte asserts that individual rights are not compatible with the supposed obligation to serve others.
Some argue that the ethical doctrine, if taken to its logical conclusion, leads to tyranny.
Adolf Hitler is sometimes presented as an example of this, and has been described as advocating altruism.</entry>
  <entry author_id="141644" end="50" start="39">If one is an adherent to the ethical doctrine called altruism (that people have an ethical obligation to help or further the welfare of others), it can become a moral justification for forcing, or advocating forcing individuals to help others.
In the realm of politics, the altruist may employ an agent in the form of government to enforce this supposed moral obligation.
This is not to say that an ethical altruist will necessarily force this on anyone.
An altruist may allow others the freedom to behave in a manner they believe to be immoral or selfish.
In other words, their ethical doctrine would not manifest itself politically.

Finally, many believe that helping others or serving society is not a moral obligation at all, but that altrusm is an arbitrary pronouncement not philosophically derivable.
These oppose all government-enforced charity.
Individualist anarchist Pierre-Joseph Proudhon in 1847 warns of enforcing charity: "That is why charity, the prime virtue of the Christian, the legitimate hope of the socialist, the object of all the efforts of the economist, is a social vice the moment it is made a principle of constitution and a law; that is why certain economists have been able to say that legal charity had caused more evil in society than proprietary usurpation" (The Philosophy of Poverty).

Comte asserts that individual rights are not compatible with the supposed obligation to serve others.
Some argue that the ethical doctrine, if taken to its logical conclusion, leads to tyranny.
Adolf Hitler is sometimes presented as an example of this, and has been described as advocating altruism.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1107880" end="60" start="50">Some opponents of the ethical doctrine called altruism (that people have an ethical obligation to help or further the welfare of others) argue that the doctrine is dangerous as it can lead to violations of individual liberty if the state enforces the principle.
For example, David Kelley says, "If self-sacrifice is an ideal--if service to others is the highest, most honorable course of action--why not force people to act accordingly?"
He believes this can ultimately result in the state forcing everyone into a collectivist political system.

A prominent example of the former branch of altruist political thought is Lysander Spooner, who, in Natural Law, writes: "Man, no doubt, owes many other moral duties to his fellow men; such as to feed the hungry, clothe the naked, shelter the homeless, care for the sick, protect the defenceless, assist the weak, and enlighten the ignorant.
But these are simply moral duties, of which each man must be his own judge, in each particular case, as to whether, and how, and how far, he can, or will, perform them."
Things such as a law that motorists pull over to let emergency vehicles pass may also be justified by appealing to the altruism ethic.
Finally, radical altruists of this branch may take things further and advocate some form of collectivism or communalism.

On a somewhat related note, altruism is often held - even by non-altruists - to be the kind of ethic that should guide the actions of politicians and other people in positions of power.
Such people are usually expected to set their own interests aside and serve the populace.
When they do not, they may be criticized as defaulting on what is believed to be an ethical obligation to place the interests of others above their own.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7520043" end="75" start="60">Kabbalah defines altruism as the desired goal of creation.
The Kabbalist Rav Abraham Kook stated that love is the most important attribute in humanity.
This is defined as bestowal, or giving, which is the intention of altruism.
This can be altruism towards humanity that leads to altruism towards the creator or God.
Kabbalah defines God as the force of giving in existence.
Rabbi Moshe Chaim Luzzatto in particular focused on the ‘purpose of creation’ and how the will of God was to bring creation into perfection and adhesion with this upper force.

Modern Kabbalah developed by Rabbi Yehuda Ashlag, in his writings about the future generation, focuses on how society could achieve an altruistic social framework.
Ashlag proposed that such a framework is the purpose of creation, and everything that happens is to raise humanity to the level of altruism, love for one another.
Ashlag focused on society and its relation to divinity.

Swami Sivananda, an Advaita scholar, reiterates the same views in his commentary synthesising Vedanta views on the Brahma Sutras, a Vedantic text.
In his commentary on Chapter 3 of the Brahma Sutras, Sivananda notes that karma is insentient and short-lived, and ceases to exist as soon as a deed is executed.
Hence, karma cannot bestow the fruits of actions at a future date according to one's merit.
Furthermore, one cannot argue that karma generates apurva or punya, which gives fruit.
Since apurva is non-sentient, it cannot act unless moved by an intelligent being such as God.
It cannot independently bestow reward or punishment.</entry>
  <entry author_id="16448665" end="90" start="75">The International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences defines psychological altruism as "a motivational state with the goal of increasing another’s welfare".
Psychological altruism is contrasted with psychological egoism, which refers to "a motivational state with the goal of increasing one’s own welfare" (1).
There has been some debate on whether or not humans are capable of psychological altruism.
The "empathy-altruism hypothesis" states that psychological altruism does exist and is evoked by the empathic desire to help someone who is suffering.
Feelings of empathic concern are contrasted with feelings of personal distress, which compel people to reduce their own unpleasant emotions.
People with empathic concern help others in distress even when exposure to the situation could be easily avoided, whereas those lacking in empathic concern avoid helping unless it is difficult or impossible to avoid exposure to another's suffering.
Helping behavior is seen in humans at about two years old, when a toddler is able to understand subtle emotional cues.

Research has found that people are most likely to help if they recognize that a person is in need and feel personal responsibility for reducing the person's distress.
Research also suggests that the number of bystanders witnessing distress or suffering affects the likelihood of helping (the "Bystander effect").
Greater numbers of bystanders decrease individual feelings of responsibility.
Hudson, James M. &amp; Bruckman, Amy S. (2004).
"The Bystander Effect: A Lens for Understanding Patterns of Participation".
Journal of the Learning Sciences 13 (2): 165–195.
doi:10.1207/s15327809jls1302_2.
However, a witness with a high level of empathic concern is likely to assume personal responsibility entirely regardless of the number of bystanders.</entry>
</article>
