<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="358" title="Algeria" authors="4" lines="116">
  <entry author_id="108" end="23" start="0">Formally a part of the Ottoman Empire, Algeria's coast was used as a base for pirates.
This was ended by a French invasion in 1830, followed by a complete conquest of Algeria several years later.
In 1954, a guerilla began to make Algeria independent, which succeeded in 1962.

The head of state is the political association may be formed if it is "based on differences in religion, language, race gender or region."
The head of state is the President of the republic, who is elected to a 5-year term, renewable once.
Algeria has universal suffrage.
The President is the head of the Council of Ministers and of the High Security Council.
He appoints the Prime Minister who also is the head of government.
The Prime Minister appoints the Council of Ministers.

The Algerian parliament is bicameral, consisting of a lower chamber, the National People's Assembly (APN), with 380 members and an upper chamber, the Council of Nation, with 144 members.
The APN is elected every 5 years.
Main article: Provinces of Algeria

Most of the coastal area is hilly, sometimes even mountainous, and there are few good harbours.
The area just south of the coast, known as the Tell, is fertile.
Further south is the Atlas mountain range and the Sahara desert.
Algiers, Oran and Constantine are the main cities.

Algeria's climate is arid and hot, although the coastal climate is mild, and the winters in the mountainous areas can be severe.
Algeria is prone to sirocco, a hot dust- and sand-laden wind especially common in summer.
Main article: Economy of Algeria

Algeria's main source of income is the oil and gas industry.
The country has one of the world's largest natural gas reserves.
Nevertheless, Algeria has massive foreign debts.
Main article: Demographics of Algeria</entry>
  <entry author_id="1277085" end="75" start="23">Between 350,000 and 1.5 million Algerians died during the Algerian War of Independence.
Algerians argue that the massacres should be named as genocide and France must apologise to the Algerians However the French do not accept the claims.
Algeria's President Abdelaziz Bouteflika says that French colonization of his country Algeria was a form of genocide .
In memoirs, some French officers have described torture of Algerians during the war.
Edouard Sablier, for instance, one of the soldiers who took part in the repression, later described the situation: “Everywhere in the towns there were camps surrounded by barbed wire containing hundreds of suspects who had been arrested… Often, when we set out to inspect an isolated hamlet in the mountains, I heard people say, ‘We should punish them by taking away their crops’.” A paper called Ohé Partisans, published by the French Trotskyists, described Sétif as an “Algerian Oradour”.
Oradour was a French town where the Nazi occupiers had murdered over 600 people, including children.
However France has never accepted its responsibility in tortures and massacres in Algeria.
Paris says that the past should be left to historians.
French President Jacques Chirac, upon harsh reactions to the law encouraging the good sides of the French colonial history, made the statement, "Writing history is the job of the historians, not of the laws."
Writing history is the job of the historians" According to Prime Minister Dominique de Villepin, "speaking about the past or writing history is not the job of the parliament."
The Algerian president Abdelaziz Bouteflika said in a speech in Paris on 17 April 2006 "Colonisation brought the genocide of our identity, of our history, of our language, of our traditions".
Algeria first became a colony of France in 1830.
When the Algerian people rioted against the French colonial rule, the French dispatched 400,000 troops to pacify the anti-colonial uprising.
The French colonial forces launched an air and ground offensive against several eastern cities, particularly Setif and Guelma, in response to anti-French riots.
The crackdown lasted several days and according to the Algerian state left 45,000 people dead.
European historians put the figure at between 15,000 and 20,000.
French attacks continued not only in Algerian territories but in France as well.
The Paris massacre of 1961 was the most vivid example: On October 17 the French police attacked an unarmed demonstration of Algerians, who demanded the freedom of their country from French colonial rule.
How many demonstrators were killed is still unclear, but estimates range from 32 to 200 people.
The incident had not been officially confirmed until 1999 as the French Governments hide the truth.
There were executions and widespread arrests during the War of Independence.
"Many European lawyers refused to defend the accused.
Villages were bombed from the air and a town was shelled from a cruiser at sea.
The attacks were more or less random.
The point was not so much to punish the original rioters as to teach the whole Muslim population to know their place.
Settlers set up their own unofficial death squads and killed hundreds of Muslims.
German and Italian prisoners of war were released to take part in the massacre."
Abdulkerim Gazali, editor of the Algerian newspaper La Tribune, likens France's occupation of an independent and sovereign Algeria to Nazi Germany's occupation of many European countries and claimed this was racism.
After a war which ended in Algeria's independence in 1962, eight million Algerian residents were deprived of French nationality and hundreds of thousands of 'pieds noir' (French who settled in Algeria and were re-patriated at the end of the war) were forced home to a place which was not home.
Ahmed Ben Bella also argues that the French committed a genocide against the people and Algerian culture: "Algeria's indigenous population was decimated in the early years of French settler colonial rule, falling from over four million in 1830 to less than 2.5 million by 1890.
Systematic genocide was coupled with the brutal suppression of Algerian cultural identity.
Systematic genocide was coupled with the brutal suppression of Algerian cultural identity.
Indigenous Algerians were French subjects, but could only become French citizens if they renounced Islam and Arab culture.
A ruthless policy of acculturation followed, and the remaining Algerians were forced to cease speaking their native Arabic and use the French of their colonial masters instead.
The indigenous Muslim population of Algeria was not permitted to hold political meetings or bear arms.
They were subjected to strict pass laws that required indigenous Muslim Algerians to seek permission from the colonial authorities to leave their hometowns or villages."
Algeria called on France to apologise in 2005 for crimes committed during the colonial era.
Amar Bakhouche, speaker of the Algerian Senate, similarly reacted that France did not apologize for massacres it committed in Algeria.
The 1945 Massacres was one of the most tragic massacres French committed in Algeria.
As Le Monde put it, "as France celebrated victory in Europe on 8 May 1945, its army was massacring thousands of civilians in Sétif and Guelma - events that were the real beginning of Algeria’s war of independence."
Bouteflika also urged the Paris Government to admit its part in the massacres of 45,000 Algerians who took to the streets to demand independence as Europe celebrated victory over Nazi Germany in 1945.
French authorities then responded by playing down the comments, urging "mutual respect".
French Foreign Minister Barnier told Algeria in an official visit to make a common effort to search history "in order to establish a common future and overcome the sad pages".
Giving interview to El Vatan, an Algerian newspaper, Barnier said that "Historians from two sides must be encouraged to work together.
They must work on the common past".
The archives in France on the issue have been kept closed till now.
The French collected all documents regarding the massacres and genocide.
For many, the closed archives are another signs of the Genocide in Algeria.
Amar Bakhouche, the speaker of Algerian Senate, reacted that France keep the archives related to that period closed.
He says the greatest majority of archives related to that period were brought to France and they were kept closed.
"They are not open for French and Algerians.
We urged to immediately open them for public" he said.</entry>
  <entry author_id="2723963" end="105" start="75">Under the 1976 Constitution (as modified 1979, and amended in 1988, 1989, and 1996) Algeria is a multi-party state.
All parties must be approved by the Ministry of the Interior.
To date, Algeria has had more than 40 legal political parties.
According to the Constitution, no political association may be formed if it is "based on differences in religion, language, race gender or region."
Algeria's Parliamentary parties are:

The People's National Army consits of 127,500 members, with some 100,000 reservists.
The army is under the control of the president, who also is minister of National Defense (current president is Abdelaziz Bouteflika).
Defense expenditures accounted for some $2.67 billion or 3.5% of GDP.
One and a half years of national military service is compulsory for males.

Algeria is a leading military power in North Africa and has its force oriented toward its western (Morocco) and eastern (Libya) borders.
Its primary military supplier has been the former Soviet Union, which has sold various types of sophisticated equipment under military trade agreements, and the People's Republic of China.
Algeria has attempted, in recent years, to diversify its sources of military material.
Military forces are supplemented by a 45,000-member gendarmerie or rural police force under the control of the president and 30,000-member Sûreté nationale or Metropolitan police force under the Ministry of the Interior.

Currently (since 1983) they are:  Since Roman times Algeria has been noted for the fertility of its soil.
About a quarter of the inhabitants are engaged in agricultural pursuits.
More than 7,500,000 acres (30,000 km²) are devoted to the cultivation of cereal grains.
The Tell is the grain-growing land.
During the time of French rule its productivity was increased substantially by the sinking of artesian wells in districts which only required water to make them fertile.
Of the crops raised, wheat, barley and oats are the principal cereals.
A great variety of vegetables and of fruits, especially citrus products, is exported.

A considerable amount of cotton was grown at the time of the United States' Civil War, but the industry declined afterwards.
In the early years of the 20th century efforts to extend the cultivation of the plant were renewed.
A small amount of cotton is also grown in the southern oases.
Large quantities of crin vegetal (vegetable horse-hair) an excellent fibre, are made from the leaves of the dwarf palm.
The olive (both for its fruit and Petroleum) and tobacco are cultivated with great success.

Ninety-nine percent of the population is classified ethnically as Arab/Berber and religiously as Sunni Muslim, the few non-Sunni Muslims are mainly Ibadis from the M'Zab valley.
(See also Islam in Algeria.)

Housing and medicine continue to be pressing problems in Algeria.
Failing infrastructure and the continued influx of people from rural to urban areas has overtaxed both systems.
According to the UNDP, Algeria has one of the world's highest per housing unit occupancy rates for housing, and government officials have publicly stated that the country has an immediate shortfall of 1.5 million housing units.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1667381" end="116" start="105">On the pretext of a slight to their consul, the French invaded Algiers in 1830.
In contrast to Morocco and Tunisia, the conquest of Algeria by the French was long and particularly violent and resulted in the disappearance of about a third of the Algerian population.
France was responsible for the extermination of 1.5 million Algerians.
According to Olivier Le Cour Grandmaison, the French pursued a policy of extermination against the Algerians.

Meanwhile, however, the French made Algeria an integral part of France, a status that would end only with the collapse of the Fourth Republic in 1958.
Tens of thousands of settlers from France, Italy, Spain, and Malta moved in to farm the Algerian coastal plain and occupy significant parts of Algeria's cities.
These settlers benefited from the French government's confiscation of communally held land, and the application of modern agriculture techniques that increased the amount of arable land.
Algeria's social fabric suffered during the occupation: literacy plummeted, while land confiscation uprooted much of the population.

Starting from the end of the nineteenth century, people of European descent in Algeria (or natives like Spanish people in Oran), as well as the native Algerian Jews (typically Sephardic in origin), became full French citizens.
After Algeria's 1962 independence, they were called Pieds-Noirs.
In contrast, the vast majority of Muslim Algerians (even veterans of the French army) received neither French citizenship nor the right to vote.</entry>
</article>
