<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="569" title="Anthropology" authors="9" lines="506">
  <entry author_id="82856" end="66" start="0">While anthropologists today claim a number of earlier thinkers as their forebearers and the discipline itself could be traced to many roots, anthropology can best be understood as an outgrowth of the Age of Enlightenment.
It was during this period that Europeans attempted to systematically to study human behavior.
Traditions of jurisprudence, history, philology and sociology developed during the enlightenment and informed the development of the social sciences of which anthropology was a part, while the romantic counterreaction to the Enlightenment produced thinkers such as Herder and later Wilhelm Dilthey whose work formed the basis for the culture concept which is central to the discipline.

Institutionally, however, anthropology emerged from the natural history (expounded by authors such as Buffon) as the study of human beings - typically people living in European colonies.
Thus studying the language, culture, physiology, and artifacts of European colonies was more or less equivalent to studying the flora and fauna of those places.
It was for this reason, for instance, that Lewis Henry Morgan could write monographs on both the The League of the Iroquois and The American Beaver and His Works.
It is for this reason, for example, that the material culture of 'civilized' nations such as China have historically been displayed in fine arts museums alongside European art while artifacts from African or Native North American cultures were displayed in Natural History Museums with dinosaur bones and nature dioramas.
This being said, curatorial practice has changed dramatically in recent years, and it would be wrong to see anthropology as merely an extension of colonial rule and European chauvinism, since its relationship to imperialism was and is complex.

Anthropology grew increasingly distinct from natural history and by the end of the nineteenth century the discipline began to crystallize into its modern form - by 1935, for example, it was possible for T.K.
Penniman to write a history of the discipline entitles A Hundred Years of Anthropology.
At the time, the field was dominated by 'the comparative method'.
It was assummed that all societies passed through a single evolutionary scale from most primitive to most advanced.
Non-European societies were thus seen as evolutionary dead ends that could be studied in order to understand European societies before they evolved.
Scholars wrote histories of prehistoric migrations which were often fanciful.
It was during this time that Europeans first accurately traced Polynesian migrations across the Pacific Ocean for instance - although some of them believed it originated in Egypt.
Finally, the concept of race was actively discussed as a way to classify - and rank - human beings based on inherent biological difference.
Anthropology in the United States was essentially founded by Franz Boas, who used his positions at Columbia University and the American Museum of Natural History to train and develop multiple generations of students.
Boasian anthropology was politically active and suspicious of generalizations.
Boas studied immigrant children in order to demonstrate that biological race was not immutable and that humans conduct and behavior was the result of nature rather than nurture.
Drawing on his German roots, he argued that the world was full of distinct 'cultures' rather than societies whose evolution could be measured by how much or how little 'civilization' they had.
Boas felt that each culture has to be studied in its particularity, and argued that cross-cultural generalizations like those made in the natural sciences were not possible.
In doing so Boas fought discrimination against immigrants, African Americans, and Native North Americans.

Boas's first generation of students included Alfred Kroeber, Robert Lowie, and Edward Sapir.
All of these scholars produced richly detailed studies which were to first to describe Native North America.
In doing so they provided a wealth of details used to attack evolutionary theory.
Their focus on Native American languages also helped establish linguistics as a truly general science and free it from its historical focus on Indo-European languages.

The publication of Alfred Kroeber's textbook Anthropology marked a turning point in American anthropology.
After three decades of amassing material the urge to generalize grew.
This was most obvious in the 'Culture and Personality' studies carried out by younger Boasians such as Margaret Mead and Ruth Benedict.
Influenced by psychologists such as Sigmund Freud and Carl Jung, these authors sought to understand that way that individual personalities were shaped by the wider cultural and social forces in which they grew up.
While Culture and Personality works such as Coming of Age in Samoa and The Chrysanthemum and the Sword remain popular with the American public, Mead and Benedict never had the impact on the discipline of anthropology that some expected.
While Boas had planned that Ruth Benedict succeed him as chair of Columbia's anthropology department, she was sidelined by Ralph Linton, and Mead was limited to her offices at the ANHM.
Whereas Boas picked his opponents to pieces through attention to detail, in Britain modern anthropology was formed by rejecting historical reconstruction in the name of a science of society that focused on analyzing how societies held together in the present.

The two most important names in this tradition were Alfred Reginald Radcliffe-Brown and Bronislaw Malinowski, both of whom released seminal works in 1922.
Radcliffe-Brown's initial fieldwork in the Andaman Islands was carried out in the old style, but after reading Emile Durkheim he published an account of his research (entitled simply The Andaman Islanders) which drew heavily on the French sociologist.
Over time he developed an approach known as structure-functionalism, which focused on how institutions in societies worked to balance out or create an equilibirum in the social system to keep it functioning harmoniously.
Malinowski, on the other hand, advocated an unhyphenated 'functionalism' which examined how society functioned to meet individual needs.
Malinowski is best known not for his theory, however, but for his detailed ethnography and advances in methodology.
His classic Argonauts of the Western Pacific advocated getting 'the native's point of view' and an approach to field work that became standard in the field.

Malinowksi and Radcliffe-Brown's success stem from the fact that they, like Boas, actively trained students and aggresively built up institutions which furthered their programmatic ambitions.
This was particularly the case with Radcliffe-Brown, who spread his agenda for 'Social Anthropology' by teaching at universities across the Commonwealth.
From the late 1930s until the post-war period a string of monographs and edited volumes appeared which cemented the paradigm of British Social Anthropology.
Famous ethnographies include The Nuer by Edward Evan Evans-Pritchard and The Dynamics of Clanship Among the Tallensi by Meyer Fortes, while well known edited volumes include African Systems of Kinship and Marriage and African Political Systems.
Anthropology in France has a less clear genealogy than the British and American traditions.
Most commentators consider Marcel Mauss to be the founder of the French anthropological tradition.
Mauss was a member of Durkheim's Annee Sociologique group, and while Durkheim and other examined the state of modern societies, Mauss and his collaborators (such as Henri Hubert and Robert Hertz) drew on ethnography and philology to analyze societies which were not as 'differentiated' as European nation states.
In particular, Mauss's Essay on the Gift was to prove of enduring relevance in anthropological studies of exchange and reciprocity.

Above all, however, it was Claude Levi-Strauss who helped institutionalize anthropology in France.
In addition to the enormous influence his structuralism exerted across multiple disciplines, Levi-Strauss established ties with American and British anthropologists.
At the same time he established centers and labratories within France to provide an institutional context within anthropology while training influential students such as Maurice Godelier and Francoise Heritier who would prove influential in the world of French anthropology.
Before WWII British 'social anthropology' and American 'cultural anthropology' were still distinct traditions.
It was after the war that the two would blend to create a 'sociocultural' anthropology.

In the 1950s and mid 1960s anthropology tended increasingly to model itself after the natural sciences.
Some such as Llyd Fallers and Clifford Geertz focused on processes on modernization by which newly independent states could develop.
Others, such as Julian Steward and Leslie White focused on how societies evolve and fit their ecological niche - an approach popularized by Marvin Harris.
Economic Anthropology as influenced by Karl Polanyi and practiced by Marshall Sahlins and Greg Dalton focused on how traditional economics ignored cultural and social factors.
In England, British Social Anthropology's paradigm began to fragment as Max Gluckman and Peter Worsley experimented with Marxism and authors such as Rodney Needham and Edmund Leach incorporated Levi-Strauss's structuralism into their work.

Structuralism also influenced a number of development in 1960s and 1970s, including cognitive anthropology and componential analysis.
Authors such as David Schneider, Clifford Geertz, and Marshall Sahlins developed a more fleshed out concept of culture as a web or meaning or signification which proved very popular.
In keeping with the times, much of anthropology became politicized through its opposition to the Vietnam War and the Algerian War of Independence and the authors of volumes such as Reinventing Anthropology worried about its relevance and Marxism became more and more popular in the discipline.

In the 1980s issues of power, such as those examined in Eric Wolf's Europe and the People Without History - were central to the discipline.
Books like Anthropology and the Colonial Equality pondered anthropology's ties to colonial inequality, while the immense popularity of authors such as Antonio Gramsci and Michel Foucault moved issues of power and hegemony into the spotlight.
Gender and sexuality became a popular topic, as did the relationship between history and anthropology, influenced by Marshall Sahlins (again) who drew on Levi-Strauss and Fernand Braudel to examine the relationship between cultural structure and individual agency.

In the late 1980s and 1990s authors such as George Marcus and James Clifford pondered ethnographic authority and how and why anthropological knowledge was possible and authoritative.
This was part of a more general trend of postmodernism that was popular.
Currently anthropology focuses on globalization, medicine and biotechnology, indigenous rights, and the anthropology of Europe.</entry>
  <entry author_id="98" end="77" start="66">These intellectual movements in part grappled with one of the greatest paradoxes of modernity: as the world is becoming smaller and more integrated, people's experience of the world is increasingly atomized and dispersed.
As Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels observed in the 1840s:  Ironically, this universal interdependence, rather than leading to greater human solidarity, has coincided with increasing racial, ethnic, religious, and class divisions, and new – and to some confusing or disturbing – cultural expressions.

In the twentieth century academic disciplines began to organize around three main domains.
The "sciences" seeks to derive natural laws through reproducable and falsifiable experiments.
The "humanities" reflected an attempt to study different national traditions, in the form of history and the arts, as an attempt to provide people in emerging nation-states with a sense of coherence.
The "social sciences" emerged at this time as an attempt to develop scientific methods to address social phenomena, in an attempt to provide a universal basis for social knowledge.
Anthropology does not easily fit into one of these categories, and different branches of anthropology draw on one or more of these domains.

Drawing on the methods of the natural sciences as well as developing new techniques involving not only structured interviews but unstructured "participant-observation" – and drawing on the new theory of evolution through natural selection, they proposed the scientific study of a new object: "humankind," conceived of as a whole.
Crucial to this study is the concept "culture," which anthropologists defined both as a universal capacity and propensity for social learning, thinking, and acting (which they see as a product of human evolution and something that distinguishes Homo sapiens – and perhaps all species of genus Homo – from other species), and as a particular adaptation to local conditions that takes the form of highly variable beliefs and practices.
Thus, "culture" not only transcends the opposition between nature and nurture; it transcends and absorbs the peculiarly European distinction between politics, religion, kinship, and the economy as autonomous domains.
Anthropology thus transcends the divisions between the natural sciences, social sciences, and humanities to explore the biological, linguistic, material, and symbolic dimensions of humankind in all forms.</entry>
  <entry author_id="263343" end="201" start="77">By Ubirathan Miranda.
Theologian.
Life Christian Univesrity

What do liberalism, atheism, communism, socialism; humanism, evolutionism, and Satanism have in common?
Could all of these distinct beliefs and ideologies actually be related?
Is there a common thread linking these systems of thought?
Yes.
Not only is there a link, but all of these belief systems are linked not only in essence, but also in an agenda.
That agenda has been carefully and cleverly concealed from the human race by dark spiritual powers bent on the destruction and damnation of every human soul on this planet.
It is a dark and dangerous agenda that is now in full bloom, not only in America, but all around the globe.
All societies, regardless of race, religion, or nationality have been impacted by this insidious agenda from the very pit of hell.
Its ultimate end is the destruction and eternal separation of the human race from the very loving God who created it.
But while progressing towards its ultimate goal, this agenda continues to bring death, destruction and pain in all societies.
The precepts of this agenda touch all members of the human race, regardless of ethnicity, social standing, economics or education.
Unless recognized, this agenda will continue to reap victims along the way and leave pain, destruction, and mayhem along the way.

The doctrine of the self is so inherently dangerous in its implications and so destructive to the human race that at the end of the ages only the intervention of God Himself will bring an end to it.
To understand the doctrine itself, it’s important to understand the genesis of this doctrine.
To be self-aware, to be sentient, and to have the ability for consciousness and free-will is one of God’s greatest gifts to His creation, be it angelic or human.
That ability should only causes us to be further closer to the Creator.
It’s not a dependency based on fear or the mandate from the Monarch of the Universe.
This is a dependence and adoration based on love and gratefulness to God.
It is indeed a wonderful mutually-satisfying relationship with the Almighty.
In it, humanity finds its ultimate fulfillment as unique individuals, beloved by the Creator.
In it, the Lord enjoys fellowship and camaraderie with His creation, for all of God’s creation, only humanity has in its soul God’s very image.
At the onset of the creation, the fulfillment of the self, be it angelic or human, was based solely on the individual’s relationship with God.
In God’s created order, the fulfillment of the self without regards to godly norms, conventions and boundaries was an aberration, an anomaly closely linked with sinful and willful rebellion.
This selfish fulfillment of the self was contrary to natural and spiritual norms and consequently, deadly both physically and spiritually.

Lucifer, in his quest to fulfill the self, became the originator of the concept and process of adulation, adoration and the fulfillment of the self regardless of cost to the individual and society.
Lucifer in a sense became the first cause in regards to the pursuit and ultimate establishment of the doctrine of the self.
The fallen cherub became the foundation stone on which the further manifestations of the worship of the self would be played upon the stage of the human experience.
And how painful that experience would be as the worship of the self would be the foundational bedrock on which rebellious individuals would base their lust for the self and self aggrandizement.
Throughout the centuries, these manifestations of the self would take different philosophical and ideological shape and forms and leave their destructive marks in the human experience.

4 that you will take up this proverb against the king of Babylon, and say: "How the oppressor has ceased, The golden city ceased!
5 The Lord has broken the staff of the wicked, The scepter of the rulers; 6 He who struck the people in wrath with a continual stroke, He who ruled the nations in anger, Is persecuted and no one hinders.
7 The whole earth is at rest and quiet; They break forth into singing.
8 Indeed the cypress trees rejoice over you, And the cedars of Lebanon, Saying, 'Since you were cut down, No woodsman has come up against us.'
9 "Hell from beneath is excited about you, To meet you at your coming; It stirs up the dead for you, All the chief ones of the earth; It has raised up from their thrones All the kings of the nations.
10 They all shall speak and say to you: 'Have you also become as weak as we?
Have you become like us?
11 Your pomp is brought down to Sheol, And the sound of your stringed instruments; The maggot is spread under you, And worms cover you.'
12 "How you are fallen from heaven, O Lucifer, son of the morning!
How you are cut down to the ground, You who weakened the nations!
13 For you have said in your heart: 'I will ascend into heaven, I will exalt my throne above the stars of God; I will also sit on the mount of the congregation On the farthest sides of the north; 14 I will ascend above the heights of the clouds, I will be like the Most High.'
15 Yet you shall be brought down to Sheol, To the lowest depths of the Pit.
16 "Those who see you will gaze at you, And consider you, saying: 'Is this the man who made the earth tremble, Who shook kingdoms, 17 Who made the world as a wilderness And destroyed its cities, Who did not open the house of his prisoners?'
18 "All the kings of the nations, All of them, sleep in glory, Everyone in his own house; 19 But you are cast out of your grave Like an abominable branch, Like the garment of those who are slain, Thrust through with a sword, Who go down to the stones of the pit, Like a corpse trodden underfoot.
20 You will not be joined with them in burial, Because you have destroyed your land And slain your people.
The brood of evildoers shall never be named.
21 Prepare slaughter for his children Because of the iniquity of their fathers, Lest they rise up and possess the land, And fill the face of the world with cities."
22 "For I will rise up against them," says the Lord of hosts, "And cut off from Babylon the name and remnant, And offspring and posterity," says the Lord.

When asked if Satanists worship the Devil, Anton LaVey, the founder of the Church of Satan in America, answered that in reality Satan is only an example for Satanist to follow.
That in reality, a Satanist worships only the self.
This is of course in line with Luciferian philosophy and practice.
At its core, Satanism is only the worship of the self regardless of cost or consequence to anyone else or society in general.
The fulfillment of one’s desires is the very foundation of Satanism.
Lucifer and his rebellion against God is only used as an example of how to accomplish that basic foundational belief and apply the Satanic philosophic concept in the life of the individual.

It can be said that humanism is a philosophy of good intentions but devoid of any real life or godly principles.
Sophocles, the brilliant ancient playwright summed up the very essence of humanism when he stated that man is the measure of all things.
Humanistic philosophy places in kind the ultimate solution for all the woes that assails humanity without the need for Divine intervention.
Humanism in a sense elevates mankind to the level of deity and delegates humanity the role of the gods of the age, completely able to conquer any challenge that is placed in its path.
This of course has been proven wrong due to the inability of humanity to tame or control its fallen nature and tendency to lean towards evil.
If anything, the wars, genocides, and plagues of the twentieth century deal the philosophy of humanism a deadly blow.
However, humanism continues to plague humanity with its empty braggadocio and promises of a better and enlightened future while neglecting the main fallacy of the philosophy: the enshrinement of the self, the worship of the human nature and the rejection of the Divine.
Again, at its essence, humanism is simply Satanism posed as a spiritually-neutral and entirely human philosophy and practice of the exaltation of the self.

In its rejection of any form of religion or belief in God, atheism proves to be another satanic philosophy in that atheism exalts the self.
It embraces humanism philosophically while at its core lies the very elevation of the self.
It could be said that atheism is a religious expression of humanism.
While denying God’s very existence, atheists do elevate the self, the ego, the human nature, condition and experience.
The self if placed on the altar of the spirit and humanism is used as a means to placate the voice of conscience.
The atheist’s belief is in the very nature of humanism and the abilities of the self rather than the existence of the Divine and the human dependence on God.

Charles Darwin’s theory of evolution has become one of the cornerstone beliefs of modern-day scientists.
Not only has the theory of evolution revolutionized the scientific field, but it has impacted other academic and social fields as well.
The Nazis used Darwin’s theory to justify their demented pseudo-science obsession with race and was a foundational element to justify the Holocaust.
At its core, evolution is truly about the struggle of the self against one’s hostile environment.
The survival of the fittest translates into the law of the jungle, and by application, the theory lends itself to all sorts of applications in several concepts, but the overall theme is the focus on the lack of any Divine intervention and the complete trust in the inner and supposed random works of nature.
The strength of the self is celebrated, the focus mainly on the continuous evolutionary nature of man and nature.
Evolution not only negates Divine intervention and creation by Divine fiat, but strips mankind of the very image of God.
It’s a direct rejection of the Divine and once again the exaltation of the self.
The very fact that evolution has been disproved as a viable theory is to no effect to the scientific and academia community.
Not a single shred of fossil evidence exists to link present humanity with the hominids of the past and yet, most scientists still persist in their stubborn embrace of this failed theory.
To deny the theory of evolution would mean a complete acceptance of God’s existence and His direct act of creation.
And if God is embraced, the self is no longer the main drive and focus of the system.
To profess creation by Divine fiat would deal a death blow to many of the extension of the theory of evolution in many of our current philosophical theories and concepts and ultimately, its practices.
Thus, the survival of the theory of evolution in the face of so many concrete contradictory evidence as to its veracity proves that the theory should really be known as the survival of the stubborn self.

Communism and socialism is simply a political extension of the doctrine of the self.
It could really be argued that socialism and communism are in essence the same political theory.
Socialism is simply a blander version of communism with capitalist and democratic elements thrown in the mix.
The insidiousness of communism is the fact that the state attempts to supplant God in matters of faith and spiritual needs.
The state becomes the great provider of not only material and social goods, but also the provider of the intrinsic needs of human being.
In one hand the state denies the very existence of God and on the other, the state attempts to become God.
In communism, the state absorbs the self and by extension, the self becomes the state and takes on the characteristics of the state.
The supremacy of the state is in a fact a simple exaltation of the self.
When communism speaks of the collective will of the people, it is simply stating the will of the self as transformed by the will of the state.
Without the Luciferian basis of the foundational doctrine of the self, the, the philosophy of humanism, and the pseudo-science theory of evolution, communism cannot exist.
Once again, the self, albeit translated into the collective will and essence of the state, is the main focus and modus operandi of communism.

Liberalism is a political and social philosophy based entirely on the worship and fulfilling of the self.
Liberalism is a very egocentric philosophy despite the deception posed by liberals concerning their pseudo-compassion for the masses.
Most liberals are deep believers in alternate systems of religious belief which centers mostly on the rejection of the Judeo-Christian articles of faith and values and world-view.
By far, most alternate religious systems are based solely or partly on the fulfillment of the self regardless of consequence to the self or one’s community.
Liberalism is simply an extension of Luciferian philosophy, humanism, evolutionism, socialism and communism.
It is a system of beliefs that encompasses the enshrinement of the self to the exclusion of others.
Liberals are wont to call themselves compassionate people.
That is true when it comes to the adoption and absorption of their beliefs by the blind masses.
But their level of intolerance is most evident when faced with opposition.
Liberals simply do not understand that the core of their liberal beliefs is Luciferian and based on the enshrinement of the self.
Liberalism is simply another politically correct way of self-gratification and aggrandizement.
Liberalism is a most evil and insidious philosophy.
It could be simply argued that liberals embrace liberalism with religious fervor and zeal simply because without liberalism their world-view and compilation of selfish beliefs crumble to the ground never again to see the light of day.

As shown throughout history, the links between the various philosophies has been exposed down to their very genesis –Luciferian philosophy.
No one with a clear mind can simply dismiss this possibility without further inquiry and soul searching.
Are all adherents to these philosophies evil?
Some are and history is proof that some leaders have utilized these philosophies in one way or another to wage war, commit atrocities, rob, and bring genocide to whole races of people.
Most who embrace the aforementioned philosophies are simply blinded to the true nature of their dearly-held philosophies.
They have been deceived by a sinister spiritual agenda with great influence over many of the world’s institutions.
There are among the deceived masses good people, great philanthropists, and individuals who truly desire to make the world a better place.
It could truly be stated that the road to perdition is paved with good intentions and the sad reality is that many a good people end up in hell.
What are we as Christians to do concerning this truly sad reality?
Should we like gorillas pound our righteous chests and leave the deceived masses on their path to spiritual deception?
No.
We must put aside religious dogma and take on the nature of Christ and by doing so; He will shine through our humanity.
We must show the deceived that we too struggle with the issues of life.
We suffer losses; are assailed by sickness; struggle with living out our faith at times; suffer temptation; give in to sin often; and are partakers of the shroud of humanity.
But at no time should we adopt the stated philosophies and practices simply to prove a point.
Because while sharing the temporal fallen human nature, we have been redeemed by the Savior and been made clean by His atoning sacrifice and shed blood at the cross of Calvary; and our living should at least reflect that reality.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1633608" end="221" start="201">--The claim that the discipline grew out of colonialism, perhaps was in league with it, and derived some of its key notions from it, consciously or not.
(See, e.g., Gough, Pels and Salemink, but cf. Lewis 2004).
It is often assumed that an example of this exploitative relationship can be seen in the relationship between of British anthropologists and colonial forces in Africa, yet this assumption has not been supported by much evidence.
(See Asad et al; cf.
Desai.)

--The idea that social and political problems must arise because anthropologists usually have more power than the people they study; it is a form of colonialist theft in which the anthropologist gains power at the expense of subjects (Rabinow, Dwyer, McGrane).
Anthropologists, they argue, can gain yet more power by exploiting knowledge and artifacts of the people they study while the people they study gain nothing, or even lose, in the exchange (e.g. Deloria).
Little critical writing has been published in response to these wide-ranging claims, themselves the product of the political concerns and atmosphere of their own times.
(See Trencher for a critique.)

--It is claimed the discipline was ahistorical, and dealt with its "objects" (sic) "out of time," to their detriment (Fabian).
It is often claimed that anthropologists regularly "exoticized 'the Other,'" or, with equal assurance, that they inappropriately universalized "Others" and "human nature."
(For references and a response see Lewis 1998.)

--Other more explicitly political concerns have to do with anthropologists’ entanglements with government intelligence agencies, on the one hand, and anti-war politics on the other.
Franz Boas publicly objected to US participation in World War I, and after the war he published a brief expose and condemnation of the participation of several American archeologists in espionage in Mexico under their cover as scientists.
But by the 1940s, many of Boas' anthropologist contemporaries were active in the allied war effort against the "Axis" (Nazi Germany, Fascist Italy, and Imperial Japan).
Many served in the armed forces but others worked in intelligence (e.g. Office of Strategic Services and the Office of War Information).
David H. Price's work on American anthropology during the Cold War provides detailed accounts of the pursuit and dismissal of several anthropologists for their vocal left-wing sympathies.
On the other hand, attempts to accuse anthropologists of complicity with the CIA and government intelligence activities during the Vietnam War years have turned up surprisingly little.
(Anthropologists did not participate in the stillborn Project Camelot, for example.)
(See Lewis 2005) On the contrary, many anthropologists (students and teachers) were active in the antiwar movement and a great many resolutions condemning the war in all its aspects were passed overwhelmingly at the annual meetings of the [[American Anthropological Association] (AAA).
</entry>
  <entry author_id="2568717" end="235" start="221">Early anthropology was divided between proponents of unilinealism, who argued that all societies passed through a single evolutionary process, from the most primitive to the most advanced, and various forms of non-lineal theorists, who tended to subscribe to ideas such as diffusionism.
Most 19th-century social theorists, including anthropologists, viewed non-European societies as windows onto the pre-industrial human past.
As academic disciplines began to differentiate over the course of the 19th century, anthropology grew increasingly distinct from natural history, on the one hand, and from purely historical or literary fields such as Classics, on the other.

In the twentieth century, academic disciplines have often been institutionally divided into three broad domains.
The natural and biological sciences seek to derive general laws through reproducible and falsifiable experiments.
The humanities generally study different local traditions, through their history, literature, music, and arts, with an emphasis on understanding particular individuals, events, or eras.
The social sciences have generally attempted to develop scientific methods to understand social phenomena in a generalizable way, though usually with methods distinct from those of the natural sciences.

Anthropology as it emerged among the colonial powers (mentioned above) has generally taken a different path than that in the countries of southern and central Europe (Italy, Greece, and the successors to the Austro-Hungarian and Ottoman empires).
In the former, the ecounter with multiple, distinct cultures, often very different in organization and language from those of Europe, has led to a continuing emphasis on cross-cultural comparison and a receptiveness to certain kinds of cultural relativism.
In the successor states of continental Europe, on the other hand, anthropologists often joined with folklorists and linguists in the nationalist/nation-building enterprise.
Ethnologists in these countries tended to focus on differentiating among local ethnolinguistic groups, documenting local folk culture, and representing the prehistory of the nation through museums and other forms of public education.
(In this scheme, Russia occupied a middle position.
On the one hand, it had a large Asian region of highly distinct, pre-industrial, often non-literate peoples, similar to the situation in the Americas; on the other hand, Russia also participated to some degree in the nationalist discourses of Central and Eastern Europe.
After the Revolution of 1917, anthropology in the USSR and later the Soviet Bloc countries were highly shaped by the need to conform to Marxist theories of social evolution.)</entry>
  <entry author_id="5028664" end="433" start="235">Anthropology (from Greek: ἀνθρωπος, anthropos, "human being"; and λόγος, logos, "knowledge") is the study of humanity.
Anthropology has origins in the natural sciences, the humanities, and the social sciences.
Ethnography is both one of its primary methods, and the text that is written as a result of the practice of anthropology.

Since the work of Franz Boas and Bronisław Malinowski in the late 19th- and early 20th-and social anthropology has been distinguished from other social science disciplines by its emphasis on in-depth examination of context, cross-cultural comparisons (socio-cultural anthropology is by nature a comparative discipline), and the importance it places on long-term, experiential immersion in the area of research, often known as participant-observation.
Cultural-Social anthropology in particular has emphasized cultural relativity and the use of their findings to frame cultural critiques.
This has been particularly prominent in America, from Boas's arguments against 19th-century racial ideology, through Margaret Mead's advocacy for gender equality and sexual liberation, to current criticisms of post-colonial oppression and promotion of multiculturalism.
The anthropologist Eric Wolf once described anthropology as "the most scientific of the humanities, and the most humanistic of the sciences."
Contemporary anthropologists claim a number of earlier thinkers as their forebears, and the discipline has several sources; Claude Lévi-Strauss, for example, claimed Montaigne and Rousseau as important influences.
Anthropology can best be understood as an outgrowth of the Age of Enlightenment, a period when Europeans attempted systematically to study human behavior, the known varieties of which had been increasing since the 15th century as a result of the First European colonization wave.
The traditions of jurisprudence, history, philology, and sociology then evolved into something more closely resembling the modern views of these disciplines and informed the development of the social sciences, of which anthropology was a part.
At the same time, the Romantic reaction to the Enlightenment produced thinkers, such as Johann Gottfried Herder and later Wilhelm Dilthey, whose work formed the basis for the "culture concept," which is central to the discipline.

Institutionally, anthropology emerged from the development of natural history (expounded by authors such as Buffon) that occurred during the European colonization of the 17th, 18th, 19th and 20th centuries.
Programs of ethnographic study originated in this era as the study of the "human primitives" overseen by colonial administrations.
There was a tendency in late 18th century Enlightenment thought to understand human society as natural phenomena that behaved in accordance with certain principles and that could be observed empirically.
In some ways, studying the language, culture, physiology, and artifacts of European colonies was not unlike studying the flora and fauna of those places.

Early anthropology was divided between proponents of unilinealism, who argued that all societies passed through a single evolutionary process, from the most primitive to the most advanced, and various forms of non-lineal theorists, who tended to subscribe to ideas such as diffusionism.
Most 19th-century social theorists, including anthropologists, viewed non-European societies as windows onto the pre-industrial human past.
As academic disciplines began to differentiate over the course of the 19th century, anthropology grew increasingly distinct from natural history, on the one hand, and from purely historical or literary fields such as Classics, on the other.
A common criticism has been that other fields focus disproportionately on the Westerns while anthropology focuses disproportionately on "others".

In the twentieth century, academic disciplines have often been institutionally divided into three broad domains.
The natural and biological sciences seek to derive general laws through reproducible and falsifiable experiments.
The humanities generally study different local traditions, through their history, literature, music, and arts, with an emphasis on understanding particular individuals, events, or eras.
The social sciences have generally attempted to develop scientific methods to understand social phenomena in a generalizable way, though usually with methods distinct from those of the natural sciences.
In particular, social sciences often develop statistical descriptions rather than the general laws derived in physics or chemistry, or they may explain individual cases through more general principles, as in many fields of psychology.
Anthropology (like some fields of history) does not easily fit into one of these categories, and different branches of anthropology draw on one or more of these domains.

Anthropology as it emerged among the colonial powers (mentioned above) has generally taken a different path than that in the countries of southern and central Europe (Italy, Greece, and the successors to the Austro-Hungarian and Ottoman empires).
In the former, the encounter with multiple, distinct cultures, often very different in organization and language from those of Europe, has led to a continuing emphasis on cross-cultural comparison and a receptiveness to certain kinds of cultural relativism.
In the successor states of continental Europe, on the other hand, anthropologists often joined with folklorists and linguists in the nationalist/nation-building enterprise.
Ethnologists in these countries tended to focus on differentiating among local ethnolinguistic groups, documenting local folk culture, and representing the prehistory of the nation through museums and other forms of public education.
In this scheme, Russia occupied a middle position.
On the one hand, it had a large Asian region of highly distinct, pre-industrial, often non-literate peoples, similar to the situation in the Americas; on the other hand, Russia also participated to some degree in the nationalist discourses of Central and Eastern Europe.
After the Revolution of 1917, anthropology in the USSR and later the Soviet Bloc countries were highly shaped by the need to conform to Marxist theories of social evolution.

E. B. Tylor (1832 October 2–1917 January 2) and James George Frazer (1854 January 1 – 1941 May 7) are generally considered the antecedents to modern sociocultural anthropology in Britain.
Though Tylor undertook a field trip to Mexico, both he and Frazer derived most of the material for their comparative studies through extensive readings of Classical materials (literature and history of Greece and Rome), the work of the early European folklorists, and reports from missionaries, travelers, and contemporaneous ethnologists.
Tylor advocated strongly for unilinealism and a form of "uniformity of mankind".
Tylor in particular laid the groundwork for theories of cultural diffusionism, stating that there are three ways that different groups can have similar cultural forms or technologies: "independent invention, inheritance from ancestors in a distant region, transmission from one race to another."
Tylor formulated one of the early and influential anthropological conceptions of culture as "that complex whole which includes knowledge, belief, art, morals, law, custom, and any other capabilities and habits acquired by man as a member of society."
However, as Stocking notes, Tylor mainly concerned himself with describing and mapping the distribution of particular elements of culture, rather than with the larger function, and generally seemed to assume a Victorian idea of progress rather than the idea of non-directional, multilineal cultural development proposed by later anthropologists.
Tylor also theorized about the origins of religious feelings in human beings, proposing a theory of animism as the earliest stage, and noting that "religion" has many components, of which he believed the most important to be belief in supernatural beings (as opposed to moral systems, cosmology, etc.).
James George Frazer, a Scottish scholar with a broad knowledge of Classics, also concerned himself with religion, myth, and magic.
His comparative studies, most influentially in the numerous editions of The Golden Bough, analyzed similarities in religious belief and symbolism worldwide.

Neither Tylor nor Frazer, however, was particularly interested in fieldwork, nor were they interested in examining how the cultural elements and institutions fit together.
Towards the turn of the century, a number of anthropologists became dissatisfied with this categorization of cultural elements; historical reconstructions also came to seem increasingly speculative.
Under the influence of several younger scholars, a new approach came to predominate among British anthropologists, concerned with analyzing how societies held together in the present (synchronic analysis, rather than diachonic or historical analysis), and emphasizing long-term (one to several years) immersion fieldwork.
Cambridge University financed a multidisciplinary expedition to the Torres Strait Islands in 1898, organized by Alfred Court Haddon and including a physician-anthropologist, W. H. R. Rivers, as well as a linguist, a botanist, other specialists.
The findings of the expedition set new standards for ethnographic description.

A decade and a half later, Polish-born anthropology student Bronisław Malinowski (1884-1942) was beginning what he expected to be a brief period of fieldwork in the old model, collecting lists of cultural items, when the outbreak of the First World War stranded him in New Guinea.
As a subject of the Austro-Hungarian Empire resident on a British colonial possession, he was effectively confined to New Guinea for several years.
He made use of the time by undertaking far more intensive fieldwork than had been done by British anthropologists, and his classic ethnography, Argonauts of the Western Pacific, (1922) advocated an approach to fieldwork that became standard in the field: getting "the native's point of view" through participant observation.
Theoretically, he advocated a functionalist interpretation, which examined how social institutions functioned to meet individual needs.

A. R. Radcliffe-Brown also published a seminal work in 1922.
He had carried out his initial fieldwork in the Andaman Islands in the old style of historical reconstruction.
However, after reading the work of French sociologists Émile Durkheim and Marcel Mauss, Radcliffe-Brown published an account of his research (entitled simply The Andaman Islanders) that paid close attention to the meaning and purpose of rituals and myths.
Over time, he developed an approach known as structural-functionalism, which focused on how institutions in societies worked to balance out or create an equilibrium in the social system to keep it functioning harmoniously.
(This contrasted with Malinowski's functionalism, and was quite different from the later French structuralism, which examined the conceptual structures in language and symbolism.)

Malinowski and Radcliffe-Brown's influence stemmed from the fact that they, like Boas, actively trained students and aggressively built up institutions that furthered their programmatic ambitions.
This was particularly the case with Radcliffe-Brown, who spread his agenda for "Social Anthropology" by teaching at universities across the British Commonwealth.
From the late 1930s until the postwar period appeared a string of monographs and edited volumes that cemented the paradigm of British Social Anthropology (BSA).
Famous ethnographies include The Nuer, by Edward Evan Evans-Pritchard, and The Dynamics of Clanship Among the Tallensi, by Meyer Fortes; well-known edited volumes include African Systems of Kinship and Marriage and African Political Systems.

Max Gluckman, together with many of his colleagues at the Rhodes-Livingstone Institute and students at Manchester University, collectively known as the Manchester School, took BSA in new directions through their introduction of explicitly Marxist-informed theory, their emphasis on conflicts and conflict resolution, and their attention to the ways in which individuals negotiate and make use of the social structural possibilities.
Later in the 1960s and 1970s, Edmund Leach and his students Mary Douglas and Nur Yalman, among others, introduced French structuralism in the style of Lévi-Strauss; while British anthropology has continued to emphasize social organization and economics over purely symbolic or literary topics, differences among British, French, and American sociocultural anthropologies have diminished with increasing dialogue and borrowing of both theory and methods.
Today, social anthropology in Britain engages internationally with many other social theories and has branched in many directions.

In countries of the British Commonwealth, social anthropology has often been institutionally separate from physical anthropology and primatology, which may be connected with departments of biology or zoology; and from archaeology, which may be connected with departments of Classics, Egyptology, and the like.
In other countries (and in some, particularly smaller, British and North American universities), anthropologists have also found themselves institutionally linked with scholars of folklore, museum studies, human geography, sociology, social relations, ethnic studies, cultural studies, and social work.
From its beginnings in the early 19th century through the early 20th century, anthropology in the United States was influenced by the presence of Native American societies.
As in other colonial powers (including Britain, France, Spain, Portugal, and the countries of Latin America) this encounter with colonial subjects manifested in several ways.
Curiosity, admiration, desire to "reform" or "civilize" native practices, or simple puzzlement at how societies could function with such different social and political systems, all motivated early ethnographers.
Practical concerns of Christian missionaries and colonial administrators, seeking to communicate with native peoples or figure out how to incorporate them, helped gain funding and institutional attention.
Statements of ethnologists (as well as many amateurs, missionaries, and colonial administrators, who were not clearly distinguished from more committed scholars in this era prior to professionalization of anthropology) often played into political debates around the definition humanity and citizenship.
These conflicts between what may be seen as the pursuit of pure knowledge or the facilitation of intercultural understanding on the one hand, and the potentially exploitative, oppressive, or coercive uses to which that knowledge might be put, on the other, concerned many early anthropologists and has become a major source of controversy and self-examination within the discipline since at least the mid-20th century.
The claim that anthropology accompliced to the "project of colonialism" is a misconception mostly based on few "slander pieces" from the 1960s and 70s.

Cultural anthropology in the United States was influenced greatly by the ready availability of Native American societies as ethnographic subjects.
The field was pioneered by staff of the Bureau of Indian Affairs and the Smithsonian Institution's Bureau of American Ethnology, men such as John Wesley Powell and Frank Hamilton Cushing.
Lewis Henry Morgan (1818-1881), a lawyer from Rochester, New York, became an advocate for and ethnological scholar of the Iroquois.
His comparative analyses of religion, government, material culture, and especially kinship patterns proved to be influential contributions to the field of anthropology.
Like other scholars of his day (such as Edward Tylor), Morgan argued that human societies could be classified into categories of cultural evolution on a scale of progression that ranged from savagery, to barbarism, to civilization.
Generally, Morgan used technology (such as bowmaking or pottery) as an indicator of position on this scale.

Franz Boas established academic anthropology in the United States in opposition to this sort of evolutionary perspective.
Boasian anthropology was politically active and suspicious of research dictated by the U.S. government and wealthy patrons.
It was rigorously empirical and skeptical of overgeneralizations and attempts to establish universal laws.
Boas studied immigrant children to demonstrate that biological race was not immutable, and that human conduct and behavior resulted from nurture, rather than nature.

Influenced by the German tradition, Boas argued that the world was full of distinct cultures, rather than societies whose evolution could be measured by how much or how little "civilization" they had.
He believed that each culture has to be studied in its particularity, and argued that cross-cultural generalizations, like those made in the natural sciences, were not possible.
In doing so, he fought discrimination against immigrants, African Americans, and Native North Americans.
Many American anthropologists adopted his agenda for social reform, and theories of race continue to be popular targets for anthropologists today.
The so-called "Four Field Approach" has its origins in Boasian Anthropology, dividing the discipline in the four crucial and interrelated fields of sociocultural, biological, linguistic, and prehistoric anthropology.

Boas used his positions at Columbia University and the American Museum of Natural History to train and develop multiple generations of students.
His first generation of students included Alfred Kroeber, Robert Lowie, Edward Sapir and Ruth Benedict, all of whom produced richly detailed studies of indigenous North American cultures.
They provided a wealth of details used to attack the theory of a single evolutionary process.
Kroeber and Sapir's focus on Native American languages helped establish linguistics as a truly general science and free it from its historical focus on Indo-European languages.

The publication of Alfred Kroeber's textbook, Anthropology, marked a turning point in American anthropology.
After three decades of amassing material, Boasians felt a growing urge to generalize.
This was most obvious in the 'Culture and Personality' studies carried out by younger Boasians such as Margaret Mead and Ruth Benedict.
Influenced by psychoanalytic psychologists such as Sigmund Freud and Carl Jung, these authors sought to understand the way that individual personalities were shaped by the wider cultural and social forces in which they grew up.
Though such works as Coming of Age in Samoa and The Chrysanthemum and the Sword remain popular with the American public, Mead and Benedict never had the impact on the discipline of anthropology that some expected.
Boas had planned for Ruth Benedict to succeed him as chair of Columbia's anthropology department, but she was sidelined by Ralph Linton, and Mead was limited to her offices at the AMNH.
Canadian anthropology began, as in other parts of the Colonial world, as ethnological data in the records of travellers and missionaries.
In Canada, Jesuit missionaries such as Fathers LeClercq, Le Jeune and Sagard, in the 1600s, provide the oldest ethnographic records of native tribes in what was then the Domain of Canada.

True anthropology began with a Government department: the Geological Survey of Canada, and George Mercer Dawson (director in 1895).
Dawson's support for anthropology created impetus for the profession in Canada.
This was expanded upon by Prime Minister Wilfrid Laurier, who established a Division of Anthropology within the Geological Survey in 1910.
Anthropologists were recruited from England and the USA, setting the foundation for the unique Canadian style of anthropology.
Early scholars include the brilliant linguist and Boasian, Edward Sapir, also Oxford graduates Marius Barbeau and Diamond Jenness.
Born in rural Québec, Barbeau became a Rhodes scholar and eventually a classmate of Jenness.
The two studied under Tylor and Marett at Oxford.
In Canada, Barbeau and Jenness worked at the National Museum (as it became known later).
In 1944, Canada's first home-grown anthropologist established the archive which has become a key source of ethnographic and folklore material.

Following George Mercer Dawson (of McGill, Montreal) and Franz Boas, Sapir and Barbeau conducted ethnographic research and collected material culture from the peoples of the Northwest Coast, especially Haida.
Jenness is best known for his research in the Arctic among the Copper Inuit.
However, in actuality, they all worked in a variety of areas in Canada, recording traditions and songs, studying languages, and collecting artifacts for the museum.
They essentially had sole responsibility for the development of the profession in Canada from 1910 until 1925 when Sapir left.
The development was slow relative to expansion (due to the colonizing needs) of Britain and the USA.

The first academic position in anthropology at a Canadian university was awarded to Thomas McIlwraith at the University of Toronto in 1925.
The next universities to hire anthropologists, UBC and McGill, did so only in 1947.
The first PhD in anthropology was granted in 1956, with only a few more being granted until the late 1960s.
The 1970s brought a boom in university development and in professional anthropology, and by 1980 about 400 people with doctorates in anthropology were employed in Canada, and many more with a master's degree.
Harry Hawthorne built the department at UBC and set a standard for the use of anthropological research as a guide to public policy in his classic report to the federal government, coauthored by M.-A.
Tremblay, "A Survey of the Contemporary Indians of Canada" (1966, 1967).

Anthropology in France has a less clear genealogy than the British and American traditions, in part because many French writers influential in anthropology have been trained or held faculty positions in sociology, philosophy, or other fields rather than in anthropology.
Most commentators consider Marcel Mauss (1872-1950), nephew of the influential sociologist Émile Durkheim to be the founder of the French anthropological tradition.
Mauss belonged to Durkheim's Année Sociologique group; and while Durkheim and others examined the state of modern societies, Mauss and his collaborators (such as Henri Hubert and Robert Hertz) drew on ethnography and philology to analyze societies which were not as 'differentiated' as European nation states.
Two works by Mauss in particular proved to have enduring relevance: Essay on the Gift a seminal analysis of exchange and reciprocity, and his Huxley lecture on the notion of the person, the first comparative study of notions of person and selfhood cross-culturally.

Throughout the interwar years, French interest in anthropology often dovetailed with wider cultural movements such as surrealism and primitivism which drew on ethnography for inspiration.
Marcel Griaule and Michel Leiris are examples of people who combined anthropology with the French avant-garde.
During this time most of what is known as ethnologie was restricted to museums, such as the Musée de l'Homme founded by Paul Rivet, and anthropology had a close relationship with studies of folklore.

Above all, however, it was Claude Lévi-Strauss who helped institutionalize anthropology in France.
In addition to the enormous influence his structuralism exerted across multiple disciplines, Lévi-Strauss established ties with American and British anthropologists.
At the same time he established centers and laboratories within France to provide an institutional context within anthropology while training influential students such as Maurice Godelier and Françoise Héritier who would prove influential in the world of French anthropology.
Much of the distinct character of France's anthropology today is a result of the fact that most anthropology is carried out in nationally funded research laboratories (CNRS) rather than academic departments in universities.

Other influential writers in the 1970s include Pierre Clastres, who explains in his books on the Guayaki tribe in Paraguay that "primitive societies" actively oppose the institution of the state.
Therefore, these stateless societies are not less evolved than societies with states, but took the active choice of conjuring the institution of authority as a separate function from society.
The leader is only a spokesperson for the group when it has to deal with other groups ("international relations") but has no inside authority, and may be violently removed if he attempts to abuse this position.

The most important French social theorist since Foucault and Lévi-Strauss is Pierre Bourdieu, who trained formally in philosophy and sociology and eventually held the Chair of Sociology at the Collège de France.
Like Mauss and others before him, however, he worked on topics both in sociology and anthropology.
His fieldwork among the Kabyles of Algeria places him solidly in anthropology, while his analysis of the function and reproduction of fashion and cultural capital in European societies places him as solidly in sociology.
Anthropology in Greece and Portugal is much influenced by British anthropology.
In Greece, there was since the 19th century a science of the folklore called laographia (laography), in the form of "a science of the interior", although theoretically weak; but the connotation of the field deeply changed after World War II, when a wave of Anglo-American anthropologists introduced a science "of the outside".
In Italy, the development of ethnology and related studies did not received as much attention as other branches of learning.

Germany and Norway are the countries that showed the most division and conflict between scholars focusing on domestic socio-cultural issues and scholars focusing on "other" societies.
Before WWII British 'social anthropology' and American 'cultural anthropology' were still distinct traditions.
After the war, enough British and American anthropologists either borrowed ideas and approaches from each other that some began to speak of them collectively as 'sociocultural' anthropology.

In the 1950s and mid-1960s anthropology tended increasingly to model itself after the natural sciences.
Some anthropologists, such as Lloyd Fallers and Clifford Geertz, focused on processes of modernization by which newly independent states could develop.
Others, such as Julian Steward and Leslie White, focused on how societies evolve and fit their ecological niche — an approach popularized by Marvin Harris.
Economic anthropology as influenced by Karl Polanyi and practiced by Marshall Sahlins and George Dalton focused on how traditional economics ignored cultural and social factors.
In England, British Social Anthropology's paradigm began to fragment as Max Gluckman and Peter Worsley experimented with Marxism and authors such as Rodney Needham and Edmund Leach incorporated Lévi-Strauss's structuralism into their work.

Structuralism also influenced a number of developments in 1960s and 1970s, including cognitive anthropology and componential analysis.
Authors such as David Schneider, Clifford Geertz, and Marshall Sahlins developed a more fleshed-out concept of culture as a web of meaning or signification, which proved very popular within and beyond the discipline.
In keeping with the times, much of anthropology became politicized through the Algerian War of Independence and opposition to the Vietnam War; Marxism became a more and more popular theoretical approach in the discipline.
By the 1970s the authors of volumes such as Reinventing Anthropology worried about anthropology's relevance.

In the 1980s issues of power, such as those examined in Eric Wolf's Europe and the People Without History, were central to the discipline.
Books like Anthropology and the Colonial Encounter pondered anthropology's ties to colonial inequality, while the immense popularity of theorists such as Antonio Gramsci and Michel Foucault moved issues of power and hegemony into the spotlight.
Gender and sexuality became popular topics, as did the relationship between history and anthropology, influenced by Marshall Sahlins (again), who drew on Lévi-Strauss and Fernand Braudel to examine the relationship between social structure and individual agency.
Also influential in these issues were Nietzsche, Heidegger, the critical theory of the Frankfurt School, Derrida and Lacan.

In the late 1980s and 1990s authors such as George Marcus and James Clifford pondered ethnographic authority, particularly how and why anthropological knowledge was possible and authoritative.
They were reflecting trends in research and discourse initiated by Feminists in the academy, although they excused themselves from commenting specifically on those pioneering critics.
Nevertheless, key aspects of feminist theorsing and methods became de rigeur as part of the 'post-modern moment' in anthropology: Ethnographies became more reflexive, explicitly addressing the author's methodology, cultural, gender and racial positioning, and their influence on his or her ethnographic analysis.
This was part of a more general trend of postmodernism that was popular contemporaneously.
Currently anthropologists have begun to pay attention to globalization, medicine and biotechnology, indigenous rights, and the anthropology of industrialized societies.
Principally in the United States, anthropology is often defined as being "holistic" and based on a "four-field" approach.
There is an ongoing dispute on this view; supporters consider anthropology holistic in two senses: it is concerned with all human beings across times and places, and with all dimensions of humanity (evolutionary, biophysical, sociopolitical, economic, cultural, psychological, etc.); also many academic programs following this approach take a "four-field" approach to anthropology that encompasses physical anthropology, archeology, linguistics, and cultural anthropology or social anthropology.
The definition of anthropology as holistic and the "four-field" approach are disputed by some leading anthropologists, that consider those as artifacts from 19th century social evolutionary thought that inappropriately impose scientific positivism upon cultural anthropology.
While originating in the US, both the four field approach and debates concerning it have been exported internationally under American academic influence.
(for more details see the section on the relations with the natural sciences and the Humanities)

The four fields are: A number of subfield or modes of anthropology cut across these divisions.
For example, medical anthropology is often considered a subfield of socio-cultural anthropology; however, many anthropologists who study medical topics also look at biological variation in populations or the interaction of culture and biology.
They may also use linguistic analysis to understand communication around health and illness, or archaeological techniques to understand health and illness in historical or prehistorical populations.
Similarly, forensic anthropologists may use both techniques from both physical anthropology and archaeology, and may also practice as medical anthropologists.
Environmental or ecological anthropology, a growing subfield concerned with the relationships between humans and their environment, is another example that brings cultural and biological—and at times, archaeological—approaches together, as it can deal with a broad range of topics from environmentalist movements to wildlife or habitat conservation to traditional ecological knowledge and practices.
Biocultural anthropology is a broad term used to describe syntheses of cultural and biological perspectives.
Applied anthropology is perhaps better considered an emphasis than a subfield in the same sense as the standard four; applied anthropologists may work for government agencies, nongovernmental agencies, or private industry, using techniques from any of the subfields to address matters such as policy implementation, impact assessments, education, marketing research, or product development.

More recently, anthropology programs at several prominent U.S. universities have begun dividing the field into two: one emphasizing the humanities, critical theory, and interpretive or semotic approaches; the other emphasizing evolutionary theory, quantitive methods, and explicit theory testing (over idiographic description), though there have also been institutional pressures to rejoin at least one high-profile split department.
At some universitities, biological anthropology and archaeology programs have also moved from departments of anthropology to departments of biology or other related fields.
This has occasioned much discussion within the American Anthropological Association, and it remains to be seen whether some form of the four-field organization will persist in North American universities.

As might be inferred from the above list of subfields, anthropology is a methodologically diverse discipline, incorporating both qualitative methods and quantitative methods.
Ethnographies—intensive case studies based on field research—have historically had a central place in the literature of sociocultural and linguistic anthropology, but are increasingly supplemented by mixed-methods approaches.
Currently, technological advancements are spurring methodological innovation across anthropology's subfields.
Radiocarbon dating, population genetics, GPS, and digitial video- and audio-recording are just a few of the many technologies spurring new developments in anthropological research.
During the first four decades of the 20th century, American cultural anthropology developed under the powerful influence of Franz Boas and his students and their struggle against racial determinism and the ethnocentrism of 19th-century cultural evolutionism.
With the additional impact of the Great Depression and World War II, American anthropology developed a pronounced liberal-left tone by the 1950s.
However, the discipline's deep involvement with nonwestern cultures put it in a vulnerable position during the campus upheavals of the late 1960s and in the subsequent "culture wars."
The "politics of anthropology" has become a pervasive concern since then.
Whatever the realities, the notion of anthropology as somehow complicit in morally unacceptable projects has become a significant topic both within the discipline and in "cultural studies" and "post-colonialism," etc.

A few of the central elements in this discourse are the following:  Professional anthropological bodies often object to the use of anthropology for the benefit of the state.
Their codes of ethics or statements may proscribe anthropologists from giving secret briefings.
The Association of Social Anthropologists of the UK and Commonwealth (ASA ) has called certain scholarships ethically dangerous.
The AAA's current 'Statement of Professional Responsibility' clearly states that "in relation with their own government and with host governments... no secret research, no secret reports or debriefings of any kind should be agreed to or given."

Other political controversies come from the emphasis in American anthropology on cultural relativism and its long-standing dismissal of the concept of race.
The development of sociobiology in the late 1960s was opposed by cultural anthropologists such as Marshall Sahlins, who argued that these positions were reductive (for more details see the section on the relations with the natural sciences and the Humanities).
While authors such John Randal Baker continued to develop the biological concept of race into the 1970s, the rise of genetics has proven to be central to developments on this front.
As genetics continues to advance as a science, scholars such as Luca Cavalli-Sforza have continued to transform and advance notions of race through the use of recent developments in genetics, such as tracing past migrations of peoples through their mitochondrial and Y-chromosomal DNA, and ancestry-informative markers.
It is often argued that Anthropology originated and developed as the study of the "Other", both in terms of time (past societies) and space (non-European/non-Western societies).
However there exist many works focusing on peoples and topics very close to the author's "home".
It is also argued that other fields of study, like History and Sociology, on the contrary focus disproportionately on the West.

It has been reported that there has been an "institutional and academic apartheid" between the two sorts of anthropology, the one focusing on the "Other" and the one focusing on the "Self" contemporary society; an apartheid ranging from a "no contact" status to even open conflict.
The countries where this was greater were Germany and Norway, but it was also significant in the 1980s France.
The pressure for the "integration" of socio-cultural anthropology (inherently associated with the humanities), with "biological-physical anthropology" (inherently associated with the natural sciences), has been criticized as an inappropriate imposition of positivism (the belief that the only proper knowledge is that derived from the scientific method) upon cultural anthropology.
This criticism argument has been raised towards the development of sociobiology in the late 1960s (by cultural anthropologists such as Marshall Sahlins), and towards the "four field holism" of American Anthropology.</entry>
  <entry author_id="9157909" end="446" start="433">Its basic questions concern, "What is a human being/Homo sapiens?"
"What are their physical traits?"
"How do they behave?"
"Why are there variations and differences among different groups of humans?"
"How has the evolutionary past of Homo sapiens influenced its social organization and culture?"
and so forth.
A single anthropologist, like Napoleon Chagnon might publish on various aspects of a culture, such as their population genetics or use of protein (issues that are typically considered part of biological or physical anthropology)C, or he might focus on aspects considered more cultural.
The goal of an overall anthropology, then, is to provide a holistic account of humans and human nature.
A major trend, within anthropology, has been the methodological drive to study societies with simple social organization, sometimes called "primitive" in anthropological literature, but without any connotation of "inferior."
Today, most anthropologists use terms like "less complex" societies or refer to specific modes of subsistence or production, such as "hunter-gatherer" or "forager" or "simple farmer" to refer to humans living in non-industrial, non-Western cultures, such people or folk (ethnos) remaining of great interest within anthropology.

Anthropologists are interested in both human variation and in the possibility of human universals (behaviors, ideas or concepts shared by virtually human cultures) They use many different methods of study, but modern populationgenetics, participant observation and other techniques often take anthropologists "into the field" which means traveling to a community in its own setting, to do something called "fieldwork."
On the biological or physical side, human measurements, genetic samples, nutritional data may be gathered and published as articles or monographs.
On the cultural side, the resulting form of writing is called an ethnography.</entry>
  <entry author_id="9157909" end="466" start="446">Cultural anthropology is often based on ethnography, a kind of writing used throughout anthropology to present data on a particular people or folk (from the Greek, ethnos/Έθνος).
Ethnology and ethnography are closely related terms, in general both refer to studying and writing about other cultures, using some sort of ojective] observational method, such as participant observation.
Many topics in cultural anthropology require familiarity with other subfields, as when ancient writings are used to provide context to contemporary cultural studies.

Archaeology is the study of human material culture, including both artifacts (older pieces of human culture) carefully gathered in situ, museum pieces and modern garbage.
Archaeologists work closely with biological anthropologists, art historians, physics laboratories (for dating), and museums.
They are charged with preserving the results of their excavations and are often found in museums.

Linguistics is the study of language.
One criticism of the four subfield method of describing anthropology has been the relationship of Linguistics, as a general field in its own right, to anthropological linguistics.
Traditionally, anthropological linguistics has been more concerned with how language is learned in the field (when a person encounters a new people whose language is unknown), the construction of grammars and lexicons for unstudied languages, comparative and historical linguistics, including the reconstruction of past languages, from which our current languages have descended.
Anthropological linguistics is also concerned with the evolution of the parts of the brain that deal with language.

At the same time, anthropologists urge, as part of their quest for scientific objectivity, cultural relativism, which has an influence on all the subfields of anthropology.
This is the notion that particular cultures should not be judged by one culture's viewpoints, but that all cultures should be viewed as relative to each other.
There should be no notions, in good anthropology, of one culture being better or worse than another culture.
Ethical commitments in anthropology include noticing and documenting genocide, infanticide, racism, mutilation including especially circumcision and subincision, and torture.
Topics like racism, slavery or human sacrifice, therefore, attract anthropological attention and theories ranging from nutritional deficiencies to genes to acculturation have been proposed, not to mention theories of acculturation, colonialism and many others as root causes of man's inhumanity to man.

In addition to dividing up their project by theoretical emphasis, anthropologists typically divide the world up into relevant time periods and geographic regions.
Human time on Earth is divided up into relevant cultural traditions based on material, such as the and the, of particular use in archaeology.
Further cultural subdivisions according to tool types, such as Olduwan or Mousterian or Levallois help archaeologists and other anthropologists in understanding major trends in the human past.
Anthropologists and geographers share approaches to Culture regions as well, since mapping cultures is central to both sciences.
By making comparisons across cultural traditions (time-based) and cultural regions (space-based), anthropologists have developed various kinds of comparative method, a central part of their science.</entry>
  <entry author_id="0" end="484" start="466">"All old-established national industries have been destroyed or are daily being destroyed.
They are dislodged by new industries, whose introduction becomes a life and death question for all civilized nations, by industries that no longer work up indigenous raw material but raw material drawn from the remotest zones; industries whose products are consumed, not only at home, but in every quarter of the globe.
In place of the old wants, satisfied by the production of the country, we find new wants, requiring for their satisfaction the products of distant lands and climes.
In place of the old local and national seclusion and self-sufficiency, we have intercourse in every direction, universal interdependence of nations."

In the 19th century numerous scholars grappled with these issues.
The "humanities" reflected an attempt to consolidate and celebrate differnt national traditions, in the form of history and the arts, as an attempt to provide people in emerging nation-states with a sense of coherence.
The "social sciences" emerged at this time as an attempt to develop scientific methods to address social phenomena, in an attempt to provide a universal basis for social knowledge.

Some scholars gave a name to the dimension of human action in which these problems are most evident, and the concept through which they could be solved: society.
The new discipline of sociology would study the ties that bind people not only as individuals, but as members of associations, groups, and institutions.
Through such studies sociologists could develop "the antidote to social disintegration."

Nevertheless, this new discipline, in the very process of distinguishing "society" from "the individual," "the state" and "the market," and by placing itself among complementary social sciences such as psychology, political-science, and economics represented in intellectual form the very social divisions it sought to understand and heal.
Moreover, the most obvious sites for the study of modernity, and the most convenient sites for the application of new scientific, quantitative research methods, was in the sociologists' own societies, at the core of the emerging world system.
Consequently, they neglected the study of those societies on or beyond modernity's frontiers.

At the same time that social scientists were defining this new object and method of study, however, a diverse group of scholars – with training in jurisprudence, psychology, geography, physics, mathematics, and other disciplines, and drawing on the methods of the natural sciences as well as developing new techniques involving not only structured interviews but unstructured "participant-observation" – dedicated themselves precisely to the study of those people on Europe's colonial frontiers.
Drawing on the new theory of evolution through natural selection, they proposed the scientific study of a new object: "humankind," conceived of as a whole.
Moreover, they proposed a new discipline, anthropology, that would transcend the divisions between the natural sciences, social sciences, and humanities to explore the biological, linguistic, material, and symbolic dimensions of humankind in all forms.
Crucial to this study is the concept "culture," which anthropologists defined both as a universal capacity and propensity for social learning, thinking, and acting, and as a particular adaptation to local conditions that takes the form of highly variable beliefs and practices.
Thus, "culture" not only transcends the opposition between nature and nurture; it transcends and absorbs the peculiarly European distinction between politics, religion, kinship, and the economy as autonomous domains.</entry>
  <entry author_id="13751899" end="506" start="484">One of the more recent and fruitful anthropological theories has been developed by the Australian biologist Jeremy Griffith.
Griffith operates from outside the academy and his work is unorthodox and does not follow the accepted rigors and protocols of academic discourse.
Yet in some sense this is a positive for his thinking is not hobbled by the need to acquiesce to established paradigms for reasons of funding or career aggrandizement.
His most succinct account of human biological and social evolution is contained in his 1998 book ‘Free: The End of the Human Condition.’ This book outlines a radical interdisciplinary thesis that seeks to account for cultural change and development from our primate ancestors, through the stage of hunter-gather life to the present.
The primatology, from which Griffith extrapolates to human behavior, is probably his most significant contribution.
Particularly relevant in this sense is his theory of ‘Love Indoctrination’, which emphasizes the primary role of the mother/infant bond in the evolutionary development of the human species.
His thesis is echoed by the work Allan Schore, one of the leading researchers in the field of neuropsychology.
In his Affect Regulation and the Origin of the Self (1999) Schore meticulously demonstartes how the interactions between mother and infant that occurs during the period from 9-13 months is indstrumental in triggring chemical processes asscoaited with the growth of the orbito-frontal cortex, the seat of socio-emotioal memory.
Grifith simialrly argues that mother/infant interactions resulted in the evolution of social instincts and also what religious thinkers and artists have referred to as the soul.
Orthodox science to date has not been able to come to terms with in any depth the evolutionary origins of creativity nor the religious dimension of life.
This is one of the particular strengths of Griffith’s work.

Another component of this theory revolves around the notion of sexual selection, which combined with nurturing, became one of the prime movers in human evolution.
As Geoffrey Miller argued in ‘The Mating Mind’ one of the chief characteristics of sexual in humans is a ‘spirit of generosity’, a trait which understandably people find welcoming and pleasant in a partner.
Further, Griffith’s explanation of how sexual selection resulted in the loss of body hair and the process of psychological and physical retardation that biologists refer to as neoteny, is also revolutionary.
That humans, in other words, over thousands of years of sexual selection, retained both the physical and psychological traits of infants – hence the smooth, hairless and silky, baby-like skin of women and the sense of ‘cuteness’ as an indicator of sexual attractiveness.

Biologists have yet to provide an adequate and coherent account of these phenomena that is both non-reductive and also explanatorily powerful.
Not only does Griffith’s theory account for these phenomena it also provides a rigorous evolutionary framework in which to understand aspects of human culture such as the initiation rites of hunter-gather societies, literary motifs and archetypes, the psychobiological foundation of gender difference, mental illness and the fraught dualities of political life.
His work also represents an advance on the project began by Freud and extended by Jung and others to ground a theory of human psychology and culture in brain physiology and evolution.

Griffith’s work often lacks academic and intellectual rigor and much of what he has to say about hunter-gather cultures is unsubstantiated and seems to be more of a Western imaginary construction of the ‘other’ than any genuine empirical account of tribal life.
But this is not to overlook the explanatory power of his general thesis which rigorously explains many of the enigmas of human life, morality and culture that have till now remained inexplicable with the parameters of an evolutionary paradigm..
It will be the task of future researchers to sort the wheat from the chaff.
But there is not doubt that his work will in the decades to come inaugurate a paradigm shift in our knowledge of human beings and human culures.</entry>
</article>
