<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="573" title="Alchemy" authors="6" lines="102">
  <entry author_id="658677" end="14" start="0">There are two different types of alchemy.
The more commonly known form is physical alchemy, an early protoscientific discipline combining the elements of chemistry, metallurgy, physics and medicine.
The less commonly known version is a spiritual alchemy, a hermetic practice originating with the priests of Ancient Egypt (for Western Alchemy) which combined aspects of metaphysics, astrology, semiotics, mysticism, and art.
Certainly, at times, some alchemists tried to mix both alchemical arts into one.

Spiritual alchemists may partially be to blame for this, as they wrote their work in the same language of mixing mercury and sulphur with an intention to hide the true meaning of their art.
Much of the Egyptian alchemical texts were destroyed in 292 CE when Emperor Diocletian ordered the burning of alchemical books in the aftermath of an unsuccessful revolt in Alexandria.
The origins of the spiritual art (in Europe) predate Christianity by millenia and originate in elite Egyptian religion, making it a pagan art.

Knowning this, and the power of the Roman Catholic Church in Europe, spiritual alchemists did not want to be found guilty of heresy and face the wrath of one of the Inquisition movements.
As Michel de Nostradame hid his scrying in his quatrains by being vague and out of chronological order in order to avoid persecution and the destruction of his work, spiritual alchemists used the language of metallurgy to hide their work.
It is possible that by veiling alchemy in the language of metallurgy, spiritual alchemy created physical alchemy.
Through the use of the metaphor of turning lead into gold, spiritual alchemists made the concept of physical alchemy very appealing.
In turn, though physical alchemists do not appear to have ever successfully turned lead into gold, as spiritual alchemists (metaphorically speaking of course) have, physical alchemy was able to make earnest scientific advancement, eventually leading to the creation of chemistry.
It should be noted, however, that the metaphors of spiritual alchemy were designed so they could only make sense to an initiate who recieves their explanation.
Therefore, the practitioners of physical alchemy could not have realized the misunderstanding they had, and instead created a new wonderful art.</entry>
  <entry author_id="328972" end="32" start="14">Up to the 18th century, alchemy was actually considered serious science in Europe; for instance, Isaac Newton devoted considerably more of his time and writing to the study of alchemy than he did to either optics or physics, for which he is famous, (see Isaac Newton's occult studies).
Other eminent alchemists of the Western world are Roger Bacon, Saint Thomas Aquinas, Tycho Brahe, Thomas Browne, and Parmigianino.
The decline of alchemy began in the 18th century with the birth of modern chemistry, which provided a more precise and reliable framework for matter transmutations and medicine, within a new grand design of the universe based on rational materialism.

Matter transmutation, the old goal of alchemy, enjoyed a moment in the sun in the 20th century when physicists were able to convert lead atoms into gold atoms via a nuclear reaction.
However, the new gold atoms, being unstable isotopes, lasted for under five seconds before they broke apart.
More recently, reports of table-top element transmutation — by means of electrolysis or sonic cavitation — were the pivot of the cold fusion controversy of 1989.
None of those claims have yet been reliably duplicated.

Alchemical symbolism has been occasionally used in the 20th century by psychologists and philosophers.
Carl Jung reexamined alchemical symbolism and theory and began to show the inner meaning of alchemical work as a spiritual path.
Alchemical philosophy, symbols and methods have enjoyed something of a renaissance in post-modern contexts, such as the New Age movement.
Even some physicists have played with alchemical ideas in books such as The Tao of Physics and The Dancing Wu Li Masters.

Whereas Western alchemy eventually centered on the transmutation of base metals into noble ones, Chinese alchemy had a more obvious connection to medicine.
The philosopher's stone of European alchemists can be compared to the Grand Elixir of Immortality sought by Chinese alchemists.
However, in the hermetic view, these two goals were not unconnected, and the philosopher's stone was often equated with the universal panacea; therefore, the two traditions may have had more in common than it initially appears.

Black powder may have been an important invention of Chinese alchemists.
Described in 9th century texts and used in fireworks by the 10th Century, it was used in cannons by 1290.
From China, the use of gunpowder spread to Japan, the Mongols, the Arab world and Europe.
Gunpowder was used by the Mongols against the Hungarians in 1241, and in Europe starting with the 14th century.</entry>
  <entry author_id="727143" end="45" start="32">In 1989, Stanley Pons and Martin Fleischmann's experience fused deuterium atoms into helium-4.
It emmited basically no heat.
The fusion was realised by compressing the deuterium in a piece of porous metal (palladium), thanks to an electrolysis: using an electrical current generated between a palladium cathode and a titanium anode, they oblige the deuterium to go into the porous metal.

A few years later, the italian Antonella De Ninno used the same principal as Stanley Pons and Martin Fleischmann.
The main difference was that the palladium cathode was nearly uni-dimensional, reduced to a very thing thread.
20 times more helium-4 was produced then external contaminations and just over 20 mWt (milliwat thermal).

No theory could explain why the deuterium atoms cross the coulomb barrier in those two experiments.
They are also not easily redone in other laboratories since you need a palladium with always the same porousity.
This is why the first few scientist who claimed to have done a cold fusion were ignored in the scientific community and in magazines such as Nature and Science.

Because alchemistry is often referred as a medieval science, it has been named many different ways.
Some of them include: Cold Fusion, CMNS (Condensed Matter Nuclear Science), LENR (Low Energy Nuclear Reaction), CANR (Chemically Assisted Nuclear Reaction).
Those researches are not the ones which will (in legends) make you live forever.
It is the legend of "turning everything into gold" when a cold fusion takes place of course, turning a person into gold is totally impossible.</entry>
  <entry author_id="163575" end="72" start="45">The best known goals of the alchemists were the transmutation of common metals into gold or silver (less well known is plant alchemy, or "Spagyric"), and the creation of a "panacea," a remedy that supposedly would cure all diseases and prolong life indefinitely.
Although these were not the only uses for the science, they were the ones most documented and well known.
Starting with the Middle Ages, European alchemists invested much effort on the search for the "philosopher's stone", a legendary substance that was believed to be an essential ingredient for either or both of those goals.
The philosopher's stone was believed to mystically amplify the user's knowledge of alchemy so much that anything was attainable.
Alchemists enjoyed prestige and support through the centuries, though not for their pursuit of those goals, nor the mystic and philosophical speculation that dominates their literature.
Rather it was for their mundane contributions to the "chemical" industries of the day—the invention of gunpowder, ore testing and refining, metalworking, production of ink, dyes, paints, and cosmetics, leather tanning, ceramics and glass manufacture, preparation of extracts and liquors, and so on (It seems that the preparation of aqua vitae, the "water of life", was a fairly popular "experiment" among European alchemists).

On the other hand, alchemists never had the inclination to separate the physical (chemical) aspects of their craft from the metaphysical interpretations.
Indeed, from antiquity until well into the Modern Age, a physics devoid of metaphysical insight would have been as unsatisfying as a metaphysics devoid of physical manifestation.
For one thing, the lack of common words for chemical concepts and processes, as well as the need for secrecy, led alchemists to borrow the terms and symbols of biblical and pagan mythology, astrology, kabbalah, and other mystic and esoteric fields; so that even the plainest chemical recipe ended up reading like an abstruse magic incantation.
Moreover, alchemists sought in those fields the theoretical frameworks into which they could fit their growing collection of disjointed experimental facts.

Starting with the Middle Ages, some alchemists increasingly came to view these metaphysical aspects as the true foundation of alchemy; and chemical substances, physical states, and material processes as mere metaphors for spiritual entities, states and transformations.
In this sense, the literal meanings of alchemical formulas were a blind hiding their true spiritual philosophy, which being at odds with the Medieval Church was a necessity that could have otherwise lead them to the "stake and rack" of the Inquisition under charges of heresy.
Thus, both the transmutation of common metals into gold and the universal panacea symbolized evolution from an imperfect, diseased, corruptible and ephemeral state towards a perfect, healthy, incorruptible and everlasting state; and the philosopher's stone then represented some mystic key that would make this evolution possible.
Applied to the alchemist himself, the twin goal symbolized his evolution from ignorance to enlightenment, and the stone represented some hidden spiritual truth or power that would lead to that goal.
In texts that are written according to this view, the cryptic alchemical symbols, diagrams, and textual imagery of late alchemical works typically contain multiple layers of meanings, allegories, and references to other equally cryptic works; and must be laboriously "decoded" in order to discover their true meaning.

Since its earliest times, alchemy has been closely connected to astrology—which, in the Islamic world and Europe, generally meant the traditional Babylonian-Greek school of astrology.
Alchemical systems often postulated that each of the seven planets known to the ancients "ruled" or was associated with certain metals.
See the separate article on astrology and alchemy for further details.
In Hermeticism it is linked with both astrology and theurgy.
Carl Jung saw alchemy as a Western proto-psychology dedicated to the achievement of individuation; in his interpretation, alchemy was the vessel by which Gnosticism survived its various purges into the Renaissance.
In this sense, Jung viewed alchemy as comparable to a Yoga of the West.
Jung also interpreted Chinese alchemical texts in terms of his analytical psychology as means to individuation.
Bahá'u'lláh, founder of the Bahá'í Faith, promised the realisation of the discovery of a radical approach to the transmutation of elements as one of the signs of the coming of age of humanity.
He prophesied, as well, that after this discovery a great calamity would overcome the world, unless mankind would accept his Faith.
Bahá'u'lláh also refers to the elixir and the philosopher's stone, but states that these are spiritual in nature, and refer to the Word of God.
As regards the actual practice of alchemy, in the Kitáb-i-Iqán, Baha'u'llah states that alchemy (among other sciences) is "contemptible in the eyes of the truly learned."
(p. 187).</entry>
  <entry author_id="4978210" end="89" start="72">chemia mysterium, the highest we can speak at this time on par with the exploration of various levels of mathematically explainable reiteration and other neuroexcitements such as increased bilateral cofussion.
Finite, however inexplainable by modern common tongues.
A mergence with the sciences and religion tracing to the importance of the moon landing new forms of consciousness are being explored, such as virtual reality.
Simulations of various states such as ecstacy.
Or truly justified speakings of prophecy.

Thus any person can see that which in past ages was restricted to the few.
Those beyond the veil of illusion as some traditions begin to understand the seriphs and alohim as you transcend you see his lowest chakra at the phalis of krishna.
The chemistry being microdots of macrodots.

and for the search to be complete please see: Manna of the Lycaeum.
as we pass through the garden of The Lord's bountiful disclosure we design robots that work better than us.
Then get sad when they eat us because we taste like mushrooms.
Then there of course is the more rational aspect which is much greater impressed by the extravigance of the effulgience and connot but yet begin to comprehend even the concept of the bardos.
Yet the threat of great danger in the stocks purchased of pure ignorance, we pray for the redirection of the back end structure of the society.

As we fall from the heights in the dark sea of peril.
Darkness lingering as a stench.
The contemplation of the being manifesting as the evolved form as a butterfly from the sac of a coccoon.
With the evolvement of pharmacy into the cyber-entheo-alchemical revolution we find the capacity unlike, well quite frankly the stench of it's current incarnation of voodoo.</entry>
  <entry author_id="6327128" end="102" start="89">In the 1400's a French Alchemist named Nicholas Flamel was visited by an Angel in his dreams.
He was seeing a peice of parchment.
Sure enough a few days later a poor man in desperate need of money came to his house and offered the Parchment he had seen in the dream for some money.
Flamel obviously accepted and read it.
It said only Scribes and Nobles could read it or they would be smited.
Since Flamel was a scribe, he read it and with many tries, created the philosopher's stone.
It transmuted lead to gold, and was said to give immortality.
After his death, theives ransacked his house and found nothing of the stone or his body.
He had been immortal.
Still sightings have been seen today and those brave enough, search for the stone.
Yet it can still be created, with Mercury and Sulphur made at the right heat, it will be the famous stone.
Yet it does not sound real, it is all too much.
For all skeptics, im not trying to change your lifestyle, just teaching you about real information.</entry>
</article>
