<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="584" title="Amoeboid" authors="1" lines="39">
  <entry author_id="10000194" end="39" start="0">Amoeboids are unicellular life-forms characterized by their similarity to amoebae.
==Structure==    The phylum Rhizopoda has naked and shelled amoebas.
They tend to ingest food and creep toward food.
They move using Pseudopodia, which are bulges of cytoplasm.
Naked amoebas use all of their body for pseudopod movement.
Usually half is used in shelled amoebas.
the other half grips the shell.
Amoebas breathe using their entire cell membrane that is constantly immersed in water.
Because they live in water, they have no problem keeping it wet.
But it does have one drawback.
Excess water often crosses into the cytosol.
All have one contractile vacuole that expells excess water.
This contraction is powered by contracting cytosol.
The nuclei of amoebas do not have chromosomes.
They also persist during cell division.
The nuclear membrane pinches in two during telophase.
Amoebas also don't go through meiosis.
Amoebas have one or more nucleoli.
The food scources vary in rhizopoda.
Some consume bacteria.
Others are detritivores and eat dead organic material.
Still others eat other protists.
They extend a pair of pseudopodia around food.
They fuse to make a food vacuole which then fuses with a lysosome to add digestive chemicals.
Undigestied food is expelled at the cell membrane.
Amoebas use pseudopodia to move and feed.
they are powered by flexible microfilaments near the membrane.
Microfilaments are at least 50% of the cytoskeleton.
The other parts are more stiff and are composed of intermediate filaments and macrotubules.
These are not used in amoeboid movement, but are stiff skeletons on which organelles are supported or can move on.
The shells of amoebas are often composed of calcium ar other materials.
The proteins or materials are synthesised in the cell and exported just outside the cell membrane.
the shells are stiff and flexible, but not too much of either trait.
Amoebas seem to have connections with two phyla of the lineage funguslike protists.
The two phyla are myxomycota(plasmodial slime molds), and acrasiomycota(cellular slime molds).
These two phyla use amoeboid movement in their feeding stage.
One is baisically a giant multinucleate amoeba, while the other lives solitary until food runs out; in which a colony of these functions as a unit.
Myxomycotes use amoeboid gametes, as well.
They definately have a connection.</entry>
</article>
