<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="593" title="Animation" authors="2" lines="35">
  <entry author_id="307355" end="10" start="0">Émile Cohl began drawing cartoon strips and created a film in 1908 called Fantasmagorie.
The film was largely comprised of a stick figure moving about and encountering all manner of morphing objects, such as a wine bottle that transforms into a flower.
There were also sections of live action where the animator’s hands would enter the scene.
The film was created by drawing each frame on paper and then shooting each frame onto negative film, which gave the picture a blackboard look to it.

Winsor McCay created detailed animations that required a team of artists and painstaking attention for detail.
Each frame was drawn on paper, requiring backgrounds to be redrawn, as well characters to be animated.
His films such as Gertie the Dinosaur (1914) and The Sinking of the Lusitania (1918) were of an impressive scale.

In 1919 Otto Messmer created the character of Felix the cat for Pat Sullivan's animation studios.
The importance of Felix lies in the character's strong personality, created largely through gesture and actions.
Animation techniques are incredibly varied and difficult to categorize.</entry>
  <entry author_id="307355" end="23" start="10">Georges Méliès was a creator of special effect films, such as A Trip to the Moon.
He used many techniques – one of which was to stop the camera rolling, change something in the scene, and then continue rolling the film.
This is a very similar idea to that of stop-motion animation.
Méliès accidentally happened upon the technique when his camera broke down while shooting a bus driving by.
When the camera was fixed, a horse happened to be passing by just as Méliès continued to film.
The result was that the bus appeared to change into a horse.

Émile Cohl began drawing cartoon strips and created a film in 1908 called Fantasmagorie.
The film largely consisted of a stick figure moving about and encountering all manner of morphing objects, such as a wine bottle that transforms into a flower.
There were also sections of live action where the animator’s hands would enter the scene.
The film was created by drawing each frame on paper and then shooting each frame onto negative film, which gave the picture a blackboard look.

Winsor McCay created detailed animations that required a team of artists and painstaking attention for detail.
Each frame was drawn on paper, requiring backgrounds to be redrawn, as well characters to be animated.
His films such as Gertie the Dinosaur (1914) and The Sinking of the Lusitania (1918) were of an impressive scale, although The Sinking of the Lusitania used cels.</entry>
  <entry author_id="223739" end="35" start="23">There is no single person who can be considered the "creator" of the art of film animation, as there were several people doing several projects which could be considered various types of animation all around the same time.
The production of animated short films, typically referred to as "cartoons", became an industry of its own during the 1910s, and cartoon shorts were produced to be shown in movie theaters.
The most successful early animation producer was John Randolph Bray, who, along with animator Earl Hurd, patented the cel animation process which dominated the animation industry for the rest of the decade.

Also called cel animation, traditional animation was the process used for most animated films of the 20th century.
The individual frames of a traditionally animated film are photographs of drawings, which are first drawn on paper.
To create the illusion of movement, each drawing differs slightly from the one before it.
The animators' drawings are traced or photocopied onto transparent acetate sheets called cels, which are filled in with paints in assigned colors or tones on the side opposite the line drawings.
The completed character cels are photographed one-by-one onto motion picture film against a painted background by a rostrum camera.

The traditional cel animation process became obsolete by the beginning of the 21st century.
Today, the animators' drawings and the backgrounds are either scanned into or drawn directly into a computer system.
Various software programs are used to color the drawings and simulate camera movement and effects.
The final animated piece is output to one of several delivery mediums, including traditional 35 mm film and newer media such as digital video.</entry>
</article>
