<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="594" title="Apollo" authors="5" lines="211">
  <entry author_id="3671" end="46" start="0">The name Phoebus (also spelled Phevos), Greek for "shining one") was also used in the context as the god of light.
As Smintheus ("rat") and Parnopius ("grasshopper"), he was the god of the plague and defender against rats and locusts.
Due to his connection to dolphins, he was known Delphinios ("dolphin" or "porpoise"), also the source of the place-name Delphi.
His title was sometimes Archigetes, ("leader of colonists") or Musagetes ("leader of the muses").
He was known as Pythian Apollo at Delphi; he was also called Apotropaeus ("he who averts evil") and Apollo Nymphegetes ("Apollo who looks after nymphs").
As the protector of flocks from wolves, he was known as Lukeios and as the pastoral shepherd-god, he was Nomius.

When Hera discovered that Leto was pregnant and that Hera's husband, Zeus, was the father, she banned Leto from giving birth on "terra-firma", or the mainland, or any island at sea.
She found the floating island of Delos, which was neither mainland nor a real island and gave birth there.
The island was surrounded by swans.
As a gesture of gratitude, Delos was secured with four pillars.
The island later became sacred to Apollo.
Alternatively, Hera kidnapped Ilithyia, the goddess of childbirth, to prevent Leto from going into labor.
The other gods forced Hera to let her go.

As a young man, Apollo killed the vicious dragon, Python, which lived in Delphi beside the Castalian Spring.
This was the spring which emitted vapors that caused the Oracle at Delphi to give her prophesies.
Apollo killed Python but had to be punished for it, since Python was a child of Gaia.

When he returned after the nine years, Apollo came disguised as a dolphin and brought Cretan priests to help found his cult in Delphi.
He also blessed the priestess of the Oracle at Delphi, making it one of the most famous and accurate oracles in Greece.
He had other oracles, including Clarus and Branchidae.

A mortal woman, Niobe boasted of her superiority to Leto because she had fourteen children, seven male and seven female, while Leto had only two.
Apollo killed her sons and Artemis her daughters.
A devastated Niobe turned into stone as she wept.

Hyacinth was a Spartan prince, very handsome and athletic.
The pair were practicing throwing the discus when Hyacinth was struck by one, blown off course by Zephyrus, who was jealous of Apollo and loved Hyacinth as well.

Another homosexual lover was Cyparissus, a descendant of Heracles.
Apollo gave the boy a tame deer as a companion but Cyparissus accidentally killed it was a javelin as it lay sleep in the undergrowth.
Cyparissus asked Apollo to let his tears fall forever.
Apollo turned the sad boy into a cypress tree, which was said to be a sad tree because the sap forms droplets like tears on the trunk.

Apollo also had affairs with women, such as a mortal princess named Leucothea, daughter of Orchamus and sister of Clytia.

Apollo chased the nymph Daphne, daughter of Ladon, who had scorned him.
His infatuation was caused by an arrow from Eros, who was jealous because Apollo had made fun of his archery skills.
Eros also claimed to be irritated by Apollo's singing.
Daphne prayed to the river god Peneus to help her and he changed her into a laurel tree, which became sacred to Apollo.

With Hecuba, wife of King Priam of Troy, Apollo had a son named Troilius.
An oracle prophesied that Troy would not be defeated as long as Troilius reached the age of twenty alive.
He and his sister, Polyxena were ambushed and killed by Achilles.

Apollo also fell in love with Cassandra, daughter of Hecuba and Priam, and Troilius' half-sister.
He promised Cassandra the gift of prophecy to seduce her, but she rejected him afterwards.
Enraged, Apollo cursed her with the ability to know the future but the curse that no one would ever believe her.

Coronis, daughter of Phlegyas, King of the Lapiths, was another of Apollo's liasons.
Pregnant with Asclepius, Coronis fell in love with Ischys, son of Elatus.
A crow informed Apollo of the affair and he sent his sister, Artemis, to kill Coronis.
Apollo rescued the baby though and gave it to the centaur Chiron to raise.

His attributes included: swans, wolves, dolphins, bows and arrows, a laurel crown, the cithara (or lyre) and plectrum.
The tripod is another attribute, representative of his prophetic powers.
The Pythian Games were held in his honor every four years at Delphi.</entry>
  <entry author_id="3671" end="61" start="46">
Apollo had an affair with a mortal princess named Leucothea, daughter of Orchamus and sister of Clytia.

Hermes was born on Mt. Cyllene in Arcadia.
The story is told in the Hymn to Hermes attributed to Homer.
His mother, Maia, had been secretly impregnated by Zeus, in a secret affair.
Maia wrapped the infant in blankets but Hermes escaped while she was asleep.
Hermes ran to Thessaly, where Apollo was grazing his cattle.
The infant Hermes stole a number of his cows and took them to a cave in the woods near Pylos, covering their tracks.
In the cave, he found a tortoise and killed it, then removed the insides.
He used one of the cow's intestines and the tortoise shell and made the first lyre.
Apollo complained to Maia that her son had stolen his cattle, but Hermes had already replaced himself in the blankets she had wrapped him in, so Maia refused to believe Apollo's claim.
Zeus intervened and claimed to have seen the events, and siding with Apollo.
Hermes then began to play music on the lyre he had invented.
Apollo, a god of music, fell in love with the instrument and offered to allow exchange the cattle for the lyre.
Hence, Apollo became a master of the lyre and Hermes invented a kind of pipes-instrument called a syrinx.

Later, Apollo exchanged a caduceus for a flute from Hermes.
</entry>
  <entry author_id="3671" end="74" start="61">Once Pan had the audacity to compare his music with that of Apollo, and to challenge Apollo, the god of the lyre, to a trial of skill.
Tmolus, the mountain-god, was chosen to umpire.
Pan blew on his pipes, and with his rustic melody gave great satisfaction to himself and his faithful follower, Midas, who happened to be present.
Then Apollo struck the strings of his lyre.
Tmolus at once awarded the victory to Apollo, and all but Midas agreed with the judgment.
He dissented, and questioned the justice of the award.
Apollo would not suffer such a depraved pair of ears any longer, and caused them to become the ears of an ass.

King Midas was moritifed at this mishap.
But he attempted to hide his misfortune with an ample turban or headdress.
But his hairdresser of course knew the secret.
He was told not to mention it.
He could not keep the secret; so he went out into the meadow, dug a hole in the ground, whispered the story into it, and covered the hole up.
A thick bed of reeds sprang up in the meadow, and began whispering the story and saying "King Midas has an ass' ears."</entry>
  <entry author_id="54617" end="85" start="74">The Apollo program was designed to land humans on the Moon and bring them safely back to Earth.
Six of the missions (Apollos 11, 12, 14, 15, 16, and 17) achieved this goal.
Apollos 7 and 9 were Earth orbiting missions to test the Command and Lunar Modules, and did not return lunar data.
Apollos 8 and 10 tested various components while orbiting the Moon, and returned photography of the lunar surface.
Apollo 13 did not land on the Moon due to a malfunction, but also returned photographs.
The six missions that landed on the Moon returned a wealth of scientific data and almost 400 kilograms of lunar samples.
Experiments included soil mechanics, meteoroids, seismic, heat flow, lunar ranging, magnetic fields, and solar wind experiments.

The Apollo mission consisted of a Command Module (CM) and a Lunar Module (LM).
The CM and LM would separate after lunar orbit insertion.
One crew member would stay in the CM, which would orbit the Moon, while the other two astronauts would take the LM down to the lunar surface.
After exploring the surface, setting up experiments, taking pictures, collecting rock samples, etc., the astronauts would return to the CM for the journey back to Earth.</entry>
  <entry author_id="146755" end="186" start="85">No satisfactory etymology of the name has been given, the least improbable perhaps being that which connects it with the Doric απελλα ("assembly") (Hesychius; who also gives the explanation σηκος ("fold"), in which case Apollo would be the god of flocks and herds.)
so that Apollo would be the god of political life (for other suggested derivations, ancient and modern, see C. Wernicke in Pauly-Wissowa's Realencyclopädie).
The derivation of all the functions assigned to him from the idea of a single original light- or sun-god, worked out in his Lexikon der Mythologie by Roscher, who regards it as "one of the most certain facts in mythology," has not found general acceptance, although no doubt some features of his character can be readily explained on this assumption.

In the legend, as set forth in the Homeric hymn to Apollo and the ode of Callimachus to Delos, Apollo is the son of Zeus and Leto.
The latter, pursued by the jealous Hera, after long wandering found shelter in Delos (originally Asteria), where she bore a son, Apollo, under a palm-tree at the foot of Mount Cynthus.
Before this, Delos--like Rhodes, the centre of the worship of the sun-god Helios, with whom Apollo was wrongly identified in later times--had been a barren, floating rock, but now became stationary, being fastened down by chains to the bottom of the sea.
Apollo was born on the 7th day (ἡβδομαγενης) of the month Thargelion according to Delian, of the month Bysios according to Delphian, tradition.
The 7th and 20th, the days of the new and full moon, were ever afterwards held sacred to him.
In Homer Apollo appears only as the god of prophecy, the sender of plagues, and sometimes as a warrior, but elsewhere as exercising the most varied functions.
He is the god of agriculture, specially connected with Aristaeus, which, originally a mere epithet, became an independent personality (see, however, Farnell, Cults of the Greek States, iv. 123).
This side of his character is clearly expressed in the titles Sitalcas ("protector of corn"); Erythibius ("preventer of blight"); Parnopius ("destroyer of locusts"); Smintheus ("destroyer of mice"), in which, however, some modern inquirers see a totemistic significance (e.g. A. Lang, "Apollo and the Mouse," in Custom and Myth, p. 101; against this, W. W. Fowler, in Classical Review, November 1892); Erithius ("god of reapers"); and Pasparius ("god of meal").
He is further the god of vegetation generally--Nomios, "god of pastures" (explained, however, by Cicero, as "god of law"), Hersos, "sender of the fertilizing dew."
Valleys and groves are under his protection, unless the epithets Napaeus and Hylates belong to a more primitive aspect of the god as supporting himself by the chase, and roaming the glades and forests in pursuit of prey.
Certain trees and plants, especially the laurel, were sacred to him.
As the god of agriculture and vegetation he is naturally connected with the course of the year and the arrangement of the seasons, so important in farming operations, and becomes the orderer of time (Horomedon, "ruler of the seasons"), and frequently appears on monuments in company with the Horae.

Apollo is also the protector of cattle and herds, hence Poimnius ("god of flocks"), Tragius ("of goats"), Kereatas ("of horned animals").
Carneius (probably "horned") is considered by some to be a pre-Dorian god of cattle, also connected with harvest operations, whose cult was grafted on to that of Apollo; by others, to have been originally an epithet of Apollo, afterwards detached as a separate personality (Farnell, Cults, iv. p. 131).
The epithet Maleatas, which, as the quantity of the first vowel (ă) shows, (The authority for the quantity is Isyllus.)
cannot mean god of "sheep" or "the apple-tree," is probably a local adjective derived from Malea (perhaps Cape Malea), and may refer to an originally distinct personality, subsequently merged in that of Apollo (see below).
Apollo himself is spoken of as a keeper of flocks, and the legends of his service as a herdsman with Laomedon and Admetus point in the same direction.
Here probably also is to be referred the epithet Lyceius, which, formerly connected with λυκ- ("shine") and used to support the conception of Apollo as a light-god, is now generally referred to λυκος ("wolf") and explained as he who keeps away the wolves from the flock (cf. λυκοεργος, λυκοκτονος).
In accordance with this, the epithet λυκηγενης will not mean "born of" or "begetting light," but rather "born from the she-wolf," in which form Leto herself was said to have been conducted by wolves to Delos.
The consecration of the wolf to Apollo is probably the relic of an ancient totemistic religion (Farnell, Cults, i. 41; W. Robertson Smith, Religion of the Semites, new ed., 1894, p. 226).

With the care of the fruits of the earth and the lower animals is associated that of the highest animal, man, especially the youth on his passage to manhood.
As such Apollo is κουροτροφος ("rearer of boys") and patron of the palaestra.
In many places gymnastic contests form a feature of his festivals, and he himself is proficient in athletic exercises (εναγωνιος).
Thus he was supposed to be the first victor at the Olympic games; he overcomes Hermes in the foot-race, and Ares in boxing.

The transition is easy to Apollo as a warlike god; in fact, the earlier legends represent him as engaged in strife with Python, Tityus, the Cyclopes and the Aloidae.
He is Boëdromios ("the helper"), Eleleus ("god of the war-cry"), and the Paean was said to have been originally a song of triumph composed by him after his victory over Python.
In Homer he frequently appears on the field, like Ares and Athene, bearing the aegis to frighten the foe.
This aspect is confirmed by the epithets Argyrotoxos ("god of the silver bow"), Hecatebolos ("the shooter from afar"), Chrysaoros ("wearer of the golden sword"), and his statues are often equipped with the accoutrements of war.
(Hence some have derived "Apollo" from απomicron;λλυναι, "to destroy.")

The fame of the Pythian oracle at Delphi, connected with the slaying of Python by the god immediately after his birth, gave especial prominence to the idea of Apollo as a god of prophecy.
Python, always represented in the form of a snake, sometimes nameless, is the symbol of the old chthonian divinity whose home was the place of "enquiry" (πυθεσθαι).
When Apollo Delphinius with his worshippers from Crete took possession of the earth-oracle Python, he received in consequence the name Pythius.
That Python was no fearful monster, symbolizing the darkness of winter which is scattered by the advent of spring, is shown by the fact that Apollo was considered to have been guilty of murder in slaying it, and compelled to wander for a term of years and expiate his crime by servitude and purification.
Possibly at Delphi and other places there was an old serpent-worship ousted by that of Apollo, which may account for expiation for the slaying of Python being considered necessary.
In the solar explanation, the serpent is the darkness driven away by the rays of the sun.
(On the Delphian cult of Apollo and its political significance, see Amphictyony, Delphi, Oracle; and Farnell, Cults, iv. pp. 179-218.)
Oracular responses were also given at Claros near Colophon in Ionia by means of the wdter of a spring which inspired those who drank of it; at Patara in Lycia; and at Didyma near Miletus through the priestly family of the Branchidae.
Apollo's oracles, which he did not deliver on his own initiative but as the mouthpiece of Zeus, were infallible, but the human mind was not always able to grasp their meaning; hence he is called Loxias ("crooked," "ambiguous").
To certain favoured mortals he communicated the gift of prophecy (Cassandra, the Cumaean sibyl, Helenus, Melampus and Epimenides).
Although his favourite method was by word of mouth, yet signs were sometimes used; thus Calchas interpreted the flight of birds; burning offerings, sacrificial barley, the arrow of the god, dreams and the lot, all played their part in communicating the will of the gods.

Closely connected with the god of oracles was the god of the healing art, the oracle being frequently consulted in cases of sickness.
These two functions are indicated by the titles Iatromantis ("physician and seer") and Oulios, probably meaning "health-giving" (so Suidas) rather than "destructive."
This side of Apollo's character does not appear in Homer, where Paieon is mentioned as the physician of the gods.
Here again, as in the case of Aristaeus and Carneius, the question arises whether Paean (or Paeon) was originally an epithet of Apollo, subsequently developed into an independent personality, or an independent deity merged in the later arrival (Farnell, Cults, iv. p. 234).
According to Wilamowitz-Möllendorff in his edition of Isyllus, the epithet Maleatas alluded to above is also connected with the functions of the healing god, imported into Athens in the 4th century B.C. with other well-known health divinities.
In this connexion, it is said to mean the "gentle one," who gave his name to the rock Malion or Maleas (O. Gruppe, Griechische Mythologie, ii. 1442) on the Gortynian coast.
Apollo is further supposed to be the father of Asclepius (Aesculapius), whose ritual is closely modelled upon his.
The healing god could also prevent disease and misfortune of all kinds: hence he is αλεξικακος ("averter of evil") and αποτροπαιος.
Further, he is able to purify the guilty and to cleanse from sin (here some refer the epithet ιατρομαντις, in the sense of "physician of the soul").
Such a task can be fitly undertaken by Apollo, since he himself underwent purification after slaying Python.
According to the Delphic legend, this took place in the laurel grove of Tempe, and after nine years of penance the god returned, as was represented in the festival called Stepterion or Septerion (see A. Mommsen, Delphika, 1878).
Thus the old law of blood for blood, which only perpetuated the crime from generation to generation, gave way to the milder idea of the expiatory power of atonement for murder (cf. the court called τ&amp;omicron επι Δελφινιω at Athens, which retained jurisdiction in cases where justifiable homicide was pleaded).

The same element of enthusiasm that affects the priestess of the oracle at Delphi produces song and music.
The close connexion between prophecy and song is indicated in Homer (Odyssey, viii. 488), where Odysseus suggests that the lay of the fall of Troy by Demodocus was inspired by Apollo or the Muse.
The metrical form of the oracular responses at Delphi, the important part played by the paean and the Pythian nomos in his ritual, contributed to make Apollo a god of song and music, friend and leader of the Muses (μουσαγετης).
He plays the lyre at the banquets of the gods, and causes Marsyas to be flayed alive because he had boasted of his superior skill in playing the flute, and the ears of Midas to grow long because he had declared in favour of Pan, who contended that the flute was a better instrument than Apollo's favourite, the lyre.

A less important aspect of Apollo is that of a marine deity, due to the spread of his cult to the Greek colonies and islands.
As such, his commonest name is Delphinius, the "dolphin god," in whose honour the festival Delphinia was celebrated in Attica.
This cult probably originated in Crete, whence the god in the form of a dolphin led his Cretan worshippers to the Delphian shore, where he bade them erect an altar in his honour.
He is Epibaterius and Apobaterius ("embarker" and "disembarker"), Nasiotas ("the islander"), Euryalus ("god of the broad sea").
Like Poseidon, he looks forth over his watery kingdom from lofty cliffs and promontories (ακταιος, and perhaps ακριτας).

These maritime cults of Apollo are probably due to his importance as the god of colonization, who accompanied emigrants on their voyage.
As such he is αγητωρ ("leader"), οικιστης ("founder"), δωματιτης ("god of the home").
As Agyieus ("god of streets and ways"), in the form of a stone pillar with painted head, placed before the doors of houses, he let in the good and kept out the evil (see Farnell, Cults, iv. p. 150, who takes Agyieus to mean "leader"); on the epithet Prostaterius, he who "stands before the house," hence "protector," see G. M. Hirst in Journal of Hellenic Studies, xxii. (1902).
Lastly, as the originator and protector of civil order, Apollo was regarded as the founder of cities and legislation.
Thus, at Athens, Apollo Patroös was known as the protector of the lonians, and the Spartans referred the institutions of Lycurgus to the Delphic oracle.

It has been mentioned above that W. H. Roscher, in the article "Apollo" in his Lexikon der Mythologie, derives all the aspects and functions of Apollo from the conception of an original light- and sun-god.
The chief objections to this are the following.
It cannot be shown that on Greek soil Apollo originally had the meaning of a sun-god; in Homer, Aeschylus and Plato, the sun-god Helios is distinctly separated from Phoebus Apollo; the constant epithet Φοιβος, usually explained as the brightness of the sun, may equally well refer to his physical beauty or moral purity; λυκηγενης has already been noticed.
It is not until the beginning of the 5th century B.C. that the identification makes its appearance.
The first literary evidence is a fragment of Euripides (Phaëthon), in which it is especially characterized as an innovation.
The idea was taken up by the Stoics, and in the Roman period generally accepted.
But the fact of the gradual development of Apollo as a god of light and heaven, and his identification with foreign sun-gods, is no proof of an original Greek solar conception of him.
Apollo-Helios must be regarded as "a late by-product of Greek religion" (Farnell, Cults, iv. p. 136; Wernicke in Pauly-Wissowa's Realencydopädie).
For the manner in which the solar theory is developed, reference must be made to Roscher's article, but one legend may here be mentioned, since it helps to trace the spread of the cult of the god.
It was said that Apollo soon after his birth spent a year amongst the Hyperboreans, who dwelt in a land of perpetual sunshine, before his return to Delphi.
This return is explained as the second birth of the god and his victory over the powers of winter; the name Hyperboreans is explained as the "dwellers beyond the north wind."
This interpretation is now, however, generally rejected in favour of that of H. L. Ahrens,--that Hyperborei is identical with the Perphereës ("the carriers"), who are described as the servants of Apollo, carriers of cereal offerings from one community to another (Herodotus iv. 33).
This would point to the fact that certain settlements of Apolline worship along the northernmost border of Greece (Illyria, Thrace, Macedonia) were in the habit of sending offerings to the god to a centre of his worship farther south (probably Delphi), advancing by the route from Tempe through Thessaly, Pherae and Doris to Delphi; while others adopted the route through Illyria, Epirus, Dodona, the Malian gulf, Carystus in Euboea, and Tenos to Delos (Farnell, Cults, iv. p. 100).

The most usual attributes of Apollo were the lyre and the bow; the tripod especially was dedicated to him as the god of prophecy.
Among plants, the bay, used in expiatory sacrifices and also for making the crown of victory at the Pythian games, and the palm-tree, under which he was born in Delos, were sacred to him; among animals and birds, the wolf, the roe, the swan, the hawk, the raven, the crow, the snake, the mouse, the grasshopper and the griffin, a mixture of the eagle and the lion evidently of Eastern origin.
The swan and grasshopper symbolize music and song; the hawk, raven, crow and snake have reference to his functions as the god of prophecy.

Among the Romans the worship of Apollo was adopted from the Greeks.
There is a tradition that the Delphian oracle was consulted as early as the period of the kings during the reign of Tarquinius Superbus, and in 430 a temple was dedicated to Apollo on the occasion of a pestilence, and during the Second Punic War (in 212) the Ludi Apollinares were instituted in his honour.
It was in the time of Augustus, who considered himself under the special protection of Apollo and was even said to be his son, that his worship developed and he became one of the chief gods of Rome.
After the battle of Actium, Augustus enlarged his old temple, dedicated a portion of the spoil to him, and instituted quinquennial games in his honour.
He also erected a new temple on the Palatine hill and transferred the secular games, for which Horace composed his Carmen Saeculare, to Apollo and Diana.

Apollo was represented more frequently than any other deity in ancient art.
As Apollo Agyieus he was shown by a simple conic pillar; the Apollo of Amyclae was a pillar of bronze surmounted by a helmeted head, with extended arms carrying lance and bow.
There were also rude idols of him in wood (xoana), in which the human form was scarcely recognizable.
In the 6th century, his statues of stone were naked, stiff and rigid in attitude, shoulders square, limbs strong and broad, hair falling down the back.
In the riper period of art the type is softer, and Apollo appears in a form which seeks to combine manhood and eternal youth.
His long hair is usually tied in a large knot above his forehead.
The most famous statue of him is the Apollo Belvidere in the Vatican (found at Frascati, 1455), an imitation belonging to the early imperial period of a bronze statue representing him, with aegis in his left hand, driving back the Gauls from his temple at Delphi (279 B.C.), or, according to another view, fighting with the Pythian dragon.
In the Apollo Citharoedus or Musagetes in the Vatican, he is crowned with laurel and wears the long, flowing robe of the Ionic bard, and his form is almost feminine in its fulness; in a statue at Rome of the older and more vigorous type he is naked and holds a lyre in his left hand; his right arm rests upon his head, and a griffin is seated at his side.
The Apollo Sauroctonus (after Praxiteles), copied in bronze at the Villa Albani in Rome and in marble at Paris, is a naked, youthful, almost boyish figure, leaning against a tree, waiting to strike a lizard climbing up the trunk.
The gigantic statue of Helios (the sun-god), "the colossus of Rhodes," by Chares of Lindus, celebrated.as one of the seven wonders of the world, is unknown to us.
Bas-reliefs and painted vases reproduce the contests of Apollo with Tityus, Marsyas, and Heracles, the slaughter of the daughters of Niobe, and other incidents in his life.</entry>
  <entry author_id="681815" end="197" start="186">It appears that both Greek and Etruscan Apollo's came to the Aegean during the archaic period (from 1,100 BCE till 800 BCE) from Anatolia.
Homer has him on the side of the Trojans, not the Greeks, in the Trojan War and he has close affiliations with Luwian Apaliuna, who in turn seems to have travelled west from further east.
Late Bronze Age (from 1,700 BCE - 1,200 BCE) Hittite and Hurrian "Aplu", like Homeric Apollo, was a God of the Plague, and resembles the mouse God Apollo Smitheus.
Here we have a case where a God originally of the Plague was invoked to end illness, merging over time through fusion with the Mycenaean "doctor" God Paieon, PA-JA-WO in Linear B. Paean, in Homer, was the Greek physician of the gods.
In other writers the word is a mere epithet of Apollo in his capacity as a god of healing, but it is now known from Linear B that Paean was originally a separate Deity who over time became merely an aspect of Apollo.

Homer left the question unanswered, whilst Hesiod separated the two, and in later poetry Paean was invoked independently as a health god.
It is equally difficult to discover the relation between Paean or Paeon in the sense of "healer" and Paean in the sense of "song."
It was believed to refer to the ancient association between the healing craft and the singing of spells, but here we see a shift from the concerns to the original sense of "healer" gradually giving way to that of "hymn," from the phrase Ιή Παιάν.

Such songs were originally addressed to Apollo, and afterwards to other gods, Dionysus, Helios, Asclepius, Gods associated with Apollo.
About the 4th century the paean became merely a formula of adulation; its object was either to implore protection against disease and misfortune, or to offer thanks after such protection had been rendered.
It was in this way that Apollo became recognised as the God of Music.
Its connection with Apollo as the slayer of the Python led to its association with battle and victory; hence it became the custom for a paean to be sung by an army on the march and before entering into battle, when a fleet left the harbour, and also after a victory had been won.</entry>
  <entry author_id="651586" end="211" start="197">Hera sent the serpent to hunt Leto to her death across the world.
In order to protect his mother, Apollo begged Hephaistos for a bow and arrows.

Hera then sent the giant Tityos to kill Leto.
This time Apollo was aided by his sister Artemis in protecting their mother.
During the battle Zeus finally relented his aid and hurled Tityos down to Tartarus.
There he was pegged to the rock floor, covering an area of nine acres, where a pair of vultures feasted daily on his liver.

Later in his youth Apollo became an accomplished musician, and much loved for his talent.
He became jealous however when he heard that the satyr Marsyas became renowned for his flute playing.
He challenged he satyr to a contest to be judged by the Muses.
They were deamed equal until Apollo decreed they play and sing at the same time.
As Apollo played the lyre, this was easy to do.
Marsyas could not do this as he only knew how to use the flute and could not sing at the same time.
Apollo was declared the winner because of this.
Apollo skinned Marsyas alive and nailed his shaggy skin to a nearby pine-tree.</entry>
</article>
