<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="651" title="America the Beautiful" authors="2" lines="28">
  <entry author_id="211165" end="11" start="0">The words are by Katharine Lee Bates, an English teacher at Wellesley College.
She had taken a train trip to Colorado in 1893 to teach a short summer school session, and several of the sights on her trip found their way into her poem:On that mountain, the words of the poem started to come to her, and she wrote them down upon returning to her hotel room.
The poem was initially published two years later, to commemorate the Fourth of July.
It quickly caught the public's fancy.
Amended versions were issued in 1904 and 1910.

Several existing pieces of music were adapted to the poem.
The one that had been pretty well settled upon by 1910 was the hymn Materna, composed in 1882 by Samuel A.
Ward had been similarly inspired.
The tune came to him while he was on a ferryboat trip from Coney Island back to his home in New York City after a leisurely day summer, and he immediately wrote it down.
He would died in 1903, knowing how beautiful his music was, but not knowing the national stature it would attain.
Katharine Bates also knew she had something good, and thankfully saw it come to fruition, as she lived until 1929.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7588340" end="28" start="11">On the pinnacle of that mountain, the words of the poem started to come to her, and she wrote them down upon returning to her hotel room at the original Antlers Hotel.
The poem was initially published two years later in The Congregationalist, to commemorate the Fourth of July.
It quickly caught the public's fancy.
Amended versions were published in 1904 and 1913.

Several existing pieces of music were adapted to the poem.
A hymn tune composed by Samuel A.
Ward was generally considered the best music as early as 1910 and is still the popular tune today.
Just as Bates had been inspired to write her poem, Ward too was inspired to compose his tune.
The tune came to him while he was on a ferryboat trip from Coney Island back to his home in New York City, after a leisurely summer day in 1882, and he immediately wrote it down.
He was so anxious to capture the tune in his head, he asked fellow passenger friend Harry Martin for his shirt cuff to write the tune on, thus perhaps the off the cuff analogy.
He composed the tune for the old hymn "O Mother Dear, Jerusalem", retitling the work "Materna".
Ward's music combined with Bates' poem were first published together in 1910 and titled, America the Beautiful.

At various times in the more than 100 years that have elapsed since the song as we know it was born, particularly during the John F. Kennedy administration, there have been efforts to give "America the Beautiful" legal status either as a national hymn, or as a national anthem equal to, or in place of, "The Star-Spangled Banner", but so far this has not succeeded.
Proponents prefer "America the Beautiful" for various reasons, saying it is easier to sing, more melodic, and more adaptable to new orchestrations while still remaining as easily recognizable as "The Star-Spangled Banner."
Some prefer "America the Beautiful" over "The Star-Spangled Banner" due to the latter's war-oriented imagery.
Others prefer "The Star-Spangled Banner" for the same reason, or for the reason that it does not directly invoke God.
While that national dichotomy has stymied any effort at changing the tradition of the national anthem, "America the Beautiful" continues to be held in high esteem by a large number of Americans.</entry>
</article>
