<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="689" title="Asia" authors="2" lines="50">
  <entry author_id="103961" end="19" start="0">In terms of gross domestic product, Asia's largest economy is Japan, and the smallest is East Timor, (although as of 2005 there is no reliable data for Iraq or North Korea).
Japan is the world's second largest economy, and North Korea is one of the poorest.
As of 2005, China's economy has been growing rapidly.

Agriculture constitutes a high portion of land usage.
The main agricultural products include rice, grain, and chicken.
One of Asia's major cash crops is opium, which is sold in Europe and North America.

Forestry is estensive throughout the continent, with many of the items of furniture sold in the Western World made out of Asian timber.
Fishing is a major source of food in Asia, particularly in Japan and China.
Manufacturing in Asia has traditionally been strongest in the Southeast region, particularly in mainland China, Taiwan, Japan and Singapore.
The industry varies from manufacturing cheap low-value goods such as toys to high-tech added-value goods such as computers, CD players, games consoles and cars.
Major Asian manufacturing companies include Sony, Samsung, LG, Toyota, Honda, and Nissan.
Many western companies from Europe and North America have significant operations in Asia to take avantage of the continent's abundant supply of cheap labour.

One of the major employers in manufacturing in Asia is the textile industry.
Much of the world's supply of clothing and footwear now originates in Southeast Asia, particularly Vietnam, China, Thailand, and Indonesia.
Asia has three main financial centers.
They are in Hong Kong, Singapore and Tokyo.
Call centers are becoming major employers in India, due to the availablity of many well-educated English speakers.
The rise of the business process outsourcing industry has seen the rise of India and China as the other financial centers.
Experts believe the current center of financial activity is moving toward "Chindia" -- a name used for jointly referring to China and India -- with Shanghai and Mumbai (Bombay) becoming major financial hubs in their own right.</entry>
  <entry author_id="103961" end="32" start="19">The coastal periphery was the first to be home to civilization, with each of the three regions developing early civilizations around fertile river valleys.
The civilizations in Mesopotamia, the Indus Valley, and the Yangtze shared many similarities and likely exchange technologies and ideas such as mathematics, the wheel.
Other notions such as that of writing likely developed individually in each area.
Cities states and them empire developed in these lowlands.

The steppe region had long been inhabited by mounted nomads, and from the central steppes they could reach all areas of the Asian continent.
The earliest known such central expansion out of the steppe is that of the Indo-Europeans which spread their languages into the Middle East, India, and in the Tocharians to the borders of China.
The northern part of the continent, covering much of Siberia was also inaccessible to the steppe nomads due to the dense forests and the tundra.
These areas were very sparsely populated.

The centre and periphery were kept separate by mountains and desserts.
The Caucuses, Himalaya, Karakum Desert, Gobi Desert formed barriers that the steppe horse men could only cross with difficulty.
While technologically and culturally the urban city dwellers were more advanced, they could do little militarily to defend against the mounted hordes of the steppe.
However, the lowlands did not have enough open grasslands to support a large horsebound force.
Thus the nomads who conquered states in China, India, and the Middle East were soon forced to adapt to the local societies.</entry>
  <entry author_id="84919" end="50" start="32">Asia is the largest and most populous of the geographical region or continent, depending on the definition.
It is traditionally defined as part of the landmass of Africa-Eurasia lying east of the Suez Canal, east of the Ural Mountains, and south of the Caucasus Mountains and the Caspian and Black Seas.
About 60% of the world's human population lives in Asia, of whom only 2% live in the northern and interior half (Siberia, Mongolia, Kazakhstan, Xinjiang, Tibet, Qinghai, western Uzbekistan and Turkmenistan); the other 98% live in the remaining half.

Historically, medieval European considered Asia continent in term of landmass.
However, modern discovery of the extent of Africa and Asia made this difinition rather anachronic especially in case of Asia which has number of distinct landmass (i.e. mountain) separation of South Asia and East Asia.
Geology or physical geography no longer consider Asia and Europe to be separate.
It is either defined in term of geological landmass (physical geography) or tectonic plate (geology).
In the former case, Europe is a western penninsula of Eurasia or Africa-Eurasia landmass.
In later definition, Europe and Asia are still part of Eurasia plate which exclude Arabian and Indian techtonic plate.
In human geography, there are two school of thought.
One simply treat Europe and Asia as a historical convention, then cateogrise Europe, East Asia(Orient), South Asia (British India), Middle East (Arabia and Persia) as each region in term of analysis.
The other school equate the word "continent" in term of geographical region when refering to Europe and use the term "region" to describe Asia in term of physical geography.
Because in linguistic term, "continent" imply distinct landmass, it is becoming increasing common to substitute the term "continent" with "region" so to forgo the problem of disambiguation between geography and geology all together.

There are much confusion in European languages with the term "Asian".
Because a categoy imply homogenity, the term Asian is always used to refer to subcategory of people from Asia rather than refering to "Asian" defined in term of "Asia".
In English, Asian in American English refers to East Asian (Orientals) while Asian in British English refers to South Asian which reflect this confusion.
It is sometimes not even clear what Asia precisely consists of.
Moreover,</entry>
</article>
