<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="690" title="Aruba" authors="4" lines="59">
  <entry author_id="108" end="17" start="0">Discovered and claimed for Spain in 1499, Aruba was acquired by the Dutch in 1636.
The island's economy has been dominated by three main industries.
A 19th century gold rush was followed by prosperity brought on by the opening in 1924 of an oil refinery.
The last decades of the 20th century saw a boom in the tourism industry.
Aruba seceded from the Netherlands Antilles in 1986 and became a separate, autonomous member of the Kingdom of the Netherlands.
Movement toward full independence was halted at Aruba's request in 1990.
Main article: Politics of Aruba

Aruba is a flat, riverless island renowned for its white sand beaches.
Its tropical climate is moderated by constant trade winds from the Atlantic Ocean.
Temperature is almost constant at about 27 degrees Celsius.
The highest point in Aruba is Mount Jamanota, at 188 m above sea level.

Although the official language is Dutch, Papiamento is predominant.
This creole language is formed from elements of Dutch, English, Spanish and Portuguese.
Spanish and English are also spoken.

The origins of the population and location of the island give Aruba a mixed culture.
Dutch influence is can still be seen, even though not much of the population is of Dutch origin.
Tourism from the United States has recently also increased the importance of American culture.</entry>
  <entry author_id="465131" end="31" start="17">On September 29, 2005, Eduardo Mathew won a lawsuit against the government of Aruba in the European Court of Human Rights.
Mathew claimed that there was institutional racism against him by the Dutch authorities.
The September 29, 2005, opinion found in favor of Mathew's claim of institutional racism in Aruba.

CNN raised the issue of racism on June 15, 2005 in connection with the Natalee Holloway case, where authorities arrested and held two black security guards, depite clear evidence of an alibi.
The last people to see Natalee Holloway on the night she disappeared in Aruba were the white teenage son of a local judge and two middle-class young men of Surinamese descent, according to local police.
Within days of when Holloway was last seen in the early hours of May 30, Aruban police arrested two black security guards who worked at a hotel near where she was staying.
One question swirling around the investigation was whether police initially targeted the security guards -- who were released without charges eight days later -- as suspects at least in part because of their race or class.One of the freed security guards, Mickey John raised the issue of racism, in an interview with Fox News -JOHN: Well, like I said before, the justice system, the detectives, they're all fools.
They have to go to back to school.
And they were used, like, a scapegoat, use, like, a black person in society to cover their mess.
In July, commentator Olumide K. Obayemi wrote an article entitledRacism in Aruba: The arrests of Abraham Jones and Mickey John were not only unfair, but classically racist San Francisco View (July 6, 2005).

Some Arubans claim that since the population is mixed race, there is no racism in Aruba.
However, on October 5, 2005, Jossy Mansur, the editor of the Diario newspaper, opined that the racial problems in investigation of missing Alabama teen, Natalee Holloway, were between the Dutch and the Arubans.
See 1 --  The principal suspect is Dutch, the lead investigator was Dutch, the prosecutor is Dutch and the five judges involved are Dutch.
If you think about it, an attempted boycott against Aruba is unjust, because it is misdirected and won’t achieve the desired results.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11867570" end="46" start="31">Natalee Ann Holloway (born October 21, 1986) disappeared on May 30, 2005, during a high school graduation trip to Aruba, a Caribbean country within the Kingdom of the Netherlands.
An American student from Mountain Brook, Alabama, Holloway graduated from Mountain Brook High School on May 24, 2005, shortly before the trip.
Her disappearance caused a media sensation in the United States.

Holloway was scheduled to fly home later on May 30, but failed to appear for her flight.
She was last seen by her classmates outside Carlos'n Charlie's, a Caribbean chain restaurant and nightclub in Oranjestad, in a car with locals Joran van der Sloot and brothers Deepak and Satish Kalpoe.
When questioned, the three men said they dropped her off at her hotel and denied knowing what became of Holloway.
Upon further investigation by authorities, Van der Sloot was arrested twice on suspicion of involvement in her disappearance and the Kalpoes were each arrested three times.
Due to lack of evidence the three men were released without charge after each arrest.

With the help of hundreds of volunteers, Aruban investigators conducted an extensive search for Holloway.
Special Agents from the FBI, fifty Dutch soldiers and three specially equipped Dutch Air Force F-16 aircraft participated in the search.
In addition to the ground search, divers examined the ocean floor for evidence of Holloway's body.
The searches were unsuccessful, and according to Aruban authorities she is most likely dead.
On December 18, 2007, Aruban prosecutors announced that the case would be closed without any charges sought against the former suspects.
The Aruban prosecutor's office reopened the case on February 1, 2008, after receiving video footage of Joran van der Sloot, under the influence of marijuana, making statements that Holloway died on the morning of May 30, 2005, and that he disposed of her body.
Van der Sloot later denied that what he said was true, and subsequently gave Greta Van Susteren an interview (the contents of which he later retracted) in which he stated that he sold Holloway into white slavery.</entry>
  <entry author_id="2559599" end="59" start="46">On Thursday, May 26, 2005, Holloway and 124 fellow graduates of Mountain Brook High School, located in a wealthy suburb of Birmingham, Alabama, arrived in Aruba for a five-day, unofficial graduation trip.
The graduates were accompanied by seven chaperones.
According to teacher and chaperone Bob Plummer, the chaperones met with the students each day to ensure nothing was wrong.
However, Jodi Bearman—the chaperone who organized the trip, stated, "the chaperones were not supposed to keep up with their every move".
Police Commissioner Gerold Dompig, who would head the investigation from mid-2005 until 2006, described the behavior of the Mountain Brook students, stating there was "wild partying, a lot of drinking, lots of room switching every night.
We know the Holiday Inn told them they weren't welcome next year.
Natalee, we know, she drank all day every day.
We have statements she started every morning with cocktails—so much drinking that Natalee didn't show up for breakfast two mornings".
Two of Holloway's classmates, Liz Cain and Claire Fierman, "agreed that the drinking was kind of excessive".

Holloway was last seen by her classmates leaving the Aruban bar and night club Carlos'n Charlie's around 1:30 a.m. on Monday, May 30.
Holloway left with 17-year-old Joran van der Sloot, a Dutch honors student living in Aruba and attending the Aruba International School, and his two Surinamese friends, 21-year-old Deepak Kalpoe and 18-year-old Satish Kalpoe, in Deepak Kalpoe's car.
Holloway, who had been scheduled to fly home later on May 30, did not appear for her return flight, and her packed luggage and passport were found in her Holiday Inn room.
Aruban authorities initiated searches for Holloway throughout the island and surrounding waters but did not find her.</entry>
</article>
