<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="706" title="Economy of Angola" authors="2" lines="47">
  <entry author_id="90" end="32" start="0">Angola's is the fastest-growing economy in Africa, largely due to a major oil boom, but it also ranks in the bottom 10 of socioeconomic conditions in the world.
Aside from the oil sector and diamonds, it is in economic disarray because of 26 years of nearly continuous warfare.
Despite abundant natural resources, output per capita remains among the world's lowest.
Subsistence agriculture and dependence on humanitarian food assistance sustain the large majority of the population.
Little industry exists.

By contrast, the rapidly expanding petroleum industry now producing up to 800,000 barrels per day, behind only Nigeria in Africa, accounts for more than 60% of GNP and 90% of government revenues.
Oil production remains largely offshore and has few linkages with other sectors of the economy.
Block Zero, located of the enclave of Cabinda, provides the majority of Angola's crude oil production.
There, ChevronTexaco, through its subsidiary Cabinda Gulf Oil Company, is the operator with a 39.2% share, with SONANGOL (the Angolan state oil company), TotalFinaElf, and ENI-Agip splitting up the rest.
ChevronTexaco also operates Angola's first producing deepwater section, Block 14, which started pumping in January 2000.
The U.S. takes more than half of Angola's production, by far the largest importer.
Exports to Asian countries have grown rapidly in recent years, however, especially China.
Significant discoveries have been made on deepwater Blocks 15, 17, 18, and 24, with ExxonMobil, BP, Statoil, Norsk Hydro, and Agip having major interests.
TotalFinaElf operates Angola's one refinery (in Luanda) as a joint venture with SONANGOL; plans for a second refinery in Lobito are moving forward.

In the last decade of the colonial period, Angola was a major African food exporter but now is forced to import almost all its food.
Because of severe wartime conditions, including extensive planting of landmines throughout the countryside, agricultural activities have been brought to a near standstill.
Some efforts to recover have gone forward, however, notably in fisheries.
Coffee production, though a fraction of its pre-1975 level, is sufficient for domestic needs and some exports.
In sharp contrast to a bleak picture of devastation and bare subsistence is expanding oil production, now almost half of GDP and 90% of exports, at 800,000 barrels a day.
Diamonds make up most of the remaining exports--and have provided much of the revenue for Jonas Savimbi's UNITA rebellion through illicit trade.
Other rich resources await development: gold, forest products, fisheries, iron ore, coffee, and countless fruits.

An economic reform effort was launched in 1998.
In April 2000, Angola started an International Monetary Fund (IMF) Staff-Monitored Program (SMP).
The program formally lapsed in June 2001, but the IMF remains engaged.
In this context, the Government of Angola has succeeded in unifying exchange rates and has raised fuel, electricity, and water rates.
The Commercial Code, telecommunications law, and Foreign Investment Code are being modernized.
A privatization effort, prepared with World Bank assistance, has begun with the BCI bank.
Nevertheless, a legacy of fiscal mismanagement and corruption persists.

Angola is the third-largest trading partner of the United States in Sub-Saharan Africa, largely because of its petroleum exports.
The U.S. imports about 4% of its oil from Angola, a share which should continue to increase.
By the same token, U.S. companies account for more than half the investment in Angola, with Chevron-Texaco leading the way.
The U.S. exports industrial goods and services--primarily oilfield equipment, mining equipment, chemicals, aircraft, and food--to Angola, while principally importing petroleum.</entry>
  <entry author_id="6817753" end="47" start="32">Kingdom of Portugal's explorers and settlers, founded trading posts and forts along the East Coast of Africa since de 15th century, and reached the Angolan coast in the 16th century.
Portuguese explorer Paulo Dias de Novais founded Luanda in 1575 as "São Paulo de Loanda", and the region developed as a slave trade market with the help of local Imbangala and Mbundu peoples who were notable slave hunters.
Trade was mostly with the Portuguese colony of Brazil; Brazilian ships were the most numerous in the ports of Luanda and Benguela.
By this time, Angola, a Portuguese colony, was in fact like a colony of Brazil, paradoxically another Portuguese colony.
A strong Brazilian influence was also exercised by the Jesuits in religion and education.
War gradually gave way to the philosophy of trade.
The great trade routes and the agreements that made them possible were the driving force for activities between the different areas; warlike states become states ready to produce and to sell.
In the Planalto (the high plains), the most important states were those of Bié and Bailundo, the latter being noted for its production of foodstuffs and rubber.
The colonial power, Portugal, becoming ever richer and more powerful, would not tolerate the growth of these neighbouring states and subjugated them one by one, so that by the beginning of this century the Portuguese had complete control over the entire area.

From 1764 onwards, there was a gradual change from a slave-based society to one based on production for domestic consumption.
Meanwhile, the slave trade was abolished in 1836, and in 1844 Angola's ports were opened to foreign shipping.
By 1850, Luanda was one of the greatest and most developed Portuguese cities in the vast Portuguese Empire outside Mainland Portugal, full of trading companies, exporting (together with Benguela) palm and peanut oil, wax, copal, timber, ivory, cotton, coffee, and cocoa, among many other products.
Maize, tobacco, dried meat and cassava flour also began to be produced locally.
The Angolan bourgeoisie was born.
From the 1920s to the 1960s, strong economic growth, abundant natural resorces and development of infrastruture, led to the arrival even more Portuguese settlers from the metropole.</entry>
</article>
