<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="711" title="Albert Sidney Johnston" authors="3" lines="119">
  <entry author_id="0" end="15" start="0">General Albert Sidney Johnson (b. February 2, 1803 – d. April 6, 1862) was a Kentucky native and in 1826 graduated from the United States Military Academy at West Point, NY.
As a US Army officer, he was assigned to posts in New York and Missouri.
He served in the Black Hawk War in 1832.
After resigning his US Army commission in 1834, he returned to Kentucky to care for his dying wife.

He moved to Texas in July of 1836 and enlisted in The Republic Army.
One month later he was appointed to the position of Adjutant General and in January of 1837, he became Senior Brigadier General in Command of the Republic Army.
The Second President of the Republic of Texas Mirabeau B. Lamar appointed him Secretary of War in December of 1838.
In 1840, he returned to Kentucky and married Eliza Griffin in 1843.
They settled in China Grove, TX on his large plantation and lived there until 1849.

During the Mexican War, he commanded a company of Texas Volunteers.
Later as a Colonel in the United States Army, he served on the Texas frontier and in the West.
At the outbreak of the Civil War, he resigned from the US Army and was appointed a Confederate General by President of the Confederate States of America Jefferson Davis.

He was killed at the Battle of Shiloh in 1862 and was buried in New Orleans, LA.
In 1866, a joint resolution of the Texas Legislature was passed to have his body reinterred to the state cemetery in Austin (the re-interment occurred in 1867).
Four decades later, the state appointed Elisbet Ney to design a monument and sculpture of him to be erected at his gravesite.</entry>
  <entry author_id="36708" end="46" start="15">Albert Sidney Johnston (February 2, 1803 – April 6, 1862) was a career U.S. Army officer and a Confederate general during the American Civil War.
Considered by some to be the finest general in the Confederacy, he was killed early in the war at the Battle of Shiloh.
Johnston was born in Washington, Kentucky, but lived much of his life in Texas and considered that his home.
In 1826 he graduated from the United States Military Academy with a commission as a second lieutenant in the 2nd U.S. Infantry.
He was assigned to posts in New York and Missouri and served in the Black Hawk War in 1832.
After resigning his commission in 1834, he returned to Kentucky to care for his dying wife.
In April of 1834, Johnston took up farming in Texas, but enlisted as a private in the Texas Army during the Texas War of Independence against Mexico in 1836.
One month later, Johnston was promoted to major and the position of aide-de-camp to General Sam Houston.
He was named Adjutant General as a colonel in the Republic of Texas Army on August 5, 1836.
On January 31, 1837, he became Senior Brigadier General in command of the Texas Army.

On February 7, 1837, he fought in a duel with Brig.
Gen. Felix Huston, challenging each other for the command of the Texas Army; Johnston refused to fire on Huston and lost the position after he was wounded in the pelvis.
The second president of the Republic of Texas, Mirabeau B. Lamar, appointed him Secretary of War on December 22, 1838.
In February of 1840, he resigned and returned to Kentucky, where he married Eliza Griffin in 1843.
They settled on a large plantation he named China Grove in Brazoria County, Texas.
Johnston returned to the Texas Army during the Mexican-American War under General Zachary Taylor as a colonel of the 1st Texas Rifle Volunteers, fighting at the Battle of Monterrey on September 20–24, 1846.
Johnson returned to the U.S. Army as a major and was made a U.S. Army Paymaster in December of 1849.
He served on the Texas frontier and elsewhere in the West.
He received a brevet promotion to brigadier general in 1857 for his service in Utah.
At the outbreak of the American Civil War, Johnston was the commander of the U.S. Army Department of the Pacific in the California.
He declined and instead resigned from the U.S. Army and was appointed a general by his friend, President of the Confederate States of America Jefferson Davis.
On may 30, 1861, Johnston became the second highest ranking Confederate General (after the little-known Samuel Cooper) as commander of the Western Department.
He raised the Army of Mississippi to defend Confederate lines from the Mississippi River to Kentucky and the Allegheny Mountains.

Although the Confederate Army won a morale-boosting victory at First Bull Run in the East in 1861, matters in the West turned ugly by early 1862.
Johnston's subordinate generals lost Fort Henry on February 6, 1862, and Fort Donelson on February 14, 1862, to Union Maj. Gen. Ulysses S. Grant.
And Union Maj. Gen. Don Carlos Buell captured the vital city of Nashville, Tennessee.
Gen. P.G.T.
Beauregard was sent west to join Johnston and they organized their forces at Corinth, Mississippi, planning to ambush Grant's forces at Pittsburg Landing, Tennessee.
Johnston conducted a massive surprise attack against Grant at the Battle of Shiloh on April 6, 1862.
As the Confederate forces overran the Union camps, Johnston seemed to be everywhere, personally leading and rallying troops up and down the line.
While leading one of those charges, he was wounded, taking a bullet behind his right knee.</entry>
  <entry author_id="12744454" end="119" start="46">Early in the Civil War, Confederate President Jefferson Davis decided that the Confederacy would attempt to hold as much of its territory as possible and he distributed its forces around its borders and coasts.
In the summer of 1861, Davis appointed several generals to defend Confederate lines from the Mississippi River to Kentucky and the Allegheny Mountains.
The most sensitive, and in many ways the most crucial area, along the Mississippi River and in western Tennessee along the Tennessee River and the Cumberland River was placed under the command of Maj. Gen. Leonidas Polk and Brig.
Gen. Gideon J. Pillow, who had been initially in command as Tennessee's top general.
Their impolitic occupation of Columbus, Kentucky on September 3, 1861, two days before Johnston arrived in Richmond, Virginia after his cross–country journey, drove Kentucky from its stated neutrality and the majority of Kentuckians into the Union camp.
It also allowed Union Brig.
Gen. Ulysses S. Grant an excuse to take control of the even more important and strategically located town of Paducah, Kentucky without raising the ire of most Kentuckians.
On September 10, 1861, Johnston was assigned to command the huge area of the Confederacy west of the Allegheny Mountains, except for coastal areas, and became commander of the Confederacy's western armies in the area often called the Western Department or Western Military Department.
He was permitted to call on governors of Arkansas, Tennessee and Mississippi for new troops, although this authority was largely stifled by politics, especially with respect to Mississippi.
After his appointment, Johnston immediately headed for his new territory.
On September 13, 1861, in view of the decision of the Kentucky legislature to side with the Union after the occupation of Columbus by Polk, Johnston ordered Brig.
Gen. Felix Zollicoffer with 4,000 men to occupy Cumberland Gap in Kentucky to block Union troops from coming into eastern Tennessee.
By September 18, Johnston had Brig.
Gen. Simon Bolivar Buckner with another 4,000 men blocking the railroad route to Tennessee at Bowling Green, Kentucky.

Johnston had less than 40,000 men spread throughout Kentucky, Tennessee, Arkansas and Missouri.
Of these, 10,000 were in Missouri under Missouri State Guard Maj. Gen. Sterling Price.
Johnston's initial call upon the governors for more men did not result in many immediate recruits but Johnston had another, even bigger, problem since his force was seriously short of arms and ammunition even for the troops he had.
As the Confederate government concentrated efforts on the units in the East, they gave Johnston only small numbers of reinforcements and minimal amounts of arms and material.Johnston could only keep up his defense by raids and other measures to make it appear he had larger forces than he did, a strategy that worked for several months.
Johnston's tactics had so annoyed and confused Union Brig.
Gen. William Tecumseh Sherman that he had to be relieved by Brig.
Gen. Don Carlos Buell on November 9, 1861.
Eastern Tennessee was held for the Confederacy by two unimpressive brigadier generals appointed by Davis, Felix Zollicoffer, a brave but untrained and inexperienced officer, and soon to be Maj. Gen. George B. Crittenden, a former army officer with apparent alcohol problems.
While Crittenden was away in Richmond, Zollicoffer moved his forces to the north bank of the upper Cumberland River near Mill Springs (now Nancy, Kentucky), putting the river to his back and his forces into a trap.
Zollicoffer decided it was impossible to obey orders to return to the other side of the river.
When Union Brig.
Gen. George H. Thomas moved against the Confederates, Crittenden decided to attack one of the two parts of his force at Logan's Cross Roads before they could unite.
On January 19, 1862, the ill-prepared Confederates, after a night march in the rain, attacked with some initial success.
Zollicoffer was killed in the battle, Crittenden was unable to lead the force since he was probably intoxicated and the Confederates were turned back and routed by a bayonet charge, suffering 533 casualties from their force of 4,000.
The forces which escaped were assigned to other units.

After the Confederate defeat at the Battle of Mill Springs, Davis sent Johnston a brigade and a few other scattered reinforcements, and Gen. P.G.T.
Beauregard, who was supposed to attract recruits because of his victories early in the war and give Johnston a competent subordinate.
The brigade, however, came with the incompetent Brig.
Gen. John B. Floyd, who was to take command at Fort Donelson just before it was attacked.
Beauregard's move to the west also spurred the Union commanders to action against the forts before, in their view, he could make a difference in the theater and bring the 15 regiments he was supposedly, but not actually, bringing with him to the defense of the forts.
Based on the assumption of Kentucky neutrality as a shield, Tennessee had sent men to Virginia and concentrated defenses in the Mississippi Valley, circumstances that no longer applied in September 1861.
Even before Johnston arrived in Tennessee, two forts had been started to defend the Tennessee River and the Cumberland River.
Both had been sited in Tennessee, however, in order to respect Kentucky neutrality and were not in ideal locations.
Fort Henry on the Tennessee River was in an especially unfavorable low lying location commanded by hills on the Kentucky side of the river.
Fort Donelson on the Cumberland River also was not in the best location and did not have enough heavy artillery for its defense.

Maj. Gen. Polk ignored the problems of Fort Henry and Fort Donelson and at first refused to comply with Johnston's order to send an engineer, Lt. Joseph K. Dixon, to inspect the forts, Fort Donelson in particular.
Polk ultimately had to allow Dixon to proceed.
Dixon recommended that the forts be maintained and strengthened, even though they were not in ideal locations, because much work had been done on them.
Johnston accepted the recommendations.
Johnston wanted Major, later Lt. Gen., Alexander P. Stewart to command the forts but Davis appointed Brig.
Gen. Lloyd Tilghman as commander.
In order to prevent Polk from dissipating his forces by allowing some men to join a partisan group, Johnston ordered him to send Pillow and 5,000 men to Fort Donelson.
Pillow took up a position at nearby Clarksville, Tennessee and did not move into the fort itself until February 7, 1862.
Alerted by a Union reconnaissance on January 14, 1862, Johnston ordered Tilghman to fortify the high ground opposite Fort Henry which Polk had failed to do, despite Johnston's orders.
Tilghman also failed to act decisively on these orders, which in any event were now too late to be adequately carried out.

Gen. Beauregard arrived at Johnston's headquarters at Bowling Green on February 4, 1862 and was given overall command of Polk's force at the western end of Johnston's line at Columbus, Kentucky.
On February 6, 1862, Union Navy gunboats quickly reduced the defenses of ill-sited Fort Henry, inflicting 21 casualties on the small remaining Confederate force.
Brig.
Gen. Lloyd Tilghman surrendered the 94 remaining officers and men of his approximately 3,000-man force which had not been sent to Fort Donelson before U.S. Grant's force could even take up their positions.
Johnston knew he could be trapped at Bowling Green if Fort Donelson fell, so he moved his force to Nashville beginning on February 11, 1862.

Johnston also reinforced Fort Donelson with 12,000 more men, including those under Floyd and Pillow, a curious decision in view of his thought that the Union gunboats alone might be able to take the fort.
He did order the commanders of the fort to evacuate the troops if the fort could not be held.
The senior generals sent to the fort to command the enlarged garrison, Gideon J. Pillow and John B. Floyd, squandered their chance to avoid having to surrender most of the garrison and on February 16, 1862, Brig.
Gen. Simon Buckner, having been abandoned by Floydand Pillow, surrendered Fort Donelson.
Colonel Nathan Bedford Forrest escaped with his cavalry force of about 700 men before the surrender.
The Confederates suffered about 1,500 casualties with an estimated 12,000 to 14,000 taken prisoner.
Union casualties were 500 killed, 2,108 wounded, 224 missing.

Johnston, who had little choice in allowing Floyd and Pillow to take charge at Fort Donelson on the basis of seniority after he ordered them to add their forces to the garrison, took the blame and suffered calls for his removal because a full explanation to the press and public would have exposed the weakness of the Confederate position.
His passive defensive performance while positioning himself in a forward position at Bowling Green, spreading his forces too thinly, not concentrating his forces in the face of Union advances, and appointing or relying upon inadequate or incompetent subordinates subjected him to criticism at the time and by later historians.
The fall of the forts exposed Nashville to imminent attack, and it fell without resistance to Union forces under Buell on February 25, 1862, two days after Johnston had to pull his forces out in order to avoid having them captured as well.
Johnston had various remaining military units scattered throughout his territory and retreating to the south to avoid being cut off.
Johnston himself retreated with the force under his personal command, the Army of Central Kentucky, from the vicinity of Nashville.
He decided to concentrate forces with those formerly under Polk and now already under Beauregard's command at the strategically located railroad crossroads of Corinth, Mississippi, which he reached by a circuitous route.
Johnston kept the Union forces, now under the overall command of the ponderous Maj. Gen. Henry Halleck, confused and hesitant to move, allowing Johnston to reach his objective undetected.
This delay allowed Jefferson Davis finally to send reinforcements from the garrisons of coastal cities and another highly rated but prickly general, Braxton Bragg, to help organize the western forces.
Bragg at least calmed the nerves of Beauregard and Polk who had become agitated by their apparent dire situation before the arrival of Johnston on March 24, 1862.

Johnston now planned to defeat the Union forces piecemeal before the various Union units in Kentucky and Tennessee under Grant with 40,000 men at nearby Pittsburg Landing, Tennessee, and the now Maj. Gen. Don Carlos Buell on his way from Nashville with 35,000 men, could unite against him.
Johnston started his army in motion on April 3, 1862, intent on surprising Grant's force as soon as the next day, but they moved slowly due to their inexperience, bad roads and lack of adequate staff planning.
Johnston's army was finally in position within a mile or two of Grant's force, and undetected, by the evening of April 5, 1862.</entry>
</article>
