<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="713" title="Android (robot)" authors="1" lines="30">
  <entry author_id="6400929" end="30" start="0">The world's first Android DER 01 was developped by Japanese Research Group.
And in 2006, Kokoro Co. developped new DER 2 android.
Height of the human body part of "DER2" is 165cm.
There are 47 mobile points.
DER2 moves not only the expression but also hands and feet and can twist a body.
"The air servosystem" which Kokoro Co. developed originally is used for the actuator.
As a result of having controlled an actuator with air pressure via servosystem precisely, the movement is very fluent and noise is very small.
"DER2" realized a slim body than a former version by using a small cylinder.
Outwardly "DER2" becomes a more beautiful proportion.
Compared to the previous model, DER2 has thinner arms and a wider repertoire of expressions.
The smoothness of her movement has also been improved, making it now even more likely for the uninitiated to confuse her with an actual human being.
Once programmed, she is able to choreograph her motions and gestures with her voice.

Now she is working at Science University of Tokyo as a guide.

The Waseda University(Japan) and NTT Docomo's manufacturers have succeeded in creating a shape-shifting robot WD-2.
It is capable of changing its face.
At first, the creators decided the position of the necessary points to express the outline, eyes, nose and so on of a certain person.
The robot expresses his/her face by moving all points to the decided positions", they say.
It looks spooky to me, though.
The first version of the robot was first developed back in 2003.
After that, a year later, they did a couple of major improvements in the design.
The robot features an elastic mask made from the average head dummy.
It uses a driving system with a 3DOF unit.
The WD-2 robot can change its facial features by activating specific facial points on a mask, with each point possessing three degrees of freedom.
This one has 17 facial points, for a total of 56 degrees of freedom.
As for the materials they used, the WD-2’s mask is fabricated with a highly elastic material called Septom, with bits of steel wool mixed in for added strength.
Other technical features reveal a shaft is driven behind the mask at the desired facial point, driven by a DC motor with a simple pulley and a slide screw.
Apparently, the researchers can also modify the shape of the mask based on actual human faces.
To "copy" a face, they only need a 3D scanner to determine the locations of an individual’s 17 facial points.
After that, they are then driven into position using a laptop and 56 motor control boards.
In addition, the researchers also mention that the shifting robot can even display an individual’s hair style and skin color, if a photo of their face is projected onto the 3D mask.</entry>
</article>
