<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="717" title="Alberta" authors="4" lines="60">
  <entry author_id="1591" end="13" start="0">Albertans poltics are more right-wing than those of any Canadian province.
The provincial government has been from a series of right wing parties for decades, first with social credit and today with the conservatives.
The current premier of Alberta is Ralph Klein, who despite problems with alcohol, and frequent statemetns that many would consider bigoted is extermely popular in the province.
Alberta is the heartland of the Canadian Alliance Party, the seond largest party in parliament and the furthest right.
Both provincial governments and the Alliance reflect Alberta more socially consrvative nature than other provinces.
Albertans are more opposed to ideas such as gay marriage, gun control, and abortion than other Canadians.
They are also more pro-death penalty and two-tier healthcare.
In recent years these opinions, and the xtent to which they differ from central Canada and hte governing Liberals have left many ALbertans allienated and there are occasional mutterings of seperatism from the province.

Albertans are the lowest taxed people in Canada, mostly becasue of the province's considerable oil and gas income.
Alberta is the only province without a sales tax.
The federal government has attempted on a number of occassions to reditribute Alberta's wealth, most famously with Trudeau]'s National Energy Policy (NEP).
This policy was removed by the Mulroney conservatives in 1984, however.
Alberta is still one of three provinces that pays transfer payments to the other seven poorer provinces.</entry>
  <entry author_id="14346" end="32" start="13">The legislature is headed by the Premier, Ralph Klein, the Lieutenant-governor, and the cabinet, and the city of Edmonton is Alberta's government seat.
The province's revenue comes mainly from sales of oil, natural gas, beef, softwood lumber, and wheat, but also includes grants from the federal government primarily for infrastructure projects.
Albertans are the lowest taxed people in Canada, and Alberta is the only province in Canada without a provincial sales tax.
Alberta's towns and cities have their own municipal governments which (usually) work in cooperation with the provincial government.

Alberta has traditionally had three political parties, the Progressive Conservatives, the centrist Liberals, and the social democratic New Democratic Party.
A fourth party, the strongly conservative Social Credit Party, was a power in Alberta for a number of decades, but disappeared from the political map when the Progressive Conservatives came to power in the early 1970s.
Since that time, no other political party has led Alberta.

Alberta has two main east-west corridors.
The northern corridor, known as the Yellowhead Highway, runs from Lloydminster in eastern Alberta, through Edmonton, and then west to Jasper National Park and into British Columbia.
The southern corridor, the Alberta portion of the Trans-Canada Highway, enters the province near Medicine Hat, rus westward through Calgary, and leaves Alberta through Banff National Park.
On a sunny spring or fall day, one of the most scenic drives in the world is along the Icefield Parkway, which runs some 300 km between Jasper and Banff, with mountain ranges and glaciers on either side of its entire length.

Alberta is well-connected by air, with international airports at both Edmonton and Calgary.
Calgary's airport is the busier of the two, as it is a hub airport for all connecting international flights in and out of Alberta.
There are over 9 000 km of operating mainline railroad track, and many tourists see Alberta as they pass through on Canadian National Railways' ViaRail service.
.

Tourism is also important to Albertans.
Thousands of visitors come to Alberta each year just for Calgary's world-famous Stampede and for Edmonton's Klondike Days.
Edmonton, as the kicking-off point to the only Canadian route to the Yukon gold fields, and the only route which did not require gold-seekers to travel the exhausting and dangerous Chilkoot Pass, also has a history of early air service to the North.
Many of the first bush pilots, among them Wop May, flew out of Edmonton's Blatchford Field.</entry>
  <entry author_id="164876" end="47" start="32">As with any Canadian province, the Alberta government is highest authority in education, creating and regulating the school boards, public colleges, universities, and other education isntitutions.
The vast majority of of Alberta's schools are run by publicly funded school boards (each with its own district of authority).
The largest are English language Public school boards.
Alberta also has English Separate Catholic boards throughout the province, which serve a substantial minority of students.
There is one protestant school board in part of the province.
Where numbers warrant, there are francophone school boards (Public and Separate Catholic).
All five of these types of boards are fully publicly funded (without tuition) by local property taxes and provincial grants given on an equal per student basis by the province (with some adjustments).
The different types of school boards are a necessity under the Canadian constitution, which guarantees the francophones and Catholic communities both the right to their own schools, and the right to administer them.

Originally in Alberta, school boards had the power to levy property taxes within their respective districts.
However.
However, this meant districts with a low tax base were underfunded, so the province moved to a system that pools the education property tax, and distributes it based on student population and need.
The largest two universities in Alberta are the University of Calgary and Edmonton's University of Alberta.
There is also Athabasca University, which focusses on distance learning, and the the University of Lethbridge.
There are 15 colleges that receive direct public funding, along with two technical institutes.
Students may also receive government loans and grants while attending selected private instiutions.</entry>
  <entry author_id="952266" end="60" start="47">The most recent significant development in the governance of education in Alberta has been the emergence of francophone education authorities in response to the adoption of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms (1982).
There are five francophone authorities in Alberta.
In the south a public francophone authority and a separate francophone authority share co-terminous boundaries.
In the north there are three authorities which provide both public and separate school education.
The francophone authorities, together, cover the province, but they are not required to provide francophone education from place to place, except where numbers warrant, and it is the responsibility of the board of the authority to decide whether numbers warrant.

For many years the provincial government has funded the greater part of the cost of providing K - 12 education.
Prior to 1994 public and separate school boards in Alberta had the legislative authority to levy a local tax on property, as supplementary support for local education.
In 1994 the government of the province eliminated this right for public school boards, but not for separate school boards.
Since 1994 there has continued to be a tax on property in support of K - 12 education; the difference is that the mill rate is now set by the provincial government, the money is collected by the local municipal authority and remitted to the provincial government.
The provincial government pools the property tax funds from across the province and distributes them, according to a formula, to both public and separate school jurisdictions.

Since 1994 all boards with a civil electorate (public, separate, francophone) are funded almost entirely by the provincial government.
School boards may, and many do, allow the school administration to levy fees for books and special materials, special programs or services, etc.
Such fees range from $20.00/student/year (more or less) to $750.00/student/year.</entry>
</article>
