<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="751" title="Aikido" authors="4" lines="170">
  <entry author_id="84606" end="83" start="0">Aikido (合気道 Aikidō, also 合氣道 using an older style of kanji), literally meaning "harmony energy way", or with some poetic license, "way of the harmonious spirit") is a gendai budo — a modern Japanese martial art.
Practitioners of aikido are known as aikidoka.
It was developed by Morihei Ueshiba (植芝盛平) (also known by aikidoka as o-sensei (大先生)) over the period of the 1930s to the 1960s.
Technically, the major parts of aikido are derived from Daitō-ryū Aiki-jūjutsu (大東流合気柔術), a form of jujutsu with many joint techniques, and kenjutsu　(剣術), or Japanese sword technique.
Aikido is also considered to contain a significant spiritual component.
The name aikido is formed of three Japanese characters, 合気道, usually romanised as ai, ki and do.
These are often translated as meaning harmony, energy and way, so aikido can be translated as "the way of harmony through energy".
Another common interpretation of the characters is harmony, spirit and way, so aikido can also mean "the way of spiritual harmony".
Both interpretations draw attention to the fact that aikido's techniques are designed to control an attacker by controlling and redirecting their energy instead of blocking it.
An analogy is often made of the way a flexible willow bends with the storm whereas the stout oak will break if the wind blows too hard.
(The Korean martial art commonly known as hapkido uses the same three characters: some suggest a historical link through Daito Ryu, the main origin of aikido).

Morihei Ueshiba developed aikido mainly from Daito Ryu aikijutsu, incorporating training movements such as those for the yari (spear), jo (a short quarterstaff), and perhaps also juken (bayonet).
But arguably the strongest influence is that of the katana (sword).
In many ways, an aikido practitioner moves as an empty handed swordsman.
The aikido strikes shomenuchi and yokomenuchi originate from weapon attacks, and resultant techniques likewise from weapon take-aways.
Some schools of aikido do no weapons training at all, others, such as Iwama Ryu usually spend substantial time with bokken (wooden sword), jo, and tanto (knife).
In some lines of aikido, all techniques can be performed with a sword as well as unarmed.

Aikido was brought to the United Kingdom in 1955, United States in the 1960s, to Australia in 1965 and to many other countries.
Today there are many aikido dojos available to train at throughout the world.
Aikido incorporates a wide range of techniques which use principles of energy and motion to redirect, neutralize and control attackers.
Because aikido techniques allow practitioners to move considerably during their execution, as well as for other reasons, some believe aikido is particularly suited to multiple-attacker circumstances.
However, like all martial arts claims, this is debated.
At its highest level, aikido can be used to defend oneself without causing serious injury to either the aggressor or the defender.
If performed correctly, size and strength are not important for efficency in the techniques.
Aikido is considered one of the most difficult of the Japanese martial arts to gain proficiency in.
The methods of training vary from organization to organization and indeed even between different dojo in a single organization but typically, a class basically means that the teacher shows techniques or principles and the students imitate.
Training is done through mutual technique, not by sparring.
Uke, the receiver of the technique, usually initiates an attack against nage or tori, who neutralizes it with an aikido technique.
The uke and the nage have equally important roles.
Students must practice both positions in order to learn to defend against an attack and to safely receive the defense.
When o-sensei taught, all his students were uke until he deemed them knowledgeable enough of the technique to be nage.
Movement, awareness, precision and timing are all important to the execution of techniques as students progress from rigidly defined exercises to more fluid and adaptable applications.
Eventually, students take part in jiyu-waza and/or randori, where the attacks are less predictable.
Some schools, such as Shodokan Aikido, employ training methods wherein uke actively attempts to employ counter-techniques, or kaeshi-waza.

O-Sensei didn't allow competition in training because some techniques are considered too dangerous and because he believed that competition didn't develop good character in students.
Most styles of aikido continue this tradition although Shodokan Aikido (see ) started with competitions early on.
In the Ki Society there are also competitions held, in a small scale.
Aikido techniques are mostly based on keeping the attacker out of balance and locking joints.
Much of aikido's repertoire of defenses can be performed either as throwing techniques (nage-waza) or as controls (katame-waza), depending on the situation.
Entering, irimi, and turning, tenkan, are widely used Aikido concepts, as is striking, atemi, although this is mostly performed as distraction rather than to hurt.
Manipulation of uke's balance by entering is often referred to as "taking uke's center".
It is sometimes said that aikido contains only defense, and the attacks that are performed are not really aikido.
From a historical perspective this claim is questionable, but many if not most aikidoka have the defense techniques as the focus of their training.

Aikido attacks used in normal training include various stylized strikes and grabs such as shomenuchi (a vertical strike to the head), yokomenuchi (a lateral strike to the side of the head and/or neck), munetsuki (a straight punch), ryotedori (a two handed grab) or katadori (a shoulder grab).
Many of the -uchi strikes resemble blows from a sword or other weapon.
Kicks are sometimes used, but are not usually part of basic curricula.
Most aikido techniques can also be applied to a response to an attack, e.g. to a block, and some schools use this as the "basic" form of a given class of technique.
Beginners also tend to work with techniques executed in response to a grab.
Grabs are considered good for basic practice because the connection with uke is very clear and strong, and it is easier to "feel out" body mechanics and lines of force.

There is also the matter of atemi, or strikes employed during an aikido technique.
The role and importance of atemi is a matter of some debate in aikido.
Some view atemi as strikes to "vital points" that can be delivered during the course of a technique's application, to increase effectiveness.
Others consider atemi to be methods of distraction, particularly when aimed at the face.
For instance, if a movement would expose the aikido practitioner to a counter-blow, he or she may deliver a quick strike to distract the attacker or occupy the threatening limb.
Atemi can be interpreted as not only punches or kicks but also, for instance, striking with a shoulder or a large part of the arm.
Some throws are arguably effected through an unbalancing or abrupt application of atemi.
Many sayings about atemi are attributed to Morihei Ueshiba, although their precise content varies considerably based on the one doing the telling.
Weapons training in aikido usually consists of jo (staff) and bokken (sword) and/or tanto (knife).
Both weapons-taking and weapons-retention are sometimes taught, to integrate the armed and unarmed aspects of aikido.
For example, a technique done with a straight punch may be done with a tanto or jo thrust instead, or a grab technique may be illustrated as a way to draw/strike with a weapon while being grabbed.

Many schools, also others than those who are his students in lineage, train versions of Morihiro Saitos weapons system: aiki-jo and aiki-ken.
It contains solo kata with jo, and paired exercises with jo and bokken.
In other lines of aikido, paired training with bokken in kata derived from old sword schools is common.
Quite a few aikido teachers have also developped weapons systems on their own, such as Mitsugi Saotome's "two sword aikido."
The ending "do" in the word aikido indicates a spiritual path, unlike the ending "jitsu" in the word aikijujitsu, which indicates an art of war.
Many people see this difference as important as well as regarding iaijitsu and iaido, jujitsu and judo, and kenjutsu and kendo.
Others see this distinction as a historically incorrect and somewhat unnatural division.

Ueshiba taught that, while it was important to become proficient in physical technique, this is not the ultimate purpose of training.
He taught that the principles learned through training in physical technique are universal and are to be applied to all aspects of one's life.
He once commented that he was teaching students not how to move their feet but, rather, how to move their minds.

Many agree that Ueshiba's style became softer, more fluid, and effortless as he grew older.
Some suggest this was due to a shift in focus to the spiritual aspects of the art, while others suggest that this was simply a natural result of Ueshiba becoming more proficent in physical technique.
Various interpretations have arisen since Ueshiba's death.

A range of aikido schools can be found, each placing a different emphasis on physical techniques, underlying principles, and spirtual concepts.
This is largely a result of at what point the founder of each of these schools trained with Ueshiba--earlier or later in Ueshiba's life.
The former tend to focus more on physical technique, while the latter tend to focus more on spiritual concepts.
However, this should not be overstated, especially since there is considerable variance from sensei to sensei, and an "aikido continuum" is quite problematic to actually construct.

The major styles of aikido each have their own Hombu Dojo in Japan; these define their various syllabi.
The following is an incomplete list: Although Iwama Ryu no longer exists as an organisation, it is reasonable to mention it as a style since it was a large organisation for a few decades.
Technically Iwama Style is one of the many branches within the Aikikai, but by no means the most different one from the others.
It is sometimes said that in Japan the term aikidoka (合気道家) mainly refers to a professional while in the west, any one who practices may call themselves an aikidoka.
The Ueshiba family members: Other well-known Japanese aikidoka (in alphabetical order): Frequently Asked Questions list.
Much of the content was taken from the aikido-L mailing list.</entry>
  <entry author_id="884870" end="113" start="83">Aikido is not the art of fighting using brute strength or deadly weapons, or the use of physical power or deadly weapons to destroy one's enemies, but a way of harmonizing the world and unifying the human race as one family.
It is a path of service that works through the spirit of God's love and universal harmony by the fulfillment of each individual's respective role.
This way is the way of the universe; the training in Aiki is training in divine technique.
Begin to put this into practice, and the power of the universe will come forth and you will be in accord with the universe itself.

He also said: Aiki is love.
It is the path that brings our hearts into oneness with the spirit of the universe to complete our mission in life by instilling in us a love and reverence for all of nature.
Aiki overcomes self.
It not only takes hostility from our hearts but by transforming those who appear as enemies into enemies no more, it leads to absolute perfection of self.

There is no set form in Aikido.
There is no set form, it is the study of the spirit.
One must not get caught up in set form, because in doing so, one is unable to perform the function sensitively.
In Aikido, frist we begin with the cleansing of the ki of one's soul.
Following this, the rebuilding of one's spirit is essential.
Through the physical body, the performance of kata is that of haku (the lower self).
We study kon (the higher self/the spirit).
We must advance by harmoniously uniting the higher and lower selves.
The higher self must make use of the lower self.

All technique should be compoletely in accordance with the true principles of the universe.
Technique that is not performed in accordance with these principles will turn back upon one's self and lead to self-destruction.
This kind of martial technique cannot create a connection to the universe and thus is not the martial art of takemusu.
A martial art that connects us to the universe is also one that connects human beings on a horizontal level through the blessing of love.
Therefore, this marital art that connects us to the universe is takemusu no bu.

Perfoming technique in harmony and accordance with the principles of the universe is essential.
This is none other than fostering a sincere spirit.
Progress and advancement in budo training will fail to come if one ramains self-centered, relying ony on ego.
This kind of budo is misguided and will inevitably turn back upon one's self, bringing about misfortune.
Instead, one must form a sincere, harmonious connection with theh ki of the universe, not becoming caught up in the feeling of concern for immediate victory or defeat.
When feelings and intentions remain trapped in the physical body there can be no rebirth and no regeneration.
Things first come to life through harmonious union.
Through harmonious unification, feelings and intentions transform to divine power and all things become clear.</entry>
  <entry author_id="122683" end="137" start="113">An irimi (entering-body) style technique consists of movements inward towards uke, while tenkan (turning) style uses a pivoting motion.
Much of aikido's repertoire can also be performed either as throws (nage-waza) or as pins (katame-waza), depending on the situation.
Thus from less than 20 basic techniques, there are thousands of possible implementations.

Specific aikido kata are typically referred to with the formula "attack-technique(-modifier)".
For instance, katate-dori ikkyō refers to any ikkyō technique executed when uke is holding one wrist.
This could be further specified as katate-dori ikkyō omote(-waza), referring to any forward-moving ikkyō technique from that grab.
Atemi are strikes (or feints) employed during an aikido technique.
Some view atemi as attacks against "vital points" meant to cause damage in and of themselves.
For instance, Gozo Shioda, in his book Aikido Shugyo, describes using atemi in a brawl to quickly down a gang's leader.
Others consider atemi, especially to the face, to be methods of distraction meant to enable other techniques.
A strike, whether or not it is blocked, can startle the target and break his or her concentration.
The target may also become unbalanced in attempting to avoid the blow, for example by jerking the head back, which may allow for an easier throw.
Atemi can be used for defense: if a movement would expose nage to a counter-blow, he or she may deliver a quick strike to distract uke and occupy the threatening limb.

Many sayings about atemi are attributed to Morihei Ueshiba, who considered them an essential element of technique.
Although attacks aren't studied as thoroughly as in striking-based arts, honest attacks (a strong strike or an immobilizing grab) are needed to study correct and effective application of technique.
The uchi strikes of aikido are often said to resemble blows from a sword or other grasped object, which may suggest origins in techniques intended for armed combat.
Kicks are generally reserved for upper-level variations: reasons cited include that falls from kicks are especially dangerous, and that kicks (high kicks in particular) were uncommon during the types of combat prevalent in feudal Japan.Beginners in particular often practice techniques from grabs, both because they are safer and because it is easier to feel the energy and lines of force of a hold than a strike.
Some grabs are historically derived from attempts to pin a hand down so that a weapon could not be drawn; a technique could then be used to free the hand and/or immobilize the grabbing person.
The kata- (single-) prefixed forms are listed below.
The prefix ryo- indicates "both" instead; e.g., katate-dori (single-hand-grab) becomes ryotedori (both-hands-grab).
(Note: another kanji, 肩, also pronounced kata, means "shoulder", which may lead to some confusion.)
Common variants include mochi instead of dori.Ukemi (lit.
"receiving-body"), is a martial arts term for protective techniques, such as parries or safe falls.
One of the first skills taught to beginning students of aikido is how to land when thrown so as to avoid injury.
</entry>
  <entry author_id="2245683" end="156" start="137">"&lt;ref  Aikido, as envisioned by its founder, is not only the synthesis of the founder's martial training, but also the expression of his personal philosophy of universal peace and reconciliation.
Today, aikido continues its evolution from the koryū (old-style martial arts) in which the founder excelled, to a wide variety of expressions by martial artists throughout the world.
Aikido was created by Morihei Ueshiba (植芝 盛平 Ueshiba Morihei, 14 December 1883 – 26 April 1969), known today by aikido practitioners as Ōsensei ("Great Teacher").
Ueshiba developed aikido primarily during the late 1920s through the 1930s through the synthesis of the older martial arts that he had studied.
The core martial art from which aikido derives is Daitō-ryū aiki-jūjutsu, which Ueshiba studied directly with Takeda Sokaku (武田 惣角 Takeda Sōkaku, 1859 – 1943), who is known as the modern day revivor of that art.
Additionally, Ueshiba is known to have studied Tenjin Shin'yo-ryū with Tozawa Tokusaburō (戸沢 徳三郎, 1848 – 1912) in Tokyo in 1901, Gotōha Yagyu Shingan-ryū under Nakai Masakatsu (中井 正勝) in Sakai from 1903 to 1908, and judo with Kiyoichi Takagi (高木 喜代子 Takagi Kiyoichi, 1894 – 1972) in Tanabe in 1911.

It is generally accepted, however, that the art of Daitō-ryū is the primary technical influence upon aikido.
Along with empty-handed throwing and joint-locking techniques, Ueshiba incorporated training movements with weapons, such as those for the yari (spear), jō (a short quarterstaff), and perhaps also juken (bayonet).
However, the strongest influence is arguably that of kenjutsu, and in many ways, an aikido practitioner moves as an empty handed swordsman.
Today, some schools of aikido do not train with weapons at all; others, such as the so-called Iwama style of the late Morihiro Saito, usually spend substantial time with bokken (wooden katana), jō, and tantō (knife).

Ueshiba moved to Hokkaidō in 1912, and Ueshiba's studies under Takeda Sokaku can be documented as beginning as early as 1915.
His official association with Daitō-ryū continued until 1937.
However, during the latter part of that period, Ueshiba had already begun to distance himself from Takeda and the Daitō-ryū.
Also at this time, Ueshiba was referring to the martial art he was teaching as "Aiki Budō".
It is unclear when exactly Ueshiba began using the name "aikido", but aikido officially became the name of the art in 1942, when the Dai Nihon Butokukai (Great Japanese Martial Virtue Society) was engaged in a government sponsored reorganization and centralization of Japanese martial arts.

Significantly, one of the primary features of Ōmoto-kyō is its emphasis on the attainment of utopia during one's life.
This is the primary influence upon Ueshiba's martial philosophy of love and compassion, especially for those who seek to harm others.
Aikido demonstrates this philosophy in its emphasis upon mastering martial arts so that one may recieve an attack and harmlessly redirect it.
In an ideal resolution, not only is the reciever unharmed, but so is the attacker.</entry>
  <entry author_id="2245683" end="170" start="156">In aikido, as in virtually all Japanese martial arts, there are both physical and mental aspects of training, which are often dependant and interrelated.
The physical training in aikido is diverse, covering both general physical fitness and conditioning, as well as several specific areas.
Because a substantial portion of any aikido curriclae consists of throws, the first thing most students learn is how to safely fall or roll.
The specific techniques for attack include both strikes and grabs; the techniques for defense consist of throws and pins.
After basic techniques are learned, students study freestyle defense against multiple opponents, and in some styles, techniques with weapons.

, literally meaning "receiving-body", is the term used in aikido for protective techniques, such as parries or safe falls.
Aikido training is based primarily on pre-arranged forms (kata), practiced by two persons together rather than freestyle practice (randori).
The basic pattern is for the receiver of the technique (uke) to initiate an attack against the executor of the throw or pin (nage, also referred to as tori or shite depending on aikido style), who neutralises this attack with an aikido technique.

Many of the of aikido are often said to resemble blows from a sword or other grasped object, which may suggest origins in techniques intended for armed combat.
Other techniques which appear to explicitly be punches (tsuki), are also practiced as thrusts with a knife or sword.
Kicks are generally reserved for upper-level variations; reasons cited include that falls from kicks are especially dangerous, and that kicks (high kicks in particular) were uncommon during the types of combat prevalent in feudal Japan.
Some basic strikes include:Beginners in particular often practice techniques from grabs, both because they are safer and because it is easier to feel the energy and lines of force of a hold than a strike.

Common variants include mochi instead of dori.
The following are examples of some basic grabs: Some common techniques and their Aikikai terminology:  Weapons training in aikido traditionally includes wooden jō (short staff), bokken (wooden katana), and tantō (knife).

</entry>
</article>
