<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="798" title="Aries (constellation)" authors="1" lines="23">
  <entry author_id="4264700" end="11" start="0">Phrixos and Helle were the son and daughter of King Athamas and his first wife Nephele.
The king's second wife, Ino, was jealous and wished to kill his children.
To accomplish this, she induced a famine in Boeotia, then falsified a message from the Oracle of Delphi that said Phrixos must be sacrificed to end the famine.
Athamas was about to sacrifice his son atop Mount Laphystium when Aries, sent by Nephele, arrived.
Helle fell off of Aries's back in flight and drowned in the Dardanelles, also called the Hellespont in her honor.
After arriving, Phrixos sacrificed the ram to Zeus and gave the Fleece to Aeëtes of Colchis, who rewarded him with an engagement to his daughter Chalciope.
Aeëtes hung its skin in a sacred place where it became known as the Golden Fleece and was guarded by a dragon.

NGC 772 is a spiral galaxy with an integrated magnitude of 10, located southeast of β Arietis and 15 arcminutes west of 15 Arietis.
It is a relatively bright galaxy and shows obvious nebulosity and ellipticity in an amateur telescope.
It is 7.2 by 4.2 arcminutes, meaning that its surface brightness, magnitude 13.6, is significantly lower than its integrated magnitude.
NGC 772 is a class SA(s)b galaxy, which means that it is an unbarred spiral galaxy without a ring that possesses a somewhat prominent bulge and spiral arms that are wound somewhat tightly.</entry>
  <entry author_id="4264700" end="23" start="11">Teegarden's Star is the closest star to Earth in Aries.
It is a brown dwarf of magnitude 15.14 and spectral class M6.5V.
It has a proper motion of 5.1 arcseconds per year; it is the 24 closest star to Earth overall.

Two other unusual galaxies in Aries are Segue 2 and Arp 276.
Segue 2 is a dwarf galaxy that is a satellite galaxy of the Milky Way, recently discovered to be a potential relic of the epoch of reionization.
Arp 276 is the pair of interacting galaxies, consisting of NGC 935 and IC 1801.

Aries also contains several stars with extrasolar planets.
HIP 14810, a G5 type star, is orbited by three giant planets (those more than ten times the mass of Earth).
HD 12661 is also a G-type main sequence star, slightly larger than the Sun, with two orbiting planets.
One planet is 2.3 times the mass of Jupiter, and the other is 1.57 times the mass of Jupiter.
HD 20367 is a G0 type star, approximately the size of the Sun, with one orbiting planet.
The planet, discovered in 2002, has a mass 1.07 times that of Jupiter and orbits every 500 days.</entry>
</article>
