<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="800" title="Anime" authors="6" lines="284">
  <entry author_id="65897" end="70" start="0">Though filmmakers in Japan had been experimenting with animation beforehand, the first widely popular anime series was Osamu Tezuka's Astro Boy in 1963.
During the 1970s, anime developed further, separating itself from its Western roots, and developing unique genres such as mecha.
Notable shows in this period include Lupin III and Mazinger Z.

In the 1980s, anime found itself accepted in the mainstream in Japan, and experienced a boom in production.
The start of the Gundam franchise, and the beginnings of Rumiko Takahashi's career have their roots here.
Akira set records in 1988 for the production costs of an anime.

The 1990s and 2000s saw the increased acceptance of anime in overseas markets.
Cowboy Bebop was widely popular in Japan and attracted attention in the West.
Spirited Away shared the first prize at the 2002 Berlin Film Festival and won the Academy Award for Best Animated Feature in 2003, and was featured at the 2004 Cannes Film Festival.
Anime features a wide variety of genres and unique artistic styles which varies from artist to artist.
It can have as many genres as live action cinema, including adventure, science fiction, children's stories, romance, medieval fantasy, erotica (hentai), occult/horror, action.
Most anime includes a variety of thematic elements.
For example, it is not uncommon for strongly action-themed anime to involve humor, romance, and even poignant social commentary, and romance-themed anime may involve a strong action element.

Osamu Tezuka adapted and simplified many Disney animation precepts to reduce the budget and number of frames.
This was intended to be a temporary measure to allow him to produce one episode every week with inexperienced animation staff.
Anime studios have since perfected techniques to draw as little new animation as possible, using scrolling or repeating backgrounds, still shots of characters sliding across the screen, and dialogue which involves only animating the mouths while the rest of the screen remains absolutely still, a technique not wholly unfamiliar to Western animation.
The overall effect of these techniques—reduced frame rate, many still shots, scrolling backgrounds—has led some critics to accuse anime of choppiness or poor quality in general.
(See also limited animation.)

However, there are often scenes where the frame rate of the animation far exceeds the norm of the rest of the work.
These are commonly called "money shots", where more effort is put into the animation of one scene to give it emphasis over the rest of the work.
Animator Yasuo Otsuka was the pioneer of this technique.

Exceptions to these rules are big budget films, often from Studio Ghibli.
These movies have much higher production values, due to their anticipated success at the box office.
Some animators in Japan can overcome production values by using different techniques than Disney or the old Tezuka/Otsuka norms of anime.
Directors such as Hiroyuki Imaishi (RE: Cutey Honey, Dead Leaves) simplify backgrounds so that more attention can be paid to character animation.
Other animators like Tatsuyuki Tanaka (in Koji Morimoto's Eternal Family in particular) use squash and stretch, an animation technique not often used by Japanese animators; Tanaka makes other shortcuts to compensate for this.
Some higher-budgeted television and OVA series also forego shortcuts found in most other anime.

Anime has been available in the North America and Europe for some time.
Anime releases there are usually dubbed into the language of the country in which they are released.
Anime series are also sometimes edited by Western distributors to remove what they feel local audiences would consider to be objectionable content.
This is especially true with series that are marketed to children, such as the Yu-Gi-Oh!
anime (Yu-Gi-Oh!
Duel Monsters in Japan) produced by Nihon Ad Systems and Pokémon.
In other cases, editing is done to change content to make it easier for Western viewers to understand.
Some anime enthusiasts object to one or both forms of editing.
Those viewers often watch anime titles in DVD format, because DVD releases are typically unedited and often include both the dubbed audio and the original Japanese audio with subtitles.
Another advantage of DVD releases is that there are no commercials, unlike in television releases.
Although it is a violation of copyright laws in most countries, some fans also watch fansubs, recordings of anime series that have been subtitled by fans.
The ethical implications of producing, distributing, or watching fansubs is a topic of much controversy.
See fansub for further discussion of those ethical issues.

Mainstream anime is often very stylized.
Because of this stylization certain features or concepts have become so common that they have been given names of their own.
Often in comedic anime, characters that are shocked or surprised will perform a "face fault", in which they take an extremely exaggerated expression.
Angry characters may exhibit a "vein" effect, where four lines vaguely in the shape of a pair of crossed veins will appear on their forehead.
Angry women will sometimes summon a mallet from nowhere and strike someone with it, leading to the concept of Hammerspace.
Embarrassed characters will invariably produce a massive sweat-drop, which has become something of a stereotype of anime.

More auteuristic schools of anime don't use such shorthands or find different but similar ways to express the same thing.
FLCL is known for more wild exaggerated stylized emotions than in most mainstream works.
In contrast an Isao Takahata film like Only Yesterday takes a much more realistic approach emphasizing realism over stylization.

Another unique aspect of anime not found in other commercial animation markets is the lack of a directoral system.
In most animation produced around the world animators are all forced to conform to a set style by the director or animation director.
In Japan starting with the animation director Yoshinori Kanada (as a means to save time and money) each animator brings his/her own style to the work.
The most extreme examples of this can be found in Mindgame or The Hakkenden.
The Hakkenden is particularly extreme showing constanly shifting styles of animation based upon the key animator that worked on that particular episode.
This approach combined with Otsuka's "money shots" make key animators important individuals in the style and production of an anime film.

Many non-Japanese cartoons are starting to incorporate mainstream anime shortcuts and symbols as a result of the tremendous growth of the form.
The following section is devoted to those artists who made an impact through direct contributions to anime as opposed to other artists who were in manga and other fields that had an impact on the development of Japanese animation.
The work of prominent manga (Japanese comics) artists often has an impact of anime, even when they are not themselves directly involved in anime.
Most anime can be categorized as one of three types: It is very common for one title to spawn several different releases.
A title that starts as a popular television series might then have a movie produced at a later date.
A good example is Tenchi Muyo—originally an OVA, Tenchi Muyo!
spawned three movies, three television series, and several spinoff titles and specials.

Other types of releases include compilation movies, which are television episodes edited together and presented in theaters for various reasons, and are hence a concentrated form of a television serial.
It may, however, be longer than the average movie.
The reverse, an anticompilation movie, is simply an exploitation of the characters.
These are of lower quality and of shorter length than a feature film.
Shōjo anime is intended for girls.
Most anime is assumed to be shōnen, intended for boys, so it is usually not necessary to label it.
While seinen (intended for men) and josei (intended for women) anime does exist, anime that fall specifically and exclusively into those genres is rare.
The only one of these terms in common use is shōjo.</entry>
  <entry author_id="91658" end="168" start="70">Anime (アニメ) is Japanese animation, sometimes billed in the west under the portmanteau Japanimation.
It is often characterized by stylized colorful images depicting vibrant characters in a variety of different settings and storylines, aimed at a variety of different audiences.
Anime is influenced by the drawing style of manga, or Japanese comics.
The Japanese term for animation is アニメーション (animēshon, pronounced: ), written in katakana.
It is a direct transliteration of the English term "animation."
The Japanese term is abbreviated as アニメ (anime, pronounced: ).
Both the original and abbreviated forms are valid and interchangeable in Japanese.
The term is a broad one, and does not specify a animation's nation of origin or style.

In turn, the English word anime is a transliteration of the abbreviated version of this Japanese term, and it is typically pronounced as.
As with a few other Japanese words such as Pokémon and Kobo Abé, anime is sometimes spelled as animé in English with an acute accent over the final e to cue the reader that the letter is pronounced as.
For example, "Abé" can be mistaken as a nickname for Abraham without the accent, which wouldn't pronounce the last letter.

Internationally, anime once bore the popular name Japanimation, but this term has fallen into disuse.
It saw the most usage during the 1970s and 1980s, which broadly comprise the first and second waves of anime fandom.
The term survived at least into the early 1990s but seemed to fade away shortly before the mid-1990s anime resurgence.
In general, the term now only appears in nostalgic contexts.
The term Japanimation is much more commonly used in Japan to refer to domestic animation.
Since anime or animeshon is used in Japan to describe all forms of animation regardless of national origin, Japanimation is meant to distinguish Japanese work from that of the rest of the world.

In more recent years, anime has also frequently been referred to as manga in Europe, a practice that may stem from the Japanese usage.
In Japan, manga refers to both animation and comics.
Among English speakers, manga usually has the stricter meaning of "Japanese comics".
An alternate explanation is that it is due to the prominence of Manga Entertainment, a distibutor of anime to the US and UK markets.
This term is much more common in Europe since Manga Entertainment started out in the UK.

The voice actors for anime usually bear the Japanese equivalent designation, seiyū.
Though filmmakers in Japan had been experimenting with animation beforehand, the first widely popular anime series was Osamu Tezuka's Astro Boy in 1963.
During the 1970s, anime developed further, separating itself from its Western roots, and developing unique genres such as giant robots (popularly known among English-speaking fans as mecha).
Notable shows in this period include Lupin III and Mazinger Z.

In the 1980s, anime found itself accepted in the mainstream in Japan, and experienced a boom in production.
The start of the Gundam franchise, and the beginnings of Rumiko Takahashi's career have their roots here.
Akira set records in 1988 for the production costs of an anime.

The 1990s and 2000s saw the increased acceptance of anime in overseas markets.
Cowboy Bebop was widely popular in Japan and attracted attention in the West.
Spirited Away shared the first prize at the 2002 Berlin Film Festival and won the Academy Award for Best Animated Feature in 2003, and was featured at the 2004 Cannes Film Festival.
Anime features a wide variety of genres and unique artistic styles which varies from artist to artist.
It can have as many genres as live action cinema, including adventure, science fiction, children's stories, romance, medieval fantasy, erotica (hentai), occult/horror, action.
Most anime includes a variety of thematic elements.
For example, it is not uncommon for strongly action-themed anime to involve humor, romance, and even poignant social commentary, and romance-themed anime may involve a strong action element.

Osamu Tezuka adapted and simplified many Disney animation precepts to reduce the budget and number of frames.
This was intended to be a temporary measure to allow him to produce one episode every week with inexperienced animation staff.
Anime studios have since perfected techniques to draw as little new animation as possible, using scrolling or repeating backgrounds, still shots of characters sliding across the screen, and dialogue which involves only animating the mouths while the rest of the screen remains absolutely still, a technique not wholly unfamiliar to Western animation.
The overall effect of these techniques—reduced frame rate, many still shots, scrolling backgrounds—has led some critics to accuse anime of choppiness or poor quality in general.
(See also limited animation.)

However, there are often scenes where the frame rate of the animation far exceeds the norm of the rest of the work.
These are commonly called "money shots" outside Japan, where more effort is put into the animation of one scene to give it emphasis over the rest of the work.
Animator Yasuo Otsuka was the pioneer of this technique.

Exceptions to these rules are big budget films, such as those produced by the enormously successful Studio Ghibli.
These movies have much higher production values, due to their anticipated success at the box office.
Some animators in Japan can overcome production values by utilizing different techniques than Disney or the old Tezuka/Otsuka norms of anime.
Directors such as Hiroyuki Imaishi (RE: Cutey Honey, Dead Leaves) simplify backgrounds so that more attention can be paid to character animation.
Other animators like Tatsuyuki Tanaka (in Koji Morimoto's Eternal Family in particular) use squash and stretch, an animation technique not often used by Japanese animators; Tanaka makes other shortcuts to compensate for this.
Some higher-budgeted television and OVA series (Original Video Animation) also forego shortcuts found in most other anime.

Anime has been available in the North America and Europe for some time.
Anime releases there are usually dubbed into the language of the country in which they are released.
Anime series are also sometimes edited by Western distributors to remove what they feel local audiences would consider to be objectionable content.
This is especially true with series that are marketed to children, such as the Yu-Gi-Oh!
anime (Yu-Gi-Oh!
Duel Monsters in Japan) produced by Nihon Ad Systems and Pokémon.
In other cases, editing is done to change content to make it easier for Western viewers to understand.
Some anime enthusiasts object to one or both forms of editing.
Those viewers often watch anime titles in DVD format, because DVD releases are typically unedited and often include both the dubbed audio and the original Japanese audio with subtitles.
Another advantage of DVD releases is that there are no commercials, unlike in television releases.
Although it is a violation of copyright laws in most countries, some fans also watch fansubs, recordings of anime series that have been subtitled by fans.
The ethical implications of producing, distributing, or watching fansubs is a topic of much controversy.
See fansub for further discussion of those ethical issues.

Mainstream anime is often very stylized.
Because of this stylization certain features or concepts have become so common that they have been given names of their own.
Often in comedic anime, characters that are shocked or surprised will perform a "face fault", in which they take an extremely exaggerated expression.
Angry characters may exhibit a "vein" or "stressmark" effect, where four lines representing stylized bulging veins will appear on their forehead.
Angry women will sometimes summon a mallet from nowhere and strike someone with it, leading to the concept of Hammerspace.
Embarrassed characters will invariably produce a massive sweat-drop, which has become something of a stereotype of anime.

More auteuristic schools of anime don't use such shorthands or find different but similar ways to express the same thing.
FLCL is known for more wild exaggerated stylized emotions than in most mainstream works.
In contrast an Isao Takahata film like Only Yesterday takes a much more realistic approach emphasizing realism over stylization.

Another unique aspect of anime not found in other commercial animation markets is the lack of a directoral system.
In most animation produced around the world animators are all forced to conform to a set style by the director or animation director.
In Japan starting with the animation director Yoshinori Kanada (as a means to save time and money) each animator brings his/her own style to the work.
The most extreme examples of this can be found in Mindgame or The Hakkenden.
The Hakkenden is particularly extreme showing constanly shifting styles of animation based upon the key animator that worked on that particular episode.
This approach combined with Otsuka's "money shots" make key animators important individuals in the style and production of an anime film.

Many non-Japanese cartoons are starting to incorporate mainstream anime shortcuts and symbols as a result of the tremendous growth of the art form.
Large, saucer-like eyes are a striking and common feature of anime characters.
This is mainly due to the influence of Osamu Tezuka, who was inspired by the exaggerated features of Western cartoon characters such as Betty Boop and Mickey Mouse and from Disney's Bambi.
Tezuka found that large eyes allowed his characters to better express their emotions.
Some Western audiences have interpreted such stylized eyes as more Caucasian, but Japanese animators and audiences do not perceive them as being inherently more or less foreign.
Kyoto Seika University associate professor and translator Matt Thorn examines these perceptions as an anthropological issue in The Face of the Other essay.

When he began drawing Ribbon No Kishi, the first manga specifically targeted at young girls, Tezuka further exaggerated the size of the characters' eyes.
Indeed, through Ribbon No Kishi, Tezuka set a stylistic template that later shōjo artists tended to follow.
Most anime can be categorized as one of three types: It is very common for one title to spawn several different releases.
A title that starts as a popular television series might then have a movie produced at a later date.
A good example is Tenchi Muyo—originally an OVA, Tenchi Muyo!
spawned three movies, three television series, and several spinoff titles and specials.
Shōjo anime is intended for girls.
Most anime is assumed to be shōnen, intended for boys, so it is usually not necessary to label it.
While seinen (intended for men) and josei (intended for women) anime does exist, anime that fall specifically and exclusively into those genres is rare.
The only one of these terms in common use is shōjo.
The following are genres and designations that are specific to anime and manga.
(For other possible genres, see list of movie genres.)
The following section is devoted to those artists who made an impact through direct contributions to anime as opposed to other artists who were in manga and other fields that had an impact on the development of Japanese animation.
The work of prominent manga (Japanese comics) artists often has an impact on anime, even when they are not themselves directly involved in anime.</entry>
  <entry author_id="316173" end="188" start="168">The Japanese term for animation is アニメーション (animēshon, pronounced: ), written in katakana.
It is a direct transliteration of the English term "animation."
The Japanese term is abbreviated as アニメ (anime, pronounced: ).
Both the original and abbreviated forms are valid and interchangeable in Japanese.
The term is a broad one, and does not specify a animation's nation of origin or style.

In turn, the English word anime is a transliteration of the abbreviated version of this Japanese term, and it is typically pronounced as.
Some non-Japanese speakers theorize the word comes from the French animé ("animated") or "les dessins animés" (animated drawings.)
As with a few other Japanese words such as Pokémon and Kobo Abé, anime is sometimes spelled as animé in English with an acute accent over the final e to cue the reader that the letter is pronounced as.
For example, "Abé" can be mistaken as a nickname for Abraham without the accent, which wouldn't pronounce the last letter.

Internationally, anime once bore the popular name Japanimation, but this term has fallen into disuse.
It saw the most usage during the 1970s and 1980s, which broadly comprise the first and second waves of anime fandom.
The term survived at least into the early 1990s but seemed to fade away shortly before the mid-1990s anime resurgence.
In general, the term now only appears in nostalgic contexts.
The term Japanimation is much more commonly used in Japan to refer to domestic animation.
Since anime or animeshon is used in Japan to describe all forms of animation regardless of national origin, Japanimation is meant to distinguish Japanese work from that of the rest of the world.

In more recent years, anime has also frequently been referred to as manga in Europe, a practice that may stem from the Japanese usage.
In Japan, manga refers to both animation and comics.
Among English speakers, manga usually has the stricter meaning of "Japanese comics".
An alternate explanation is that it is due to the prominence of Manga Entertainment, a distibutor of anime to the US and UK markets.
This term is much more common in Europe since Manga Entertainment started out in the UK.</entry>
  <entry author_id="618727" end="232" start="188">Osamu Tezuka adapted and simplified many Disney animation precepts to reduce the budget and number of frames, though it should be noted that Disney films are not anime.
This was intended to be a temporary measure to allow him to produce one episode every week with inexperienced animation staff.
Anime studios have since perfected techniques to draw as little new animation as possible, using scrolling or repeating backgrounds, still shots of characters sliding across the screen, and dialogue which involves only animating the mouths while the rest of the screen remains absolutely still, a technique not wholly unfamiliar to Western animation.
The overall effect of these techniques—reduced frame rate, many still shots, scrolling backgrounds—has led some critics to accuse anime of choppiness or poor quality in general.
(See also limited animation.)

However, there are often scenes where the frame rate of the animation far exceeds the norm of the rest of the work.
These are commonly called "money shots" outside Japan, where more effort is put into the animation of one scene to give it emphasis over the rest of the work.
Animator Yasuo Otsuka was the pioneer of this technique.

Exceptions to these rules are early classic films, such as those produced by Toei Animation up to the mid 1960s, and recent big budget films, such as those produced by the enormously successful Studio Ghibli.
These movies have much higher production values, due to their anticipated success at the box office.
Some animators in Japan can overcome production values by utilizing different techniques than Disney or the old Tezuka/Otsuka norms of anime.
Directors such as Hiroyuki Imaishi (RE: Cutey Honey, Dead Leaves) simplify backgrounds so that more attention can be paid to character animation.
Other animators like Tatsuyuki Tanaka (in Koji Morimoto's Eternal Family in particular) use squash and stretch, an animation technique not often used by Japanese animators; Tanaka makes other shortcuts to compensate for this.
Some higher-budgeted television and OVA (Original Video Animation) series also forego shortcuts found in most other anime.

Mainstream anime is often very stylized.
Because of this stylization certain features or concepts have become so common that they have been given names of their own.
Often in comedic anime, characters that are shocked or surprised will perform a "face fault", in which they take an extremely exaggerated expression.
Angry characters may exhibit a "vein" or "stressmark" effect, where four lines representing stylized bulging veins will appear on their forehead.
Angry women will sometimes summon a mallet from nowhere and strike someone with it, leading to the concept of Hammerspace.
Male characters will develop an inexplicable bloody nose around their female love interests (typically to indicate arousal).
Embarrassed characters will invariably produce a massive sweat-drop, which has become something of a stereotype of anime.

More auteuristic schools of anime don't use such shorthands or find different but similar ways to express the same thing.
FLCL (pronounced "Furi Kuri" and sometimes called "Fooly Cooly") is known for more wild exaggerated stylized emotions than in most mainstream works.
In contrast an Isao Takahata film like Only Yesterday takes a much more realistic approach emphasizing realism over stylization.

Another unique aspect of anime not found in other commercial animation markets is the lack of a directoral system.
In most animation produced around the world animators are all forced to conform to a set style by the director or animation director.
In Japan starting with the animation director Yoshinori Kanada (as a means to save time and money) each animator brings his/her own style to the work.
The most extreme examples of this can be found in Mindgame or The Hakkenden.
The Hakkenden is particularly extreme showing constantly shifting styles of animation based upon the key animator that worked on that particular episode.
This approach combined with Otsuka's "money shots" make key animators important individuals in the style and production of an anime film.

Many non-Japanese cartoons are starting to incorporate mainstream anime shortcuts and symbols to appeal to anime's tremendously growing fanbase and cut costs.
Large, saucer-like eyes are a striking and common feature of anime characters.
This is mainly due to the influence of Osamu Tezuka, who was inspired by the exaggerated features of Western cartoon characters such as Betty Boop and Mickey Mouse and from Disney's Bambi.
Tezuka found that large eyes allowed his characters to better express their emotions.
Some Western audiences have interpreted such stylized eyes as more Caucasian.
Cultural anthropologist Matt Thorn argues that Japanese animators and audiences do not perceive them as inherently more or less foreign.

Anime is available outside of Japan in localized form, referred to as licensed anime or Dubs.
Licensed anime is modified by western distributors through dubbing into the language of the country.
The anime may also be edited to alter cultural references that may not be understood by a non-Japanese person and companies may remove what may be perceived as objectionable content.
For the fans who may object to the editing and dubbing anime titles in released in DVD format may be preferred to watch.
DVD releases often include both the dubbed audio and the original Japanese audio with subtitles, are typically unedited and lack commercials.
Although it is a violation of copyright laws in many countries, some fans watch fansubs, recordings of anime series that have been subtitled by fans.
Watching subtitled Japanese versions is usually seen as the intended method of watching anime by enthusiasts.
The ethical implications of producing, distributing, or watching fansubs is a topic of much controversy even when fansub groups do not profit from and cease distribution of their work once the series has been licensed.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1100073" end="251" start="232">Anime ABC’S  A is for Angel sanctuary, Apple seed, Angelic layer, Azumangel Diaoh, Ai Yori Aoshi, Akira, Avatar: the Last Airbender, Ah!
My Goddess,  B is for Bust Angel, Blood lust, Blood the last vampire, Blood reign, Berserk,  Boogiepop phantom, Battle Vixens, Big-O, Blue Submarine No.6, Battle Angel Alita.
C is for Chobits, Cowboy bebop, clamp, case closed, Card captor sakura, Cutie Honey, Cyborg009, Chrono Crusader.
D is for DNA2, DNAngel, Dragon ball, Dragon ball Z, Dragon Ball GT, Dragon ball AF, Dot haukers, Dark side Blues, Dirty Pair, Desert Coral, Darkstalkers.
E is for Evangelian, Excel Saga, Ebichu housekeeping hamster, Elfen Lied, Escaflowne.
F is for Fruits Basket, Full metal alchemist, Fushigi Yuugi, FLCL.
G is for Gundam, Graduation, Gankutu Ou, Gunskn, Ghost in the Shell, Getbackers  H is for.Hack//sign,.hack//g.u, Hi kuru no go, Hunter- Hunter, Heavy Metal, Hamtaro, Hellsing.
I is for Inuyasha, Infinity Rybausu, I, My, ME Strawberry eggs, Initial D. J is for JoJo.
K is for KITE, Kakkaishi, King of Band Jin, Kenshin, Kikaider, Knights of Ramunes.
L is for Lupin the 3rd, Lain, Love Hina, lovely Idol, Lum.
M is for Macross Pluss, Mahoromalic, Mi yuki Chan, Mermaid Scar, Mad Bull 34, Mezzo, Mobile Suit Gundam.
N is for Naruto, Noir, Ninja Scroll, Nesima.
O is for One Peace, Onegai sensei, Oleami, Oudoro Boujin, Out Law Star.
P is for Please Teacher, PatLabor, Pilot Candidate, Paranoia Agent, Panyo Panyo Digi Chart, Princess Moninoke, Preteal, Peach, Puni Puni, Poemy, Per Shop of Horrors, Pita Ten.
Q is for Queen Emeraldas R is for Real Bout High School, Ridins Bean, Ranima ½, Rave Master RAZEFON, R.O.D,  S is for Samurai Deeper, Scraped Princess, Slayers, Scocerer Hunters, Skull Man, Spike, Samurai X, Saiyuki, Sailor Moon, Samurai Champloo, S-Cry-ed, Serial Experiments Lain.
T is for Trigun, Taro Café, Tenchi, Tsubasa, Twin Signal.
U is for Utaka  V is for Vampire Hunter D, Vampire Wars, Vampire Princess Miyu.
W is for Wild Arms, Weiss Kreuz, Weiss Kreuz: Gluhen, Wolfs Reign, Witch Hunter Robin.
X is for X. Y is for Yu-gi-oh Z is for Zatch Bell, Z.O.E, Zoids.</entry>
  <entry author_id="946166" end="284" start="251">Anime, probably the most disgusting waste of time ever, was developed in the laboratories of the Japanese Self-Defense Force in 1952 B.C., just after the end of the American Occupation.
Professor Hayao Miyazaki of Tokyo University, still angry over Japan's loss in World War II, developed a secret plan to erode away the culture of all world nations and replace it with a culture devoted to specially formulated cartoons that were mainly erotic pulp, but more importantly Japanese.
By doing this, over a period of 100 years, Japan would eventually command the world by being the only remaining source of television and pornography.

So far the project has been running smoothly.
Severe cases of anime fanaticism can actually alter facial features.
Note the victim's self-satisfaction, having tricked herself into thinking she's part of a subculture.
Enlarge Severe cases of anime fanaticism can actually alter facial features.
Note the victim's self-satisfaction, having tricked herself into thinking she's part of a subculture.

Anime originally started (and still is) a new religion all over the planet which is expected to supplant the Pope and instaurate a new ruler of our Pizza World.
The ruler's name is Goku, a monkey god who flies over clouds, emits multi-colored lights from his hands, lectures villians for 26 minutes before attacking them, and doesn't take drugs.
His bastard son is Naruto, who will populate the world with Naruto-looking people.

Aside from its theological implications, anime is a popular masturbatory aid for Japanese males of all ages, and has now become a worldwide and non-respectable art form.
Most popular films usually involve tentacle rape monsters chasing a myriad of impossibly proportioned schoolgirls.
These chases invariably involve the schoolgirls tight white cotton panties being ripped off by the monsters.
Throw in some philosophy, incest, large eyes, giant robots, dragons, giant robot dragons - and you're guaranteed to have a hit.
It is also a piece of shit.

After being pirated on some random podunk Japaneese trawler heading to America, the disease known as "Wapanobesity", where white kids that think they are asian and execessively consume Japaneese products, quickly spread through out America, often zombifying many kids ever.
Kids were delivered sublimenal messaging through "popular children's shows" like Pokemon, Digimon, etc. and were told to launch a revolution, where these "anime zealots" would attempt to poorly diss everyone else and conquer the world.
The messaging lost its effect in many children, but in others however, It stuck with them and encouraged them to be come increasingly consumeristic and dependant on Japan.
Many believe this plan was created by some of the popular distributers of "Japanimation" related products to rapidly increase thier market, in essence a psuedo-imperialist movement by private corperations.
The movement hasn't been as sucessful in Europe, but it threatens to take hold in most of Europe and the other areas of the world as well.

Though originally drawn and animated by hand, most modern anime is generated automatically by computer programs with little or no human intervention.
Typically, the anime creation process begins with the title, ufacturorswhich is generated by a random number algorithm that selects several words that have absolutely nothing to do with each other and make no sense when put together (e.g.
Neon Genesis Evangelion, Cowboy Bebop, Full Metal Alchemist, Mobile Suit Gundam, Toaster Fedora Hologram, and, of course, Bleach).
A screenwriting program then generates a storyline that has nothing to do with the title or with any of the words in it.

Male anime characters must have the intellectual properties of a foot stool, and females must be very, very, very whiny and irritating to the point of causing dogs to howl and humans to develop brain tumors.
Specialized drawing and animation programs add "artwork" to the story, featuring hair colors not found in nature and large, glistening, creepy eyes the size of dinner plates.
These elements are required by law, as competing artistic styles were outlawed by the Japanese government in 1977.

Lastly, a sophisticated pedophilia program adjusts the depravity level of the production to conform to industry standard requirements for sexual perversity.
This should not be confused with child porn, which is exactly the same thing only slightly cheaper.
Anime that is exported to Western countries goes through an additional production step, wherein the voices are dubbed by English-speaking actors who undergo a rigorous screening process designed to weed out all but the most horrendously untalented voiceover "artists."
Hitlerbear enjoying anime.
Enlarge Hitlerbear enjoying anime.</entry>
</article>
