<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="802" title="Ankara" authors="4" lines="232">
  <entry author_id="123239" end="35" start="0">Anıtkabir: Located on an imposing hill in the Anittepe quarter of the city stands the mausoleum of Kemal Ataturk, founder of the Republic of Turkey.
Completed in 1953, it is an impressive fusion of ancient and modern architecture.
An adjacent museum houses a superior wax statue of Ataturk, his writings, letters and personal items, as well as an exhibition of photographs recording important moments in his life and in the establishment of the Republic (Anitkabir is open everyday, and the adjacent museum every day except Mondays).

The War of Independence Museum (Kurtuluş Savaşı Müzesi): In Ulus Square, is what was originally the first parliament building of the Republic of Turkey.
There the War of Independence was planned and directed here as recorded in various photographs and items presently on exhibition.
In another display, wax figures of former presidents of the Republic of Turkey are on exhibit.

Ankara Castle: The foundations of the castle were laid by the Galatians on a prominent lava outcrop, and the rest was completed by the Romans.
The Byzantines and Seljuks further made restorations and additions.
The area around and inside the castle, being the oldest part of Ankara, contains many fine examples of traditional architecture.
There are also recreational areas to relax.
Many restored traditional Turkish houses inside the castle area have found new life as restaurants, serving local cuisine, music and of course, Raki.

Roman Theatre: The remains, the stage, and the backstage, can be seen outside the castle.
Roman statues that were found here are exhibited in the Museum of Anatolian Civilizations (see above).
The seating area is still under excavation.

Temple of Augustus: It was built by the Galatian King Pylamenes in AD 10 as a tribute and sign of fidelity to Augustus, and was reconstructed by the Romans on the ancient Ankara Acropolis in the 2nd century.
It is important for the "Monument Ancyranum", the sole surviving political testament of Augustus, detailing his achievements inscribed on its walls in Latin and Greek.
In the fifth century the temple was converted into a church by the Byzantines.The temple is in the Ulus quarter of the city.

Roman Bath: This bath has all the typical features of a classical Roman bath: a frigidarium (cold room), tepidarium (cool room) and caldarium (hot room).
The bath was built in the reign of Emperor Caracalla in 3rd century AD to honour the Asclepios, the God of Medicine.
Today only the basement and first floors remain.
Situated in Ulus quarter.

Column of Julian: This column, in Ulus, was erected in 362 A.D., to commemorate a visit by the Roman Emperor Julian the Apostate.
It stands fifteen meters high and has a typical leaf decoration on the capital.
Monument to a Secure, Confident Future: This monument, in Güven Park, Bakanlıklar quarter, was erected in 1935 and bears Ataturk's advice to his people: "Turk!
Be proud, work hard, and believe in yourself."

Hatti Monument: Built in the 1970's in Sıhhiye Square, this impressive monument symbolizes the Hatti gods and commemorates Anatolia's earliest known civilization.
Kocatepe Mosque: It is a 20th century mosque of great proportions conceived in classical Ottoman design with four minarets.
The mosque is built between 1967 and 1987 in the Kocatepe quarter, and its size and prominent situation have made it a landmark that can be seen from most anywhere in central Ankara.

Atatürk Farm and Zoo (Atatürk Orman Çiftliği, AOÇ) is an expansive recreational farming area housing a Zoo, several small agricultural farms, greenhouses, restaurants, a dairy farm and a brewery.
It is very a pleasant place to spend a day with family, be it for picnics, hiking, biking or simply enjoying good food and nature.
There is also an exact replica of the house where Ataturk was born in 1881, in Thessaloniki, Greece.
Visitors to the "Çiftlik" (farm) as it is affectionately called by Ankarans, can sample such famous products of the farm as its excellent old-fashioned beer and ice cream, fresh dairy products and meat rolls/kebaps made on charcoal, through an excellent traditional restaurant (Merkez Lokantasi, Central Restaurant), cafés and other establishments scattered in the farm.

Foreign visitors to Ankara usually like to visit the old shops in Çıkrıkçılar Yokuşu (Weavers' road) near Ulus, where a myriad of things ranging from traditional fabrics, hand-woven carpets and leather products can be found for bargain prices.
Bakırcılar Çarşısı (Bazaar of coppersmiths) is particularly popular, and many interesting items, not just of copper, can be found here...like jewelry, carpets, costumes, antiques and embroidery.
Walking up the hill to the castle gate, you find many shops selling a huge and fresh collection of spices, dried fruits, nuts, and other produce.</entry>
  <entry author_id="123239" end="86" start="35">Ankara is the capital of Turkey and the country's second largest city after Istanbul.
It is also the capital of Ankara Province.
The city has a population of 3,582,000 (2003), and a mean elevation of 850 m. ( 2800 ft.) It was formerly known as Angora or Engürü, and in the classical period, as Ancyra.

Centrally located in Anatolia, Ankara is an important commercial and industrial city, has been the neural center of Turkish Government, and houses all the foreign embassies.
It is an important crossroads of trade, strategically located at the center of Turkey's highway and rail network, and serves as the marketing center for the surrounding agricultural area.
The city was famous for its long-haired goat and its wool (Angora wool), a unique breed of cat (Ankara Cat), white rabbits, pear, honey, and the region's muscat grapes

Ankara is situated upon a steep and rocky hill, which rises 500 ft. above the plain on the left bank of the Enguri Su, a tributary of the Sakarya (Sangarius) river.
The hill is crowned by the ruins of the old castle, which add to the picturesqueness of the view; but the town was not well built, many of its houses constructed of sun-dried mud bricks and the streets are narrow.
There are, however, many fine remains of Greek, Roman and Byzantine architecture, the most remarkable being the temple of Augustus, on the walls of which is the famous Monumentum Ancyranum

It is home to the Middle East Technical University (METU), Hacettepe University, Ankara University, Gazi Üniversitesi, Bilkent University, among others.
The National Library, the Archaeological Museum and the Ethnographical Museum are located in Ankara, and the city is home to the state theater and the Presidential Philharmonic Orchestra.
Anıtkabir, the mausoleum of Kemal Atatürk, one of the most important figures in twentieth century history, is also located in Ankara.

After Ankara became the capital of Turkey, new development has divided the city into an old section, called Ulus, and new section, called Yenişehir.
Ancient buildings reflecting Roman, Byzantine, and Ottoman history and narrow winding streets mark the old section.
The new section has the trappings of a more modern city: wide streets, hotels, theaters, shopping malls, and high-rises.
Government offices and foreign embassies are also located in the new section.
The region's vibrant history goes back to the Bronze Age Hatti civilization, which was succeeded in the 2nd millennium BC by the Hittites, in the 10th century BC by the Phrygians, then by the Lydians and Persians.
After these came the Galatians, a Gaulish race who were the first to make Ankara their capital in the 3rd century BC.
It was then known as Ancyra, meaning "anchor," one of the oldest words in the language of the sea-loving Gauls.
The city subsequently fell to the Romans, and to the Byzantines.
Seljuk Sultan Alparslan opened the door into Anatolia for the Turks at the victory of Malazgirt in 1071.
Then in 1073, he annexed Ankara, an important location for military transportation and natural resources, to Turkish territory.

At the close of World War I, Turkey was under control of the Ottoman sultan and was being invaded by Greek forces.
The leader of the Turkish nationalists, Kemal Atatürk established the headquarters of his resistance movement in Ankara in 1919 (See Turkish War of Independence).

Ankara Castle: The foundations of the castle were laid by the Galatians on a prominent lava outcrop, and the rest was completed by the Romans.
The Byzantines and Seljuks further made restorations and additions.
The area around and inside the castle, being the oldest part of Ankara, contains many fine examples of traditional architecture.
There are also recreational areas to relax.
Many restored traditional Turkish houses inside the castle area have found new life as restaurants, serving local cuisine, music and of course, Raki.

Roman Theatre: The remains, the stage, and the backstage, can be seen outside the castle.
Roman statues that were found here are exhibited in the Museum of Anatolian Civilizations (see above).
The seating area is still under excavation.

Temple of Augustus: It was built by the Galatian King Pylamenes in AD 10 as a tribute and sign of fidelity to Augustus, and was reconstructed by the Romans on the ancient Ankara Acropolis in the 2nd century.
It is important for the "Monument Ancyranum", the sole surviving political testament of Augustus, detailing his achievements inscribed on its walls in Latin and Greek.
In the fifth century the temple was converted into a church by the Byzantines.
The temple is in the Ulus quarter of the city.

Roman Bath: This bath has all the typical features of a classical Roman bath: a frigidarium (cold room), tepidarium (cool room) and caldarium (hot room).
The bath was built in the reign of Emperor Caracalla in 3rd century AD to honour the Asclepios, the God of Medicine.
Today only the basement and first floors remain.
Situated in Ulus quarter.

Column of Julian: This column, in Ulus, was erected in 362 A.D., to commemorate a visit by the Roman Emperor Julian the Apostate.
It stands fifteen meters high and has a typical leaf decoration on the capital.
Monument to a Secure, Confident Future: This monument, in Güven Park, Bakanlıklar quarter, was erected in 1935 and bears Ataturk's advice to his people: "Turk!
Be proud, work hard, and believe in yourself."

Atatürk Farm and Zoo (Atatürk Orman Çiftliği, AOÇ) is an expansive recreational farming area housing a Zoo, several small agricultural farms, greenhouses, restaurants, a dairy farm and a brewery.
It is very a pleasant place to spend a day with family, be it for picnics, hiking, biking or simply enjoying good food and nature.
There is also an exact replica of the house where Ataturk was born in 1881, in Thessaloniki, Greece.
Visitors to the "Çiftlik" (farm) as it is affectionately called by Ankarans, can sample such famous products of the farm as its excellent old-fashioned beer and ice cream, fresh dairy products and meat rolls/kebaps made on charcoal, through an excellent traditional restaurant (Merkez Lokantasi, Central Restaurant), cafés and other establishments scattered in the farm.

Foreign visitors to Ankara usually like to visit the old shops in Çıkrıkçılar Yokuşu (Weavers' road) near Ulus, where a myriad of things ranging from traditional fabrics, hand-woven carpets and leather products can be found for bargain prices.
Bakırcılar Çarşısı (Bazaar of coppersmiths) is particularly popular, and many interesting items, not just of copper, can be found here...like jewelry, carpets, costumes, antiques and embroidery.
Walking up the hill to the castle gate, you find many shops selling a huge and fresh collection of spices, dried fruits, nuts, and other produce.</entry>
  <entry author_id="720292" end="137" start="86">It is probable that there was a Hittite settlement where Ankara castle is today and there are prehistoric mounds in several parts of the city.
Early artefacts discovered in the capital date it at least to the Phrygian period, that is about 1000 years B.C.E.
According to tradition,King Midas, the Phrygian monarch who turned everything he touched into gold, was born here.
Phrygian rule was succeeded by Lydian and then by Persian rule, though the strongly Phrygian character of the peasantry is evident from gravestones of the Roman period.

The Celtic element was probably relatively small in numbers, a warrior aristocracy, who ruled over Phrygian-speaking peasants.
However some Celtic was spoken in Galatia for many centuries.
At the end of the fourth century, St. Jerome, a native of Galatia, observed that the language spoken around Ankara was very similar to that being spoken in the north west of the Roman world near Trier

Aigustus then reorganised the area, turning tribal centres into formal cities.
The Temple of Augustus in Ankara, set up by him, contains an account of the work he did in Romanising and Hellenising the interior of Anatolia.
Ankara is in fact one of Europe’s oldest capital cities, having been a major urban centre though not a capital, for far longer than London or Paris or Madrid, let alone Istanbul.
When Istanbul, then the Roman provincial town of Byzantium, was being groomed as a new capital for the Eastern Empire in 325, Ankara was already an important administrative centre from which most of the northern half of Turkey was run.
A later monarch, the Roman Emperor Augustus, decided to make Ankara one of three main administrative centres in central Turkey.
It was then populated by Phrygians and Celts--the ‘Galatians’ who spoke a language closely related to Welsh and Gaelic.
Ankara was the centre of a tribe known as the ‘Tectosages’ and August upgraded into a major centre.
Two other tribal centres, Tavium near Yozgat and Pessinus (Balhisar) to the west near Sivrihisar were reasonably important places in Roman times, but it was Ankara that grew into a grand metropolis.
An estimated 200,000 people lived here in good times during the Roman Empire, a far greater number than was to be the case after the fall of the Empire until the twentieth century.
A small river, the Ankara Cayi, ran through the centre of the town.
It has now been covered over and diverted, but it formed the boundary of the Roman, Byzantine, and Ottoman town on the north side.
Cankaya, the rim of the majestic hill to the south of the town, stood well outside the Roman city, but may have been a summer resort.
In the 19th century, the remains of at least one Roman villa or large house were still standing not far from where the presidential palace stands today in the Cankaya district.
Ankara’s importance rest on the fact was that it was the point at which the roads in northern Anatolia running north-south and east-west intersected.
The great imperial road running east passed through Ankara and a succession of emperors and their armies came this way.
Unfortunately they were not the only ones to use the highway.
It was equally convenient for invaders.
In the second half of the third century, Ankara was invaded in rapid succession by Goths coming from the west, who rode far into the interior of Cappadocia, taking slaves and pillaging, and then by Arabs.
For about a decade, the town was one of the western outposts of one of the brilliant queens of the ancient world, the Arab empress Zenobia from Palmyra in the Syria desert, but took advantage of a period of weakness and disorder in the Roman empire to set up a short-lived state of her own.
The town was reincorporated into the Roman Empire under the Emperor Aurelian in 272 AD.
The tetrarchy, the system of multiple emperors introduced by Diocletian (284-305), seems to have engaged in a substantial programme of rebuilding and of road construction from Ankara westwards to Germe and Dorylaeum, now Eskisehir.
In normal times, Ankara was a large market and trading centre but it also functioned as a major administrative capital, where a high official ruled from the city's Praetorium, a large administrative palace or office.
During the third century, life in Ankara, as in other Anatolian towns seems to have become somewhat militarised in response to the invasions and instability of the town, but in common with other regions of central Anatolia it was also undergoing Christianisation.
Early martyrs, about whom little is known included Proklos and Hilarios who were natives of the otherwise unknown village of Kallippi, near Ancyra, who suffered during under the emperor Trajan (98-117 AD).
In the 280's we hear of Philumenos, a Christian corn merchant from southern Anatolia, being caprtured and martyred in Ankara, and Eustathius.
Like other Roman towns however, the reign of Diocletian was a turning point.
In 303, Ankara was one of the towns where the Emperors Diocletian and his deputy Galerius launched their persecution of Christians.
In Ankara their first target was the 38 year old Bishop of the town whose name was Clement.
Clement's life describes how he was taken to Rome, then sent back, and forced to undergo many interrogations and hardship before he, and his brother, and various companions were put to death.
The remains of a church of St. Clement can be found today in a building just off Işıklar Caddesi in Ulus.
Quite possibly this marks the site where Clement was originally buried.
Four years later, a doctor of the town, called Plato, and his brother, Antiochus, also become celebrated martyrs under Galerius.
However the persecution proved unsuccessful and in 314 Ankara was the centre of an important council of the early church which considered ecclesiastical policy for the reconstruction of the Christian church after the persecutions and in particular the treatment of 'lapsi'--Christians who had given in and conformed to paganism during the persecutions.
Though paganism was probably tottering in Ankara in Clement’s day, it may still have been the majority religion.
Twenty years later, Christianity and monotheism had taken its place.
Ankara quickly turned into a Christian city, with a life dominated by monks and priests and theological disputes.
The town council or senate gave way to the bishop as the main local figurehead.
During the middle of the fourth century, Ankara was involved in the complex theological disputes over the nature of Christ and a form of Arianism seems to have originated there.
IN 363, the Emperor Julian "the Apostate" passed through Ankara on his way to an ill-fated campaign against the Persian and according to Christian sources engaged in a persecution of various holy men.
The stone base for a statue, with an inscription describing Julian as "Lord of the whole world from the British Ocean to the barbarian nations" can still be seen built into the eastern side of the inner circuit of walls of Ankara castle.
There is also a column in Ankara which is called after Julian, though it probably dates from about two hundred years after his time.
In the later fourth century Ankara became something of an imperial holiday resort.
After Istanbul became the east Roman capital, emperors in the fourth and fifth century would retire from the humid summer weather on the Bosporus to the drier mountain atmosphere of Ankara and emperors such as Theodosius II (408-450) kept court in the town in the summer.
Laws issued in Ankara testify to the time they spent there.</entry>
  <entry author_id="3654844" end="208" start="137">The oldest settlements in and around the city center of Ankara belong to the Hatti civilization which lived during the Bronze Age.
Artifacts discovered in the city have revealed that the Hittites called Ankara with the name Ankuwash prior to 1200 BC.
The city significantly grew in size and importance under the Phrygians starting from around 1000 BC, experiencing a large expansion following the mass migration from Gordion, the capital of Phrygia, after an earthquake which severely damaged that city in antiquity.
In Phrygian tradition, King Midas was venerated as the founder of Ancyra, but Pausanias mentions that the city was actually far older, in line with the present-day knowledge that we have on its history.
Apart from the Phrygian period in which the city experienced its largest expansion in the ancient times, another important expansion took place under the Greeks of Pontos who came there and developed the city as a trading center for the commerce of goods between the Black Sea ports and Crimea to the north; Assyria, Cyprus, and Lebanon to the south; and Georgia, Armenia and Persia to the east.
By that time the city also took its name Áγκυρα-Ànkyra (meaning Anchor in Greek) which is still used by the Turks with the slightly modified form of Ankara.

In 278 BC, the city, along with the rest of central Anatolia, was occupied by the Celtic race of Galatians, who were the first to make Ankara one of their main tribal centres, the headquarters of the 'Tectosage' tribe.
Other centres were Pessinos, today's Balhisar near Sivrihisar, for the 'Trocmi' tribe; and Tavium, to the east of Ankara, for the 'Tolstibogii' tribe.
The city was then known as Ancyra.
The Celtic element was probably relatively small in numbers; a warrior aristocracy which ruled over Phrygian-speaking peasants.
However, the Celtic language continued to spoken in Galatia for many centuries.
At the end of the 4th century AD, St. Jerome, a native of Galatia, observed that the language spoken around Ankara was very similar to that being spoken in the northwest of the Roman world near Trier.

The city was subsequently conquered by Augustus in 25 BC and passed under the control of the Roman Empire.
Now the capital city of the Roman province of Galatia, Ancyra continued to be a center of great commercial importance.
Ankara is also famous for the Monumentum Ancyranum (Temple of Augustus and Rome) which contains the official record of the Acts of Augustus, known as the Res Gestae Divi Augusti, an inscription cut in marble on the walls of this temple.
The ruins of Ancyra still furnish today valuable bas-reliefs, inscriptions and other architectural fragments.

Augustus decided to make Ancyra one of three main administrative centres in central Anatolia.
The town was then populated by Phrygians and Celts—the Galatians who spoke a language closely related to Welsh and Gaelic.
Ancyra was the center of a tribe known as the Tectosages, and Augustus upgraded it into a major provincial capital for his empire.
Two other Galatian tribal centres, Tavium near Yozgat, and Pessinus (Balhisar) to the west, near Sivrihisar, continued to be reasonably important settlements in the Roman period, but it was Ancyra that grew into a grand metropolis.

An estimated 200,000 people lived in Ancyra in good times during the Roman Empire, a far greater number than was to be the case after the fall of the Roman Empire until the early twentieth century.
A small river, the Ankara Çayı, ran through the centre of the Roman town.
It has now been covered over and diverted, but it formed the northern boundary of the old town during the Roman, Byzantine and Ottoman periods.
Çankaya, the rim of the majestic hill to the south of the present city center, stood well outside the Roman city, but may have been a summer resort.
In the 19th century, the remains of at least one Roman villa or large house were still standing not far from where the Çankaya Presidential Residence stands today.
To the west, the Roman city extended until the area of the Gençlik Park and Railway Station, while on the southern side of the hill, it may have extended downwards as far as the site presently occupied by Hacettepe University.
It was thus a sizeable city by any standards and much larger than the Roman towns of Gaul or Britain.

Ankara's importance rested on the fact was that it was the junction point where the roads in northern Anatolia running north-south and east-west intersected.
The great imperial road running east passed through Ankara and a succession of emperors and their armies came this way.
Unfortunately they were not the only ones to use the Roman highway network, which was equally convenient for invaders.
In the second half of the 3rd century, Ancyra was invaded in rapid succession by the Goths coming from the west (who rode far into the heart of Cappadocia, taking slaves and pillaging) and later by the Arabs.
For about a decade, the town was one of the western outposts of one of the most brilliant queens of the ancient world, the Arab empress Zenobia from Palmyra in the Syrian desert, who took advantage of a period of weakness and disorder in the Roman Empire to set up a short-lived state of her own.

In its heydays, Roman Ankara was a large market and trading center but it also functioned as a major administrative capital, where a high official ruled from the city's Praetorium, a large administrative palace or office.
During the 3rd century, life in Ancyra, as in other Anatolian towns, seems to have become somewhat militarised in response to the invasions and instability of the town.
In this period, like other cities of central Anatolia, Ankara was also undergoing Christianisation.

Like in other Roman towns, the reign of Diocletian marked the culmination point of repression against Christians.
In 303, Ancyra was one of the towns where the co-Emperors Diocletian and his deputy Galerius launched their anti-Christian persecution.
In Ancyra, their first target was the 38-year-old Bishop of the town, whose name was Clement.
Clement's life describes how he was taken to Rome, then sent back, and forced to undergo many interrogations and hardship before he, and his brother, and various companions were put to death.
The remains of the church of St. Clement can be found today in a building just off Işıklar Caddesi in the Ulus district.
Quite possibly this marks the site where Clement was originally buried.
Four years later, a doctor of the town named Plato and his brother Antiochus also became celebrated martyrs under Galerius.
Theodotus of Ancyra is also venerated as a saint.

However, the persecution proved unsuccessful and in 314 Ancyra was the center of an important council of the early church; which considered ecclesiastical policy for the reconstruction of the Christian church after the persecutions, and in particular the treatment of 'lapsi'—Christians who had given in and conformed to paganism during these persecutions.
Three councils were held in the former capital of Galatia in Asia Minor, during the 4th century.
The first, an orthodox plenary synod, was held in 314, and its 25 disciplinary canons constitute one of the most important documents in the early history of the administration of the Sacrament of Penance.
Nine of them deal with conditions for the reconciliation of the lapsi; the others, with marriage, alienations of church property, etc.

Though paganism was probably tottering in Ancyra in Clement's day, it may still have been the majority religion.
Twenty years later, Christianity and monotheism had taken its place.
Ancyra quickly turned into a Christian city, with a life dominated by monks and priests and theological disputes.
The town council or senate gave way to the bishop as the main local figurehead.
During the middle of the 4th century, Ancyra was involved in the complex theological disputes over the nature of Christ, and a form of Arianism seems to have originated there.

In 362-363, the Emperor Julian the Apostate passed through Ancyra on his way to an ill-fated campaign against the Persians, and according to Christian sources, engaged in a persecution of various holy men.
The stone base for a statue, with an inscription describing Julian as "Lord of the whole world from the British Ocean to the barbarian nations", can still be seen, built into the eastern side of the inner circuit of the walls of Ankara Castle.
The Column of Julian which was erected in honor of the emperor's visit to the city in 362 still stands today.
In 375, Arian bishops met at Ancyra and deposed several bishops, among them St. Gregory of Nyssa.
The modern Ankara, also known in some Western texts as Angora, remains a Roman Catholic titular see in the former Roman province of Galatia in Asia Minor, suffragan of Laodicea.
Its episcopal list is given in Gams, "Series episc.
Eccl.
cath.
"; also that of another Ancyra in Phrygia Pacatiana.

In the later 4th century Ancyra became something of an imperial holiday resort.
After Constantinople became the East Roman capital, emperors in the 4th and 5th centuries would retire from the humid summer weather on the Bosphorus to the drier mountain atmosphere of Ancyra.
Theodosius II (408-450) kept his court in Ancyra in the summers.
Laws issued in Ancyra testify to the time they spent there.
The city's military as well as logistical significance lasted well into the long Byzantine reign.
Although Ancyra fell into the hands of several Arab armies numerous times after the 6th century, it remained an important crossroads polis within the Byzantine Empire until the late 11th century.

In 1071, the Seljuk Sultan Alparslan opened the gates of Anatolia for the Turks with his victory at the Battle of Manzikert (Malazgirt).
He then annexed Ankara, an important location for military transportation and natural resources, to his territory in 1073.
Orhan I, second Bey of the Ottoman Empire, captured the city in 1356.
Another Turkic ruler, Timur, defeated the Ottomans at the Battle of Ankara in 1402 and captured the city, but in 1403 Ankara was again under Ottoman control.</entry>
  <entry author_id="10092576" end="232" start="208">The Angora rabbit () is a variety of domestic rabbit bred for its long, soft hair.
The Angora is one of the oldest types of domestic rabbit, originating in Ankara, Turkey, along with the Angora cat and Angora goat.
The rabbits were popular pets with French royalty in the mid 1700s, and spread to other parts of Europe by the end of the century.
They first appeared in the United States in the early 1900s.
They are bred largely for their long Angora wool, which may be removed by shearing, combing, or plucking (gently pulling loose wool.)

Angoras are bred mainly for their wool because it is silky and soft.
They have a humorous appearance, as they oddly resemble a fur ball.
Most are calm and docile but should be handled carefully.
Grooming is necessary to prevent the fiber from matting and felting on the rabbit.
A condition called "wool block" is common in Angora rabbits and should be treated quickly.
Sometimes they are shorn in the summer as the long fur can cause the rabbits to overheat.

This breed was first mentioned in the time of Moses, roughly in 1500 BC.
The first Angora goats were brought to Europe by Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor, about 1554, but, like later imports, were not very successful.
Angora goats were first introduced in the United States in 1849 by Dr. James P. Davis.
Seven adult goats were a gift from Sultan Abdülmecid I in appreciation for his services and advice on the raising of cotton.

The fleece taken from an Angora goat is called mohair.
A single goat produces between five and eight kilograms of hair per year.
Angoras are shorn twice a year, unlike sheep, which are shorn only once.
Angoras have high nutritional requirements due to their rapid hair growth.
A poor quality diet will curtail mohair development.
The United States, Turkey, and South Africa are the top producers of mohair.

For a long period of time, Angora goats were bred for their white coat.
In 1998, the Colored Angora Goat Breeders Association was set up to promote breeding of colored Angoras.
Now Angora goats produce white, black (deep black to greys and silver), red (the color fades significantly as the goat gets older), and brownish fiber.</entry>
</article>
