<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="809" title="Anaconda" authors="3" lines="144">
  <entry author_id="4261200" end="82" start="0">The name anaconda is said to come from a Tamil word meaning “elephant killer,” originally used for pythons in Sri Lanka.
Local names for the snakes in South America include the Spanish term matatoro, meaning “bull killer,” and the Native American terms sucuri, yakumama, and jibóia.
Anacondas are members of the boa family and are sometimes called Water boas.
Anacondas live mainly in wet tropical regions with marshes, lakes, or rivers.
They will also move into areas that flood during part of the year such as the llanos found in Venezuela and Colombia.
In some regions, they use caves under tree roots along river banks as a shelter during the dry season or droughts.

Anacondas are only found in South America east of the Andes.
The four species have combined ranges from Venezuela south to Argentina.
The Green Anaconda is found through much of the Amazon River basin, as well as in the Orinoco River basin and parts of the Guyana region, and on the island of Trinidad.
The Yellow Anaconda is found further south, through the Paraná and Uruguay river basins from Bolivia and southern Brazil into Paraguay and Argentina.
The Dark-spotted or de Schauensee’s Anaconda lives in parts of northeastern Brazil and French Guiana.
The Bolivian Anaconda is mainly restricted to Bolivia.

Like boas and pythons, anacondas retain primitive features that indicate ancient lizard ancestors.
The snakes have traces of a pelvis and hind limbs.
The tiny hind limbs in anacondas are reduced to clawed spurs that are larger in males and used to stimulate the females during mating.
Anacondas also have two functioning lungs, unlike more advanced snakes, which have only one functional lung.

Anacondas show the greatest difference in size between adult males and females of any kind of vertebrate except for certain fishes.
The average female green anaconda, the largest species, is almost 5 times as heavy as an average male.
Fully grown female green anacondas may reportedly reach 10 m (32 ft) in length and weigh up to 250 kg (about 550 lb), although around 6 m (20 ft) and 107 kg (235 lb) is average.
The yellow anaconda is smaller, up to 4 m (13 ft) in length and 30 kg (66 lb) in weight.
Anacondas are sometimes called the largest snakes in the world.
Reticulated pythons are longer on average, reaching 11 m (33 ft), but female green anacondas are heavier with a bigger girth.

Anacondas have loosely constructed skulls and jaws, with some bones held together by ligaments or skin that allow the jaws to spread apart to many times their normal size.
The lower jaws can open almost 180 degrees and are not fused together in front, permitting a huge gape.
Massive jaw muscles give anacondas a powerful bite.
The jaws have more than 100 sharp, backward-curving teeth that prevent prey from pulling away.
Anacondas, along with boas and pythons, have two extra rows of teeth on the roof of the mouth, called pterygoid teeth.
These additional rows of teeth aid in holding and ingesting prey, and can be moved independently, helping the snake “walk” its jaws and head over prey to swallow the victim.

An important feature found in anacondas, boas, and pythons are heat-sensing pits along the lips.
These organs can detect the body heat given off by warm-blooded animals even in dark conditions.
A special smelling organ, called Jacobson’s organ, on the roof of the mouth reads the chemical clues collected by the snake’s flicking tongue.
An anaconda’s hearing is limited, but it may detect sounds and vibrations underwater, as well as through the ground.
Its skin is also sensitive.

The anaconda’s scientific name Eunectes means “good swimmer” in Greek and reflects the snake’s mainly aquatic habits.
Its eyes and nostrils are set high on its head, allowing it to see and breathe with the rest of its body under water.
An anaconda can reportedly hold its breath for 45 minutes or more, but in normal circumstances the snake may stay submerged for around 10 minutes.

Anacondas have skin colors and patterns that provide camouflage in swampy or jungle environments.
Shades of green, brown, and yellow are common, patterned with dark spots and blotches.
The underbelly scales are generally lighter in color.

It takes male anacondas around 18 months to reach sexual maturity.
Females need three years.
Anacondas can live 30 or more years, but the average life span in the wild is about 10 years for snakes that reach adulthood.

Female anacondas give off a special scent called a pheromone that males can detect with their flicking tongues.
Like some other types of snakes, anacondas sometimes form breeding balls in which many males swarm over a single female to attempt to mate.
Up to a dozen or more male anacondas may wrap themselves around a much larger female, trying to insert their sex organs into the female’s cloaca.
The males scratch with their tiny hind leg spurs to stimulate the female to mate.
A successful male leaves a waxy plug in the female's cloaca to block other males from mating.
Anaconda breeding balls take place in shallow water and can last for weeks.
Females may also breed with single males they encounter.

Anacondas give birth to live young, unlike pythons, which all lay eggs.
However, anacondas are actually oviviparous, meaning they retain eggs internally until the young hatch.
While they are carrying developing eggs inside, females typically do not eat.
The gestation period is about six to seven months.
The number of young born can range from 20 to 100.

Two forms of cannibalism are reported with female anacondas.
Large females sometimes kill and eat male anacondas, more than often following mating.
Like other live-bearing members of the boa family, female anacondas also eat stillborn offspring and undeveloped eggs expelled when giving birth.
Since females do not feed while carrying developing young, both behaviors may be related to nutritional needs.
The females may eat adult males as a ready protein source before they stop feeding.
Consuming stillborn young and unhatched eggs likely allows the females to recover more quickly from a long period without food.
Anacondas are mainly ambush predators, similar to other constrictors.
However, they are more specialized for aquatic hunting.
Smell and body heat help the snakes find prey.
Sounds or vibrations carried through water may also help.
Eyesight is probably used only for the final up-close attack.
Anacondas often swim just below the surface, hidden by vegetation before they strike.
They first bite to hold the prey then throw massive coils around its body.

Anacondas use constriction to squeeze prey to death.
They gradually tighten their powerful coils, preventing an animal from breathing.
Recent research indicates that the enormous pressure of the coils may also stop the heart from beating, quickly cutting off circulation and the blood supply to the brain.
Constriction may also snap the animal's neck or spine, and break other bones.
In many cases, anacondas simply drown victims by holding them underwater.
Once dead, the prey is generally swallowed headfirst.

Adult anacondas feed on a range of animals, usually caught in or near water.
Mammals hunted include capybaras, deer, tapirs, peccaries, and on occasion jaguars or other cats.
Domestic dogs or sheep may also fall victim to anacondas.
Aquatic birds and reptiles such as caymans are also commonly preyed on.
Young anacondas eat fish, frogs, and small rodents.
After a large meal, anacondas may not eat again for months.

Humans are the main threat to adult anacondas, which have few predators in the wild.
Large caymans may eat anacondas they can overpower.
Young anacondas are prey for many animals, including caymans and members of the cat family.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7716526" end="111" start="82">As all snakes do, green anacondas sexually reproduce meaning they have internal fertilization.
Such a courtship, in many cases, lasts over a time period of several months.
This mating period usually lasts from April to May.
The female is typically assumed to lay down a trail of pheromone, which unconditionally attracts the male anaconda toward her.
If that does not occur another possibility might be that the female herself releases a type of an air-born chemical indication.
Such a signal is also emitted to attract the male toward her.
This process is thoroughly supported by the simple observation of the mating female noticably immobie, yet multiple males gather and retreat toward her from all directions.
The male anacondas also frequently lick the air in order to fully recognize chemical signals signaling the presence of the female.

Although it does not appear that it is necessary for there to be more than one male, quite frequently the snakes tend to grouping in a breeding ball.
This breeding ball could potentially consist of up to twelve males wrapped around one female snake.
The group could stay in this position from two to four weeks.
This ball seems to be a type of a slow-motion wrestling match between the males; each one fighting for the right to mate with the female.
The strongest and largest, of couse, often becomes victorious.
However, the female anaconda, naturally physically much larger and stronger, may herself choose or deflect certain males.
Courtship and copulation frequently take place in water.
The gestation period for the green anaconda is about 6 months.
A gravid female may feed during this period.
However, males kept together during breeding season may refuse food.

The male uses its spurs to stimulate the female during mating.
The male presses his cloacal region against the female while scratching her with his spurs.
This makes a scratching sound.
The end of the courtship comes when the stimulus of the males' spurs induces the female to raise her cloacal region, allowing the two cloacas to come together.
The male wraps his tail around the female while they copulate.

This species is viviparous, giving birth to live young.
A female anaconda can give birth to as many as a hundred young, though typically the size of the litter ranges from 20 to 40.
The female may lose up to half of her pre-birthing weight after birth.
The neonates are usually around 70-80 cm long at birth.
Because of their small size they often fall prey to other animals.
They grow rapidly until they reach sexual maturity in their first few years, after which their rate of growth continues at a slower pace.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7716526" end="131" start="111">Anacondas, like other snakes and most other reptiles, can quite easily adapt to a change in the climate, environment, and near surroundings if needed.
Reasons for an anaconda needing to adapt can vary.
They may need to adapt to adjust to the terms of feeding as far as what, when and how they are being fed, and a change might need to be made in terms of sanitation to avoid sickness and diseases they may be exposed to in new surroundings.
An anaconda might also have to adjust to an environment in dealing with the climate of its new home (temperature and humidity).
Obviously, the temperature could drastically affect the snake due to the fact that it is ectothermal, meaning that it relies on it surrounding and environment to determine its inner body temperature, also known as endothermic.
If the temperature of its updated surroundings increases, a snake will do anything possible to prevent its body temperature from sky-rocketing, and if it decreases, it will attempt to lay in heated areas to increase the possibility of maintaining is usual temperature that it is accustomed to.
Anacondas, as all other snakes do, control and regulate their body temperates to a reasonable level by changing the amount of surface of their skin exposed to the sun frequently, directly related to heat.
If the terrarium, location/"tank" where a reptile is kept, is uniformly heated producing what is known as "the greenhouse effect", then the snake could possibly form and die from what is known as hyperthermia.
Hyperthermia could simply be described as an extremely abnormally high fever the snake might recieve.
The humidity, or wetness of its surroundings might also be slightly different than that of which the snake was previously used to.
This could potentially drastically alter its shedding cycle.
The obstruction of the cycle is extremely dangerous.
The hindrance of an anaconda's shedding cycle most often causes retention of eye caps.
Due to these conditions and emotions of the snake, anacondas are known for their aggressive disposition when being held in captivity specifically.

One may reasonably maintain an average and acceptable temperature for the snake by the use of a simple heater and infrared light bulbs.
Anacondas and other snakes must be exposed to ultraviolet(UV) radiation.
This is exceptionally significant because the snake needs it in order to produce vitamin D for further bone development in its body.
Occasional exposure to light bulbs that emit UV radiation with proper wavelength, or better yet, the sun, is also necessary to maintain the positive heath of an anaconda.
Humidity can be quite confusing and difficult to positively maintain in which research must be done on the snake in order for the humidity level to be correct.
A percentage of just less than 80% humidity must be maintained for caging an anaconda species from the tropical region, while a slightly less than 30% humidity must be maintained for a species of a desert region.</entry>
  <entry author_id="15578276" end="144" start="131">a full grown anaconda often reaches a length of about 30 feet and a weight of 250 kg.
the diet of this extraordinary large snake contains equally large animals, including caimans(a kind of crocodiles) and jaguars!!!
this is the case of the hunter himself becoming hunted.
the caimans often gobble up baby anacondas.
more than half of babies that hatch out of the eggs don't see their first birthday.
but full grown anacondas are indeed the kings of amazon rainforests, unquestioned, except very rarely by extremely bold and colossal jaguars.
their other favourite food items include capybaras, the biggest rodents in the world, and sometimes monkeys.
but being more agile and arboreal, monkeys are difficult to catch than other earthbound animals.
naturally, anacondas don't attack human beings.
human beings are not among their natural diet.
but there are incidents of some anacondas attacking human beings near water bodies, probably they were either so desperately hungry or they mistook men for some other animal.
movies about man eating anacondas are famous all over the world.
an extremely giant anaconda, perhaps more than some 60 feet in length, is seen in these films, but one has to understand the fact that it can happen only in a movie and can never happen in real world.</entry>
</article>
