<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="825" title="Austrian German" authors="1" lines="19">
  <entry author_id="110304" end="19" start="0">In Austria, there is no unitary Austrian language, but a variety of Germanic dialects are spoken.
Ordinarily, the latter dialects are considered to belong either to the Central Austro-Bavarian or Southern Austro-Bavarian subgroups, with the latter encompassing the languages of the Tyrol, Carinthia and Styria and the former including the dialects of Vienna, Upper Austria and Lower Austria.
Austrians from outside Vorarlberg normally cannot understand the dialect of that region, as it is more closely related to Swiss German than to other Austrian dialects.
While strong forms of the various dialects are not normally comprehensible to Northern Germans, there is virtually no communication barrier to speakers from Bavaria.
The Central Austro-Bavarian dialects are more intelligible to speakers of Standard German than the Southern Austro-Bavarian dialects of Tirol.
Wienerisch, the Austro-Bavarian dialect of Vienna, is most frequently used in Germany for impersonations of the typical inhabitant of Austria.

Simple words in the various dialects are very similar, but pronunciation is distinct for each and it is very easy for an Austrian after a few spoken words to judge which kind of dialect of Austria someone speaks.
However, if it goes into the dialects of the deeper valleys of Tyrol, sometimes even other Tyroleans are hopeless to understand the dialect.
Speakers from the different states of Austria can usually easily be distinguished from each other by their particular accents (probably more so than Bavarians), with those of Carinthia, Styria, Vienna, Upper Austria and the Tyrol being very characteristic.
Speakers from those regions, even those speaking Standard German, can usually easily be identified by their accent even by an untrained listener.

Interestingly, the geographic borderlines between the different accents coincide strongly with the borders of the states and also with the border to Bavaria, with Bavarians having a markedly different rhythm of speech in spite of the similarities in the language as such.
With German being a pluricentric language, Austrian dialects should not be confused with the variety of Standard German spoken by most Austrians, which is distinct from that of Germany or Switzerland.
Distinctions in vocabulary persist e.g. in culinary terms, where communication with Germans is frequently difficult, and administrative and legal language, which is due to Austria's exclusion from the development of a German nation in the late 19th century and its manifold particular traditions.

Austrians speaking Standard German can almost always be recognized by their accent, much more so than speakers from most regions of Germany.
Under the influence of TV, dialects are receding in Austria as they are in most areas of Europe, but it can safely be said that they are more persistent than in most of Germany.
Dialects are frequently used in TV series or movies in situation where it is appropriate for the particular character and situation.
A classic example of a strong form of Viennese working-class dialect, for example, would be Ein echter Wiener geht nicht unter.
However, strong varieties of dialect are not used quite as much as e.g. in Switzerland.
For example, educated people in Vienna usually speak a very slight form of dialect or simply Standard German, but with the characteristic Viennese accent and, where it exists, particular Austrian and Viennese vocabulary.</entry>
</article>
