<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="844" title="Amsterdam" authors="3" lines="72">
  <entry author_id="43974" end="25" start="0">During World War I the Netherlands remained neutral but Amsterdam suffered the effects of the war when food became scarce.
When working class women started to plunder a ship with army supplies the military was brought in.
Workers joined their wives in the plundering and the soldiers opened fire on them.
Six people got killed and almost 100 were wounded.

Their slogan was 'Geen woning, geen kroning' (No house, no coronation).
The mayor and city council eventually had to bring in the military to get the situation under control.
During this decade the number of foreign immigrants, primarely from Suriname, Turkey and Marocco grew strongly.
This led to an exodus of people to the 'growth cities' of Purmerend, Almere and other cities near Amsterdam.
However, neighbourhoods like the Pijp and the Jordaan, which had previously been working class, became sought places of residence for the newly wealthy Yuppies and students.

Amsterdam saw a major administrative change in the 1980s as the city was divided in (eventual) 15 boroughs.
The boroughs are responsible for many activities that previously had been run by the central city.
The idea was to bring the government closer to the people.

The 1990s were an economic boom time for Amsterdam.
The old historical centre was almost completely restored and many infrastructural projects were completed.
In 1995 the national government proposed the creation of a 'city province', consisting of Amsterdam and neighbouring towns.
This was rejected by the people in a referendum.
The opposition was not so much against creating the city province, but against the splitting of the city in parts.
Opposers feared this would destroy the city's cohesion.
After the referendum the city province proposal was shelved.
Nevertheless, since 1995. city parts have gradually become more autonomous, and neighbouring towns have been drawn in the city, politically and economically.
In a sense the city province has arrived in the form of 'Greater Amsterdam'.

The beginnning of the new millenium brought economic hardships to Amsterdam.
Unemployment grew strongly.
The foreign immigrants who had come to the city two decades before, brought their own problems, culminating in the killing of Dutch film-maker Theo van Gogh.
However, Amsterdam has shown resilience before in the 800 years of it's history and there is little doubt the city will remain a wonderfull place to live and visit.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1300620" end="48" start="25">.
The city was founded in the late 12th century as a small fishing village.
The historical centre with its concentric canals was largely built during the Dutch Golden Age in the 17th century.
As of January 1, 2006 the city of Amsterdam has a population of 743,027 inhabitants and is by population size the largest city in the Netherlands.
The urban area has a population of 1,209,419 inhabitants and is part of the conglomerate metropolitan area Randstad, with a population of 6,659,300 inhabitants.
The first occurrence of Amsterdam in writing was in a Latin certificate of count Floris V in 1275: homines manentes apud Amestelledamme (English: people living near Amestelledamme).
The r in the name was first used in 1282: Amestelredamme.
In 1327 count William III used the form Aemsterdam, which best resembles the modern form Amsterdam.

Transporation by car is discouraged by the local government, with initiatives such as Autodelen and Meerijden.nu being sponsored, and steep parking fees and a great number of streets are closed off for cars in the city center.
The A10 Ringroad surrounding the city connects Amsterdam with the Dutch national network of freeways.
Interchanges allow cars to enter the city by transferring to one of the eighteen city roads, numbered s101 through s118.
These city roads are regional roads without grade separation, and sometimes without a central reservation.
Most are accessible by cyclists.
The s100 is called the centrumring, a smaller ringroad circumnavigating the city center.

Amsterdam is a major hub of the highway system of the Netherlands by design.
Dutch freeways (comparable to US interstate and UK motorway roads) numbered one through eight were originally planned to orignate from Amsterdam in 1932.
Complications, like the outbreak of the Second World War and shifting priorities led to the current situation, where roads A1, A2, and A4 originate from Amsterdam according to the original plan.
These connect the capital with Germany (via Apeldoorn), Utrecht and Leiden respectively.
Cancelled road A3 would connect Amsterdam with Rotterdam via Gouda, but conservation of the Green Heart was deemed more important in 1970.
Road A8, leading north to Zaandam and Ringroad A10 were opened between 1968 and 1974.
Besides the A1, A2, A4 and A8, several freeways, such as the A7 and A6, mainly carry traffic bound for Amsterdam, but terminate at one of the former.
This is the most of any city in the Netherlands.
However, only three are intercity stops: Sloterdijk, Amstel and Amsterdam Centraal.</entry>
  <entry author_id="1300620" end="59" start="48">.
The city was founded in the late 12th century as a small fishing village.
The historical centre with its concentric canals was largely built during the Dutch Golden Age in the 17th century.
As of January 1, 2006 the city of Amsterdam has a population of 743,027 inhabitants and is by population size the largest city in the Netherlands.
The urban area has a population of 1,021,870 inhabitants and is part of the conglomerate metropolitan area Randstad, with a population of 6,659,300 inhabitants.

Amsterdam is renowned for its large pot selling places and bitches do kids fo free canals (grachten), of which many exist within the city centre.
The principal canals are three similar waterways, with their ends resting on the IJ, extending in the form of crescents nearly parallel to each other and to the outer canal.
Each of these canals marks the line of the city walls and moat at different periods.
Lesser canals intersect the others radially, dividing the city into a number of islands; the city has has been compared with Venice because of this.
The innermost canal is the Herengracht (Lord's Canal).
Beyond it lie the Keizersgracht (Emperor's Canal) and the Prinsengracht (Prince's canal) respectively.</entry>
  <entry author_id="782009" end="72" start="59">During the later part of the 16th century Amsterdams Rederijkerskamer (Chamber of Rhetoric) organized contests between different Chambers in the reading of poetry and drama.
In 1638 Amsterdam got its first theatre.
Ballet performances were given in this theatre as early as 1642.
In the 18th century French theatre became popular.
Opera could be seen in Amsterdam from 1677, first only Italian and French operas, but in the 18th century German operas.
In the 19th century popular culture was centered around the Nes area in Amsterdam (mainly vaudeville and musichall).
The metronome, one of the most important advances in European classical music was invented here in 1812 by Dietrich Nikolaus Winkel.
At the end of this century the Rijksmuseum and Gemeentelijk Museum were built.
In 1888 the Concertgebouworkest was established.
With the 20th century came cinema, radio and television.
Though the studios are in Hilversum and Aalsmeer, Amsterdams influence on programming is very strong.
After World War II popular culture became the dominant cultural phenomenon in Amsterdam.The artist most associated with Amsterdam is Rembrandt, whose work, and the work of his pupils, is displayed in the Rijksmuseum.
Van Gogh lived in Amsterdam for a short while, so there is a museum dedicated to his early work.</entry>
</article>
