<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="872" title="Akira Kurosawa10" authors="1" lines="187">
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="10" start="0">Despite the extraordinary acclaim that Kurosawa’s work has received both in Japan and abroad, his films, as well as Kurosawa as an individual, have also been subject to considerable criticism, much of it harsh.
The majority of these negative judgments can be considered to fall into one or more of the following categories:In the early-to-mid 1950s, while Kurosawa’s films were being widely viewed in Europe and North America, the final films of a Japanese film master of the older generation, Kenji Mizoguchi, also began to be shown internationally and receive film festival prizes.
This simultaneous exposure led to frequent critical comparisons between the two directors.
A number of critics belonging to the French New Wave, such as Jean-Luc Godard, championed Mizoguchi’s films at the expense of Kurosawa’s work:

Godard’s fellow New Wave critic-filmmaker, Jacques Rivette, writes: “"You can compare only what is comparable and that which aims high enough.
Mizoguchi, alone, imposes a feeling of a unique world and language, is answerable only to himself...
He seems to be the only Japanese director who is completely Japanese and yet is also the only one that achieves a true universality, that of an individual."

It should be noted that Kurosawa himself deeply admired the older master, particularly his indefatigable perfectionism.
In his eulogy at Mizoguchi's funeral, Kurosawa said, “Mizoguchi’s greatness was that he would do anything to heighten the reality of every scene.
He never made compromises… Of all Japanese directors, I have the greatest respect for him... With the death of Mizoguchi, Japanese film has lost its truest creator.”</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="21" start="10">During the Second World War, workers on all levels of the Japanese film industry were under immense pressure to create works that not only omitted the slightest criticism of the ruling military dictatorship, but which actively promoted kokusaku ("national policy"), that is, militarism and other aspects of fascist ideology.
It was in this highly politicized atmosphere that Kurosawa began his career as a director in 1943.
Therefore, some controversy exists about the extent to which his films of this period could be considered fascist propaganda.

The cultural historian Peter B.
High sees Kurosawa’s wartime cinema as part of the general propagandistic cultural trends of Japan at war and as reflecting many of these conventions.
About his second film, The Most Beautiful, which High refers to as a "dark and gloomy rendition of the standard formulas of the front genre", he writes: "The film announces its spiritist message in the very first scene.
Over a loudspeaker, the factory manager (Shimura Takashi) is giving his morning pep talk to the factory personnel: 'Only an indomitable spirit of deep responsibility can achieve outstanding production results.
There can be no improvement in production without an improvement in personal character!'
The montage cuts back and forth between Shimura and the workers lined up in military fashion.
One of the lines is made up of extremely young boys – a depressing sight."
High also claims that Kurosawa during this period demonstrated “a talent and enthusiasm for national policy scenarios,” writing the blatantly propagandistic Winged Victory (for director Satsuo Yamamoto) and submitting several other scripts that won prizes in “people’s cinema script” contests given by the wartime Information Bureau.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="33" start="21">A number of critics have reacted negatively to the female characters in Kurosawa’s movies.
(Kurosawa himself once noted: "Of course, all my women my films are rather strange, I agree.")
Joan Mellen, in her examination of this subject, praises only the director’s characterization of Yukie (Setsuko Hara), the heroine of No Regrets for Our Youth, remarking that "her face expresses the very potential of the Japanese woman that has been so often, during all these long centuries, left wasted and latent."
Of the main female character in Rashomon, Masago, Mellen claims that "in none of the versions the film’s self-contradictory narrative is the woman (Machiko Kyo) granted self-respect, dignity or spiritual value," and argues that Masago represents one aspect of a "whore-madonna" dichotomy on the part of her creator.

Mellon also claims that, after Rashomon, Kurosawa stopped portraying women’s potential in his works "as if repelled by Masago, that half-demon of his own creation."
She maintains that many of Kurosawa’s later heroines fall into one of two categories: the destructive and the masochistic woman.
Speaking of The Idiot, she wrote, "the sensual woman is portrayed as the castrating bitch and the ‘good’ girl is devoid of any capacity for pleasure."
In the Gorky adaptation, The Lower Depths, one heroine is "manipulative and malicious," and the other is "weak and unable to survive on her own."
By the time of Red Beard (1965), "women in Kurosawa have become not only unreal and incapable of kindness, but totally bereft of autonomy, whether physical, intellectual, or emotional… Women at their best may only imitate the truths men discover."

Mitsuhiro Yoshimoto has noted that Kurosawa’s films often offer a paradoxical bond between good and evil male protagonists, in which the distinction between them becomes blurred.
Outside this "Möbius strip of male bonding," any woman "functions as a catalyst of sentimentalism by neutralizing" this duality.
"Without being able to produce any value by herself," Yoshimoto writes, "the woman in Kurosawa’s films is often the embodiment of passivity threatening the solipsism of the split male subject."</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="44" start="33">All biographical sources, as well as the filmmaker’s own comments, agree that Kurosawa was a completely “hands-on” director, passionately involved in every aspect of the filmmaking process.
As one interviewer summarized, “he (co-writes his scripts, oversees the design, rehearses the actors, sets up all the shots and then does the editing.”  Kurosawa emphasized time and again that the screenplay was the absolute foundation of a successful film and that a good film can never be made out of a bad script.
"For truly cinematic expression, the camera and the microphone must be able to cross both fire and water… The script must be something that has the power to do this."
During the postwar period, he began the practice of collaborating with a rotating group of five screenwriters: Eijirō Hisaita, Ryuzo Kikushima, Shinobu Hashimoto, Hideo Oguni, and Masato Ide.
Whichever members of this group happened to be working on a particular film would gather around a table, often at a hot-springs resort, where they would not be distracted by the outside world.
(Seven Samurai, for example, was written in this fashion.)
Often they all (except Oguni, who acted as “referee”) would work on the exact same pages of the script, and Kurosawa would choose the best-written version of each particular sequence.
This method was adopted "so that each contributor might function as a kind of foil, checking the dominance of any one person’s point-of-view."

In addition to the actual script, Kurosawa at this stage often produced extensive, fantastically detailed notes to elaborate his vision.
For example, for Seven Samurai, he created six notebooks in which he produced detailed biographies of the samurai, including what they wore and ate, how they walked, talked and behaved when greeted, even how each tied his shoes.
For the 101 peasant characters in the film, he created a registry consisting of 23 families and instructed the performers playing these roles to live and work as these “families” for the duration of shooting.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="58" start="44">During the actual production of a film, Kurosawa was most concerned with capturing the action of the script as vividly as possible.
This involved careful work with his actors, and he often gave them great freedom to shape their own performances.
During the shooting of Drunken Angel, for example, Toshiro Mifune’s performance as a young gangster was so aggressive that Kurosawa feared it would unbalance the drama by overshadowing the main character of the alcoholic doctor (played by Takashi Shimura).
However, he was even more afraid of smothering Mifune’s immense vitality, so he let the actor do what he wanted.
Said Kurosawa: “In the end, although the title refers to the doctor, it is Mifune that everyone remembers.”

Beginning with Seven Samurai (1954), Kurosawa's cinematic technique changed drastically, through his extensive use in that film of telephoto lenses and multiple cameras.
The director claimed that he used these lenses and several cameras rolling at once to help the actors -- allowing them to be photographed at some distance from the cameras, without the knowledge of which particular camera's image would at any given moment represent the final "take" -- making their performances much more natural.
(Tatsuya Nakadai agreed that the multiple cameras did help his performances with the director.)
But these changes had a powerful effect as well on the look of the action scenes in that film, particularly the final battle in the rain.
"He can use the telephoto lenses to get under the horses, in between their hooves, to plunge us into the chaos of that battle in a visual way that is really quite unprecedented, both in Kurosawa’s own work and in the samurai genre as a whole."

For all his films, but particularly in his "period" pictures (jidai-geki), Kurosawa insisted on absolute authenticity.
The director felt that giving an actor in a jidai-geki a brand new costume made the character look less than plausible.
To resolve this, he often gave his cast their costumes weeks before the beginning of shooting, requiring them to wear them on a daily basis and "bond with them."
In some cases, such as with Seven Samurai, where most of the cast portrayed poor farmers, the actors were told to make sure the costumes were worn down and tattered by the time shooting started.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="69" start="58">Kurosawa often remarked that he shot a film simply in order to have material to edit, because the editing of a picture was the most important and creatively interesting part of the process for him.
Kurosawa’s creative team believed that the director’s skill with editing was his greatest talent.
Said Hiroshi Nezu, a longtime production supervisor on his films, “Among ourselves, we think that he is Toho’s best director, that he is Japan’s best scenarist, and that he is the best editor in the world.
He is most concerned with the flowing quality which a film must have… The Kurosawa film flows over the cut, as it were.”

The director’s frequent crew member Teruyo Nogami confirms this view.
“Akira Kurosawa’s editing was exceptional, the inimitable work of a genius… No one was a match for him.” She claimed that Kurosawa carried in his head all the information about all shots filmed, and if, in the editing room, he asked for a piece of film and she handed him the wrong one, he would immediately recognize the error, though she had taken detailed notes on each shot and he had not.
She compared his mind to a computer, which could do with edited segments of film what computers do today.

Kurosawa’s habitual method – at variance with the standard Hollywood practice of editing a film only after all footage has been shot – was to edit a film daily, bit by bit, during production.
This helped particularly when he started using multiple cameras, which resulted in a large amount of film to assemble.
“I always edit in the evening if we have a fair amount of footage in the can.
After watching the rushes, I usually go to the editing room and work.” Because of this practice of editing as he went along, the post-production period for a Kurosawa film could be startlingly brief: Yojimbo had its Japanese premiere on April 20, 1961, four days after shooting concluded on April 16th.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="88" start="69">Kurosawa drew upon an enormous range of influences from cinematic, theatrical and literary traditions – both those of his native culture and of the West – in the creation his films.
According to his own statements, one of the strongest influences on Kurosawa was the cinema of the silent period.
Recalling, near the end of his life, a 1928 French Edgar Allen Poe adaptation, La Chute de la Maison Usher (The Fall of the House of Usher), directed by Jean Epstein, he said, “As you know, it's a silent movie… That power of expression.
Simply wonderful.
And before I start to make a movie, every time I try to imagine how I would have made this picture if it was a silent movie.” Prior to making Rashomon, he did extensive silent film research (with very limited resources at that time in Japan) to recapture that special aesthetic.
“Since the advent of the talkies in the 1930s, I felt, we had misplaced and forgotten what was so wonderful about the old silent movies… I believed that there was something to be learned from the spirit of the French avant-garde films of the 1920s… Rashomon would be my testing ground, the place where I could apply the ideas and wishes growing out of my silent film research.”

Among American sound film directors, Kurosawa held Frank Capra and John Ford in particular esteem.
Critics have asserted that, of the Japanese director's early films, both One Wonderful Sunday and Scandal owe a debt to Capra’s work in general, and the latter film includes scenes that appear to allude directly to It’s a Wonderful Life.
Kurosawa often cited Ford as one of his favorite directors: “There is one more film director I would like to resemble as I grow old: the late American film director John Ford.” and he identified My Darling Clementine as his favorite film by the director (“It’s a model of what cinema should be”).
(On the other hand, he once remarked, “I’m sure that my films do show some influence from John Ford, whose work I like very much, but I’m certainly not conscious of doing anything to imitate him.”)

Ford was, of course, an acknowledged master of the Western, and the influence of that genre (or lack of it) on Kurosawa’s work has been frequently discussed by critics and scholars, though there has been no consensus on the subject.
Donald Richie compares Yojimbo, for example, to such classic Westerns as Shane, Bad Day at Black Rock and High Noon.
Stephen Prince, on the other hand, maintains that Kurosawa “cannot simply make Westerns, since the social perceptions and the national tradition that they express are quite foreign Japan,” and cites a quote by the director, in which he remarked that he had learned from the “grammar” of the Western, to argue that Kurosawa utilized only “certain syntactic features” from the genre and not its content.
Joan Mellen asserts, “Questions of whether Kurosawa influenced Western films – or that they influenced him – are irrelevant to understanding him as a film-maker.”

So much attention has been given to the influence of Hollywood on Kurosawa that it is often overlooked that the classic European art cinema also inspired him.
In his autobiography, he lists the titles of nearly a hundred non-Japanese films he viewed during his youth, under the influence of his brother Heigo, and this list includes celebrated works by such continental directors as Ernst Lubitsch, Abel Gance, Carl Theodore Dreyer, F.W.
Murnau, Sergei Eisenstein and Jean Renoir.
The last-named director particularly impressed Kurosawa: he was a great admirer of Renoir’s Grand Illusion.
He described Renoir as “a warm and broad-minded person” when he met the Frenchman in Paris and later called him one of two major directors (the other being John Ford), compared to whom he himself, in his view, was “no more than a little chick.” Near the end of his life, he prepared a list of 100 favorite films, which included works by such distinguished postwar European figures as Roberto Rossellini, Federico Fellini, Jean-Luc Godard, Louis Malle, Francois Truffaut and Andrei Tarkovsky.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="99" start="88">Nature is a crucial element in Kurosawa’s films.
According to Stephen Prince, "Kurosawa’s sensibility, like that of many Japanese artists, is keenly sensitive to the subtleties and beauties of season and scenery."
The director himself once said, "I like hot summers, cold winters, heavy rains and snows, and I think most of my pictures show this.
I like extremes because I find them most alive."
He has never hesitated to exploit climate and weather as plot elements, to the point where they become "active participants in the drama… The oppressive heat in Stray Dog and Record of a Living Being is omnipresent and becomes thematized as a signifier of a world disjointed by economic collapse and the atomic threat."

Wind is also a powerful symbol: "The persistent metaphor of Kurosawa’s work is that of wind, the winds of change, of fortune and adversity."
"The visually flamboyant battle Yojimbo takes place in the main street, as huge clouds of dust swirl around the combatants… The winds that stir the dust… have brought firearms to the town along with the culture of the West, which will end the warrior tradition."
It is also difficult not to notice the importance of rain to Kurosawa: "Rain in Kurosawa’s films is never treated neutrally.
When it occurs… it is never a drizzle or a light mist but always a frenzied downpour, a driving storm."
"The final battle Seven Samurai is a supreme spiritual and physical struggle, and it is fought in a blinding rainstorm, which enables Kurosawa to visualize an ultimate fusion of social groups… but this climactic vision of classlessness, with typical Kurosawan ambivalence, has become a vision of horror.
The battle is a vortex of swirling rain and mud… The ultimate fusion of social identity emerges as an expression of hellish chaos."</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="116" start="99">Kurosawa sometimes created, for dramatic contrast, adversarial characters that functioned as "doubles" of his heroic protagonists.
For his debut, Sanshiro Sugata, Kurosawa created an elegant, Westernized villain, Higaki (Ryunosuke Tsukigata), who issues a challenge to the hero, which Sugata first refuses, than accepts.
"Higaki, in fact," writes Stephen Prince, "is Sanshiro’s double, as he makes clear through similar actions that he has each character repeat."

In Stray Dog, the detective-hero, Murakami, slowly realizes that the pistol thief he is chasing, Yusa, is almost exactly like himself: a veteran without strong family ties who, like Murakami, had his army knapsack with all his belongings stolen, while returning from the war.
In the climactic scene, the detective has located the thief (who is now also a murderer) and fights him in a muddy field to arrest him and get his pistol back.
As Donald Richie describes this scene: "The camera looks at cop and robber, both so mud-covered that it is difficult to tell which is which.
They look identical… Man’s fight against evil is artificial, man himself is both hero and villain, in himself.” Stephen Prince takes a different view: "The thief and killer… represents a national self, crushed and deformed by the war and its aftermath, and recovery entails suppressing and abandoning this self.
In this sense, Yusa is Murakami’s evil double, a doppelgӓnger who must be symbolically apprehended."

In one of Kurosawa’s most discussed scenes, the conclusion of High and Low, the protagonist, Gondo, faces the taunting kidnapper who has ruined him – but there is a glass-and-wire barrier between them and the image of the face of each is reflected in the glass on his own side, so that, at times, the two faces seem to overlap one another.
As Richie writes, "We know two characters are not one – they are good and evil; they are opposite poles… Yet, here… Kurosawa is showing us something entirely different.
He is suggesting that, despite everything, good and evil are the same, that all men are equal."
Again, Prince disagrees: "These compositions do not make a statement about the equality or common humanity of the characters, any more than the bath of mud at the end of Stray Dog implied the equivalence of Murakami and Yusa… High and Low offers, finally, structures of separation, not humanistic reconciliation."

In Kagemusha, the great feudal Lord, Shingen Takeda, confronts his literal double: a thief who bears an uncanny resemblance to himself.
At first this thief, like the criminal in High and Low, taunts his “betters”: he has only stolen a few coins, after all, while Shingen, as a warlord, has murdered many, so which of them is the real criminal?
In this, Prince sees a momentary reassertion of "the critique of economic and political oppression that sustained and lifted Seven Samurai to greatness."
But then Shingen points out to the thief that his savagery serves a higher purpose: to unify the nation in order to end the civil wars and prevent even greater bloodshed.
After the thief grasps this, he begins to be transformed from antagonist to disciple – but one who, as noted above, can only follow his master to the grave.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="128" start="116">Beginning with Throne of Blood (1957), what Stephen Prince calls "the countertradition to the committed, heroic mode of Kurosawa’s cinema" first appears: an obsession with historical cycles of inexorable savage violence.
According to Donald Richie, within the world of that film, "Cause and effect is the only law.
Freedom does not exist."
and Prince claims that its events "are inscribed in a circle of time that infinitely repeats."
(He uses as evidence the fact that Washizu’s lord, unlike the kindly Duncan of Shakespeare’s play, had murdered his own lord years before to seize power, and is then murdered in turn by Washizu for the same reason.)
"The fated quality to the action of Macbeth was transposed by Kurosawa with a sharpened emphasis upon predetermined action and the crushing of human freedom under the laws of karma."

Prince claims that Kurosawa’s last epics, Kagemusha and particularly Ran, mark a major turning point in the director’s vision of the world.
In Kagemusha, "where once the world of his films the individual could grasp events tightly and demand that they conform to his or her impulses, now the self is but the epiphenomenon of a ruthless and bloody temporal process, ground to dust beneath the weight and force of history."
The following epic, Ran, is “a relentless chronicle of base lust for power, betrayal of the father by his sons, and pervasive wars and murders."
The film is "a commentary on what Kurosawa now perceives as the timelessness of human impulses toward violence and self-destruction."
"History has given way to a perception of life as a wheel of endless suffering, ever turning, ever repeating," which is compared in many instances in the screenplay with hell.
"Kurosawa has found hell to be both the inevitable outcome of human behavior and the appropriate visualization of his own bitterness and disappointment."</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="145" start="128">Virtually all commentators have noted Kurosawa’s bold, dynamic style, which many have compared to the traditional Hollywood style of narrative moviemaking, one that emphasizes, in the words of one such scholar, "chronological, causal, linear and historical thinking."
But it has also been claimed that, from his very first film, the director displayed a technique quite distinct from the seamless style of classic Hollywood.
This technique involved a disruptive depiction of screen space through the use of numerous unrepeated camera setups, a disregard for the traditional 180-degree axis of action around which Hollywood scenes have usually been constructed, and an approach in which “narrative time becomes spatialized,” with fluid camera movement often replacing conventional editing.
The following are some idiosyncratic aspects of the artist’s style.
In his films of the 1940s and 1950s, Kurosawa frequently employs the "axial cut," in which the camera moves closer to (or further away from) the subject, not through the use of tracking shots or dissolves, but through a series of matched jump cuts.
For example, in Sanshiro Sugata II, the hero takes leave of the woman he loves, but then, after walking away a few feet, turns and bows to her, and then, after walking a bit further, turns and bows once more.
This sequence of shots (illustrated on film scholar David Bordwell's blog) is reproduced on this page.
The three shots are not connected in the film by camera movements or dissolves, but by a series of two jump cuts.
The effect is to stress the duration of Sanshiro's departure.

In the opening sequence of Seven Samurai in the peasant village, the axial cut is used twice.
When the villagers are outdoors, gathered in a circle, weeping and lamenting the imminent arrival of the bandits, they are glimpsed from above in extreme long shot, then, after the cut, in a much closer shot, then in an even closer shot, until finally the viewer is at ground level, and the dialogue begins.
A few minutes later, when the villagers go to the mill to ask the village elder's advice, there is a long shot of the mill, with a slowly turning wheel in the river, then a closer shot of this wheel, and then a still closer shot of it.
(As the mill is where the elder lives, these shots forge a mental association in the viewer's mind between that character and the mill.)
A number of scholars have pointed out Kurosawa’s tendency to “cut on motion”: that is, to edit a sequence of a character or characters in motion so that an action is depicted in two or more separate shots, rather than one uninterrupted shot.
A commentator, as an example, describes a tense scene in Seven Samurai in which the samurai Shichiroji, who is standing, wishes to console the peasant Manzo, who is sitting on the ground, and he gets down on one knee to talk to him.
Kurosawa chooses to film this simple action in two shots rather than one (cutting between the two only after the action of kneeling has begun) to fully convey Shichiroji’s humility.
Numerous other instances of this device are evident in the movie.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="163" start="145">Goodwin also points out that in The Lower Depths, in which Kurosawa completely avoided wipes, the director cleverly manipulated people and props “in order to slide new visual images in and out of view much as a wipe cut does.”  Kurosawa by all accounts always gave great attention to the soundtracks of his films (Teruyo Nogami’s memoir gives many such examples).
In the late 1940s, he began to employ music for what he called "counterpoint" to the emotional content of a scene, rather than merely to reinforce the emotion, as Hollywood traditional did (and still does).
The inspiration for this innovation came from a family tragedy.
When news reached Kurosawa of his father's death in 1948, he wandered aimlessly through the streets of Tokyo.
His sorrow was magnified rather than diminished when he suddenly heard the cheerful, vapid song "The Cuckoo Waltz", and he hurried to escape from this "awful music."
He then told his composer, Fumio Hayasaka, with whom he was working on Drunken Angel, to use "The Cuckoo Waltz" as ironic accompaniment to the scene in which the dying gangster, Matsunaga, sinks to his lowest point in the narrative.

"Ah, counterpoint," said Hayasaka.
"Right.
The Sharpshooter," Kurosawa answered.
This referred to a Soviet film both men had liked (which Teruyo Nogami more accurately refers to as The Sniper), a World War I drama in which, during a scene in which an enemy sniper is stabbed to death, cheerful French music is heard by the characters.
By using "The Cuckoo Waltz" rather than sad music during a grim scene, Kurosawa and Hayasaka sought to emulate the dramatic effect they so admired in the earlier movie.

This ironic approach to music can also be found in Stray Dog, a film released a year after Drunken Angel.
In the climactic scene, the detective Murakami is fighting furiously with the murderer Yusa in a muddy field.
The sound of a Mozart piece is suddenly heard, played on the piano by a woman in a nearby house.
As one commentator notes, "In contrast to this scene of primitive violence, the serenity of the Mozart is, literally, other-worldly" and "the power of this elemental encounter is heightened by the music."
Nor was Kurosawa’s "ironic" use of the soundtrack limited to music.
One critic observes that, in Seven Samurai, "During episodes of murder and mayhem, birds chirp in the background, as they do in the first scene when the farmers lament their seemingly hopeless fate."
Many commentators have noted the frequent occurrence in Kurosawa’s work of the complex relationship between an older and a younger man, who serve each other as master and disciple, respectively.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11349330" end="187" start="163">Kurosawa’s is a heroic cinema, a series of dramas (mostly) concerned with the deeds and fates of larger-than-life heroes.
Stephen Prince has identified the emergence of the unique Kurosawa protagonist with the immediate postwar period, when the aim of the American Occupation to replace Japanese feudalism with individualism coincided with the director’s artistic and social agenda: "Kurosawa welcomed the changed political climate and sought to fashion his own mature cinematic voice."
The Japanese critic Tadao Sato concurs: "With defeat in World War II, many Japanese… were dumbfounded to find that the government had lied to them and was neither just nor dependable.
During this uncertain time Akira Kurosawa, in a series of first-rate films, sustained the people by his consistent assertion that the meaning of life is not dictated by the nation but something each individual should discover for himself through suffering."
The filmmaker himself remarked that, during this period, "I felt that without the establishment of the self as a positive value there could be no freedom and no democracy."

The first such postwar hero was, curiously, a woman – Yukie, played by Setsuko Hara, in No Regrets for Our Youth."
desertion of family and class background to assist a poor village, her perseverance in the face of enormous obstacles, her assumption of responsibility for her own life and for the well-being of others, and her existential loneliness… are essential to Kurosawan heroism and make of Yukie the first coherent… example."
This "existential loneliness" is also exemplified by Dr. Sanada (Takashi Shimura) in Drunken Angel: "Kurosawa insists that his heroes take their stand, alone, against tradition and battle for a better world, even if the path there is not clear.
Separation from a corrupt social system in order to alleviate human suffering, as Sanada does, is the only honorable course."

Behind these values lies the keen awareness of the filmmaker of class distinctions and the realities of poverty.
Referring to the cruel, impoverished kidnapper in High and Low, Joan Mellen writes, "Appalled as he is by kidnapper’s brutality, Kurosawa does not believe that some should live in mansions high on a hill overlooking the squalor of the working poor, confined to three tatami rooms, freezing in winter, stifling in summer."
(Mellen goes on to trace the director’s class consciousness to his brief membership in the Marxist Proletarian Artists League in the late 1920s.)

Many commentators regard Seven Samurai as the ultimate expression of the artist’s heroic ideal.
Joan Mellen’s comments are typical of this view: "Seven Samurai is above all a homage to the samurai class at its most noble… Samurai for Kurosawa represent the best of Japanese tradition and integrity."
The leader of the samurai, Kambei, is a hero not only because he takes pity on the farmers’ poverty and oppression, but because he teaches them to transcend their petty self-interest.
In a scene exactly halfway through the film, Kambei informs the community that the fields will have to be flooded to protect the village from bandits, even though this will require the abandonment of three outlying houses.
When the owners of those houses rebel against this decision and try to run off, Kambei, literally and figuratively, forces them back into line.
He then declares: "We can’t endanger twenty for three… He who thinks only about himself will destroy himself, too."
Later, Mosuke (one of the owners of the three houses), watching those houses set on fire by the bandits, dismisses them as "worthless shacks," revealing that he has learned from Kambei to put the common good above his own.

As Kurosawa’s career progressed, however, he seemed to find it increasingly difficult to sustain the heroic ideal.
As Prince notes, "Kurosawa’s is an essentially tragic vision of life, and this sensibility… impedes his efforts to realize a socially committed mode of filmmaking."
He also observes that, although Seven Samurai "embodies a belief in the centrality of class exploitation… and searches for an alternative,… an end to class differentiation would also mean an end to heroes, to those extraordinary individuals whose supremacy to the masses has constituted a moral example… central to Kurosawa’s narratives."
Furthermore, the director’s ideal of heroism is subverted by history itself: "When history is articulated as it is in Throne of Blood, as a blind force… heroism ceases to be a problem or a reality."
According to Prince, the filmmaker’s vision eventually became so bleak that he would come to view history merely as eternally recurring patterns of violence, within which the individual is depicted as not only unheroic, but utterly helpless (see “” below).</entry>
</article>
