<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="874" title="Ancient Egypt" authors="5" lines="272">
  <entry author_id="336060" end="35" start="0">The establishment of the Egyptian chronology presented some substantial difficulties, since a great many documents contain chronological contradictions.
Let us examine the correlation between the classical History by Herodotus, and the consensual chronology.
For instance, during his consecutive and coherent account of Egyptian history, Herodotus calls Cheops the successor of Rhampsinitos (Herodotus.
The Histories ofHerodotus, etc. London and New York, Everyman’s Library, 1964.).
The modern commentator will immediately “correct” in the following manner: “Herodotus creates confusion in chronology of Egypt – Rhampsinitos (Ramses II) was a king of the XIX dynasty (1345-1200 b.c.), whilst Cheops belonged to the IV (2600-2480 b.c.)”.
The discrepancy here equals 1200 years, no less.
Just think of what the figure implies and of its sheer value: twelve hundred years.
Let us carry on.According to Herodotus,Asychis was succeeded by Anysis.
Modern commentary is also rash to tell us that “Herodotus leaps from the end of the IV dynasty (about 2480 b.c.) to the beginning of the Ethiopian reign in Egypt (about 715 b.c.)”  The leap is one of 1800 years.
Eighteen hundred years!
In general, it turns out that “The chronology of kings given by Herodotus does not concur with that found in the fragments of Manetho’s list of kings”.As a rule, the chronology of Herodotus is much shorter than Scaliger’s version.
The temporal distances between kings according to Herodotus are often thousands of years shorter than corresponding periods as given by Manethon.
The History of Herodotus contains a great number of “minor errors”, those of 30-40 years; however, they only come to existence as a result of attempts at fitting his History into the Scaligerian chronology.We quote some of the numerous examples of such occurrences.
The modern commentator tells us that “Herodotus confuses king Sesostris with the king Psammetix I”.
Also: “Pittacus could not have met Croesus in 560 b.c., since he had died in 570 b.c.”.Another event related by Herodotus is commented upon thusly: “It is an error made by Herodotus… Solon could not have met Croesus”.
But how can this be true?
Herodotus devotes an entire page to relating the interactions between Croesus and Solon.
The chronology, on the other hand, tells us no The commentators also accuse Herodotus of dating solar eclipses incorrectly; and so on, and so forth.
We should note that the choice of one chronological version among several contradicting ones is far from simple.
There had been a conflict between the so-called short and long chronologies of Egypt that were developed in the XIX century.
The short chronology is the one currently used, but even it contains a great many deep contradictions which still remain unresolved.
The most prominent German Egyptologist, H. Brugsch, wrote: “When the reader inquires about whether any epochs and historical moments concerning the Pharaohs can be considered to possess a finite chronological assessment, and when his curiosity makes him turn to the tables compiled by a great variety of scientists, he will be surprised to find himself confronted with a large number of opinions on the chronological calculations of the Pharaoh era belonging to the representatives of the newest school.
For instance, the German scientists date the reign of Menes, the first Egyptian Pharaoh, as having commenced in the following years: Boeckh dates this event to 5702 b.c., Unger – to 5613 b.c., Brugsch – to 4455 b.c., Lauth – to 4157 b.c., Lepsius – to 5702 b.c., Bunsen – to 3623 b.c.
The difference between the two extreme datings is mind-boggling, since it amounts to 2079 years… The most fundamental research conducted by competent scientists for the verification of the chronological sequence of the Pharaohs’ reigns and the order of dynastical succession, had also proved the necessity of allowing for simultaneous and parallel reigns that would greatly reduce the summary reigning time of the thirty Manetho’s dynasties.
Despite all the scientific discoveries made in this area of Egyptology, the numeric data condition remains in an extremely unsatisfactory condition to this day [late XIX century – ]”.
The situation hasn’t improved to the present day.
Modern tables date the beginning of the reign of Menes differently, to “approximately 3100 b.c.,”“roughly 3000 b.c.,” etc.
The fluctuation span for this date amounts to 2700 years.
If we consider other opinions – those of the French Egyptologists [late XIX century – ], for instance, the situation becomes even more complex: Champollion gives the dating as 5867 b.c., Lesueur – as 5770 b.c., Mariette – as 5004 b.c., Chabas – as 4000 b.c., Meyer – as 3180 b.c., Andrzejewski – as 2850 b.c., Wilkinson – as 2320 b.c., Palmer – as 2224 b.c., etc.
The difference between the datings of Champollion and Palmer equals three thousand six hundred fourty three years.
No commentary is needed, really.
We discover that, generally,“Egyptology,which had poured some light over the perpetual darkness that covered the ancient age of Egypt, only came into existence 80 years ago,” as Chantepie de la Saussaye wrote at the end of the XIX century (Chantepie de la Saussaye, Manual of the Science of Religion.
London-New York, Longmans,Green and Co., 1891.).
He also said that “it has been the private domain of a very few researches… alack and alas, the results of their research have been popularized in too much haste… Thus, many erroneous views entered the circulation, which resulted in the inevitable sobering when Egyptology became a lot less in vogue and the excessive trust in the results of the research was lost… To this day, the construction of the Egyptian chronology remains impossible”.
Unfortunately, the development of the entire critical concept and the propagation of the hypercritical current of the late XIX – early XX century froze, due to the sheer lack of objective statistic methods at the time, ones that could provide for the independent and objective verification of the previous chronological identifications.</entry>
  <entry author_id="336060" end="70" start="35">The establishment of the Egyptian chronology presented some substantial difficulties, since a great many documents contain chronological contradictions.
Let us examine the correlation between the classical History by Herodotus, and the consensual chronology.
For instance, during his consecutive and coherent account of Egyptian history, Herodotus calls Cheops the successor of Rhampsinitos (Herodotus.
The Histories ofHerodotus, etc. London and New York, Everyman’s Library, 1964.).
The modern commentator will immediately “correct” in the following manner: “Herodotus creates confusion in chronology of Egypt – Rhampsinitos (Ramses II) was a king of the XIX dynasty (1345-1200 b.c.), whilst Cheops belonged to the IV (2600-2480 b.c.)”.
The discrepancy here equals 1200 years, no less.
Just think of what the figure implies and of its sheer value: twelve hundred years.
Let us carry on.According to Herodotus,Asychis was succeeded by Anysis.
Modern commentary is also rash to tell us that “Herodotus leaps from the end of the IV dynasty (about 2480 b.c.) to the beginning of the Ethiopian reign in Egypt (about 715 b.c.)”  The leap is one of 1800 years.
Eighteen hundred years!
In general, it turns out that “The chronology of kings given by Herodotus does not concur with that found in the fragments of Manetho’s list of kings”.As a rule, the chronology of Herodotus is much shorter than Scaliger’s version.
The temporal distances between kings according to Herodotus are often thousands of years shorter than corresponding periods as given by Manethon.
The History of Herodotus contains a great number of “minor errors”, those of 30-40 years; however, they only come to existence as a result of attempts at fitting his History into the Scaligerian chronology.We quote some of the numerous examples of such occurrences.
The modern commentator tells us that “Herodotus confuses king Sesostris with the king Psammetix I”.
Also: “Pittacus could not have met Croesus in 560 b.c., since he had died in 570 b.c.”.Another event related by Herodotus is commented upon thusly: “It is an error made by Herodotus… Solon could not have met Croesus”.
But how can this be true?
Herodotus devotes an entire page to relating the interactions between Croesus and Solon.
The chronology, on the other hand, tells us no The commentators also accuse Herodotus of dating solar eclipses incorrectly; and so on, and so forth.
We should note that the choice of one chronological version among several contradicting ones is far from simple.
There had been a conflict between the so-called short and long chronologies of Egypt that were developed in the XIX century.
The short chronology is the one currently used, but even it contains a great many deep contradictions which still remain unresolved.
The most prominent German Egyptologist, H. Brugsch, wrote: “When the reader inquires about whether any epochs and historical moments concerning the Pharaohs can be considered to possess a finite chronological assessment, and when his curiosity makes him turn to the tables compiled by a great variety of scientists, he will be surprised to find himself confronted with a large number of opinions on the chronological calculations of the Pharaoh era belonging to the representatives of the newest school.
For instance, the German scientists date the reign of Menes, the first Egyptian Pharaoh, as having commenced in the following years: Boeckh dates this event to 5702 b.c., Unger – to 5613 b.c., Brugsch – to 4455 b.c., Lauth – to 4157 b.c., Lepsius – to 5702 b.c., Bunsen – to 3623 b.c.
The difference between the two extreme datings is mind-boggling, since it amounts to 2079 years… The most fundamental research conducted by competent scientists for the verification of the chronological sequence of the Pharaohs’ reigns and the order of dynastical succession, had also proved the necessity of allowing for simultaneous and parallel reigns that would greatly reduce the summary reigning time of the thirty Manetho’s dynasties.
Despite all the scientific discoveries made in this area of Egyptology, the numeric data condition remains in an extremely unsatisfactory condition to this day [late XIX century – ]”.
The situation hasn’t improved to the present day.
Modern tables date the beginning of the reign of Menes differently, to “approximately 3100 b.c.,”“roughly 3000 b.c.,” etc.
The fluctuation span for this date amounts to 2700 years.
If we consider other opinions – those of the French Egyptologists [late XIX century – ], for instance, the situation becomes even more complex: Champollion gives the dating as 5867 b.c., Lesueur – as 5770 b.c., Mariette – as 5004 b.c., Chabas – as 4000 b.c., Meyer – as 3180 b.c., Andrzejewski – as 2850 b.c., Wilkinson – as 2320 b.c., Palmer – as 2224 b.c., etc.
The difference between the datings of Champollion and Palmer equals three thousand six hundred fourty three years.
No commentary is needed, really.
We discover that, generally,“Egyptology,which had poured some light over the perpetual darkness that covered the ancient age of Egypt, only came into existence 80 years ago,” as Chantepie de la Saussaye wrote at the end of the XIX century (Chantepie de la Saussaye, Manual of the Science of Religion.
London-New York, Longmans,Green and Co., 1891.).
He also said that “it has been the private domain of a very few researches… alack and alas, the results of their research have been popularized in too much haste… Thus, many erroneous views entered the circulation, which resulted in the inevitable sobering when Egyptology became a lot less in vogue and the excessive trust in the results of the research was lost… To this day, the construction of the Egyptian chronology remains impossible”.
Unfortunately, the development of the entire critical concept and the propagation of the hypercritical current of the late XIX – early XX century froze, due to the sheer lack of objective statistic methods at the time, ones that could provide for the independent and objective verification of the previous chronological identifications.</entry>
  <entry author_id="575387" end="161" start="70">seconds, a concept known as Planck time.
After this, the time is grouped into epochs.
At first, these are very short periods (seconds or minutes).
The Bogdanov publications purport to have discovered what happened before this earliest moment and even before the moment of the Big Bang itself.]]

In 1999 and 2002 Grichka and Igor Bogdanov obtained Ph.D. degrees on the basis of two theses (Grichka in mathematics and Igor in theoretical physics) from the University of Bourgogne.
In 1999 Grichka Bogdanov received the lowest possible passing grade of "honorable" for his thesis Quantum fluctuations of the signature of the metric at the Planck scale, with the condition that his thesis be considerably rewritten.
On the same day, Igor Bogdanov failed the defense of his thesis Topological Origin of Inertia.
His advisor subsequently agreed to allow him to obtain a doctorate if Igor could publish three peer-reviewed journal articles.
After publishing the requisite articles, Igor successfully defended his thesis three years later on a different topic under the responsibility of two co-advisors Topological State of Spacetime at the Planck Scale, also receiving the same lowest possible passing grade of "honorable", one that is seldom given, as told to New York Times science reporter Dennis Overbye by Bogdanov Ph.D. advisor Dr. Daniel Sternheimer.
In justifying the conferring of doctoral degrees to the Bogdanovs, Dr. Sternheimer told the Times, "These guys worked for 10 years without pay.
They have the right to have their work recognized with a diploma, which is nothing much these days."
(New York Times, November 9th 2002)

The two brothers published a total of six papers in physics and mathematics journals, including Annals of Physics and Classical and Quantum Gravity, which are both reviewed by referees.
After reading the abstracts of both theses, German physicist Max Niedermaier formed the opinion that the papers were pseudoscientific, consisting of dense technical jargon written in a manner similar to the Sokal Affair, written to prove shortcomings in the peer-review system of theoretical physics.
On 22 October 2002, Niedermaier sent an email to this effect to physicist Ted Newman, and the email was then widely distributed.
An eventual recipient of the email, the American mathematical physicist John Baez, created a discussion thread on the Usenet newsgroup sci.physics.research titled "Physics bitten by reverse Alan Sokal hoax?"
which quickly grew to hundreds of posts in length.

This controversy immediately attracted worldwide attention, both in the physics community and in the international popular press.
Following Niedermaier, the majority of the participants in the Usenet discussion thread created by Baez also made the assumption that the work was a deliberate hoax, which the Bogdanov brothers have continued to deny.
After hearing that the Bogdanovs disputed that their work was a hoax, Niedermaier issued a private and public apology to the Bogdanov brothers on 24 October 2002 for having so assumed from the outset.
However, he has endorsed neither the validity nor merit of the work in question.
The following are excerpts from the 15 Thesis Reports of Igor and Grichka Bogdanov:

Jack Morava, from the Johns Hopkins University: "the thesis work of Igor Bogdanov is of great interest, dominated by new ideas with fundamental physical implications in cosmology and in many other fields connected with gravitation."
In May 2001, the journal Classical and Quantum Gravity (CQG) reviewed an article authored by Igor &amp; Grickha Bogdanov, entitled "Topological theory of the initial singularity of spacetime".
One of the referee reports stated that the article was "Sound, original, and of interest.
With revisions I expect the paper to be suitable for publication."
The paper was accepted seven months later.

However, after the publication of the article and the publicity surrounding the controversy, the editorial board of the journal issued a statement, saying, in part, "Regrettably, despite the best efforts, the refereeing process cannot be 100% effective.
Thus the paper made it through the review process even though, in retrospect, it does not meet the standards expected of articles in this journal.
The paper was discussed extensively at the annual Editorial Board meeting and there was general agreement that it should not have been published.
Since then several steps have been taken to further improve the peer review process in order to improve the quality assessment on articles submitted to the journal and reduce the likelihood that this could happen again."
The paper in question has, however, not been withdrawn from the publication.

In 2001, the Czechoslovak Journal of Physics accepted an article written by Igor Bogdanov, entitled "Topological Origin of Inertia".
The referee's  report concluded: "In my opinion the results of the paper can be considered as original ones.
I recommend the paper for publication but in a revised form."

In 2002, the Chinese Journal of Physics published "The KMS state of spacetime at the Planck scale", from Igor Bogdanov.
The  report stated that "the viewpoint presented in this paper can be interesting as a possible approach of the Planck scale physics."
Some corrections were requested.

Not all review evaluations were positive.
Eli Hawkins, acting as a referee for the Journal of Physics A, suggested rejecting one of the Bogdanovs' papers: "It would take up too much space to enumerate all the mistakes: indeed it is difficult to say where one error ends and the next begins.
In conclusion, I would not recommend that this paper be published in this, or any, journal."

Several of the published papers are nearly identical, differing only in minor respects and in their publication title.
After the start of the controversy on Usenet, most comments were critical of the Bogdanovs' work.
The following are examples:

Lubos Motl: "he Bogdanoff brothers are proposing something that has, speculatively, the potential to be an alternative story about quantum gravity... What they are proposing a potential new calculational framework for gravity.
I find it unlikely that these things will work but it is probably more likely than loop quantum gravity and other discrete approaches whose lethal problems have already been identified in detail"  Prior to the controversy, the reports on the Bogdanov theses and most of the journal referees' reports spoke favorably of their work, describing it as original and containing interesting ideas.
This has been the basis of concerns raised about the efficacy of the peer-review system that the scientific community and academia use to determine the merit of submitted manuscripts for publication; one concern is that over-worked and unpaid refeeres may not be able to thoroughly judge the value of a paper in the little time they can afford to spend on it.
Questions were also raised in the sci.physics.research newsgroup about the fact that some aspects of theoretical physics have become so abstract, extensively relying on unproven conjectures, that verifying many statements written in published papers has become somewhat impossible.

Regarding the Bogdanov publications, physicist Steve Carlip remarked: Whereas theoretical physicist Lubos Motl commented:  In addition to a few articles in print, the Bogdanov affair has been discussed extensively in various webpages and blogs on the Internet; these discussions have taken place on various newsgroups and web fora, and the Bogdanov brothers have often participated in the discussions, both under their real names, and under several pseudonyms; they later acknowledged doing so.
Most pseudonyms purported physicists or mathematicians, defending the Bogdanovs' work and sometimes insulting their critics (among them the Nobel prize recipient Georges Charpak).
A few participants in these discussions responded in a similar manner, specifically accusing the Bogdanovs of evading scientific criticism, or lying about what they actually wrote or said.

Participants in the discussions were particularly unconvinced by the affirmation in one of the Bogdanov papers that "whatever the orientation, the plane of oscillation of Foucault's pendulum is necessarily aligned with the initial singularity marking the origin of physical space."
The Bogdanovs explained that this sentence would only be clear in the context of topological field theory.
Some physicists found this statement and subsequent attempts at its explanation somewhat peculiar, since Foucault's pendulum trajectory is accurately predicted by classical mechanics and even more precisely by General Relativity.

The participation of an unidentified "Professor Yang" created additional problems in determining the truth of the matter; an individual publishing under this name wrote to a number of individuals and on the Internet to defend the Bogdanov papers.
This individual wrote to physicists John Baez, Jacques Diestler and Peter Woit; journalist Dennis Overbye from the New York Times; and on numerous physics blogs and fora, signing his name "Professor L. Yang - Theoretical Physics Laboratory, International Institute of Mathematical Physics - HKU/Clear Water Bay, Kowloon, Hong Kong."
using an e-mail address at the domain th-phys.edu.hk.

The Bogdanovs have alleged several times that the "domain name "th-phys.edu.hk" was officially owned by Hong Kong University."
This was not confirmed officially by HKU and no Prof. Yang existed on the roster of the HKU Physics department.
The DNS record of th-phys.edu.hk did list the HKUST street address, but the domain had been registered by Igor Bogdanov, and e-mail messages from Professor L. Yang originated from a dial-up IP address in Paris, France.
The registration of th-phys.edu.hk has not been renewed.

Suspicions were consequently raised that Professor L. Yang was in fact a pseudonym of the Bogdanovs.
However, Igor Bogdanov has maintained that Professor Yang is a real mathematical physicist with expertise in KMS theory, a friend of his, and that he was posting anonymously from Igor's apartment.
As yet, no such individual has come forward publically to unambiguously identify himself as this "Professor Yang" and to identify his credentials and institutional affiliation, and no published record of this "Professor Yang" has been offered for examination.

Following this pattern, another academic domain name was also registered in Latvia (http://phys-maths.edu.lv/), hosting the  Mathematical Center of Riemannian Cosmosology.
Again, this apparent educational institution was registered by Igor Bogdanov.
However, in this case, no claim was implied of an affiliation with an official educational institution.
At the start of the controversy in 2002, numerous articles were published in worldwide media, such as the New York Times, the Washington Post, the International Herald Tribune, the Economist, but also Pravda, and Die Zeit.

In 2002, the Bogdanovs launched a new weekly TV show Rayons X on French public channel France 2.
In August 2004, they presented a 90-minute special cosmology program in which they introduced their theory among other cosmological scenarios.
They were also frequently invited to numerous TV talk shows to promote their book.
The French mainstream media, in both the press and on the Internet, covered the renewed controversy to some extent; media outlets that have reported upon it include Europe 1, Acrimed, Ciel et Espace, and Le Monde.

In early 2005, the Bogdanovs sued Ciel et Espace over the publication of an critical article entitled "The Mystification of the Bogdanovs."
The trial should take place at the end of 2005 or the beginning of 2006.
An indication of the impact that these theories may have on theoretical physics can be inferred by the references made to them in subsequent papers by other theoretical physicists.
The Bogdanov papers are cited a total of 3 times on the SPIRES database, for 6 published papers and one unpublished preprint.
This figure is extremely low when evaluated against the number of citations made to papers written by other physicists who have given critical evaluations of the Bogdanovs work.
As a matter of comparison, a recent detailed analysis of citation statistics reveals that between 1000 and 2000 citations are expected from somenone who advances to a full professor position or for a fellowship of the American Physical Society, and around 8000 citations are expected for members of the US National Academy of Sciences.
To focus on cosmological scenarios, a recent and somewhat controversial cosmological model, the ekpyrotic universe was published in 2001 and has already been cited more than 350 times.

The Bogdanovs have not, at the time of writing, published any scientific paper since 2003; however, in collaboration with theoretical physicist Arkadiusz Jadczyk, they have founded the International Institute of Mathematical Physics in order to study and develop their theories.
Despite the similarity of name, this is unaffiliated with the reputable Erwin Schrödinger International Institute for Mathematical Physics in Vienna, Austria.
In 2004, two papers have been published in peer-reviewed journals by A. Jadczyk within the framework of this Institute.
These two papers are not closely related to the issues addressed in the previous Bogdanovs' papers.

In 2004, the Bogdanovs published a successful popular science book, Avant Le Big-Bang (Before the Big Bang), based on a simplified version of their theses, where they also presented their point of view about the affair.
Both the book and the Bogdanovs' television shows have been criticized for elementary scientific inaccuracies.
Examples cited from Avant Le Big-Bang by critics include a statement that the "golden number" φ (Phi) is transcendental, which the Bogdanovs allege to be an editorial misprint, and an assumption that the limit of a decreasing sequence is always zero.
Despite these criticisms, some point out that the Bogdanovs deserve credit for bringing the subjects of cosmology and relativity to a wider audience.

The Bogdanov Affair also had some unexpected consequences in the world of theoretical physics.
Some media articles have cast a negative light on this field, stating that it has become impossible to distinguish a valid paper from a hoax.
Some people used the affair to criticize the present status of string theory.
Many comments have been made on the possible shortcomings of the referal system for published articles, and also on the criteria for acceptance of a thesis and subsequent delivery of a Ph.D degree.</entry>
  <entry author_id="454491" end="173" start="161">Archaeological findings show that nomadic hunter-gatherers lived along the Nile during the Pleistocene.
Traces of these early peoples appear in the form of artifacts and rock carvings along the Nile and in the oases.
By about 6000 B.C., organized agriculture and large building construction had appeared in the Nile Valley.
Many theories have been proposed regarding the origins of these early Egyptians, but the most widely accepted today based on the continuum of scientific evidence is that prehistoric Egyptian society was formed through the merging of North and Northeast African as well as Southwest Asian peoples, who moved to the Nile Valley successively after the Ice Age.

Modern genetics reveals this amalgam in Egyptians today.
According to more than one study, modern Egyptians are characterized by paternal lineages common to North Africans primarily, as well as Near Eastern peoples.
These lineages would have spread during the Neolithic and maintained by the predynastic period.
In addition, studies based on the maternal lineages closely links the Egyptian population with people from modern Ethiopia,.
It's worth nothing that the ancient Egyptians themselves traced their origin to a land they called Punt, or "Ta Nteru" ("Land of the Gods"), which most Egyptologists locate in the area encompassing the Ethiopian Highlands.

A recent bioanthropological study on the dental morphology of ancient Egyptians confirms that their dental traits were most characteristic of North African and to a lesser extent Southwest Asian populations.
The study was also able to establish biological continuity from the predyanstic to the post-pharaonic period.
The samples used in the analysis included skeletal material from the Hawara tombs of Fayum, which was found to most closely resemble the Badarian series of the predyanstic,.</entry>
  <entry author_id="454491" end="190" start="173">Ancient Egyptian constitutes an independent branch of the Afro-Asiatic language phylum.
Its closest relatives are the Berber, Semitic, and Beja groups of languages.
Written records of the Egyptian language have been dated from about 3200 BC, making it one of the oldest and longest documented languages.
Scholars group Egyptian into six major chronological divisions:Consists of inscriptions from the late Predynastic and Early Dynastic period.
The earliest known evidence of Egyptian hieroglyphic writing appears on Naqada II pottery vessels.The language of the Old Kingdom and First Intermediate Period.
The Pyramid Texts are the largest body of literature written in this phase of the language.
Tomb walls of elite Egyptians from this period also bear autobiographical writings representing Old Egyptian.
One of its distinguishing characteristics is the tripling of ideograms, phonograms, and determinatives to indicate the plural.
Overall, it does not differ significantly from the next stage.Often dubbed Classical Egyptian, this stage is known from a variety of textual evidence in hieroglyphic and hieratic scripts dated from about the Middle Kingdom.
It includes funerary texts inscribed on sarcophagi such as the Coffin Texts; wisdom texts instructing people on how to lead a life that exemplified the ancient Egyptian philosophical worldview (see the Ipuwer papyrus); tales detailing the adventures of a certain individual, for example the Story of Sinhue; medical and scientific texts such as the Edwin Smith Papyrus and the Ebers papyrus; and poetic texts praising a god or a pharaoh, like the Hymn to the Nile.
The Egyptian vernacular already began to change from the written language as evidenced by some Middle Kingdom hieratic texts, but classical Middle Egyptian continued to be written in formal contexts well into the Late Dynastic period (sometimes referred to as Late Middle Egyptian).Records of this stage appear in the second part of the New Kingdom, considered by many as the "Golden Age" of ancient Egyptian civilization.
It contains a rich body of religious and secular literature, comprising such famous examples as the Story of Wenamun and the Instructions of Ani.
It was also the language of Ramesside administration.
Late Egyptian is not totally distinct from Middle Egyptian, as many "classicisms" appear in historical and literary documents of this phase.
However, the difference between Middle and Late Egyptian is greater than that between Middle and Old Egyptian.
It's also a better representative than Middle Egyptian of the spoken language in the New Kingdom and beyond.
Hieroglyphic orthography saw an enormous expansion of its graphemic inventory between the Late Dynastic and Ptolemaic periods.For many years, the earliest known hieroglyphic inscription was the Narmer Palette, found during excavations at Hierakonpolis (modern Kawm al-Ahmar) in the 1890s, which has been dated to c.3200 BC.</entry>
  <entry author_id="10795" end="207" start="190">Beginning from around 2700 BC, Egyptians used pictograms to represent vocal sounds -- both vowel and consonant vocalizations (see Hieroglyph: Script).
By 2000 BC, 26 pictograms were being used to represent 24 (known) main vocal sounds.
The world's oldest known alphabet (c. 1800 BC) is only an abjad system and was derived from these uniliteral signs as well as other Egyptian hieroglyphs.

The hieroglyphic script finally fell out of use around the 4th century AD.
Attempts to decipher it began after the 15th century (see Hieroglyphica).
The Egyptian religions, embodied in Egyptian mythology, were a succession of beliefs held by the people of Egypt, as early as predynastic times and all the way until the coming of Christianity and Islam in the Graeco-Roman era.
These were conducted by Egyptian priests or magicians, but the use of magic and spells is questioned.

The religious nature of ancient Egyptian civilization influenced its contribution to the arts of the ancient world.
Many of the great works of ancient Egypt depict gods, goddesses, and pharaohs, who were also considered divine.
Ancient Egyptian art in general is characterized by the idea of order.

The art and science of engineering was present in Egypt, such as accurately determining the position of points and the distances between them (known as surveying).
These skills were used to outline pyramid bases.
The Egyptian pyramids took the geometric shape formed from a polygonal base and a point, called the apex, by triangular faces.
Hydraulic Cement was first invented by the Egyptians.
The Al Fayyum Irrigation (water works) was one of the main agricultural breadbaskets of the ancient world.
There is evidence of ancient Egyptian pharaohs of the twelfth dynasty using the natural lake of the Fayyum as a reservoir to store surpluses of water for use during the dry seasons.
From the time of the First dynasty or before, the Egyptians mined turquoise in Sinai Peninsula.</entry>
  <entry author_id="454491" end="222" start="207">Ancient Egyptian constitutes an independent part of the Afro-Asiatic language phylum.
Its closest relatives are the Berber, Semitic, and Beja groups of languages.
Written records of the Egyptian language have been dated from about 3200 BC, making it one of the oldest and longest documented languages.
Scholars group Egyptian into six major chronological divisions: For many years, the earliest known hieroglyphic inscription was the Narmer Palette, found during excavations at Hierakonpolis (modern Kawm al-Ahmar) in the 1890s, which has been dated to c.3150 BC.
However recent archaeological findings reveal that symbols on Gerzean pottery, c.3250 BC, resemble the traditional hieroglyph forms.
Also in 1998 a German archeological team under Günter Dreyer excavating at Abydos (modern Umm el-Qa'ab) uncovered tomb U-j, which belonged to a Predynastic ruler, and they recovered three hundred clay labels inscribed with proto-hieroglyphics dating to the Naqada IIIA period, circa 33rd century BC.

Egyptologists refer to Egyptian writing as hieroglyphs, today standing as the world's earliest known writing system.
The hieroglyphic script was partly syllabic, partly ideographic.
Hieratic is a cursive form of Egyptian hieroglyphs and was first used during the First Dynasty (c. 2925 BC – c. 2775 BC).
The term Demotic, in the context of Egypt, came to refer to both the script and the language that followed the Late Ancient Egyptian stage, i.e. from the Nubian 25th dynasty until its marginalization by the Greek Koine in the early centuries AD.
After the conquest of Amr ibn al-A'as in the 7th century AD, the Coptic language survived as a spoken language into the Middle Ages.
Today, it continues to be the liturgical language of the Christian minority.

Beginning from around 2700 BC, Egyptians used pictograms to represent vocal sounds -- both vowel and consonant vocalizations (see Hieroglyph: Script).
By 2000 BC, 26 pictograms were being used to represent 24 (known) main vocal sounds.
The world's oldest known alphabet (c. 1800 BC) is only an abjad system and was derived from these uniliteral signs as well as other Egyptian hieroglyphs.</entry>
  <entry author_id="454491" end="257" start="222">Archaeological evidence indicates that a developed Egyptian society extends far into prehistory (see Predynastic Egypt).
The Nile River, around which much of the population of the country clusters, has been the lifeline for Egyptian culture since nomadic hunter-gatherers began living along the Nile during the Pleistocene.
Traces of these early peoples appear in the form of artifacts and rock carvings along the terraces of the Nile and in the oases.

Along the Nile, in the 10th millennium BC, a grain-grinding culture using the earliest type of sickle blades had been replaced by another culture of hunters, fishers, and gathering peoples using stone tools.
Evidence also indicates human habitation in the southwestern corner of Egypt, near the Sudan border, before 8000 BC.
Climate changes and/or overgrazing around 8000 BC began to desiccate the pastoral lands of Egypt, eventually forming the Sahara (c.2500 BC), and early tribes naturally migrated to the Nile River where they developed a settled agricultural economy and more centralized society (see Nile: History).
There is evidence of pastoralism and cultivation of cereals in the East Sahara in the 7th millennium BC.

By about 6000 BC, organized agriculture and large building construction had appeared in the Nile Valley.
At this time, Egyptians in the southwestern corner of Egypt were herding cattle and also constructing large buildings.
Mortar (masonry) was in use by 4000 BC.
The Predynastic Period continues through this time, variously held to begin with the Naqada culture.
Some authorities however place the start of the Predynastic Period earlier, in the Lower Paleolithic.

Between 5500 and 3100 BC, during Egypt's Predynastic Period, small settlements flourished along the Nile.
By 3300 BC, just before the first Egyptian dynasty, Egypt was divided into two kingdoms, known as Upper Egypt (Ancient Egyptian: Ta Shemau) and Lower Egypt (Ancient Egyptian: Ta Mehu).
The dividing line was drawn roughly in the area of modern Cairo.

The history of ancient Egypt proper starts with Egypt as a unified state, which occurred sometime around 3150 BC.
Menes, who unified Upper and Lower Egypt, was the first king.
Egyptian culture was remarkably stable and changed little over a period of nearly 3000 years.
This includes religion, customs, art expression, architecture and social structure.

Egyptian chronology, which involves regnal years, began around this time.
The conventional Egyptian chronology is the chronology accepted during the 20th century, but it does not include any of the major revision proposals that have also been made in that time.
Even within a single work, often archeologists will offer several possible dates or even several whole chronologies as possibilities.
Consequently, there may be discrepancies between dates shown here and in articles on particular rulers.
Often there are also several possible spellings of the names.
Typically, Egyptologists divide the history of pharaonic civilization using a schedule laid out first by Manetho's Aegyptaica (History of Egypt).
A 2006 bioanthropological study on the dental morphology of ancient Egyptians shows dental traits most characteristic of indigenous North Africans and to a lesser extent Near Eastern populations.
The study also establishes biological continuity from the predynastic to the post-pharaonic periods.
Among the samples included is skeletal material from the Hawara tombs of Fayum, which was found to most closely resemble the Badarian series of the predynastic.
A study based on stature and body proportions also suggests that Nilotic or tropical body characteristics were also present in some later groups, as the Egyptian empire expanded southward during the New Kingdom.

Genetics analysis of modern Egyptians reveals that they are characterized by paternal lineages common to North Africans primarily, and to some Near Eastern peoples.
These lineages spread during the Neolithic and were maintained by the predynastic period.
Studies based on the maternal lineages also show that Egyptians are related to people from the Horn of Africa.

In c. 450 BC, Herodotus wrote, "the Colchians are Egyptians... on the fact that they are dark-skinned (melanchrôs) and wooly-haired (oulothrix)" (Histories Book 2:104).
Melanchros was also used by Homer to describe the sunburnt complexion of Odysseus (Od.
16.176).</entry>
  <entry author_id="725935" end="272" start="257">The achievements of ancient Egypt are well known, and the civilization achieved a very high standard of productivity and sophiscation.
The art and science of engineering was present in Egypt, such as accurately determining the position of points and the distances between them (known as surveying).
These skills were used to outline pyramid bases.
The Egyptian pyramids took the geometric shape formed from a polygonal base and a point, called the apex, by triangular faces.
Hydraulic cement was first invented by the Egyptians.
The Al Fayyum Irrigation (water works) was one of the main agricultural breadbaskets of the ancient world.
There is evidence of ancient Egyptian Pharaohs of the twelfth dynasty using the natural lake of the Fayyum as a reservoir to store surpluses of water for use during the dry seasons.
From the time of the First dynasty or before, the Egyptians mined turquoise in the Sinai Peninsula.

The sarcophagus found in the great pyramid has been recently re-examined.
According to the author Nigel Appleby ('Hall of the Gods') the holes drilled in the sides were considered to have been drilled at a speed and bore rate that cannot be reproduced today.
Independent published corroboration by scientists and engineers is awaited for both of these claims.

The earliest evidence (circa 1600 BC) of traditional empiricism is credited to Egypt, as evidenced by the Edwin Smith and Ebers papyri.
The roots of the scientific method may be traced back to the ancient Egyptians.
The Egyptians created their own alphabet (however, it is debated as to whether they were the first to do this because of the margin of error on carbon dated tests), decimal system and complex mathematical formularizations, in the form of the Moscow and Rhind Mathematical Papyri.
The golden ratio seems to be reflected in many constructions, such as the Egyptian pyramids, however this may be the consequence of combining the use of knotted ropes with an intuitive sense of proportion and harmony.</entry>
</article>
