<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="876" title="Motor neuron disease" authors="1" lines="17">
  <entry author_id="250530" end="17" start="0">Contrary to commonly held beliefs about MND, cognitive change can and does occur in between 33-50% of patients.
A small proportion exhibit a form of frontotemporal dementia characterised by behavioural abnormalities such as disinhibition, apathy, and personality changes.
A small proportion of patients may also suffer from an aphasia, which causes difficulty in naming specific objects.
A larger proportion (up to 50%) suffer from a milder version of cognitive change which primarily affects what is known as executive function.
Briefly, this is the ability of an individual to initiate, inhibit, sustain, and switch attention and is involved in the organisation of complex tasks down to smaller components.
Often patients with such changes find themselves unable to do the family finances or drive a car.
depression is surprisingly rare in MND (around 5-20%)relative to the frequency with which it is found in other, less severe, neurological disorders e.g. ~50% in MS and Parkinson's Disease, ~20% in Epilepsy.
Depression does not necessarily increase as the symptoms progress, and in fact many patients report being happy with their quality of life despite profound disability.
This may reflect the use of coping strategies such as reevaluating what is important in life.

In North America, the most commonly occurring mutation is known as A4V and occurs in upto 50% of SOD1 cases.
In people of Scandinavian extraction there is a relatively benign mutation called D90A which is associated with a slow progression.
Future research is concentrating on identifying new genetic mutations and the clinical syndrome associated with them.

In addition, neuroimaging and neuropathology has demonstrated extra-motor changes in the frontal lobes including the inferior frontal gyrus, superior frontal gyrus, anterior cingulate cortex, and superior temporal gyrus.
The degree of pathology in these areas has been directly related to the degree of cognitive change experienced by the patient, if any.

Some promising basic science underway is examining gene therapy and the use of stem cells, though the ethical and legal difficulties surrounding the harvesting of stem cells have slowed progress, particularly in the United States.
Recent advances have been made in the UK and South Korea, but the research remains at an early stage and confined to the laboratoy.
Clinical trials are at least five years in the future.</entry>
</article>
