<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="898" title="Antimony" authors="3" lines="70">
  <entry author_id="62" end="16" start="0">Antimony is a chemical element in the periodic table that has the symbol Sb and atomic number 51.
A metalloid, antimony has four allotropic forms.
The stable form of antimony is a blue-white metal.
Yellow and black antimony are unstable non-metals.
Used in flame-proofing, paints, ceramics, enamels, a wide variety of alloys, and rubber.

Antimony has poor heat and electrical conductance.
This is brittle, laminated or crystalline, fusible, and vaporizes at a low temperatures.
A metalloid, antimony, resembles metal in its appearance and physical properties, but does not chemically react as a metal.
It is also attacked by oxidizing acids and halogens.Antimony is increasingly being used in the semiconductor industry in the production of diodes, infrared detectors, and Hall-effect devices.
As an alloy, this semi-metal greatly increases lead's hardness and mechanical strength.
Other uses; Antimony compounds in the form of; oxides, sulfides, sodium antimonate, and antimony trichloride are used in the making of flame-proofing compounds, ceramic enamels, glass, paints, and pottery.
Antimony (Greek anti plus monos meaning "a metal not found alone") was recognized in antiquity in various compounds and was later known as a metal at the beginning of the 17th century and possibly earlier.
This element was first scientifically reported by Tholden in 1450.Even though this element is not abundant, it is found in over 100 mineral species.
Alimony is sometimes found native, but more frequently it is found in the sulfide stibnite.
Antimony and many of its compounds are toxic.
WebElements.com - Antimony  EnvironmentalChemistry.com - Antimony</entry>
  <entry author_id="62" end="40" start="16">A metalloid, antimony has four allotropic forms.
The stable form of antimony is a blue-white metal.
Yellow and black antimony are unstable non-metals.
Used in flame-proofing, paints, ceramics, enamels, a wide variety of alloys, and rubber.

Antimony in its elemental form is a silvery white, brittle, fusible, crystalline solid that exhibits poor electrical and heat conductivity properties and vaporizes at a low temperatures.
A metalloid, antimony, resembles metal in its appearance and physical properties, but does not chemically react as a metal.
It is also attacked by oxidizing acids and halogens.

Estimates of the abundance of antimony in the Earth's crust range from 0.2 to 0.5 ppm.
Antimony is chalcophile, occurring with sulfur and the heavy metals, lead, copper, and silver.
Antimony is increasingly being used in the semiconductor industry in the production of diodes, infrared detectors, and Hall-effect devices.
As an alloy, this semi-metal greatly increases lead's hardness and mechanical strength.
The most important use of antimony metal is as a hardener in lead for storage batteries.
Other uses; Antimony compounds in the form of; oxides, sulfides, sodium antimonate, and antimony trichloride are used in the making of flame-proofing compounds, ceramic enamels, glass, paints, and pottery.
Antimony trioxide is the most important of the antimony compounds and is primarily used in flame-retardant formulations.
These flame-retardant applications include such markets as children's clothing, toys, aircraft and automobile seat covers.
Antimony (Greek anti plus monos meaning "a metal not found alone") was recognized in antiquity in various compounds and was later known as a metal at the beginning of the 17th century and possibly earlier.
This element was first scientifically reported by Tholden in 1450.
The natural sulfide of antimony was known and used in Biblical times as medicine and as a cosmetic.
Even though this element is not abundant, it is found in over 100 mineral species.
Antimony is sometimes found native, but more frequently it is found in the sulfide stibnite (SbS) which is the predominant ore mineral.
Commercial forms of antimony are generally ingots, broken pieces, granules, and cast cake.
Other forms are powder, shot, and single crystals.
Antimony and many of its compounds are toxic.
WebElements.com - Antimony  EnvironmentalChemistry.com - Antimony</entry>
  <entry author_id="356300" end="59" start="40">The guidelines are:Many antimony ores are sulfides, such as stibnite () and realgar ().
Antimony pentasulfide is known, but is non-stoichiometric and contains only antimony in the +3 oxidation state.
Several complex anions of antimony and sulfur are known, such as and.

Unlike phosphorus and arsenic, the various antimony oxides do not form well-defined oxoacids.
The hypothetical antimonous acid only exists as its salts, such as sodium antimonite (), formed by fusing sodium oxide and.
Transition metal antimonites are best described as mixed metal oxides.
Antimonic acid exists only as the hydrate, forming salts containing the antimonate anion.
Dehydrating metal salts containing this anion yields mixed oxides.

On the other hand, the antimony oxides are amphoteric, and react with acid to form antimony salts.
Antimony trioxide dissolves in concentrated acid to form antimony oxo- (antimonyl) compounds such as SbOCl and.
Antimony forms two series of halides: and, where X is one of the halogens.
The trihalides antimony trifluoride, antimony trichloride,, and are all molecular compounds having trigonal pyramidal molecular geometry.
The trifluoride is prepared by the reaction of with HF: It is a strong Lewis acid that readily accepts fluoride ions to form the complex anions and.
Molten is a weak electrical conductor.

The trichloride is prepared by dissolving stibnite in hydrochloric acid: The pentahalides and have trigonal bipyramidal molecular geometry in the gas phase, but in the liquid phase, is polymeric, whereas is monomeric.
Antimony pentafluoride is a powerful Lewis acid used to make the superacid fluoroantimonic acid (), and is an important solvent used in the study of noble gas compounds.
Antimony forms antimonides with metals, such as indium antimonide (InSb), and silver antimonide ().
Treating antimonides with acid produces the unstable toxic gas stibine,: Stibine may also be produced by reacting salts with sources of the hydride ion.
Antimony does not react with hydrogen directly to form stibine.</entry>
  <entry author_id="226427" end="70" start="59">There are four known allotropes of antimony: a stable metallic form, and three meta-stable forms which are explosive, black and yellow.
Each has its own distinct physical properties, the most common of which is metallic antimony, a brittle, silver-white shiny metal.
When molten antimony is slowly cooled to metallic antimony, it forms with an hexagonal crystal structure, isomorphic with that of the grey form of arsenic.

The explosive form of antimony is formed from the electrolysis of antimony(III) trichloride, under specific temperatures and concentration.
In a bath of hydrochloric with an antimony anode and platinum foil cathode, explosive antimony is deposited on the latter.
When scratched with a sharp implement, an exothermic reaction occurs and white fumes given off as metallic antimony is formed; alternatively, when rubbed with a pestle in a mortar, an strong detonation occurs.
Black antimony is formed when gaseous metallic antimony is rapidly cooled.
It oxidies in air and is sometimes spontaneously combustible.
At 100 °C, it gradually transforms into the stable form.
Finally, the yellow allotrope of antimony is the most unstable.
While it cannot be produced as the black allotrope by rapid cooling, it can only be formed by introducing oxygen into antimony hydride at -90 °C.</entry>
</article>
