<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="915" title="Andrey Markov" authors="1" lines="22">
  <entry author_id="839661" end="22" start="0">In the beginning of the 1860s Andrey Grigorevich moved to St Petersburg to adopt the job as an asset manager of the  princess Ekaterina Aleksandrovna Valvatyeva.
In 1866 Andrey Andreevich’s school life began with his entrance into Saint Petersburg’s fifth grammar school.
Already  during his school time Andrey was intensily engaging in higher mathematics.
As a 17 years old grammar school pupil  he informed Bunyakovski,  Korkin and  Zolotarev about an apparently new method to solve linear ordinary differential equations and was invited to the so-called Korkin  Saturdays, where Korkin's students regularly met.
At last in 1874 he finished the school and began his studies at the physico-mathematical faculty of St~Petersburg  university.

His pedagogical job began after the defence of his master thesis in autumn 1880.
As a privatdozent he lectured differential and integral calculus.
Later he lecutured alternately „introduction to analysis“, probability  theory (succeeding Chebyshev who had left the university in 1882) and calculus of  differences.
From 1895/96 until 1905 he additionally lectured again diefferential calculus.

One year after the defence of the doctoral thesis he was appointed extraordinary professor (1886) and in the  same year he was elected adjunkt of the academy of sciences.
In 1890, After the death of the  academician Bunyakovski Markov became extraordinary member of the academy.
His promotion to an ordinary professor  of St~Petersburg university followed in autumn 1894.

Finally in 1896 he was elected ordinary member of the academy as the successor  of Chebyshev.
In 1905 he was appointed merited professor and got the right to retire which he immediately used.
Till 1910,  however, he continued to lecture calculus of differences.

Protesting against a decree of the ministry of education Markov rejected from a further teaching  activity at the Saint Petersburg university.
In connection with student’s riots in 1908 professor and lecturers of Saint Petersburg university were ordered to observe their students.
Firstly Markov rejected from accepting this  decree and after that he wrote an explanation where he expressed his decline from being an “agent of the governance”.
Finally he did not see any way except from a full retirement from the university.

In 1913 the council of St~Petersburg elected nine scientists honorary members of the university.
Markov was among them, but only his election was not affirmed by the minister of education.
The affirmation was done only four years later, after the February revolution in 1917.</entry>
</article>
