<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="922" title="Anxiety" authors="6" lines="212">
  <entry author_id="19858" end="26" start="0">Drug therapy acknowledges that anxiety attacks are caused by an underlying biochemical imbalance.
Unfortunately, medications fail to treat the underlying cause of anxiety attacks.
One study showed that about 40% of patients using drugs to suppress symptoms depression may have some benefit leaving about 60% of patients with treatment resistant depression.
See Insel TR (2006) the same would apply to anxiety attacks.

Psychonutritionists look upon anxiety attacks as being caused by an excess production of adrenaline, not necessarily as a result of any thought processes, or memories, but rather due to an underlying biological abnormality.
These internally driven fear hormones (mainly adrenaline and cortisol) are often associated with some environmental cue or thought, which then may become a stimulus for the adrenergic reaction.
In psychology this is known as reverse conditioning that pairs any behaviour with a stimulus that happens to be in the environment or mind.
Thus when a person is flooded with stress hormones and finds him/herself standing at that moment in a lift, the lift can become the stimulus of the fear hormone.
This explains the wide variety of phobias and unreasonable fear reactions.

Adrenaline is a hormone that functions to convert sugar stores such as GLYCOGEN into glucose.
Glucose is the universal source of biological energy called ATP.
Without that energy the body cannot manufacture the feel good neurotransmitters such as serotonin.

The brain although 2% of body weight requires about 60-70% of all available glucose to energize brain activity, whether asleep or awake.
Thus when the brain is deprived of energy for only a few seconds it is threatened with energy starvation.
This will trigger the hypothalamus- pituitary-adrenal gland axis (HPA axis), sending hormonal messages to the adrenal gland to pour adrenaline into the system.
This will increase blood sugar levels and feed the brain again with energy.
But adrenaline is not only the flight/fright hormone, but also the focusing hormone, compelling the person to focus on the enemy.
This may result in compulsive behaviours.

Energy starvation in the brain can be caused by Insulin Resistance, which causes the receptors for insulin to block the transfer of glucose and other nutrients into cells.
Hence glucose cannot be converted to ATP in mitochondria of cells.
Excess and unused glucose is stored in glycogen stores and when these are full are then converted to fat cells.
Hence insulin resistance not only can cause depression and anxieties, but also obesity.

Insulin resistance leads to a rise in blood sugar levels, which will trigger more insulin secretion from the pancreas (hyperinsulinism).
This is followed by a sudden drop in blood sugar levels called Hypoglycemia.
Now the brain is threatened with energy starvation which results in the release of stress hormones such as adrenaline.
The wildly fluctuating blood sugar levels resulting from of unstable insulin and stress hormones concentrations constitute what us called the Hypoglycemic Syndrome.</entry>
  <entry author_id="19858" end="54" start="26">Drug therapy acknowledges that anxiety attacks are caused by an underlying biochemical imbalance.
Unfortunately, medications often fail to treat the underlying cause of anxiety attacks.
Anxiety attacks are frequently a comorbid condition of depression.
One study showed that about 40% of patients using drugs to suppress symptoms depression may have some benefit leaving about 60% of patients with treatment resistant depression.
See Insel TR (2006) the same would apply to anxiety attacks.
Hence drugs do not seem to treat the underlying biochemical disorder responsible for anxiety attacks.

Psychonutritionists look upon anxiety attacks as being caused by an excess production of adrenaline, not necessarily as a result of any thought processes, or memories, but rather due to an underlying biological abnormality.
These internally driven fear hormones (mainly adrenaline and cortisol) are often associated with some environmental cue or thought, which then may become a stimulus for the adrenergic reaction.
In psychology this is known as reverse conditioning that pairs any behaviour with a stimulus that happens to be in the environment or mind.
Thus when a person is flooded with stress hormones and finds him/herself standing at that moment in a lift, the lift can become the stimulus of the fear hormone.
This explains the wide variety of phobias and unreasonable fear reactions.

Adrenaline is a hormone that functions to convert sugar stores such as GLYCOGEN into glucose (Lehninger, 732).
Glucose is the universal source of biological energy called ATP.
Without that energy the body cannot manufacture the feel good neurotransmitters such as serotonin.

The brain although 2% of body weight requires about 60-70% of all available glucose to energize brain activity, whether asleep or awake.
Thus when the brain is deprived of energy for only a few seconds it is threatened with energy starvation.
This will trigger the hypothalamus- pituitary-adrenal gland axis (HPA axis), sending hormonal messages to the adrenal gland to pour adrenaline into the system.
This will increase blood sugar levels and feed the brain again with energy.
But adrenaline is not only the flight/fright hormone, but also the focusing hormone, compelling the person to focus on the enemy.
This may result in compulsive behaviours.

Energy starvation in the brain can be caused by Insulin Resistance, which causes the receptors for insulin to block the transfer of glucose and other nutrients into cells.
Hence glucose cannot be converted to ATP in mitochondria of cells.
Excess and unused glucose is stored in glycogen stores and when these are full are then converted to fat cells.
Hence insulin resistance not only can cause depression and anxieties, but also obesity.

Insulin resistance leads to a rise in blood sugar levels, which will trigger more insulin secretion from the pancreas (hyperinsulinism).
This is followed by a sudden drop in blood sugar levels called Hypoglycemia.
Now the brain is threatened with energy starvation which results in the release of stress hormones such as adrenaline (Samra, 25).
The wildly fluctuating blood sugar levels resulting from of unstable insulin and stress hormones concentrations constitute what us called the Hypoglycemic Syndrome.</entry>
  <entry author_id="11305658" end="104" start="54">Research has provided evidence for the efficacy of two forms of treatment available for social phobia: certain medications and a specific form of short-term psychotherapy called Cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT), the central component being gradual exposure therapy.
Research has shown that cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) can be highly effective for several anxiety disorders, particularly panic disorder and social phobia.
CBT, as its name suggests, has two main components, cognitive and behavioral.
In cases of social anxiety, the cognitive component can help the patient question how they can be so sure that others are continually watching and harshly judging him or her.
The behavioral component seeks to change people's reactions to anxiety-provoking situations.
As such it serves as a logical extension of cognitive therapy, whereby people are shown proof in the real world that their dysfunctional thought processes are unrealistic.
A key element of this component is gradual exposure, in which the patient is confronted by the things they fear in a structured, sensitive manner.
Gradual exposure is an inherently unpleasant technique; ideally it involves exposure to a feared social situation that is anxiety provoking but bearable, for as long as possible, two to three times a week.
Often, a hierarchy of feared steps is constructed and the patient is exposed each step sequentially.
The aim is to learn from acting differently and observing reactions.
This is intended to be done with support and guidance, and when the therapist and patient feel they are ready.
Cognitive-behavioral therapy for social phobia also includes anxiety management training, which may include techniques such as deep breathing and muscle relaxation exercises, which may be practiced 'in-situ'.
CBT can also be conducted partly in group sessions, facilitating the sharing of experiences, a sense of acceptance by others and undertaking behavioral challenges in a trusted environment (Heimberg).

Additionally, a recent study has suggested that interpersonal therapy, a form of psychotherapy primarily used to treat depression, may also be effective in the treatment of social phobia.
Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), a class of antidepressants, are considered by many to be the first choice medication for generalised social phobia.
These drugs elevate the level of the neurotransmitter serotonin, among other effects.
The first drug formally approved by the Food and Drug Administration was paroxetine, sold as Paxil in the U.S. or Seroxat in the UK.
Compared to older forms of medication, there is less risk of tolerability and drug dependency.
However, their efficacy and increased suicide risk has been subject to controversy.

In a 1995 double-blind, placebo-controlled trial, the SSRI paroxetine was shown to result in clinically meaningful improvement in 55 percent of patients with generalized social anxiety disorder, compared with 23.9 percent of those taking placebo.
An October 2004 study yielded similar results.
Patients were treated with either fluoxetine, psychotherapy, fluoxetine and psychotherapy, placebo and psychotherapy, or a placebo.
The first four sets saw improvement in 50.8 to 54.2 percent of the patients.
Of those assigned to receive only a placebo, 31.7 percent achieved a rating of 1 or 2 on the Clinical Global Impression-Improvement scale.
Those who sought both therapy and medication did not see a boost in improvement.

General side-effects are common during the first weeks while the body adjusts to the drug.
Symptoms may include headaches, nausea, insomnia and changes in sexual behavior.
Treatment safety during pregnancy has not been established.
In late 2004 much media attention was given to a proposed link between SSRI use and juvenile suicide.
For this reason, the use of SSRIs in pediatric cases of depression is now recognized by the Food and Drug Administration as warranting a cautionary statement to the parents of children who may be prescribed SSRIs by a family doctor.
Recent studies have shown no increase in rates of suicide.
These tests, however, represent those diagnosed with depression, not necessarily with social anxiety disorder.
However, it should be noted that due to the nature of the conditions, those taking SSRIs for social phobias are far less likely to have suicidal ideation than those with depression.
Although SSRIs are often the first choice for treatment, other prescription drugs are also used, sometimes only if SSRIs fail to produce any clinically significant improvement.

In 1985, before the introduction of SSRIs, anti-depressants such as monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) were frequently used in the treatment of social anxiety.
Their efficacy appears to be comparable or sometimes superior to SSRIs or benzodiazepines.
However, because of the dietary restrictions required, high toxicity in overdose, and incompatibilities with other drugs, its usefulness as a treatment for social phobics is now limited.
Some argue for their continued use, however, or that a special diet does not need to be strictly adhered to.
A newer type of this medication, Reversible inhibitors of monoamine oxidase subtype A (RIMAs) inhibit the MAO enzyme only temporarily, improving the adverse-effect profile but possibly reducing their efficacy.

Benzodiazepines such as alprazolam and clonazepam are an alternative to SSRIs.
These drugs are often used for short-term relief of severe, disabling anxiety.
Although benzodiazepines are still sometimes prescribed for long-term everyday use in some countries, there is much concern over the development of drug tolerance, dependency and recreational abuse.
It has been recommended that benzodiazepines are only considered for individuals who fail to respond to safer medications.
Benzodiazepines augment the action of GABA, the major inhibitory neurotransmitter in the brain; effects usually begin to appear within minutes or hours.

A novel treatment approach has recently been developed as a result of translational research.
It has been shown that a combination of acute dosing of d-cycloserine (DCS) with exposure therapy facilitates the effects of exposure therapy of social phobia (Hofmann, Meuret, Smits, et al., 2006).
DCS is an old antibiotic medication used for treating tuberculosis and does not have any anxiolytic properties per se.
However, it acts as an agonist at the glutamatergic N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor site, which is important for learning and memory (Hofmann, Pollack, &amp; Otto, 2006).
It has been shown that administering a small dose acutely 1 hour before exposure therapy can facilitate extinction learning that occurs during therapy.
Aqueouscientific and Clarocet are two of the most common natural herbal supplements used to treat Anxiety disorders that promote a positive mood and reduce Anxiety.</entry>
  <entry author_id="3810835" end="129" start="104">Theologian Paul Tillich characterized existential anxiety as "the state in which a being is aware of its possible nonbeing" and he listed three categories for the nonbeing and resulting anxiety: ontic (fate and death), moral (guilt and condemnation), and spiritual (emptiness and meaninglessness).
According to Tillich, the last of these three types of existential anxiety, i.e. spiritual anxiety, is predominant in modern times while the others were predominant in earlier periods.
Tillich argues that this anxiety can be accepted as part of the human condition or it can be resisted but with negative consequences.
In its pathological form, spiritual anxiety may tend to "drive the person toward the creation of certitude in systems of meaning which are supported by tradition and authority" even though such "undoubted certitude is not built on the rock of reality".

According to Viktor Frankl, author of Man's Search for Meaning, when faced with extreme mortal dangers the most basic of all human wishes is to find a meaning of life to combat the "trauma of nonbeing" as death is near.
According to Yerkes-Dodson law, an optimal level of arousal is necessary to best complete a task such as an exam, performance, or competitive event.
However, when the anxiety or level of arousal exceeds that optimum, it results in a decline in performance.

Test anxiety is the uneasiness, apprehension, or nervousness felt by students who had a fear of failing an exam.
Students who have test anxiety may experience any of the following: the association of grades with personal worth, fear of embarrassment by a teacher, fear of alienation from parents or friends, time pressures, or feeling a loss of control.
Sweating, dizziness, headaches, racing heartbeats, nausea, fidgeting, and drumming on a desk are all common.
Because test anxiety hinges on fear of negative evaluation, debate exists as to whether test anxiety is itself a unique anxiety disorder or whether it is a specific type of social phobia.

While the term "test anxiety" refers specifically to students, many workers share the same experience with regard to their career or profession.
The fear of failing a task and being negatively evaluated for it can have a similarly negative effect on the adult.
Anxiety when meeting or interacting with unknown people is a common stage of development in young people.
For others, it may persist into adulthood and become social anxiety or social phobia.
"Stranger anxiety" in small children is not a phobia.
Rather it is a developmentally appropriate fear by toddlers and preschool children of those who are not parents or family members.
In adults, an excessive fear of other people is not a developmentally common stage; it is called social anxiety.
Anxiety can be either a short term 'state' or a long term "trait."
Trait anxiety reflects a stable tendency to respond with state anxiety in the anticipation of threatening situations.
It is closely related to the personality trait of neuroticism.
Anxiety induced by the need to choose between similar options is increasingly being recognized as a problem for individuals and for organisations:  Paradoxical anxiety is anxiety arising from use of methods or techniques which are normally used to reduce anxiety.
This includes relaxation or meditation techniques as well as use of certain medications.
In some buddhist meditation literature, this effect, although it is not referred to as anxiety there due to the religious context of the writing, is described as something which arises naturally and should be turned toward and mindfully explored in order to gain insight into the nature of emotion, and more profoundly, the nature of self.
In Positive psychology, anxiety is described as a response to a difficult challenge for which the subject has insufficient coping skills.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7520964" end="154" start="129">Theologian Paul Tillich characterized existential anxiety as "the state in which a being is aware of its possible nonbeing" and he listed three categories for the nonbeing and resulting anxiety: ontic (fate and death), moral (guilt and condemnation), and spiritual (emptiness and meaninglessness).
According to Tillich, the last of these three types of existential anxiety, i.e. spiritual anxiety, is predominant in modern times while the others were predominant in earlier periods.
Tillich argues that this anxiety can be accepted as part of the human condition or it can be resisted but with negative consequences.
In its pathological form, spiritual anxiety may tend to "drive the person toward the creation of certitude in systems of meaning which are supported by tradition and authority" even though such "undoubted certitude is not built on the rock of reality".

According to Viktor Frankl, author of Man's Search for Meaning, when faced with extreme mortal dangers the most basic of all human wishes is to find a meaning of life to combat the "trauma of nonbeing" as death is near.
According to Yerkes-Dodson law, an optimal level of arousal is necessary to best complete a task such as an exam, performance, or competitive event.
However, when the anxiety or level of arousal exceeds that optimum, it results in a decline in performance.

Test anxiety is the uneasiness, apprehension, or nervousness felt by students who had a fear of failing an exam.
Students who have test anxiety may experience any of the following: the association of grades with personal worth, fear of embarrassment by a teacher, fear of alienation from parents or friends, time pressures, or feeling a loss of control.
Sweating, dizziness, headaches, racing heartbeats, nausea, fidgeting, and drumming on a desk are all common.
Because test anxiety hinges on fear of negative evaluation, debate exists as to whether test anxiety is itself a unique anxiety disorder or whether it is a specific type of social phobia.

While the term "test anxiety" refers specifically to students, many workers share the same experience with regard to their career or profession.
The fear of failing a task and being negatively evaluated for it can have a similarly negative effect on the adult.
Anxiety when meeting or interacting with unknown people is a common stage of development in young people.
For others, it may persist into adulthood and become social anxiety or social phobia.
"Stranger anxiety" in small children is not a phobia.
Rather it is a developmentally appropriate fear by toddlers and preschool children of those who are not parents or family members.
In adults, an excessive fear of other people is not a developmentally common stage; it is called social anxiety.
Anxiety can be either a short term 'state' or a long term "trait."
Trait anxiety reflects a stable tendency to respond with state anxiety in the anticipation of threatening situations.
It is closely related to the personality trait of neuroticism.
Anxiety induced by the need to choose between similar options is increasingly being recognized as a problem for individuals and for organisations:  Paradoxical anxiety is anxiety arising from use of methods or techniques which are normally used to reduce anxiety.
This includes relaxation or meditation techniques as well as use of certain medications.
In some buddhist meditation literature, this effect, although it is not referred to as anxiety there due to the religious context of the writing, is described as something which arises naturally and should be turned toward and mindfully explored in order to gain insight into the nature of emotion, and more profoundly, the nature of self.
In Positive psychology, anxiety is described as a response to a difficult challenge for which the subject has insufficient coping skills.</entry>
  <entry author_id="14627104" end="199" start="154">ANXIETY, PANIC ATTACKS, DEPRESSION, OBSESSIONAL COMPULSIVE DISORDER (OCD) GRIEF, APATHY, PTSD, to name just a few.
Really virtually any area of your life will transform with continual use, and at lightening speed.
Emotional upsets will begin to resolve sometimes in minutes.

Take a Phobia for instance: An irrational fear of something which you know is totally disproportionate to the actual event or object.
This release method will dissolve this fear in minutes no matter what kind of fear or indeed no matter how long you may have suffered from it.
PHOBIAS!!
Are released in minutes!.

SEXUAL DYSFUNCTION (ED) Can be a real disabling issue for males of any age and can strike at any age too.
Erectile Dysfunction or ED as it is known is cause mainly by wrongful thinking, and the fear of it is enough to trigger the event.
The release method will remove all fear and resolve ED giving back that confidence much needed to perform the task in hand.
In fact this method will increase sexual libido when used, many times that of what we would consider normal.

What happens to you when you try to stop yourself from worrying about a particular issue in life?
Yes you got it, it sticks to you like glue, the more you try to remove it the more it remains and actually increases in intensity until it feels like you are locked into a very vicious cycle of fear and then more fear and when that happens you feel like your mind is on auto pilot and feel totally at its mercy.
Well no more!
Guardian Release will show you just how wrong you are, and give you back control total control.

WHAT GUARDIAN IS NOT!!
Guardian is not some kind of Hypnosis.
Has nothing to do with TFT or CBT.
Guardian has nothing to do with drugs or herbal medications whatsoever.

Guardian will teach you to release any unwanted emotion in the moment.
Panic Attacks and Anxiety will be resigned to the past and the results are permanent without relapse.
Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD) will be removed with continual use in around 48 hours depending on your commitment to practise.
In fact you will see changes right from day one in the reduction of the traumatic recurring event.
In fact when complete I challenge anyone to feel the reaction to fear of any kind.
It just won't happen.
You will still retain your memories about any emotional upset but that's all they will be Memories without the reaction to them.

Depression can feel like the world is totally black and without a future in life.
How wrong you could be.
Watch this method dissolve depression in minutes.

I make no claims here to treat or cure any kind of physical illness whatsoever, but after years of using the release method I have seen many wonderful things happening to people who were suffering from physical ailments.
I have many testimonies which we won't go into because testimonies are only as good as the proof of who sent them so I really see no point.
All too often people spend hours writing testimonies from fictitious people so I will not insult your intelligence in doing that here.
It just leads me personally to believe that emotional problems causing cellular internal stress may just be leading us to suffer from a physical condition.
That's just a personal opinion which the medical world is now looking at very seriously.
Releasing on the emotional attachment to a particular illness would appear to resolve it.
I have no explanation for this, but research is still very much ongoing.
In particular the resolution of long standing chronic pain.

Guardian is quite simply the easiest way in which to change your life completely without long drawn out months or years of therapy.
There are various methods out there which address ways to release us from our thoughts.
People spend Hundreds of Dollars or Pounds on methods which totally miss the point.

Because our problems and issues seem like mountains to climb Human being think it takes a major effort to overcome their own particular problem.
What if I told you that's the farthest statement from the truth you could imagine?
You will read this method and learn it in minutes.
Then take it with you for the rest of your life.
Download this method now and contact me with any questions that arise afterwards at Neural circuitry involving the amygdala and hippocampus is thought to underlie anxiety.</entry>
  <entry author_id="17180892" end="212" start="199">There are several approaches to treating anxiety problems (including chronic stress, situational anxiety, and panic attacks).
The most common approach is the use of anxiolytic (anti-anxiety) medications, which calm the body physically, making it less likely that a person will experience physiological symptoms.
Such medications are typically central nervous system (CNS) depressants and include such agents as Xanax, Valium, Opioids and Alcohol.
The use of such agents for prevention of anticipated situation-specific anxiety may be effective, if the agents are taken prior to encountering the situation (so the agent has time to take effect) in the smallest effective dose (for safety).
However, use of such agents to treat chronic or severe anxiety is not likely to be effective because of the issue of tolerance, where the body becomes accustomed to the agent and higher and higher doses are gradually needed to achieve the therapeutic effect.
At this point, one often experiences anxiety despite use of a medication or nonprescription agent that was previously effective.
Also, this can lead to an addiction to a prescription medication or nonprescription agent such as an opioid or alcohol, that was previously therapeutic.
In effect a person then has two problems: anxiety and addiction.
In almost all cases of anxiety, natural techniques can be used to prevent the onset of symptoms or alleviate symptoms when they occur, including stopping panic attacks.
These techniques include learning to control breathing in specific ways (aka abdominal breathing, deep breathing), learning to relax the body physically (aka progressive muscle relaxation), and use of cognitive techniques such as visualization, cognitive restructuring, prevention of automatic negative thoughts and catastrophic thinking.
These techniques are often taught to patients in Cognitive Behavioral Therapy, but they can be learned through self-help resources as well.
Such techniques have long received research support and can be learned by almost anyone, including children, and can be applied in almost any situation to help manage anxiety.
A video teaching deep abdominal breathing and progressive muscle relaxation, which also contains an explanation of the physiology underlying the effectiveness of these techniques, as well as explanations of the two-factor theory of Orval Hobart Mowrer (addressing classical conditioning and operant conditioning and avoidance learning) for the acquisition and maintenance of chronic anxiety reactions, can be found at: http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-Le3uo8lckk&amp;feature=relmfu</entry>
</article>
