<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="956" title="Asteraceae" authors="2" lines="22">
  <entry author_id="16734" end="10" start="0">Members of the Asteraceae have one or both of two kinds of florets.
The outer-most perimeter of composites like the sunflower is composed of a row of florets each possessing a long strap-like petal, termed ligule; these are the ray flowers.
The inner portion of the flower (or disc) is composed of small flowers with tubular corollas; these are the disc flowers.
The composition of Asteraceous inflorescences varies from all ray flowers (like dandelions, genus Taraxacum) to all disc flowers (like pineapple weeds).

The composite nature of the inflorescences of these plants led early taxonomists to call this family the Compositae.
However, the rules of forming names for plant families state that the name must come from the type genus, in this case Aster, thus Asteraceae.
ITIS report 2002-09-10

Dirk R. Walters and David J. Keil (1996).. 4th ed.
Kendall/Hunt Publishing Company.
Dubuque, Iowa</entry>
  <entry author_id="12185180" end="22" start="10">The Asteraceae or Compositae, also referred to as the aster, daisy, or sunflower family, is the largest family of vascular plants.
The family has more than 22,750 currently accepted species, spread across 1620 genera, and 12 subfamilies.

Many economically important products come from composites, including cooking oils, lettuce, sunflower seeds, artichokes, sweetening agents, and teas.
Several genera are also very popular with the horticultural community, these include marigolds, chrysanthemums, dahlias, zinnias, and heleniums.
The name Asteraceae is derived from the type genus Aster, which is a Greek term, meaning "star".

Daisies have a worldwide distribution, being found everywhere except Antarctica.
They are especially numerous in tropical and subtropical regions (notably Central America, eastern Brazil, the Andes, the Mediterranean, southern Africa, central Asia, and southwestern China).
The Compositae was first described in 1792 by the German botanist Paul Dietrich Giseke.

However, many closely related species in this family are notoriously difficult to identify to the species level.
Daisy roots are usually taproots, and sometimes fibrous.
Stems are generally erect, but sometimes prostrate to ascending.
Some species have underground stems in the form of caudices or rhizomes, these can be fleshy or woody depending on the species.</entry>
</article>
