<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="974" title="Ada Lovelace" authors="1" lines="20">
  <entry author_id="1289353" end="20" start="0">Annabella did not have a close relationship with the young Ada and the child often left her in the care of her grandmother Judith Milbanke, who doted on her.
However, due to the social attitudes of the time – which favoured the husband in any separation, with the welfare of any child acting as mitigation – she had to present herself as a loving mother to the rest of society.
This included writing anxious letters to her mother about Ada’s welfare, with a cover note saying to retain the letters in case she had to use them to show maternal concern.

Throughout her life, she was strongly interested in scientific developments and fads of the day, including phrenology and mesmerism.
Even after her famous work with Babbage, Ada continued to work on other projects.
In 1844, Ada would comment to a friend Woronzow Greig about her desire to create a mathematical model for how the brain gives rise to thoughts and nerves to feelings (“a calculus of the nervous system”), though she would never achieve this: in part, this was down to a long-running preoccupation, inherited from her mother, about her 'potential' madness.
As part of her research into this project, she visited electrical engineer Andrew Crosse in 1844 to learn how to carry out electrical experiments.
In the same year, she wrote review of a paper by Baron Karl von Reichenbach, ‘’Researches on Magnetism’’, but this was not published and does not appear to have progressed past the first draft.
In 1851, the last year before her cancer struck, she wrote to her mother mentioning “certain productions” she was working on regarding the relation of maths and music.

In the 1840s, Ada would flirt with scandals: first from a relaxed relationship with men who weren’t her husband, which led to rumours of affairs; and second her love of gambling, which led to her forming a syndicate with her male friends and an ambitious attempt in 1851 to create a mathematical model for successful large bets.
This went disastrously wrong, leaving her thousands of pounds in debt and being blackmailed by one of the syndicate, forcing her to admit her mess to her husband.. Ada also had a shadowy, possibly illicit relationship with Andrew Crosse’s son John from 1844 onwards.
Few hard facts are known because Crosse destroyed most of their correspondence after her death as part of a legal agreement; however, it was strong enough that she bequeathed him the only heirlooms her father had personally left to her.
During her final illness, Ada would panic at the idea of John Crosse being kept from visiting her.

Babbage and Ada had a minor falling out when the papers were published, when he tried to leave his own statement (a criticism of the government’s treatment of his Engine) as an unsigned preface – which would imply she’d written that too.
When ‘’Taylor’s Scientific Memoirs’’ ruled that the statement should be signed, Babbage wrote to Ada asking her to withdraw the paper.
This was the first she knew he was leaving it unsigned and she wrote back refusing to withdraw the paper.
Historian Benjamin Woolley was theorised that “his actions suggested he had so enthusiastically sought Ada’s involvement, and so happily indulged her… because of her ‘celebrated name’”.

The illness lasted several months, in which time Annabella would take command over who Ada saw, and put out exclusion orders on all of her friends and confidants.
Under her mother’s influence, she had a religious transformation (after previously being a materialist) and was coaxed into repenting of her previous conduct and making Annabella her executor.
Contact was lost with her husband after she confessed something to him on the 30th August, causing him to abandon her bedside; what she told him is not known but has been theorised as a confession of adultery.</entry>
</article>
