<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article article_id="981" title="Alps" authors="1" lines="48">
  <entry author_id="7411880" end="17" start="0">The largest mammal to live in the highest altitudes are the Ibex, which have been sighted as high as 3000 meters.
The ibex live in caves and descend to eat the succulent alpine grasses.
Chamois are smaller than ibex and found throughout the alps, living above the tree line, and most prevalent in Austria and Bavaria.
Areas of the eastern Alps are still home to brown bears.
In Switzerland the canton Bern was named for the bears but the last bear is recorded as having been killed above Kleine Scheidegg by three hunters from Grindelwald in 1792.

Golden eagles, which feed on snakes among other animals, are the largest birds to be found in the Alps; they nest high on rocky ledges and can be found at altitudes of 2400 meters.
The most common birds are the alpine chough which can be found scavenging at climber's huts or at the Jungfraujoch, a high altitude tourist destination.
T

Reptiles such as adders and vipers live up to the snow line in the alps; because they cannot bear the cold temperatures they hibernate underground and soak up the warmth on rocky ledges.
The high-altitude salmanders (salmandar atra) have adapted to living above the snow line by giving birth to fully developed young rather than laying eggs.
Brown trout can be found in the streams as high up as the snow line.

A number of species of moths live in the alps, some of which are believed to have evolved in the same habitat from as long as 120 million years ago, much before the alps were created.
Blue moths can commonly be seen drinking from the snow melt; some species of blue moths fly up to 1800 meters.
The butterflies are large such as those from the swallowtail Parnassus family, with a habitat that ranges to 1800 meters.

Twelve species of beetles have habitats up to the snow line; the most beautiful and collected for its colors is the Rosalia alpina.
Spiders, such as the large wolf spider, live above the snow line and have been sighted as high as 4000 meters.
Scorpions can be found in the Italian alps.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7411880" end="29" start="17">Orogeny took place continuously and tectonic subsidence is to blame for the gaps in between.In the Miocene era the mountains underwent severe erosion because of glaciation, which was noted in the mid-19th century by naturalist Louis Agassiz who was the first to present a paper in which he theorized that the Alps had been entirely covered in ice at various intervals.
He came to this conclusion after studying rocks near his Neuchâtel that he believed had originated in the Berner Oberland.
As a result of his work he came to be known as the "father of the ice-age concept" although other naturalists before him put forth similar ideas.
Agassiz studied glacier movement in the 1840s at the Unteraar glacier where he discorver that the glacier moved 100 meters per year and the movement is greater in the middle of the glacier than at the edges.

Glaciers carry rocks with them as they flow which causes erosion and over long periods of time carves valleys.
The Inn valley is an example of a valley carved by glaciers during the ice ages with a typical terraced structure caused by erosion.
Erosion from the most recent ice age lie at the bottom of the valley and top of the valley is comprised of erosion from earlier ice ages.
Moraines are piles of rocks moved by glaciers, and will be found at the edges of the glacier, down the middle of a glacier and at the end (terminus) of a glacier.

Alpine glaciers can be straight rivers of ice, sweeping rivers, glaciers that spread out in a fan-like shape (Piedmont glaciers), and glaciers of ice that hang from the vertical slopes on the mountain peaks.
At the Jungfraujoch, inside a glacier, is a laboratory to study Alpine glaciers above which is a glacier between the Jungfrau and the Monch the flows in two directions.
The stress of the movement causes the ice to break and crack loudly, a reason in the medieval period the mountains were believed to be home to dragons, which creates crevasses.
Crevasses are unpredictable and dangerous, often invisible under new snowfall, and cause the greatest danger to mountaineers.</entry>
  <entry author_id="7411880" end="48" start="29">Skills that guaranteed survival in the medieval period have become mainstays such as carpentry, woodcarving, baking and pastry-making, and cheesemaking.
Also, since the medieval period farming and haymaking have been traditional occupations, although that has become less dominant in the 20th century with the advent of tourism.
Because the steep and rocky topography of the Alps, grazing and pasture land is limited.
In the summers cows are brought to the highest pastures close to the snowline, where they are watched by herdsmen who stay in the high pastures during the summers.
In France and Italy the cowherds live in stone huts during the summers.

Cheesemaking is an ancient and traditional tradition in most Alpine countries.
A wheel of cheese from the Emmental in Switzerland can weigh up to 100 pounds, and owners of the cows traditionally receive a proportion of the cheese in relation to the proportion of the cow's milk from the summer months in the high alps.
Haying is another ancient activity performed still in mountain villages and although somewhat mechanized in areas, the steep slopes still require the use of manual scythes to cut the grass.
The hay is normally brought in twice a year, often also during festival days.

Alpine festivals vary from country to country and often include the display of Alpenhorns, wrestling matches, some pagan traditions such as Waldpurgis Night, and in many areas Carnivale is celebrated before Lent.
People live in homes that were designed in medieval times to withstand cold winters, with with a kitchen separated from the living area (called the stube because it's the area of the home heated by a stove), and bedrooms on the second floor to take advantage of the rising heat.
The typical Swiss chalet originated in the Berner Oberland.
It consists of a house, often facing south or downhill, built of solid wood, with a steeply gabled roof to prevent the build up of snow.
Stairs to upper levels are often place on the outside, and balconies are sometimes enclosed.

Food is passed from the kitchen to the stube, where the dining room table is placed.
Some meals are communal, such as fondue, where a pot is set in the middle of the table for each person to dip into.
Other meals are still served in a traditional manner on carved wooden plates.
Furniture has been traditionally elaborately carved and in many Alpine countries carpentry skills are passed from generation to generation.
Roofs are made from Alpine rocks such as pieces of schist, gneiss or slate.</entry>
</article>
